<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>187k.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <family_name>Asteraceae</family_name>
    <family_authority>Martinov</family_authority>
    <tribe_name>Astereae</tribe_name>
    <tribe_authority>Cassini</tribe_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Phys. Chim. Hist. Nat. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>88: 195. 1819</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Annuals, biennials, perennials, subshrubs, shrubs, or trees. Leaves usually cauline,
    sometimes mostly basal; alternate [opposite, whorled]; usually petiolate, sometimes sessile;
    margins entire or dentate to pinnatifid (often gland-dotted, especially in xerophytes). Heads
    homogamous (discoid; unisexual in Baccharis) or heterogamous (disciform or radiate), usually in
    corymbiform, paniculiform, racemiform, or spiciform arrays, sometimes borne singly. Calyculi 0.
    Phyllaries persistent or falling, usually in 3–5+ series (usually in spirals, sometimes in
    vertical ranks), distinct, unequal, and herbaceous to chartaceous or scarious or margins and/or
    apices notably scarious, sometimes in 1–2 series, distinct, subequal, and herbaceous with
    margins and/or apices barely to notably scarious. Receptacles usually flat to conic, sometimes
    concave, usually epaleate, rarely paleate (often foveolate, socket margins often fimbrillate;
    paleate in Eastwoodia and Rigiopappus). Ray florets 0 or in 1(–2+) series, usually pistillate,
    rarely neuter or styliferous and sterile; corollas usually yellow, cyanic, or white (laminae
    sometimes very reduced, e.g., Conyza spp.). Peripheral (pistillate) florets 0 or (in disciform
    heads) in 1–3+ series; corollas usually present, usually yellow, sometimes white, ochroleucous,
    or reddish to cyanic. Disc (inner) florets usually bisexual and fertile, rarely functionally
    staminate (e.g., Benitoa); corollas usually yellow, sometimes white, ochroleucous, or cyanic,
    actinomorphic, not 2-lipped, lobes (4–)5; anther bases obtuse or rounded, not tailed, apical
    appendages usually triangular to linear, sometimes none; styles abaxially glabrous and smooth or
    papillate (distally), branches ± linear, adaxially stigmatic in 2 lines from bases to apices or
    appendages, appendages usually deltate to lanceolate (abaxially papillate to hispidulous,
    adaxially smooth, glabrous). Cypselae monomorphic or dimorphic within heads, usually ± columnar
    to prismatic and 5-ribbed, sometimes compressed and 2-ribbed, rarely beaked, bodies smooth,
    muricate, ribbed, or rugulose (glabrous or hairy, hairs often glandular); pappi (rarely 0)
    usually persistent, usually of barbellulate to barbellate bristles in (1–)2–3+ series, sometimes
    of scales (scales sometimes aristate), rarely of both scales and bristles or of
    awns.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Genera 170, species 2800+ (77 genera, 719 species in the
    flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>almost worldwide</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>mostly temperate.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>The classification and phylogeny of tribe Astereae has been the object of recent work,
    both morphologic (K. Bremer 1994; G. L. Nesom 1994, 2000) and molecular (notably the seminal
    paper by R. D. Noyes and L. H. Rieseberg 1999). Noyes and Rieseberg showed that most genera
    present in North America belong to a single monophyletic clade, called the North American clade.
    A series of subsequent studies done in various generic groups or subtribes led to a redefinition
    of many genera (see literature cited in each genus) and to the transfer of species between
    genera. The current treatment of the tribe reflects much of these novelties, many presented in a
    floristic work for the first time. Nesom and H. Robinson (unpubl.) present a worldwide overview
    of the classification of the tribe.</discussion>
  <discussion>Large genera such as Erigeron, Symphyotrichum, and Solidago all originated on the
    continent and subsequently spread to Eurasia or South America. A few genera entered North
    America from neighboring continents, such as Aster in the strict sense (from Eurasia) or
    Baccharis (from Central America). A majority of Astereae genera in the flora of North America
    are endemic to the continent (more so if Mexico were included).</discussion>
  <discussion>The generic order of the present treatment attempts to reflect the phylogenetic
    relationships established in recent molecular phylogenetic work.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference> Anderson, L. C. and J. B. Creech. 1975. Comparative leaf anatomy
      of Solidago and related Asteraceae. Amer. J. Bot. 62: 486–493.</reference>
    <reference>Beck, J. B. et al. 2004. Is subtribe Solidagininae (Asteraceae) monophyletic? Taxon
      53: 691–698.</reference>
    <reference>Brouillet, L., L. E. Urbatsch, and R. P. Roberts. 2004. Tonestus kingii and T.
      aberrans are related to Eurybia and the Machaerantherinae (Asteraceae: Astereae) based on
      nrDNA (ITS and ETS) data: Reinstatement of Herrickia and a new genus, Triniteurybia. Sida 21:
      889–900.</reference>
    <reference>Cronquist, A. and D. D. Keck. 1957. A reconstitution of the genus Machaeranthera.
      Brittonia 9: 231–239.</reference>
    <reference>Fiz, O., V. Valcárcel, and P. Vargas. 2002. Phylogenetic position of Mediterranean
      Astereae and character evolution of daisies (Bellis, Asteraceae) inferred from nrDNA ITS
      sequences. Molec. Phylogen. Evol. 25: 157–171.</reference>
    <reference>Hall, H. M. 1928. The genus Haplopappus: A phylogenetic study in the Compositae.
      Publ. Carnegie Inst. Wash. 389. Hartman, R. L. 1976. A Conspectus of Machaeranthera
      (Compositae: Astereae) and a Biosystematic Study of the Section Blepharodon. Ph.D.
      dissertation. University of Texas. Hartman, R. L. 1990. A conspectus of Machaeranthera
      (Asteraceae: Astereae). Phytologia 68: 439–465.</reference>
    <reference>Jones, A. G. 1980. A classification of New World species of Aster (Asteraceae).
      Brittonia 32: 230–239.</reference>
    <reference>Jones, A. G. and D. A. Young. 1983. Generic concepts of Aster (Asteraceae): A
      comparison of cladistic, phenetic and cytological approaches. Syst. Bot. 8: 71–84.</reference>
    <reference>Kapoor, B. M. and J. R. Beaudry. 1966. Studies on Solidago. VII. The taxonomic status
      of the taxa Brachychaeta, Brintonia, Chrysoma, Euthamia, Oligoneuron, and Petradoria in
      relation to Solidago. Canad. J. Genet. Cytol. 8: 422–443.</reference>
    <reference>Lane, M. A. 1982. Generic limits of Xanthocephalum, Gutierrezia, Amphiachyris,
      Gymnosperma, Greenella, and Thurovia. (Compositae: Astereae). Syst. Bot. 7:
      405–416.</reference>
    <reference>Lane, M. A. et al. 1996. Relationships of North American genera of Astereae, based on
      chloroplast DNA restriction site data. In: D. J. N. Hind et al., eds. 1996. Proceedings of the
      International Compositae Conference, Kew, 1994. 2 vols. Kew. Vol. 1, pp. 49–77.</reference>
    <reference>Morgan, D. R. 1997. Reticulate evolution in Machaeranthera (Asteraceae). Syst. Bot.
      22: 599–615.</reference>
    <reference>Morgan, D. R. 2003. nrDNA external transcribed spacer (ETS) sequence data, reticulate
      evolution, and the systematics of Machaeranthera (Asteraceae). Syst. Bot. 28:
      179–190.</reference>
    <reference>Morgan, D. R. and R. L. Hartman. 2003. A synopsis of Machaeranthera (Asteraceae:
      Astereae), with recognition of segregate genera. Sida 20: 1837–1416.</reference>
    <reference>Morgan, D. R. and B. B. Simpson. 1992. A systematic study of Machaeranthera
      (Asteraceae) and related groups using restriction site analysis of chloroplast DNA. Syst. Bot.
      17: 511–531.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1991b. A phylogenetic hypothesis for the goldenasters (Asteraceae:
      Astereae). Phytologia 71: 136–151.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1993b. Taxonomic infrastructure of Solidago and Oligoneuron (Asteraceae:
      Astereae) and observations on their phylogenetic position. Phytologia 75: 1–44.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1994. Subtribal classification of the Astereae (Asteraceae). Phytologia
      76: 193–274.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1994b. Review of the taxonomy of Aster sensu lato (Asteraceae:
      Astereae), emphasizing the New World species. Phytologia 77: 141–297.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1997. Taxonomic adjustments in North American Aster sensu latissimo
      (Asteraceae: Astereae). Phytologia 82: 281–288.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 2000. Generic Conspectus of the Tribe Astereae (Asteraceae) in North
      America, Central America, the Antilles, and Hawaii. Fort Worth. [Sida Bot. Misc. 20.] Noyes,
      R. D. 2000. Biogeographical and evolutionary insights on Erigeron and allies (Asteraceae) from
      ITS sequence data. Pl. Syst. Evol. 220: 93–114.</reference>
    <reference>Noyes, R. D. and L. H. Rieseberg. 1999. ITS sequence data support a single origin for
      North American Astereae (Asteraceae) and reflect deep geographic divisions in Aster s.l. Amer.
      J. Bot. 86: 398–412.</reference>
    <reference>Ruffin, J. 1974. A taxonomic evaluation of the genera Amphiachyris, Amphipappus,
      Greenella, Gutierrezia, Gymnosperma, Thurovia, and Xanthocephalum (Compositae). Sida 5:
      301–333.</reference>
    <reference>Ruffin, J. 1977. Palynological survey of the genera Amphiachyris, Amphipappus,
      Greenella, Gutierrezia, Gymnosperma, and Xanthocephalum (Compositae). Contr. Gray Herb. 207:
      117–131.</reference>
    <reference>Semple, J. C. and L. Brouillet. 1980. A synopsis of North American asters: The
      subgenera, sections and subsections of Aster and Lasallea. Amer. J. Bot. 67:
      1010–1026.</reference>
    <reference>Semple, J. C., S. B. Heard, and L. Brouillet. 2002. Cultivated and Native Asters of
      Ontario (Compositae: Astereae). Aster L. (Including Asteromoea Blume, Diplactis Raf. and
      Kalimeris (Cass.) Cass.), Callistephus Cass., Galatella Cass., Doellingeria Nees, Oclemena E.
      L. Greene, Eurybia (Cass.) S. F. Gray, Canadanthus Nesom, and Symphyotrichum Nees (Including
      Virgulus Raf.). Waterloo. [Univ. Waterloo Biol. Ser. 41.] Semple, J. C. and J. L. A. Hood.
      2005. Pappus variation in North American Asters. I. Double, triple and quadruple pappus in
      Symphyotrichum and related aster genera (Asteraceae: Astereae). Sida 21:
      2141–2159.</reference>
    <reference>Semple, J. C., G. S. Ringius, and J. J. Zhang. 1999. The Goldenrods of Ontario:
      Solidago L. and Euthamia Nutt., ed. 3. Waterloo. [Univ. Waterloo Biol. Ser. 39.] Semple, J. C.
      and L. Tebby. 1999. A cladistic analysis of subtribe Chrysopsidinae (Asteraceae: Astereae).
      In: International Botanical Congress. [1999.] Abstracts. XVI International Botanical Congress,
      St. Louis, USA, August 1–7, 1999. [St. Louis.] Abstr. 2852, poster 401. Solbrig, O. T. 1960.
      The status of the genera Amphiachyris, Amphipappus, Greenella, Gutierrezia, Gymnosperma, and
      Xanthocephalum (Compositae). Rhodora 62: 43–53.</reference>
    <reference>Suh, Y. and B. B. Simpson. 1990. Phylogenetic analysis of chloroplast DNA in North
      American Gutierrezia and related genera (Asteraceae: Astereae). Syst. Bot.
      660–670.</reference>
    <reference>Turner, B. L. 1987b. Taxonomic study of Machaeranthera, sections Machaeranthera and
      Hesperastrum (Asteraceae). Phytologia 62: 207–266.</reference>
    <reference>Urbatsch, L. E., R. P. Roberts, and V. Karaman. 2003. Phylogenetic evaluation of
      Xylothamia, Gundlachia, and related genera (Asteraceae, Astereae) based on ETS and ITS nrDNA
      sequence data. Amer. J. Bot. 90: 634–649.</reference>
    <reference>Xiang, C. and J. C. Semple. 1996. Molecular systematic study of Aster sensu lato and
      related genera (Asteraceae: Astereae) based on chloroplast DNA restriction site analyses and
      mainly North American taxa. In: D. J. N. Hind et al., eds. 1996. Proceedings of the
      International Compositae Conference, Kew, 1994. 2 vols. Kew. Vol. 1, pp. 393–423.</reference>
    <reference> Zanowiak, D. J. 1991. An Analysis of Systematic and Phyletic Relationships
      within Baccharidinae (Asteraceae: Astereae). Ph.D. dissertation. Texas A&amp;M University.
      Zhang, J. J. 1996. A Molecular Biosystematic Study on North American Solidago and Related
      Genera (Asteraceae: Astereae) Based on Chloroplast DNA RFLP Analysis (Phylogenetics). Ph.D.
      dissertation. University of Waterloo.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Trees, shrubs (sometimes clambering, sprawling, or vinelike), or subshrubsKey A, p.
        5</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals, biennials, or perennials.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals or biennialsKey B, p. 8</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>PerennialsKey C, p. 12</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_head>Key A</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries unequal and disposed in vertical ranks.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads radiate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves cauline, blades 1-nerved (sometimes with 1–2 fainter lateral
        pairs)</statement>
      <determination>161. Chrysoma (in part) , p. 105</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and cauline, blades 3–5-nerved (veins raised, parallel)</statement>
      <determination>168. Petradoria (in part) , p. 171</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads discoid.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and cauline, blades 3-nerved; heads in glomerate clusters grouped in
        flat-topped, corymbiform arrays; phyllaries yellowish, sometimes green distally</statement>
      <determination>157. Bigelowia, p. 95</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves cauline, blades 1-nerved (sometimes with 1–2 fainter lateral pairs); heads
        (sometimes clustered) in paniculiform, corymbiform, or cymiform arrays, or borne singly;
        phyllaries stramineous, tan, or green, green or purplish distally.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces gland-dotted (in pits); heads in dense, cymiform arrays</statement>
      <determination>161. Chrysoma (in part), p. 105</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces gland-dotted (sessile) or stipitate-glandular; heads borne singly or in
        condensed, cymiform clusters, grouped in paniculiform or corymbiform arrays, or in
        congested, cymiform to corymbiform arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads in congested, cymiform to corymbiform arrays; disc florets 4–15; cypselae
        oblong to obconic</statement>
      <determination>171. Lorandersonia (in part), p. 177</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly or in condensed, cymiform clusters grouped in paniculiform or
        corymbiform arrays; disc florets (2–)5–6(–40); cypselae subcylindric</statement>
      <determination>175. Chrysothamnus (in part), p. 187</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries equal or unequal and disposed in spirals.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Trees, shrubs (sometimes clambering, sprawling, or vinelike).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants unisexual, often glutinous; heads discoid</statement>
      <determination>140. Baccharis (in part) , p. 23</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants bisexual, sometimes glutinous, gland-dotted, or stipitate-glandular; heads
        radiate, discoid, or disciform.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads discoid or disciform.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads disciform (pistillate florets 4–9), in compact glomerules grouped in terminal
        corymbiform arrays; disc corollas orange-yellow; pappi 0, or minute crowns</statement>
      <determination>156. Gymnosperma, p. 94</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads discoid, borne singly, or in clusters grouped in cymiform or racemiform
        arrays, or in cymiform, spiciform, racemiform, paniculiform, or corymbiform arrays; disc
        corollas yellow or white; pappi of scales or bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae 3–4-angled, strigoso-sericeous; pappi of (5–8) linear-lanceolate
        scales</statement>
      <determination>166. Eastwoodia, p. 169</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae prismatic, terete, subterete, or compressed, glabrous or ± densely hairy;
        pappi of bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems not resinous; leaves entire or toothed (teeth sometimes bristly); heads
        usually in spiciform, racemiform, narrowly paniculiform, or corymbiform arrays, rarely borne
        singly;phyllaries not resinous; pappi reddish brown</statement>
      <determination>206. Hazardia (in part), p. 445</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems resinous; leaves entire; heads borne singly or in clusters (at branch tips),
        and/or in usually cymiform or racemiform, sometimes paniculiform or thyrsiform arrays;
        phyllaries resinous; pappi whitish tan to reddish.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves filiform, linear, lanceolate, or spatulate (adaxially sulcate, concave or
        plane), margins sometimes undulate or crisped; heads borne singly or in usually cymiform or
        racemiform, sometimes paniculiform or thyrsiform arrays; involucres hemispheric or obconic;
        disc florets 4–70, corolla lobes equal (cypselae 2–10 mm)</statement>
      <determination>148. Ericameria (in part), p. 50</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves filiform, margins flat or involute; heads in clusters at branch tips,
        grouped in cymiform or racemiform arrays; involucres turbinate; disc florets 3–7, corolla
        lobes unequal (cypselae 1–3 mm)</statement>
      <determination>151. Gundlachia, p. 84</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads radiate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Shrubs clambering, sprawling, or vinelike; rays pale rose-purple to pale pink
        (Atlantic coastal plain)</statement>
      <determination>211. Ampelaster , p. 460</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Shrubs not clambering, sprawling, or vinelike; rays yellow or white.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants spinescent (at least with age); corollas yellow.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves sometimes in axillary fascicles; heads borne singly or in loose, corymbiform
        arrays; ray florets 5–14; disc florets 13–80, bisexual, fertile; pappi of barbellate
        scales</statement>
      <determination>173. Acamptopappus, p. 184</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves not in axillary fascicles; heads (2–4) in glomerate clusters, these grouped
        in corymbiform arrays; ray florets 1–2; disc florets 3–7, functionally staminate; pappi of
        flattened bristles (those of discs sometimes undulate to twisted)</statement>
      <determination>174. Amphipappus, p. 186</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants not spinescent; corollas white or yellow.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves entire or toothed (teeth sometimes bristly; bases clasping or subclasping);
        heads usually in racemiform, narrowly paniculiform, or corymbiform arrays, rarely borne
        singly; phyllaries in 5–9 series; cypselae fusiform to deltoid, 4–5-nerved; pappi reddish
        brown</statement>
      <determination>206. Hazardia (in part), p. 445</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves entire (bases not clasping); heads borne singly or in cymiform or racemiform
        (sometimes paniculiform or thyrsiform) arrays; phyllaries in 3–6+ series; cypselae ellipsoid
        to obconic or obovoid, ± 5–12-ribbed or -nerved; pappi whitish tan to reddish.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres hemispheric, obconic, or cylindric; disc corolla lobes equal; cypselae
        prismatic</statement>
      <determination>148. Ericameria (in part), p. 50</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres turbinate; disc corolla lobes unequal; cypselae± turbinate</statement>
      <determination>152. Neonesomia, p. 85</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Subshrubs.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants unisexual; heads discoid</statement>
      <determination>140. Baccharis (in part) , p. 23</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants bisexual; heads radiate, disciform, or discoid.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads disciform or discoid.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems eglandular; leaves entire.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly or in cymiform-racemiform arrays; involucres 11–15(–17) mm;
        florets 4–7; cypselae oblong, 5–6-ribbed, glabrous</statement>
      <determination>159. Cuniculotinus, p. 100</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly in cymiform arrays; involucres 5–7 mm; florets 12–25+; cypselae
        narrowly oblong, 8–13-nerved (per face), ± sericeous</statement>
      <determination>198. Arida (in part), p. 401</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems gland-dotted or stipitate-glandular; leaves entire, toothed, or
        pinnatifid.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly (at tips of branches) or in corymbiform arrays; cypselae
        dimorphic (ray ± 3-sided, disc compressed)</statement>
      <determination>195. Xanthisma (in part), p. 383</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads usually in spiciform, racemiform, corymbiform, or cymiform arrays, rarely
        borne singly; cypselae monomorphic (terete, subterete, or compresssed).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres broadly urceolate to hemispheric or globose; phyllaries usually looped
        to hooked, usually resinous</statement>
      <determination>202. Grindelia (in part), p. 424</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres campanulate, obconic, turbinate, or cylindric; phyllaries not hooped or
        hooked, not resinous.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves persistent; heads in compact clusters grouped in corymbiform arrays;
        involucres 3–9.5 mm; disc corollas goblet-shaped (tubes elongating, elevating throats above
        involucres at flowering); cypselae obpyramidal, 5–11-ribbed (ribs sometimes thick and
        resinous), sericeous</statement>
      <determination>205. Isocoma, p. 439</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves withering by flowering; heads in spiciform, racemiform, or cymiform
        arrays; involucres 11–13 mm; disc corollas ± tubular (tubes not elevating throats); cypselae
        fusiform to deltoid, 4–5-nerved, glabrous</statement>
      <determination>206. Hazardia (in part), p. 445</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads radiate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rays white, light blue, or purple.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants often thorny (thorns green); leaves usually entire, rarely 1–2-denticulate;
        heads borne singly or in loose, corymbo-paniculiform arrays; involucres 4.5–7.5 mm; rays
        white; disc corolla veins orange, resinous</statement>
      <determination>190. Chloracantha (in part) , p. 358</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants not thorny; leaves entire, dentate or serrate (teeth spinulose); heads borne
        singly or in corymbiform arrays; involucres 6–20 mm; rays white, light blue, or purple; disc
        corolla veins not orange-resinous.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae 7–10-nerved, glabrous (Animas River Basin, n New Mexico,s
        Colorado)</statement>
      <determination>192. Herrickia (in part), p. 361</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae 2–7-nerved or -ribbed, hairy.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae dimorphic (ray 3-sided, disc compressed), obovoid or oblong</statement>
      <determination>195. Xanthisma (in part), p. 383</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae monomorphic (compressed or terete), ovoid, fusiform, cuneiform, or
        linear.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae flattened, 2–(3–4)-nerved; pappi of outer, shorter bristles orscales plus
        inner, longer bristles</statement>
      <determination>150. Ionactis (in part), p. 82</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae ± compressed or not, 4–7-ribbed; pappi of ± unequal bristles (outer not in
        notably distinct series).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems glabrous or villous to tomentose, sometimes stipitate-glandular; phyllaries
        keeled; ray florets bisexual, fertile; cypselae ovoid, fusiform, or linear, 4-nerved,
        sericeous</statement>
      <determination>199. Xylorhiza (in part), p. 406</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems usually densely white-tomentose, sometimes glabrate or ± stipitate-glandular
        distally; phyllaries flat; ray florets neuter; cypselae cuneiform or linear, 5–7-ribbed,
        puberulent to pilose</statement>
      <determination>208. Corethrogyne (in part), p. 450</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rays yellow (sometimes drying red-purple).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries in vertical ranks; heads congested or glomerate, usually in corymbiform
        or cymiform, sometimes spiciform, arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and cauline (not crowded), 3–5-nerved (veins parallel, raised); heads
        in glomerules in corymbiform arrays; ray florets 1–3; disc florets functionally staminate,
        corolla lobes lanceolate; cypselae cylindric, plump orslightly compressed</statement>
      <determination>168. Petradoria (in part) , p. 171</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves cauline (often crowded), usually 1-nerved, sometimes with 1–2 collateral
        pairs; heads in congested cymiform or corymbiform arrays; ray florets (1–)6–8; disc florets
        bisexual, fertile; cypselae oblong to obconic or prismatic</statement>
      <determination>171. Lorandersonia (in part), p. 177</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries in spirals; heads borne singly, 3–6, or glomerate, in flat-topped or
        multi-storied, corymbiform arrays, or in ± loose corymbiform, racemiform, narrowly
        paniculiform, or spiciform arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres usually broadly urceolate, globose, or hemispheric; phyllaries filiform
        to linear, apices often looped or hooked, faces usually ± resinous</statement>
      <determination>202. Grindelia (in part), p. 424</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres cylindro-turbinate, turbinate, obconic, campanulate, or hemispheric;
        phyllaries ovate, lanceolate, oblanceolate, or lanceolate to linear, apices straight or
        recurved (not looped or hooked), faces sometimes gland-dotted (not resinous).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves pinnatifid (lobes bristle-tipped); pappi of setiform scales (or
        basally flattened bristles)</statement>
      <determination>195. Xanthisma (in part), p. 383</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves not pinnatifid; pappi of bristles and/or scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of scales</statement>
      <determination>155. Gutierrezia (in part), p. 88</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of bristles, or of outer, shorter scales plus inner, longer
        bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems prostrate to erect, mat-forming, branched; leaves cauline (crowded); heads
        borne singly</statement>
      <determination>167. Nestotus , p. 169</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems erect, not mat-forming, branched or simple; leaves basal and cauline or
        mostly cauline (then not crowded); heads in spiciform, racemiform, corymbiform, or cymiform
        arrays, or glomerate and/or pedunculate-solitary in flat-topped or multi-storied,
        corymbiform arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants rhizomatous; heads usually glomerate, sometimes pedunculate-solitary, in
        flat-topped or multi-storied, corymbiform arrays</statement>
      <determination>158. Euthamia (in part), p. 97</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted or fibrous-rooted; heads not glomerate, in spiciform, racemiform,
        corymbiform, subumbelliform, paniculiform, or cymiform arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves densely short-woolly (hairs flagelliform); heads in subumbelliform to
        paniculiform arrays; pappi of outer, triangular scales plus inner bristles in (2–)3 series;
        e North America</statement>
      <determination>182. Chrysopsis (in part), p. 213</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves glabrous, sparsely puberulent or stipitate-glandular, or
        scabroso-hispidulous (hairs not flagelliform); heads in spiciform, racemiform, corymbiform,
        or cymiform arrays, sometimes borne singly; pappi of unequal bristles in 1–4 series; w North
        America.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>40.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and cauline, margins entire; involucres cylindro-turbinate; ray
        florets 5–8; cypselae narrowly oblong, 8-nerved, moderately strigose</statement>
      <determination>165. Columbiadoria, p. 167</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mostly cauline, margins serrate (teeth bristle-tipped); involucres
        campanulate; ray florets 5–18; cypselae fusiform to deltoid, 4–5-nerved,
        glabrous</statement>
      <determination>206. Hazardia (in part), p. 445</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_head>Key B</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads discoid or disciform (sometimes radiant).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads discoid.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of (1–)2–10 setiform to subulate scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants eglandular; heads sessile or subsessile, in secund, spiciform
        arrays</statement>
      <determination>153. Thurovia (in part), p. 86</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants usually gland-dotted and/or vernicose; heads usually in corymbiform arrays,
        rarely borne singly</statement>
      <determination>202. Grindelia (in part), p. 424</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi 0, or of 3–55 bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants (gracile) 2–14 cm; leaves (linear to filiform) entire; pappi 0, or of (3–)5
        bristles or setiform scales</statement>
      <determination>145. Pentachaeta (in part), p. 46</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants (1–)2–100 cm; leaves entire, toothed, or pinnately lobed; pappi of 3–55
        bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf adaxial faces glabrous, puberulent, or canescent; involucres turbinate;
        phyllaries usually spreading to reflexed, rarely appressed; corollas yellow (limbs of
        peripheral florets not expanded); pappus bristles white to tawny, distinct</statement>
      <determination>197. Dieteria (in part), p. 395</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf adaxial faces sparsely tomentose to woolly; involucres hemispheric, obconic,
        campanulate, or narrowly cylindric; phyllaries erect or recurved; corollas white, pink,
        lavender, or yellow (limbs of peripheral florets freqently palmately expanded, heads ±
        radiant); pappus bristles tan to reddish, distinct or connate</statement>
      <determination>209. Lessingia, p. 452</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads disciform.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals (eglandular); disc corollas without prominent orange veins, style
        appendages lanceolate or linear.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly; peripheral pistillate (or reduced ray) florets in 1 series;
        pappi 0, or of (3–)5 bristles or subulate scales (not surpassing corollas at flow-ering);
        grassy areas, chaparral, California</statement>
      <determination>145. Pentachaeta (in part), p. 46</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads in paniculiform arrays (borne singly in small plants); peripheral pistillate
        florets in 2+ series; pappi of (20–)25–40(–55) bristles (surpassing corollas at flowering);
        ± saline habitats, edges of ponds, irrigation ditches, salted road-sides, saltmarshes; Rocky
        Mountains eastward</statement>
      <determination>214. Symphyotrichum (in part), p. 465</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Biennials or annuals (usually gland-dotted or stipitate-glandular, sometimes
        eglandular, in Conyza ); disc corollas sometimes with prominent orange veins ( Conyza,
        Erigeron ), style appendages deltate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Biennials; stems ascending; heads borne singly (at ends of branches), disc corolla
        throats somewhat inflated, white-indurate; pappi of outer, shorter setae plus 15–20 inner,
        barbellate bristles</statement>
      <determination>186. Erigeron (in part), p. 256</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals; stems erect; heads usually in corymbiform, paniculiform or racemiform
        arrays, rarely borne singly; disc corollas narrowly funnelform (throats neither inflated nor
        indurate); pappi of 10–30 barbellate bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces often stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted; phyllaries lacking orange to
        brown midnerves; cypselae densely sericeous, ± strigillose, or glabrous, often
        stipitate-glandular and/or gland-dotted</statement>
      <determination>142. Laënnecia (in part), p. 36</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces eglandular; phyllaries with orange to brownish midnerves; cypselae
        glabrous or strigillose, eglandular</statement>
      <determination>187. Conyza (in part) , p. 348</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads radiate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rays usually yellow or orange, sometimes cream, whitish, or white.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi usually 0, or coroniform, or of scales, rarely of relatively short bristles (
        Xanthocephalum ).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves eglandular; phyllaries subequal (± navicular, inner usually each ±
        enfolding floret); receptacles sparsely paleate between ray and disc florets (paleae
        resembling phyllaries); ray corollas yellowish, often tinged with red or purple (laminae
        inconspicuous); disc corolla lobes 2–4</statement>
      <determination>146. Rigiopappus, p. 48</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves (at least partly) stipitate-glandular; phyllaries unequal (not
        navicular nor each enfolding floret); receptacles epaleate; ray corollas yellow to
        orange-yellow or occasionally suffused with red (laminae conspicuous); disc corolla lobes
        5.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corollas abruptly ampliate, throats usually campanulate, sometimes
        funnelform.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae terete or slightly compressed with rounded edges or 4–6-sided, without
        prominent nerves, glabrous or slightly strigose; pappi of rays 0, outer discs 0 or minute
        crowns, inner 0, or usually of scales, rarely bristles; Arizona, Texas</statement>
      <determination>203. Xanthocephalum, p. 436</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae ± triquetrous, 3-nerved, sericeous; pappi of 2–8 subulate, barbellate
        scales; California</statement>
      <determination>207. Benitoa, p. 450</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corollas not abruptly ampliate, throats funnelform or cylindric.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves not glutinous; heads in paniculiform or corymbiform arrays; phyllaries
        glutinous; disc florets functionally staminate</statement>
      <determination>154. Amphiachyris, p. 87</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves glutinous; heads borne singly or in clusters of 3–6; phyllaries not
        glutinous; disc florets bisexual, fertile</statement>
      <determination>155. Gutierrezia (in part), p. 88</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of bristles, or of outer, shorter setae or scales plus inner, longer
        bristles, or of outer bristles plus inner, subulate to setiform scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves usually gland-dotted and/or resinous; involucres usually globose
        to hemispheric or broadly urceolate, sometimes campanulate or obconic; phyllaries hooked,
        looped, patent, recurved, straight, or incurved</statement>
      <determination>202. Grindelia (in part), p. 424</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves usually not resinous, sometimes gland-dotted or
        stipitate-glandular; involucres hemispheric, campanulate, turbinate, obconic, or cylindric;
        phyllaries appressed, spreading, reflexed, or recurved.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae dimorphic (rays often ± 3-angled, discs ± compressed).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <statement>Biennials; stems strigose and/or hispid, stipitate-glandular; pappi of rays 0, of
        discs of outer scales plus 30–45 inner bristles</statement>
      <determination>185. Heterotheca (in part), p. 230</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals or biennials; stems glabrous or hispid, gland-dotted or
        stipitate-glandular; pappi of basally flattened bristles (or setiform scales) in 2–4
        series.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly or in corymbiform arrays (peduncles not cobwebby); involucres
        4–10 mm; disc corolla throats gradually ampliate, ± funnelform; style-branch appendages
        lanceolate</statement>
      <determination>195. Xanthisma (in part), p. 383</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly or (2–3) in paniculiform or subcorymbiform-cymiform arrays
        (peduncles often cobwebby); involucres 7–16 mm; disc corolla throats abruptly ampliate,
        funnelform; style-branch appendages deltate</statement>
      <determination>204. Rayjacksonia (in part), p. 437</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae monomorphic (all ± compressed or all ± 3-angled).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems glabrous or glabrate, eglandular; cauline leaves narrowly oblanceolate,
        linear, or filiform, margins entire, ciliate, faces glabrous or glabrate, eglandular; heads
        borne singly (at ends of branches); phyllaries not thickened or keeled; rays yellow and
        often reddish or purplish-tinged.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres campanulate to turbinate; phyllaries equal or subequal; cypselae
        oblanceoloid, 3–5-nerved, not beaked; pappus bristles (3–)5–20 (usually in multiples of 5)
        in 1 series</statement>
      <determination>145. Pentachaeta (in part), p. 46</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres ± cylindric to turbinate or obconic; phyllaries unequal; cypselae ±
        fusifom, 5-nerved, beaked; pappus bristles (12–)30–40 in (1–)2 series (outer
        shorter)</statement>
      <determination>147. Tracyina, p. 50</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems ± hispid, pilose, woolly or arachnose, sometimes glabrous,
        stipitate-glandular or eglandular; cauline leaves ovate, oblanceolate, elliptic, lanceolate,
        or linear, margins entire, serrate, or apically dentate, sometimes coarsely ciliate, faces
        usually hairy, sometimes glabrous, sometimes stipitate-glandular; heads borne singly or in
        corymbiform, subumbelliform, or paniculiform arrays; phyllaries thickened or keeled; ray
        florets yellow to yellow-orange.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Biennials, stems arachnose to woolly or glabrous, often stipitate-glandular; heads
        in corymbiform, subumbelliform, or paniculiform arrays; pappus bristles relatively fine
        (mainly Florida, Atlantic coastal plain)</statement>
      <determination>182. Chrysopsis (in part), p. 213</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals, stems sparsely hispid or pilose, sometimes stipitate-glandular; heads
        borne singly or in loose paniculiform arrays; pappus bristles relatively thick and rigid,
        outer sometimes scalelike.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 1-nerved, faces hispido-pilose; involucres campanulate, 6–9 mm; phyllaries
        linear, sparsely stipitate-glandular; cypselae obconic, compressed, smooth or slightly
        ribbed; Gulf coastal plain, Mississippi embayment, adjacent lowlands</statement>
      <determination>181. Bradburia (in part) , p. 211</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 3-nerved (nerves ± parallel), faces thin-arachnose (in minute, abaxial
        lacunae); involucres narrowly turbinate to subcylindric, 4–8 mm; phyllaries lanceolate to
        linear-lanceolate, eglandular; cypselae turbinate, terete to weakly angled, 6–14-nerved; sc
        United States, adjacent Mexico</statement>
      <determination>184. Croptilon (in part), p. 228</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rays white, pink, purple, or blue.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Receptacles conic; pappi 0, or coroniform, or of scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves usually pinnatifid to dentate, sometimes entire; rays without midstripe
        abaxially; cypselae not or slightly compressed, glabrous or sparsely strigose (hairs not
        glochidiform); pappi cartilaginous crowns, or crowns of scales or setae, or 0.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants gland-dotted; cypselae oblong to narrowly obovoid, slightly compressed,
        2-nerved, sometimes gland-dotted</statement>
      <determination>141. Egletes, p. 35</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants eglandular; cypselae columnar to prismatic, usually 4-angled, 4–12-ribbed
        (ribs relatively thick), eglandular</statement>
      <determination>188. Aphanostephus (in part), p. 351</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves usually entire, sometimes dentate or lobed; rays usually with pink or
        purplish midstripe abaxially; cypselae strongly compressed or flattened, glabrous or hairy
        (hairs glochidiform); pappi usually of awns, scales, bristles, or 2-horned crowns, sometimes
        0.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries in 4–6+ series, unequal; pappi of 12–35+ lanceolate or subulate to
        setiform scales</statement>
      <determination>176. Townsendia (in part), p. 193</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries in 2(–3) series, subequal; pappi 0, or crowns of setae or scales, or of
        2 long plus ring of shorter awns.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves spatulate-obovate (basal), narrower distally; cypsela margins ribbed; pappi
        0, or crowns of setae or scales</statement>
      <determination>177. Astranthium (in part) , p. 203</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves oblanceolate; cypsela margins winglike; pappi of 2 long plususually ring of
        shorter awns</statement>
      <determination>178. Dichaetophora, p. 205</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Receptacles flat to convex; pappi usually of bristles (sometimes only discs or
        rays), or of setiform scales, or of bristles plus scales, or toothed cups with 1 bristle,
        sometimes of scales, or coroniform, or 0.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corollas with orange-resinous veins.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads borne singly; pappi crowns (sometimes each with 1 bristle) or of alternating
        scales and bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries in 2–6 series, unequal; pappi hyaline crowns (nearly 0) oralternating
        bristles and scales</statement>
      <determination>179. Chaetopappa (in part), p. 206</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries in 1(–2) series, equal; pappi toothed crowns plus 1 distallyplumose
        bristle, or of 1–12 bristles alternating with scales</statement>
      <determination>180. Monoptilon, p. 210</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads usually in corymbiform or paniculiform arrays, sometimes borne singly; pappi
        of bristles, or of outer, shorter setae or scales plus inner, longer bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corolla throats slightly indurate and inflated; pappi usually of outer setae
        or scales plus 10–30 inner bristles, sometimes 0</statement>
      <determination>186. Erigeron (in part), p. 256</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corolla throats not indurate or inflated; pappi of 15–25+ bristles in 1
        series</statement>
      <determination>187. Conyza (in part), p. 348</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corolla veins not orange-resinous.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of 12–35+ scales</statement>
      <determination>176. Townsendia (in part), p. 193</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of 5–80+ bristles or setiform scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappus bristles usually 5, rarely 0</statement>
      <determination>145. Pentachaeta (in part), p. 46</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappus bristles or setiform scales usually 20–80+ (ray sometimes 0).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems glabrous or hairy in lines distally, sometimes stipitate-glandular distally;
        leaf margins entire, subserrate, serrate, or pinnately lobed; heads usually in paniculiform
        or corymbiform arrays, sometimes borne singly.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems distally stipitate-glandular; cauline leaf bases clasping to subclasping,
        margins entire, coarsely toothed, or pinnately lobed, faces appressed-hairy or glabrous
        (distal stipitate-glandular); heads in corymbiform arrays; involucres broadly turbinate to
        hemispheric; phyllaries herbaceous distally, stipitate-glandular; ray florets 20–70 in 1
        series, corollas white, blue, or purple; pappi: rays 0, discs of bristles</statement>
      <determination>213. Psilactis, p. 462</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems eglandular; cauline leaf bases attenuate, cuneate, or rounded, margins entire
        or serrulate, faces glabrous, eglandular; heads in paniculiform arrays; involucres
        cylindro-campanulate, cylindric, or turbinate; phyllaries with distinct green zones
        distally, eglandular; ray florets 16–54 in 1–3 series, or 90–110 in 4–5 series, corollas
        white, pink, or lavender; pappi of bristles</statement>
      <determination>214. Symphyotrichum (in part), p. 465</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems hairy or glabrous, sometimes stipitate-glandular; leaf margins entire,
        serrate, dentate, laciniate, lobed, or ± deeply 1–2-pinnatifid (teeth or lobes apiculate,
        bristly, or spiny); heads borne singly (at ends of branches) or in cymiform or corymbiform
        arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves deeply 1–2-pinnatifid, at least many lobes or teeth acute and
        bristly</statement>
      <determination>196. Machaeranthera, p. 394</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves entire or toothed or lobed, if 1–2-pinnatifid, teeth or lobes often rounded,
        sometimes apiculate, mostly not bristly.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants hairy, sometimes stipitate-glandular; leaves entire or toothed; ray pappi of
        40–50 bristles</statement>
      <determination>197. Dieteria (in part), p. 395</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants glabrous and leaves entire or toothed (ciliate or teeth bristle-tipped or
        apiculate), or plants hairy, sometimes stipitate-glandular, and leaves 1–2-pinnatifid; ray
        pappi usually 0 (if 20–30 bristles, leaves 1–2-pinnatifid)</statement>
      <determination>198. Arida (in part), p. 401</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_head>Key C</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads discoid or disciform.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads disciform.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf margins entire or spinulose-serrate; heads borne singly or 2–3 in ±
        corymbiform arrays; cypselae subcylindric-fusiform, 3–4-angled, ± compressed, with 10–12
        faint nerves; pappi of 15–60 rigid, unequal, smooth bristles in 1 series</statement>
      <determination>201. Pyrrocoma (in part), p. 413</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf margins entire, dentate, or pinnatifid (lobed); heads in corymbiform
        arrays; cypselae oblong or oblong-obovoid to elliptic or obovoid, ± compressed or flattened,
        2(–4)-nerved or ± nerved on edges; pappi of outer setae or scales plus 5–40 bristles, or of
        30–40+ bristles in 2 series (outer usually shorter).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants ± densely white-tomentose (at least some surfaces); phyllaries 1-nerved,
        nerves not golden-resinous; disc corollas yellowish, throats narrowly funnelform, not
        indurate, veins light, not resinous; pappi of 30–40+ bristles in 2 series (outer usually
        shorter)</statement>
      <determination>142. Laënnecia (in part), p. 36</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants ± hirsute or pilose; phyllaries usually 1–3-nerved, nerves golden-resinous;
        disc corollas yellow, strongly constricted basally, throats sometimes strongly
        inflated-indurate, nerves often orange-resinous; pappi of outer setae (or 0) plus 7–25 inner
        bristles</statement>
      <determination>186. Erigeron (in part), p. 256</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads discoid.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corollas white or pale yellow; pappi of 10 basally connate scales</statement>
      <determination>153. Thurovia (in part), p. 86</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corollas yellow (white in Brintonia ); pappi usually of distinct bristles or
        of outer, shorter setae or scales plus inner, longer bristles, sometimes 0.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves resinous, gland-dotted; phyllary apices hooked or looped, or
        slightly recurved to straight; pappi of 2–8 bristles</statement>
      <determination>202. Grindelia (in part), p. 424</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves sometimes resinous, sometimes stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted;
        phyllary apices straight to squarrose; pappi of 10+ bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary midveins translucent and swollen at least basally (not
        resinous).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corollas white</statement>
      <determination>162. Brintonia, p. 106</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Disc corollas yellow</statement>
      <determination>163. Solidago (in part), p. 107</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary midveins usually not notably swollen (orange-resinous in Erigeron
        ).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary and corolla nerves orange-resinous; pappi of outer, shorter setae or
        scales plus inner, longer bristles</statement>
      <determination>186. Erigeron (in part), p. 256</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary and corolla nerves not orange-resinous, or only corolla nerves
        orange-resinous; pappi of equal or unequal bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries subequal, foliaceous</statement>
      <determination>169. Toiyabea, p. 172</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries unequal (sometimes subequal, then outer not foliaceous), outer ±
        herbaceous (sometimes foliaceous), or chartaceous, or proximally indurate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries keeled, distally only with relatively small green zones or green along
        midveins; pappus bristles in 2–3 series (outer in notably shorter series or relatively
        few).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves cauline (proximal withering by flowering), margins without coarse spreading
        cilia near bases; phyllary margins often reddish, sometimes hyaline, abaxial faces glabrous
        or glabrate to woolly, sometimes stipitate-glandular</statement>
      <determination>143. Eucephalus (in part), p. 39</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and cauline (basal and proximal withering by flowering), margins with
        coarse spreading cilia near bases or on petioles; phyllary margins not reddish, scarious,
        abaxial faces ± hispid or stipitate-glandular</statement>
      <determination>185. Heterotheca (in part), p. 230</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries usually flat, sometimes keeled, distally herbaceous or green; pappi of
        equal or unequal bristles in 1–3 series (outer not in notably shorter series).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces densely scabrous and short-stipitate-glandular; phyllaries ± keeled
        proxi-mally (Esmeralda County, Nevada)</statement>
      <determination>172. Tonestus (in part), p. 181</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces glabrous or canescent, ± puberulent, hispidulous, tomentose, or villous,
        and/or sometimes ± stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted; phyllaries sometimes
        keeled.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and cauline, basal and proximal petiolate, distal sessile; disc floret
        style appendages lanceolate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants densely stipitate-glandular, with caudices; stems densely clustered, simple;
        leaf blades obovate or oblong to broadly oblanceolate; phyllaries keeled; disc corolla
        throats cylindric; cypselae white strigoso-hirsute</statement>
      <determination>194. Triniteurybia, p. 382</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants sparsely, if at all, stipitate-glandular, taprooted; stems single, usually
        branched; leaf blades lanceolate to oblanceolate; phyllaries flat; disc corolla throats
        funnelform; cypselae sparsely appressed-hairy</statement>
      <determination>197. Dieteria (in part), p. 395</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves cauline, sessile; disc floret style appendages triangular.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary margins scarious; disc corolla lobes unequal; cypselae obpyramidal,
        sericeous; pappi of 40–50 tawny bristles</statement>
      <determination>205. Isocoma (in part), p. 439</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary margins not scarious; disc corolla lobes equal; cypselae prismatic,
        narrowly turbinate, fusiform, or deltoid, glabrous or sparsely scabrous; pappi of 15–30
        reddish brown to brownish bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems glabrous or scabrous, eglandular; leaf bases not subclasping, margins entire;
        cypselae prismatic or narrowly turbinate; pappus bristles barbellate</statement>
      <determination>200. Oönopsis (in part), p. 410</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems scabrous to sparsely tomentulose, distally stipitate-glandular; leaf bases
        subclasping, margins serrate; cypselae fusiform to deltoid; pappus bristles
        smooth</statement>
      <determination>206. Hazardia (in part), p. 445</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads radiate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rays usually yellow or orange, sometimes cream-colored or white.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi 0, or crowns, or of scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves cauline (basal withering by flowering), blades linear to lanceolate or
        spatulate, stipitate-glandular; heads borne singly or in clusters of 3–6; phyllaries in 2–4
        series; cypselae clavate or cylindric, not compresssed, 5–8-nerved, white-hairy (hairs
        clavate to bulbous); pappi usually of 5–10 scales, sometimes crowns or 0</statement>
      <determination>155. Gutierrezia (in part), p. 88</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal (present at flowering) and cauline, blades spatulate, eglandular;
        heads borne singly (± sessile); phyllaries in 3–7+ series; cypselae obovoid to lanceoloid,
        flattened, 2-nerved, hairy (hairs glochidiform); pappi of 10–12 (ray) or 20–35+ (disc),
        lanceolate to subulate or setiform scales</statement>
      <determination>176. Townsendia (in part), p. 193</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of bristles, or of outer shorter setae, bristles, or scales plus inner,
        longer bristles, or of setiform awns.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of outer shorter setae, bristles, or scales plus inner, longer bristles in 2
        series.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted or with simple caudices (and fibrous-rooted); heads borne singly
        or in 2s or 3s; phyllaries in 2–3 series, equal or subequal, flat, usually 1–3-nerved
        (nerves golden-resinous); cypselae 2-nerved, not resinous</statement>
      <determination>186. Erigeron (in part), p. 256</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted, rhizomatous, or with branched caudices; heads in corymbiform, ±
        paniculiform, or subumbelliform arrays, sometimes borne singly; phyllaries in 3–5 series,
        unequal, usually thickened or keeled (not in Bradburia ), 1-nerved, not golden-resinous;
        cypselae smooth or 1–14-nerved or -ribbed, nerves or ribs sometimes resinous.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves silky-sericeous, rarely glabrate; leaves sessile, blades
        3–11-parallel-nerved (nerves sunken), linear to lanceolate or ovate (often grasslike),
        margins entire; involucres turbinate</statement>
      <determination>183. Pityopsis, p. 222</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves whitish-strigose, pilose, hispid, or arachnose to woolly (hairs
        flagelliform, soft), or glabrous; leaves sessile or basal petiolate, blades usually 1-nerved
        (veins reticulate, raised abaxially), spatulate, ovate-oblanceolate, ovate, elliptic,
        elliptic-oblong, oblanceolate, linear-lanceolate, or (usually distal) linear, margins
        entire, serrate, or dentate (sometimes coarsely ciliate); involucres campanulate or
        turbinate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants proximally woolly, distally arachnose or pilose (hairs flagelliform); basal
        leaves sessile</statement>
      <determination>182. Chrysopsis (in part), p. 213</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants sparsely to ± densely hispid, strigose, or pilose (hairs not flagelliform);
        basal leaves petiolate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perennials (taproots relatively short and/or caudices woody); basal petioles
        ciliate; cauline leaves much reduced distally, not clasping; heads borne singly or in lax
        paniculiform arrays; cypselae monomorphic, ray pappi of outer, shorter, setiform scales or
        bristles plus inner, longer bristles</statement>
      <determination>181. Bradburia (in part) , p. 211</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perennials (caudices woody); basal petioles long-strigoso-ciliate; cauline leaves ±
        reduced distally, sometimes clasping or subclasping; heads borne singly or in corymbiform,
        sometimes paniculiform arrays; cypselae dimorphic or monomorphic, ray pappi 0, or of outer,
        linear-lanceolate scales plus inner, longer bristles</statement>
      <determination>185. Heterotheca (in part), p. 230</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of setiform scales or bristles in 1–4 series.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves resinous, gland-dotted; involucres usually globose, hemispheric,
        or broadly urceolate, sometimes campanulate to obconic, usually ± resinous; pappi of (1–)2–8
        white, straight, contorted, or curled, barbellate or smooth awns or setiform scales in 1
        series</statement>
      <determination>202. Grindelia (in part), p. 424</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves usually not resinous, sometimes stipitate-glandular or
        gland-dotted; involucres hemispheric, campanulate, turbinate, or cylindric, not resinous,
        sometimes viscid or stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted; pappi of white, tawny, brownish, or
        reddish, barbellate bristles in 1–4 series.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants ± colonial (rhizomatous); heads usually glomerate, and/or sometimes
        pedunculate-solitary in flat-topped or multi-storied, corymbiform arrays</statement>
      <determination>158. Euthamia (in part), p. 97</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants colonial (sometimes rhizomatous, stems single or clustered, usually from ±
        woody taproots or caudices); heads borne singly, or (2–5) in paniculiform to corymbiform
        arrays, or in open or dense corymbiform, paniculiform (diversely shaped in Solidago ),
        racemiform, or spiciform arrays (if glomerate, not in flat-topped, corymbiform arrays,
        arrays not storied).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants rhizomatous (often colonial); heads in dense corymbiform or paniculiform
        arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves sometimes stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted; cauline leaf bases
        not clasping, faces sometimes resinous; heads in rounded, club-shaped, wand-shaped, or
        pyramid-shaped paniculiform (often secund) arrays, or in flat-topped, corymbiform arrays;
        involucres campanulate to cylindric, 3–12 mm, sometimes stipitate-glandular; phyllary
        midveins usually swollen, translucent, apices often with green zone, sometimes reflexed; ray
        florets 3–15(–21); disc corolla lobes lanceolate, erect to reflexed, style-branch appendages
        triangular; cypselae obconic, terete or ± compressed, 5–8-nerved; pappi of unequal bristles
        in 1–2(–3) series</statement>
      <determination>163. Solidago (in part), p. 107</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves stipitate-glandular; cauline leaf bases clasping or subclasping,
        faces resinous; heads in dense, flat-topped, corymbiform arrays; involucres campanulate to
        hemispheric, 10–11 mm, stipitate-glandular; phyllary midveins not swollen, apices
        green-tipped and spreading-reflexed; ray florets 12–20; disc corolla lobes triangular,
        spreading, style-branch appendages linear; cypselae fusiform, distinctly compressed,
        12–16-nerved (nerves whitish, raised); pappi of equal bristles in 2(–3) series; w United
        States</statement>
      <determination>164. Oreochrysum, p. 166</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants usually taprooted or with caudices, sometimes also from spreading roots
        (stems single or clustered); heads usually borne singly, sometimes (2–5) in loose
        corymbiform, cymiform, or paniculiform arrays, or in spiciform, racemiform, paniculiform, or
        corymbiform arrays, or glomerate (some Oönopsis ).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems sometimes clustered; heads usually in rounded, club-shaped, wand-shaped, or
        pyramid-shaped, paniculiform, or flat-topped, corymbiform (often secund) arrays, or in
        spiciform, racemiform, or cymiform arrays, sometimes borne singly.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants with caudices (stems clustered); leaves basal and cauline; heads in rounded,
        club-shaped, wand-shaped, or pyramid-shaped, paniculiform (often secund) or flat-topped
        corymbiform arrays; involucres campanulate to cylindric, 3–12 mm; phyllary midveins usually
        swollen and translucent; cypselae 5–8-nerved</statement>
      <determination>163. Solidago (in part), p. 107</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted; leaves mostly cauline; heads usually in spiciform, racemiform, or
        cymiform arrays, sometimes borne singly; involucres campanulate, 11–13 mm; phyllary midveins
        not swollen; cypselae 4–5-nerved (California, Oregon)</statement>
      <determination>206. Hazardia (in part), p. 445</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems single or clustered; heads borne singly or (2–5) in loose, corymbiform or
        paniculiform arrays, or 2–5(–15) in racemiform, spiciform, or corymbiform
        arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems single, usually branched; cypselae dimorphic (rays 3-angled, discs ±
        compressed), obovoid, oblong, or obscurely cordate, or rays broadly ellipsoid to obovoid
        (thick-walled) and discs broadly ellipsoid to clavate (thin-walled); pappi of coarse,
        barbellate bristles or setiform scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves 1–2-pinnatifid, cauline deeply incised to coarsely dentate or ±
        entire; involucres 6–10 mm; phyllaries stiff, leathery or bases indurate, apices herbaceous;
        disc corolla throats not abruptly ampliate, style-branch append-ages lanceolate</statement>
      <determination>195. Xanthisma (in part), p. 383</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves linear to oblanceolate, coarsely serrate to entire; involucres 7–16 mm;
        phyllaries herbaceous; disc corolla throats abruptly ampliate, style-branchappendages
        deltate</statement>
      <determination>204. Rayjacksonia (in part), p. 437</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems single or clustered, usually simple; cypselae monomorphic, terete or
        compressed to ± flattened, prismatic (3–4-angled), narrowly turbinate,
        subcylindric-fusiform, cylindric, or linear (usually thin-walled); pappi of relatively fine
        barbellate bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 3-nerved, faces arachnose (in minute, abaxial lacunae); involucresnarrowly
        turbinate to subcylindric; pappi tawny to reddish brown</statement>
      <determination>184. Croptilon (in part), p. 228</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 1–3(–5)-nerved, faces glabrous, scabrous, villous, sericeous, tomentose, or
        lanate; involucres hemispheric to broadly or narrowly campanulate; pappi whitish or
        brownish.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants sometimes mat-forming; stems clustered; leaves 1–5-nerved; margins of outer
        phyllaries scarious; pappi whitish.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems eglandular or stipitate-glandular, sometimes resinous; leaf margins entire,
        faces glabrous, scabrous, villous, or lanate, usually stipitate-glandular, sometimes
        eglandular; phyllaries unequal, proximally indurate, distally chartaceous or herbaceous; ray
        florets 5–17; cypselae usually sericeous, sometimes glabrous</statement>
      <determination>170. Stenotus, p. 174</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems densely stipitate-glandular (viscid); leaf margins entire, coarsely and
        irregularly serrate, dentate, or lobed, faces glabrous or scabrous, sometimes
        stipitate-glandular; phyllaries subequal, outer foliaceous; ray florets 11–23(–35); cypselae
        glabrous or villous</statement>
      <determination>172. Tonestus (in part) , p. 181</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants not mat-forming; stems single or clustered; leaves 1-nerved; margins of
        outer phyllaries herbaceous (sometimes proximally indurate); pappi brownish.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves glabrous or sparsely tomentose, eglandular; leaves basal (usually
        withering by flowering) and cauline, blades narrowly oblanceolate to lanceolate or linear,
        margins entire; heads borne singly, or 2–12 in glomerules or in loose, corymbiform arrays
        (subtended by little-reduced distal leaves); rays 6–25; cypselae prismatic or narrowly
        turbinate</statement>
      <determination>200. Oönopsis (in part), p. 410</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves loosely tomentose to woolly, sometimes gland-dotted or
        stipitate-glandular; leaves basal (persistent) and cauline, basal blades oblanceolate to
        elliptic or linear, cauline lanceolate, margins entire, spinulose-dentate or -serrate, or
        shallowly laciniate; heads borne singly or (2–15, ± sessile) in racemiform, spiciform, or
        loose, corymbiform arrays (at ends of scapiform stems or peduncles); rays 10–80; cypselae
        subcylindric-fusiform</statement>
      <determination>201. Pyrrocoma (in part), p. 413</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Rays white, pink, purple, or blue.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <statement>Receptacles conic; rays white (pink or purplish-tinged abaxially).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 5–20 cm (scapiform, short-rhizomatous); leaves mostly basal, margins
        crenate-serrate; phyllary margins herbaceous; rays in 3–4 series (closing at night);
        cypselae obconic, compressed, margins thickened, riblike, apices not cupped; pappi
        0</statement>
      <determination>139. Bellis, p. 22</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 5–50 cm (leafy, taprooted); leaves basal and cauline, margins entire or
        toothed to pinnatifid; phyllary margins broadly scarious; rays in 1(–2) series (not closing
        at night); cypselae columnar, usually 4-angled, 4–12-ribbed, apices usually cupped; pappi of
        awns, aristate scales, short bristles, or 0</statement>
      <determination>188. Aphanostephus (in part), p. 351</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <statement>Receptacles flat or convex; rays white, pink, blue, or purple (not tinged
        abaxially).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>40.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants colonial; stems branched (lateral branches strongly ascending, commonly
        modified to green thorns); leaves early withering; phyllaries (1–)3(–5)-nerved (usually wet
        sites in arid, sw United States)</statement>
      <determination>190. Chloracantha (in part), p. 358</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants sometimes colonial; stems single or clustered, simple or branched (not
        becoming thorny); at least distal leaves persistent through flowering; phyllaries usually
        1-nerved, seldom 3-nerved.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>41.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae usually obconic or obovoid, sometimes lanceoloid, flattened or compressed,
        margins ribbed (sometimes 1–2 nerves also on faces).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>42.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves cauline; phyllaries keeled.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>43.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 10–160 cm, minutely stipitate-glandular distally; proximalmost leaves
        scalelike, proximal withering by flowering, cauline distally increasing in size to mid
        stems, mid and distal blades lanceolate or lance-ovate to elliptic; heads in racemiform or
        corymbiform arrays; cypselae glabrous, pilose, or strigose, eglandular; pappi of outer,
        shorter plus inner, longer bristles in 3 series</statement>
      <determination>143. Eucephalus (in part), p. 39</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 4–30(–70) cm, sometimes stipitate-glandular; leaves persistent to flowering,
        mostly equal in size and shape, blades spatulate (proximal), linear, narrowly oblong, or
        elliptic-lanceolate; heads borne singly or in 2s or 3s, or in corymbiform arrays; cypselae
        densely strigose or sericeous, sometimes stipitate-glandular; pappi of outer shorter
        bristles or scales plus inner, longer bristles in 2 series</statement>
      <determination>150. Ionactis (in part), p. 82</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and/or cauline; phyllaries not keeled.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>44.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces eglandular; corolla lobes lanceolate; pappi of 20–30
        bristles</statement>
      <determination>138. Aster, p. 20</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf faces often gland-dotted; corolla lobes deltate or lance-deltate; pappi
        usually of 12–35+ scales, or of outer setae or scales plus 5–40(–50) bristles (sometimes
        only on rays or on discs), sometimes 0.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>45.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted or with branched caudices; heads borne singly; leaves usually
        entire, rarely toothed or lobed; phyllaries unequal, 1-nerved (nerves not golden-resinous);
        disc corolla throats funnelform; cypselae glabrous or hairy (hairs glochidiform); pappi of
        12–35+ scales</statement>
      <determination>176. Townsendia (in part), p. 193</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants rhizomatous, sometimes taprooted; heads borne singly or in corymbiform
        arrays; leaves entire, ± dentate, or pin-natifid; phyllaries equal to unequal, 1–3-nerved
        (nerves golden-resinous); disc corolla throats sometimes strongly inflated-indurate;
        cypselae glabrous, strigose, or sericeous; pappi usually of outer, shorter setae or scales
        plus 5–40(–50) inner, longer bristles (sometimes only on rays or discs),sometimes
        0</statement>
      <determination>186. Erigeron (in part), p. 256</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypseale ± narrowly obconic, obovoid, oblanceoloid, lanceoloid, fusiform, or
        linear, ± compressed or terete, sometimes winged or wings reduced and resembling marginal
        nerves or ribs (then pappi 0 or of minute scales), usually 3–12+-nerved on faces (margins
        not ribbed).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>46.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi 0, or crowns of setae or scales, or of scales, of alternating scales and
        bristles, or of outer, shorter setae or scales plus inner, longer bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>47.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>47.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary midnerves not swollen, not orange-resinous; disc style-branch appendages
        triangular or lanceolate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>48.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>48.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves usually entire, sometimes dentate or lobed, bases clasping or subclasping;
        phyllaries subequal; pappi rings or crowns of setae or scales</statement>
      <determination>177. Astranthium (in part), p. 203</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>48.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves entire, bases not clasping; phyllaries unequal; pappi thickened rings,
        crowns of scales (basally fused or distinct), or minute outer scales plus inner
        bristles</statement>
      <determination>179. Chaetopappa (in part), p. 206</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>47.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary midnerves (or 1–3 nerves) orange-resinous; disc style-branch appendages
        deltate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>49.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>49.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants not colonial (stems ± clustered), stems and leaves stipitate-glandular;
        basal leaves persistent or withering by flowering; heads borne singly or (2–10) in
        corymbiform arrays; pappi usually of outer setae or scales plus 5–40(–50) inner bristles,
        sometimes 0</statement>
      <determination>186. Erigeron (in part), p. 256</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>49.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants colonial, stems and leaves eglandular; basal leaves withering by flowering;
        heads in corymbiform or diffuse, paniculiform arrays; pappi of 2–3 awns plus shorter
        bristles or scales, or wholly of minute scales</statement>
      <determination>189. Boltonia, p. 353</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi of bristles or setiform scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>50.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>50.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae ± dimorphic (ray 3-sided and rounded abaxially, disc ± compressed); pappi
        of relatively coarse (± flattened) bristles or setiform scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>51.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>51.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems simple; leaves mostly basal, margins serrate or serrulate; involucres
        depressed-hemispheric; cypselae 3–9-ribbed on each face; pappus bristles coarsely
        barbellate</statement>
      <determination>195. Xanthisma (in part), p. 383</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>51.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems usually branched ; leaves basal (persistent in rosettes or withering) and
        cauline (distally ± reduced) or mostly cauline, margins pinnately lobed or pinnatifid,
        toothed, or entire; involucres turbinate, campanulate, or hemispheric; cypselae 8–13-nerved
        on each face; pappus bristles barbellulate</statement>
      <determination>198. Arida (in part), p. 401</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>50.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae monomorphic; pappi of relatively fine bristles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>52.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>52.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants mostly rhizomatous, sometimes with caudices; heads in paniculiform or
        racemiform arrays, rarely borne singly.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>53.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>53.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems spreading-hirsute, eglandular; heads in narrow (wand-shaped), paniculiform
        arrays; phyllary midribs translucent and swollen; rays 7–9, corollas white to pale
        cream</statement>
      <determination>163. Solidago (in part), p. 107</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>53.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems usually glabrous, often distally hairy in lines, sometimes ± densely hairy,
        sometimes distally stipitate-glandular; heads in ± open or dense (not wand-shaped),
        paniculiform arrays; phyllary midnerves not translucent and swollen; rays (8–)12–65(–75),
        corollas white, pink, blue, or purple.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>54.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>54.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries usually unequal, sometimes subequal, proximally indurate, distally with
        defined green zone, sometimes distally foliaceous, or outer whollyfoliaceous, sometimes
        short-stipitate-glandular</statement>
      <determination>214. Symphyotrichum (in part), p. 465</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>54.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries subequal, herbaceous (without definite distal green zones, not
        foliaceous), short-stipitate-glandular.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>55.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>55.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems ± densely villous; leaves cauline, blades 1-nerved (venation reticulate),
        lanceolate to elliptic, bases auriculate-clasping, abaxial faces glabrate to ± strigose,
        adaxial sparsely villous (distal stipitate-glandular); phyllaries often purplish, apices of
        outer acuminate; disc corollas whitish to pale yellow; cold wet soils, montane (n
        Cordilleras) and boreal North America</statement>
      <determination>210. Canadanthus, p. 458</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>55.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems glabrous; leaves basal and cauline, blades 3-nerved (nerves ± parallel),
        linear, bases subclasping, faces glabrous (distal stipitate-glandular); phyllaries green,
        apices of outer acute; disc corollas yellow; damp alkaline areas, deserts and dry prairies,
        w North America</statement>
      <determination>212. Almutaster, p. 461</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>52.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted, with caudices, or rhizomatous; heads in corymbiform (or
        flat-topped racemiform) arrays or borne singly, or sometimes grouped into loose corymbiform
        arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>56.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>56.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants usually tapooted, sometimes with caudices (also rhizomatous from fibrous
        roots in Chaetopappa ); stems usually 1 (sometimes 2–5+ in clusters), branched or simple;
        heads borne singly or in loose corymbiform arrays.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>57.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>57.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves usually densely white-tomentose, sometimes glabrate,
        stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted; stems simple; ray florets neuter; cypselae cuneiform or
        linear; pappi reddish to brownish (bristles relatively coarse, California)</statement>
      <determination>208. Corethrogyne (in part) , p. 450</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>57.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves glabrous, glabrate, canescent, villous, or tomentose, sometimes
        stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted; stems simple or branched; ray florets pistillate,
        fertile; cypselae fusiform, cylindric, obovoid, or linear; pappi hyaline or white to
        tawny.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>58.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>58.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems simple; leaf margins entire; phyllaries mostly foliaceous (margins sometimes
        proximally indurate); rays white (maturing or drying bluish or purplish).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>59.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>59.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves basal and cauline (crowded), blades linear-oblanceolate to lanceolate,
        1-nerved; phyllaries not keeled; cypselae 5-nerved</statement>
      <determination>179. Chaetopappa (in part), p. 206</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>59.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mostly basal (rosettes), blades linear to oblanceolate, 3-nerved; phyllaries
        often ± keeled; cypselae 5–10-nerved (nerves raised)</statement>
      <determination>191. Oreostemma, p. 359</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>58.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems branched or simple; leaf margins entire or toothed (teeth apiculate, ±
        spinulose, or spine-tipped); phyllaries usually not foliaceous (proximally white-indurate,
        distally green or herbaceous); rays white, blue, violet, or purple.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>60.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>60.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems mostly simple (scapiform); leaves mostly basal (rosettes, often marcescent),
        margins entire or irregularly serrate (teeth apiculate or ± spinulose); phyllaries
        squarrose; cypselae 8–10-ribbed (canyons, rock faces, Utah)</statement>
      <determination>192. Herrickia (in part), p. 361</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>60.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems mostly branched; leaves basal and cauline, margins entire or toothed (teeth
        spinose-tipped); phyllaries appressed, spreading, or reflexed; cypselae 4-nerved,
        4–6-ribbed, or smooth.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>61.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>61.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems mostly single; cauline leaf blades lanceolate to oblanceolate; phyllaries not
        keeled</statement>
      <determination>197. Dieteria (in part), p. 395</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>61.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems clustered; cauline leaf blades spatulate to obovate oroblong, rarely
        elliptic; phyllaries keeled</statement>
      <determination>199. Xylorhiza (in part), p. 406</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>56.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants rhizomatous or with caudices; stems 1–5+, usually simple; heads usually in
        corymbiform arrays, sometimes borne singly (then plants long-rhizomatous, rays
        pink).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>62.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>62.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries flat, not keeled, midveins orange-resinous or swollen and
        translucent.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>63.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>63.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 40–200 cm; leaves basal (not persistent, reduced) and cauline, blades
        1-nerved (venation brochidodromous), lanceolate to elliptic; phyllary midveins
        orange-resinous; rays 2–10(–16)</statement>
      <determination>144. Doellingeria, p. 43</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>63.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 10–40 cm; leaves basal (persistent, well developed) and cauline (reduced),
        blades usually 1-nerved, sometimes ± 3-nerved (venation reticulate), linear to
        linear-lanceolate, phyllary midveins swollen, translucent; ray florets 10–20</statement>
      <determination>163. Solidago (in part), p. 107</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>62.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries ± rounded, sometimes ± keeled, midveins not swollen.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>64.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>64.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants rhizomatous and/or with woody caudices (rhizomes with swollen apical buds);
        heads in ± loose, corymbiform arrays or borne singly (nodding in bud); phyllaries
        lance-ovate to linear (membranous), proximally not indurate, green along midnerves; cypselae
        5–8-nerved (lateral 2 thicker), glabrous, ± densely gland-dotted; e North
        America</statement>
      <determination>149. Oclemena, p. 78</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>64.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants rhizomatous (rhizomes not apically swollen) and/or with caudices; heads in
        corymbiform arrays (erect in bud); phyllaries ovate, oblong, lanceolate, or
        linear-lanceolate, proximally indurate, distally with sharply delimited green apical zones;
        cypselae 7–12(–18)-nerved, glabrous, strigillose, or strigose, eglandular; e, w North
        America (excluding United States prairies).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>65.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>65.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres cylindric; ray florets 1–6, white; disc corollas white or cream-colored;
        cypselae ± densely strigose</statement>
      <determination>160. Sericocarpus, p. 101</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>65.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres cylindro-campanulate or campanulate; rays 5–60, white to purple; disc
        corollas yellow; cypselae glabrous or ± densely strigillose.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>66.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>66.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves usually stipitate-glandular, sometimes eglandular and glaucous;
        leaves mostly cauline, entire or spinulose-serrate, glabrous or scabrellous; phyllaries
        sometimes rounded, usually keeled, apices acuteto long-acuminate; rays 8–27; disc corolla
        tubes shorter than limbs (w Cordilleras)</statement>
      <determination>192. Herrickia (in part), p. 361</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>66.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems and leaves usually eglandular, sometimes stipitate-glandular (e North America
        only), not glaucous; leaves basal and/or cauline, serrate (teeth sometimes spinulose or
        spinose, blades then linear, grasslike, se North America) or entire, hairy or glabrous;
        phyllaries usually rounded, sometimes keeled, apices obtuse to acute; rays 5–60; disc
        corolla tubes shorter or longer than limbs</statement>
      <determination>193. Eurybia, p. 365</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
