<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rayjacksonia R. L. Hartman &amp; M. A. Lane" date="unknown">RAYJACKSONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. J. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>83: 368. 1996</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Astereae;genus RAYJACKSONIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Raymond Carl Jackson, b. 1928, American botanist and plant geneticist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals to perennials, 4–80 cm, herbage glabrous, prominently sessile- to stipitate-glandular; taprooted. Stems erect to decumbent-ascending, branched basally (leafy throughout). Leaves mostly cauline; alternate; sessile to subpetiolate; blades 1-nerved (pinnately veined), linear to oblanceolate, margins coarsely serrate (teeth bristle-tipped), rarely entire (apices acute to obtuse). Heads radiate, in paniculiform or subcorymbo-cymiform arrays. (Peduncles sometimes cobwebby.) Involucres hemispheric, (7–16 ×) 9–30 mm. Phyllaries 20–40 in 4–5 series, appressed or tips spreading to reflexed, 1-nerved (flat or proximally convex), linear to lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, equal to subequal, white-indurate, margins of inner scarious (apices erect, loosely spreading, or recurved, green-herbaceous, acute to acuminate), faces glabrous or glandular. Receptacles shallowly convex, pitted, epaleate. Ray florets 14–46, pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow. Disc florets 25–130, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes shorter than abruptly ampliate throats, lobes 5, erect, triangular; style-branch appendages deltate. Cypselae dimorphic, faces strigoso-sericeous; ray broadly ellipsoid to obovoid, 3-angled (thick-walled), 0–4-ribbed; disc broadly ellipsoid to clavate, ± radially compressed (thinner-walled), 5–9-ribbed; pappi persistent, of 30–40 brownish, unequal, barbellate, attenuate bristles in 3–4 series (about as long as disc corollas), outer thinner, terete, inner thick-flattened. x = 6.</description>
  <description type="distribution">s</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>204.</number>
  <discussion>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>R. L. Hartman (1990) informally recognized the three species of Rayjacksonia as an undescribed genus most closely related to Grindelia, Isocoma, Xanthocephalum, and other genera of Machaerantherinae with x = 6. The taxonomy was formalized by M. A. Lane and Hartman (1996). The Rayjacksonia species are coherent in vestiture, spinulose leaf teeth, heads borne singly, and rays with prominent, yellow laminae.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kawaguchi, S. T. 1996. Systematics of Rayjacksonia (Asteraceae: Astereae). M.S. thesis. University of Kansas.</reference>
    <reference>Lane, M. A. and R. L. Hartman. 1996. Reclassification of North American Haplopappus (Compositae: Astereae) completed: Rayjacksonia gen. nov. Amer. J. Bot. 83: 356–370.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mid-cauline leaf blades linear to linear-oblanceolate, 1–3(–4) mm wide; involucres 4–7 × 10–15 mm; rays 14–19, corollas 6.5–9.5 mm</description>
      <determination>1. Rayjacksonia aurea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mid-cauline leaf blades oblanceolate to oblong or oblong-lanceolate, (1–)4–15(–25) mm wide; involucres (4.5–)6–15 × 9–30 mm; rays (13–)17–38, corollas 6–19 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads on short, leafless or bracteate peduncles, not surpassed by distal leaves; mid-cauline leaf blades (1–)4–15(–25) mm wide; phyllaries in 3–4 series, strongly unequal, apices broadly spreading to squarrose, ca. 0.9–1 mm wide</description>
      <determination>2. Rayjacksonia annua</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads essentially sessile, often surpassed by distal leaves that continue to very base of heads; mid-cauline leaf blades (2.5–)4–13 mm wide; phyllaries in 3–4 series, subequal, apices erect to spreading, 1.3–1.7 mm wide</description>
      <determination>3. Rayjacksonia phyllocephala</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
