<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>211.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>AMPELASTER</genus_name><genus_authority>Ampelaster G. L. Nesom</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>77: 250. 1995</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek ampelos , vine, alluding to habit, and generic name Aster ]</etymology><author>John C. Semple</author><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Aster</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><section_name>Sagittiferi</section_name><section_authority>A. Gray</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in A. Gray et al., Syn. Fl. N. Amer. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1(2): 179. 1884</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Aster</genus_name><section_name>Caroliniani</section_name><section_authority>Small</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lasallea</genus_name><genus_authority>Greene</genus_authority><subsection_name>Carolinianae</subsection_name><subsection_authority>(Small) Semple &amp; Brouillet</subsection_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Virgulus</genus_name><genus_authority>Rafinesque</genus_authority><section_name>Sagittiferi</section_name><section_authority>(A. Gray) Reveal &amp; Keener</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs, 100–400 cm (clambering, sprawling, or vinelike, deciduous or evergreen by production of new growth; sometimes clonal by adventitious roots on branches in contact with soil, these becoming separated). Stems scandent, widely and diffusely branched, sparsely to densely short-pilose or hirsute, especially distally, eglandular. Leaves cauline; alternate; sessile; blades 1-nerved, elliptic or oblanceolate to lanceolate or ovate, margins entire, faces sparsely to moderately pilose. Heads radiate, in paniculiform arrays. Involucres turbino-campanulate, 8–12 × 8.5–21 mm. Phyllaries 30–50, in 5–6 series, spreading to reflexed, 1-nerved (midnerves ± raised, especially proximally, ± translucent yellow-brown to golden brown, less prominent distally; ± flat), outer linear-lanceolate to spatulate, inner linear-attenuate, strongly unequal, proximally whitish, herbaceous distally (green zone restricted to apical 1/4 or less), margins hyaline proximally (sometimes reddish), abaxial faces sparsely to moderately pilose. Receptacles flat to slightly rounded, pitted (margins irregular), epaleate. Ray florets 30–50(–70), pistillate, fertile; corollas pale rose-purple to pale pink. Disc florets 30–50, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow becoming rose-purple, weakly ampliate, tubes shorter than narrowly cylindro-campanulate throats, lobes 5, erect, triangular; style-branch appendages narrowly triangular. Cypselae narrowly cylindric to fusiform, not compressed, 9–12-ribbed (whitish, raised), faces glabrous; pappi persistent, of 30–45, light stramineous to faintly rust-orange, barbellate bristles in 2(–3) series (outermost of 0–5 midlength attenuate bristles, outer of long, distally attenuate ones, slightly shorter than inner weakly clavate ones). x = 9.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>se United States.</global_distribution></treatment>
