<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>10.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Symphyotrichum</genus_name><species_name>oblongifolium</species_name><species_authority>(Nuttall) G. L. Nesom</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>77: 287. 1995</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Oblong-leaved or aromatic aster</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Aster</genus_name><species_name>oblongifolius</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 156. 1818</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Virgulus</genus_name><species_name>oblongifolius</species_name><species_authority>(Nuttall) Reveal &amp; Keener</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials, 10–80(–100) cm, colonial; with thick, woody, short-branched caudices, sometimes ± cormoid, and thin, woody rhizomes. Stems 1–10+, ascending to erect or decumbent, light to dark brown, proximally glabrous, distally hispiduloso-hirsute or hirtellous, stipitate-glandular. Leaves (yellowish to dark green) thin, margins entire; basal sometimes persistent, sessile, blades (3-nerved) oblanceolate to spatulate, 20–50(–70) × 5–15 mm, margins entire (remotely serrate), coarsely ciliate, apices rounded, short-mucronate, faces usually hirsute, rarely glabrous, often also stipitate-glandular; proximal cauline sessile (often with clusters of smaller leaves in axils), blades oblong or linear-lanceolate, (15–)30–100 × 5–15(–20) mm, bases rounded or slightly clasping, margins scabrellous, apices acute to obtuse, spinulose-mucronate, abaxial faces scabrous, often stipitate-glandular, adaxial hirsute; distal sessile, blades lanceolate to oblong, 20–80 × 2–10(–20) mm, greatly reduced distally, bases cuneate to subclasping, margins ciliate, stipitate-glandular, apices acute to obtuse, white-mucronate, faces moderately strigose, moderately to densely stipitate-glandular. Heads in ample, corymbiform to diffusely paniculiform arrays, branches initially patent, then ascending (often from proximal nodes). Peduncles 0.5–5 cm, hispid, stipitate-glandular, bracts dense, spreading or squarrose (rarely ascending), linear to narrowly oblong, 3–8 mm, grading into phyllaries, spinulose, short-strigose. Involucres campanulate, (5–)7–9 mm. Phyllaries in 4–5(–6) series, outer oblanceolate, mid linear-lanceolate, inner linear, usually unequal, sometimes subequal, bases ± indurate, margins hyaline, scarious, erose, ciliate or ciliolate and/or stipitate-glandular, green zones often broadly foliaceous (outer), green in distal 1/3–1/2 (mid), apices spreading to reflexed (outer), acute, mid long-acuminate, faces moderately hairy, stipitate-glandular. Ray florets (10–)25–35; corollas light to dark rose-purple, lavender to deep purple, laminae 9–13(–15) × 1–2 mm. Disc florets (25–)30–40(–50); corollas yellow turning brown or reddish purple, 4.5–5.5(–6) mm, tubes 1/2 the funnelform to nearly tubular throats, lobes triangular, 0.4–0.7 mm. Cypselae dull purple or brown (nerves stramineous), obovoid, slightly falcate, not compressed, 2–2.5 mm, 7–10-nerved, faces sparsely strigillose or sericeous; pappi tawny (barb tips sometimes rose-tinged), 3.5–6 mm. 2n = 10, 20.</description><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><phenology>nov</phenology><habitat>open, dry, rocky, sandy, gravelly, or shaly soils</habitat><habitat>limestone glades and outcrops</habitat><habitat>sandstone or calcareous cliffs</habitat><habitat>open-wooded bluffs</habitat><habitat>prairies</habitat><habitat>pastures</habitat><habitat>dunes</habitat><habitat>roadsides</habitat><elevation>100–1500+ m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ark.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Colo.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ill.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ind.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Iowa</us_distribution><us_distribution>Kans.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ky.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Minn.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Miss.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mo.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nebr.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ohio</us_distribution><us_distribution>Okla.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Pa.</us_distribution><us_distribution>S.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tenn.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wis.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wyo.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Coahuila).</global_distribution><discussion>Symphyotrichum oblongifolium varies greatly in leaf size and shape, the extremes of which have been the bases for varieties that are not distinct but merely represent the ends of a continuum of variation. The species is similar to S. ×amethystinum (S. ericoides × S. novae-angliae), but the latter has more hairy stems and leaves, and eglandular phyllaries. A leafy cultivar of the species is offered in the horticulture trade. A form with pink rays, merely a population variation, has been recognized as distinct from the more purple typical form: Aster oblongifolius forma roseoligulatus Shinners. Symphyotrichum batesii (Rydberg) G. L. Nesom (syn. Aster batesii Rydberg), reported from Nebraska, is the intersectional hybrid of this species with S. ericoides var. ericoides.</discussion></treatment>
