<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>21.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Symphyotrichum</genus_name><species_name>sericeum</species_name><species_authority>(Ventenat) G. L. Nesom</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>77: 291. 1995</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Western silvery aster</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Aster</genus_name><species_name>sericeus</species_name><species_authority>Ventenat</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Descr. Pl. Nouv., plate </publication_title><place_in_publication>33. 1800</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lasallea</genus_name><species_name>sericea</species_name><species_authority>(Ventenat) Greene</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Virgulus</genus_name><species_name>sericeus</species_name><species_authority>(Ventenat) Reveal &amp; Keener</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials, (20–)30–70 cm, cespitose, eglandular; with short, woody, cormoid caudices, or short rhizomes. Stems 1–5+, ascending to erect (thin, grayish brown to dark brown), glabrous proximally, densely canescent distally. Leaves (silvery) firm, soft; basal withering by flowering, sessile, blades (1–3 nerved) elliptic-lanceolate, 10–40 × 5–15 mm, bases cuneate, weakly sheathing, margins usually entire, rarely remotely serrate, piloso-ciliate, apices acute, faces less copiously hairy than cauline; proximal cauline withering by flowering, sessile, blades oblanceolate or oblong to linear-lanceolate, 15–30(–50) × 4–10 mm, slightly and progressively reduced distally, bases rounded, subclasping, margins entire, silky-pilose, apices obtuse to acute, mucronulate, faces sparsely to densely silky-pilose; distal sessile, blades lanceolate, 10–30 × 5–8 mm, little reduced distally, bases cuneate, margins entire, apices acute, mucronate, faces ± densely silky. Heads in open, paniculiform arrays, branches sparse, fastigiate, often arching (1–5+ per branch). Peduncles subsessile or 0.5–3(–5) cm, densely sericeo-strigose, bracts crowded, 4–8(–10) mm, grading into phyllaries. Involucres campanulate to cylindric, (5–)7.5–10 mm. Phyllaries in 3–5(–6) series, outer ovate with expanded distal portion [(4–)5–6 mm], mid ovate-lanceolate [6–8(–10) mm] with expanded green portions, inner linear, unequal or sometimes subequal, outer often foliaceous, bases (mid) scarious, margins silky, green zones restricted to expanded distal 1/2–2/3 (obscured by hairs), apices (outer) spreading or squarrose to reflexed, acute, mucronulate, faces densely long-silky. Ray florets (10–)15–30; corollas usually rose-purple to deep purple, rarely white, laminae 8.5–11 × 1–1.5 mm. Disc florets (15–)25–35; corollas pink turning purple, (5–)5.5–7 mm, tubes shorter than narrowly funnelform throats (both thinly puberulent), lobes deltate, 0.7–0.9 mm. Cypselae purple or brown, obovoid, not compressed, 2–3 mm, 7–10-nerved (prominent), faces glabrous; pappi whitish or tawny, 6–7 mm. 2n = 10, 20.</description><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><habitat>open, dry, deep, sandy or loamy soils</habitat><habitat>broken limestone outcrops</habitat><habitat>open-wooded bluffs</habitat><habitat>open woods</habitat><habitat>open calcareous hammocks</habitat><habitat>prairies</habitat><habitat>fields</habitat><habitat>sand barrens</habitat><habitat>dunes</habitat><habitat>dry banks</habitat><habitat>rarely acidic shield rocks</habitat><elevation>100–500+ m;</elevation><ca_distribution>Man.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Ark.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ill</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ind.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Iowa</us_distribution><us_distribution>Kans.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mich.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Minn.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mo.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nebr.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ohio</us_distribution><us_distribution>Okla.</us_distribution><us_distribution>S.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tenn.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wis.</us_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies (Bahamas).</global_distribution><discussion>Symphyotrichum sericeum is known in the Bahamas as S. lucayanum (Britton) G. L. Nesom [syn. Aster lucayanus Britton, Virgulus lucayanus (Britton) Reveal &amp; Keener]. It is of conservation concern in Indiana, Michigan, and Canada. Symphyotrichum sericeum is distinct and unlikely to be confused with other species due to its silvery-silky leaves and phyllaries, open arrays, and cormoid rootstocks. Aster sericeus forma albiligulatus Fassett is a white form of the species, in contrast to the typically purple forma sericeus; these do not deserve formal recognition.</discussion></treatment>
