<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>214d.2.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Symphyotrichum</genus_name>
        <genus_authority>Nees</genus_authority>
        <subgenus_name>Symphyotrichum</subgenus_name>
        <section_name>Symphyotrichum</section_name>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Perennials; rhizomatous. Stems usually simple, sometimes ± branched. Heads radiate.
        Ray florets fewer than disc florets, in 1 series (corollas conspicuous). Disc corollas ±
        ampliate, lobes usually erect, sometimes spreading or reflexed. Pappi shorter than to
        equaling disc florets at flowering. x = 8.</description>
    <number_of_infrataxa>Species 39+ (36 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
    <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution>widely introduced worldwide through ornamental
        horticulture.</global_distribution>
    <discussion>Subsections have been recognized within sect. Symphyotrichum. They are not treated
        formally here. Subsectional phylogeny is mostly unresolved. Lists of species (from the flora
        area) within each subsection are provided here as a rough guide to
        relationships.</discussion>
    <discussion>Subsection Heterophylli (Nees) Semple: Symphyotrichum cordifolium, S. ciliolatum, S.
        drummondii, S. anomalum, S. shortii, S. undulatum, S. urophyllum, S. oolentangiense, S.
        laeve, S. retroflexum.</discussion>
    <discussion>Subsection Porteriana (Rydberg) G. L. Nesom: Symphyotrichum depauperatum, S.
        parviceps, S. pilosum, S. porteri, S. priceae.</discussion>
    <discussion>Subsection Dumosi (Torrey &amp; A. Gray) G. L. Nesom: Symphyotrichum dumosum, S.
        simmondsii, S. racemosum, S. eulae, S. tradescantii, S. lateriflorum, S. ontarionis, S.
        lanceolatum, S. praealtum, S. boreale, S. nahanniense, S. welshii.</discussion>
    <discussion>Subsection Symphyotrichum: Symphyotrichum elliottii, S. puniceum, S. firmum, S.
        rhiannon, S. prenanthoides, S. novi-belgii, S. anticostense, S. robynsianum.</discussion>
    <discussion>Undeteremined [often treated as monotypic sect. Turbinelli (Rydberg) Semple]:
        Symphyotrichum turbinellum.</discussion>
</treatment>
