<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Symphyotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Á. Löve &amp; D. Löve" date="unknown">laeve</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Taxon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>31: 359. 1982</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Astereae;genus Symphyotrichum;species laeve;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Aster</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">laevis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 876. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Aster;species laevis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials (15–)20–70(–120) cm, cespitose; stoutly short-rhizomatous, with thick, woody caudices or a few, long rhizomes. Stems 1–5+, erect (straight, glaucous, sometimes reddish proximally), glabrous, sometimes sparsely hirsute distally. Leaves (glaucous) thick, firm, ± fleshy, margins crenate-serrate or -serrulate or entire, scabridulous, apices mucronulate, faces glabrous; basal usually withering by flowering or sometimes persistent (var. purpuratum), petiolate (petioles ± winged, bases dilated, sheathing), blades spatulate or oblong to ovate or lanceolate-ovate, 30–200 × 10–25(–30) mm, bases attenuate or cuneate to rounded, margins crenate-serrate to serrulate, apices acute to obtuse or rounded; proximal cauline often withering by flowering, petiolate or subsessile or sessile (petioles narrowly to broadly winged, clasping), blades ovate or oblong-ovate to lanceolate or linear-lanceolate, sometimes ± panduriform, (40–)80–150(–180) × (10–)20–45 mm, bases attenuate to rounded or ± shallowly auriculate-clasping, margins entire or shallowly crenate-serrate, minutely scabrous, apices acute or obtuse, callus-pointed; distal sessile, blades lance-ovate or lanceolate to linear, 7–45 × 1–14 mm, progressively reduced distally (abruptly so in arrays), bases auriculate and ± clasping to rounded, margins entire. Heads in broad, sometimes ± flat-topped, paniculiform arrays, branches stiffly ascending (rarely arching), leafy with small, gradually reduced branch leaves. Peduncles 0.2–6+ cm, glaucous, glabrous or puberulent in lines, bracts 3–6, densely spaced, subulate or linear-lanceolate to linear, subclasping, apices sometimes purplish, grading into phyllaries. Involucres campanulate to cylindro-campanulate, (4.2–)5–7(–8) mm. Phyllaries in 4–6 series, appressed, subulate or lanceolate (outer) to oblong-lanceolate or linear-lancolate or -oblanceolate, unequal (sometimes appearing subequal), bases indurate 1/2–3/4, margins scarious, erose, hyaline, ciliolate distally, green zones mostly diamond-shaped to ± lanceolate (some inner, or most in var. geyeri), apices acute to acuminate, sometimes ± obtuse, red-mucronate or apiculate, faces glabrous. Ray florets (11–)13–23(–34); corollas usually pale to dark blue or purple, seldom white, laminae (6–)7.2–11.3(–14.6) × 1.5–2.5 mm. Disc florets (17–)19–33(–43); corollas yellow turning purplish red, 3.5–6.1 mm, tubes slightly shorter than funnelform throats, lobes triangular, (0.4–)0.6–1 mm. Cypselae deep purple to brown, oblong-obovoid, compressed, 2–3.5 mm, 4–5-nerved, faces glabrous or glabrate; pappi tawny to red- or rose-tinged, 5–7 mm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">ne Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced in other areas of Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe.</description>
  <number>36.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Smooth aster</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">aster lisse</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves lanceolate to ovate, conspicuously auric ulate-clasping, lengths less than 5 times widths.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries strongly unequal, green apical zones diamond-shaped</description>
      <determination>36a. Symphyotrichum laeve var. laeve</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries unequal, green apical zones lanceolate</description>
      <determination>36b. Symphyotrichum laeve var. geyeri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear-lanceolate to linear, slightly auriculate-clasping, lengths often 5 times widths.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves withering by flowering, cauline linear-lanceolate</description>
      <determination>36c. Symphyotrichum laeve var. concinnum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly basal and proximal at flowering, mostly linear</description>
      <determination>36d. Symphyotrichum laeve var. purpuratum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
