<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>223.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>HASTEOLA</genus_name><genus_authority>Rafinesque</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>New Fl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4: 79. 1838</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Latin hasta , spear, and - ola , diminutive, alluding to leaves of type species]</etymology><author>Loran C. Anderson</author><description>Perennials, (50–)60–240 cm. Stems usually 1, erect (unbranched proximal to heads). Leaves basal and cauline; alternate; petiolate (proximal) or sessile; blades pinnately nerved, broadly deltate or hastate (proximal) to broadly lanceolate, margins doubly-serrate, faces glabrous. Heads discoid, in corymbiform (± flat-topped) arrays. Calyculi of 4–9+ (subulate, rarely leaflike) bractlets. Involucres cylindric or campanulate to obconic, 5–8+ mm diam. (glabrous). Phyllaries persistent, 7–14+ in 1–2 series, erect, distinct, oblong, ± equal, margins chartaceous to scarious. Receptacles slightly convex or flat, foveolate, epaleate. Ray florets 0. Disc florets 10–55, bisexual, fertile; corollas usually white or ochroleucous to greenish, rarely pinkish, tubes longer than cylindric throats, lobes 5, erect to spreading, lanceolate; style branches stigmatic in 2 lines, apices truncate or truncate-penicillate (appendages essentially 0). Cypselae cylindric-fusiform, 8–12-ribbed, glabrous; pappi persistent (fragile), of 100–150+, white, barbellulate bristles. x = 10.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>e United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Asian species that have been assigned to Hasteola belong to Parasenecio.</discussion><references>
    <reference> Anderson, L. C. 1994. A revision of Hasteola (Asteraceae) in the New World. Syst. Bot. 19: 211–219.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Florets 10–14; proximal cauline leaves deltate</statement>
      <determination>1. Hasteola robertiorum</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Florets 18–55; proximal cauline leaves hastate to deltate or lanceolate</statement>
      <determination>2. Hasteola suaveolens</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
