<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Theodore M. Barkley†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">senecioneae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">TUSSILAGO</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 865. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 372. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe senecioneae;genus TUSSILAGO</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Said to be based on Latin tussi s , cough, for which the plant has a medicinal reputation]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, 5–30(–50) cm (rhizomes fibrous-rooted, creeping; plants forming extensive colonies). Stems usually 1, erect (scapiform, not branched). Leaves basal and cauline (basal usually developing after flowers); alternate; petiolate (petiole lengths 1–2 times blades) or sessile; blades (basal) palmately nerved, orbiculate to polygonal or lobed (cauline leaves lance-ovate to linear, bractlike or scale-like), margins denticulate, abaxial faces gray-tomentose, adaxial tomentulose, glabrescent. Heads (erect at flowering, nodding in fruit) radiate, borne singly. Calyculi 0 (or indistinct, bractlets intergrading with bractlike cauline leaves). Involucres cylindric to subturbinate, 10–15 mm diam. (larger in fruit). Phyllaries persistent, usually ± 21 in (1–)2 series, erect, distinct, lance-linear to linear, subequal, margins scarious (apices greenish or yellow-green). Receptacles convex, foveolate (socket margins ± membranous), epaleate. Ray florets 100–200(–300+), pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow (drying pinkish). Disc florets (20–)30–40, functionally staminate; corollas yellowish, tubes longer than campanulate throats, lobes 5, erect, linear; styles not divided. Cypselae narrowly cylindric or ± prismatic, 5(–10)-ribbed, glabrous; pappi readily falling or fragile, of 60–100+, white, barbellulate or smooth bristles. x = 30.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa.</description>
  <number>240.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Coltsfoot</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Morton, G. H. 1978. Tussilago. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Ser. 2, part 10, p. 174.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
