<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>242.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>BLENNOSPERMA</genus_name><genus_authority>Lessing</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Syn. Gen. Compos.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>267. 1832</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek blennos , mucus, and sperma , seed, alluding to cypselae becoming mucilaginous when wetted]</etymology><author>John L. Strother</author><description>Annuals, 3–12(–30) cm (taprooted). Stems usually 1, erect (usually branched ± throughout). Leaves (sometimes ± fleshy) basal and cauline; alternate; mostly sessile; blades pinnately nerved, linear (or pinnately divided into 2–15 linear lobes), ultimate margins entire, faces glabrous or sparsely floccose-tomentose. Heads radiate, borne singly. Involucres ± hemispheric, 3–6+ mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 5–13+ in ± 2 series, ± erect (inflexed in late flowering, reflexed in fruit), basally connate, elliptic to ovate, subequal, ± membranous (veiny, tips usually purple). Receptacles flat to convex, smooth or foveolate, epaleate. Ray florets 5–13+, pistillate (sometimes, some pistillate florets lack corollas); corollas sessile (lacking tubes), usually yellow, rarely white (often purplish abaxially, laminae ovate to linear). Disc florets 20–60(–100+), functionally staminate; corollas yellow, tubes shorter to longer than campanulate throats; lobes 5, ± erect, deltate to lanceolate; styles not divided. Cypselae ± ellipsoid, usually 5–6(–10)-ribbed or -angled, usually papillate (papillae becoming mucilaginous when wetted); pappi 0. x = 9.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><us_distribution>California</us_distribution><global_distribution>South America (Chile).</global_distribution><references>
    <reference> Ornduff, R. 1964. Biosystematics of Blennosperma (Compositae). Brittonia 16: 289–295.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Proximal leaves not lobed or 2–3(–5)-lobed; stigmas of ray florets red</statement>
      <determination>1. Blennosperma bakeri</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Proximal leaves usually 5–15-lobed, rarely entire; stigmas of ray florets yellow</statement>
      <determination>2. Blennosperma nanum</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
