<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">senecioneae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hooker" date="1834">CROCIDIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 335, plate 118. 1834</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe senecioneae;genus CROCIDIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek krokis , downy fibers of woolen cloth, and - idium , diminutive, alluding to axillary tomentum]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, (2–)4–12(–30) cm (usually glabrous but for axillary tomentum). Stems usually 1, erect, simple or branched near bases. Leaves (± fleshy) basal and cauline; alternate; petiolate (basal) or sessile; blades palmately nerved, spatulate or oblanceolate (basal) to lanceolate or linear, margins toothed or entire, faces glabrous or glabrate. Heads radiate, borne singly. Calyculi 0. Involucres ± hemispheric, 3–6+ mm diam. Phyllaries (veiny, often purple-tipped, each subtending a ray floret) persistent, 5–13+ in 1(–2) series, erect (reflexed in fruit), basally connate, elliptic to ovate, subequal, margins herbaceous to membranous. Receptacles dome-shaped to conic (heights equaling or greater than diameters), smooth, epaleate. Ray florets 5–13+, pistillate and fertile or neuter; corollas yellow (laminae conspicuous). Disc florets 12–60(–120+), bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes ± cylindric, longer than or equaling campanulate to cylindric throats, lobes 5, erect to spreading, deltate to lanceolate; style branches stigmatic in 2 lines, apices truncate-penicillate. Cypselae (stramineous to reddish brown) ± ellipsoid to fusiform, 5(–6)-nerved, ± papillate-hairy between nerves (papillae mucilaginous when wetted); pappi fragile or readily falling, usually of 20–40, white, barbellulate bristles (in 1 series), sometimes 0 on ray cypselae. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: w North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>w North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>243.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
