<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(de Candolle) Nuttall" date="1840">AMPHIACHYRIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Amer. Philos. Soc., n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 313. 1840</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe astereae;genus AMPHIACHYRIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek amphi -, around, and achyron , chaff or husks, alluding to ring of pappus elements]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="unknown">Brachyris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">Amphiachyris</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Soc. Phys. Genève</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 266. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Brachyris;section Amphiachyris;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 20–100(–200) cm (glabrous, with strong terpenoid smell when crushed; taprooted). Stems erect, usually branched distally (bases usually lignescent). Leaves cauline; alternate; sessile; blades (1- or 3-nerved) linear to lanceolate, margins entire, faces gland-dotted. Heads radiate, in paniculiform or corymbiform arrays. Involucres narrowly campanulate to turbinate, 2–4 mm diam. Phyllaries 12–15 in 1–2(–3) series, 1-nerved (nerves without green margins) ovate, unequal, proximal 2/3 indurate, margins hyaline, faces whitish resinous. Receptacles flat to slightly convex, smooth (glabrous or hairy with multicellular, 1-seriate hairs), epaleate. Ray florets 7–12, pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow, sometimes drying orange-tinged. Disc florets 10–21, functionally staminate; corollas yellow, tubes shorter than cylindric throats, lobes 5, erect, deltate; style-branch appendages fused (pappi of 5–8 white, basally connate, linear, spatulate-tipped scales in 1 series, ± equaling corollas). Cypselae (ray, purplish black) obovoid-turbinate, plump, 4–9-ribbed (apices attenuate to slightly clavate), faces densely long- or short-setulose (hairs appressed, white), mostly occurring in lines between ribs; pappi coroniform. x = 4, 5.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c United States.</description>
  <number>154.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Broomweed</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Amphiachyris was recently treated within a more inclusive Gutierrezia (G. M. Diggs et al. 1999); apparently, it is more closely related to monotypic Thurovia than to Gutierrezia (Y. Suh and B. B. Simpson 1990). Amphiachyris is distinguished from Gutierrezia by a combination of glandular hairs only on the abaxial leaf faces, functionally staminate disc florets, disc pappi of basally connate, narrowly spatulate scales ± equaling corollas, and abaxial nerves of the phyllaries without green borders.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Lane, M. A. 1979. Taxonomy of the genus Amphiachyris (Asteraceae: Astereae). Syst. Bot. 4: 178–189.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 20–40(–60) cm; heads in open paniculiform arrays; cypselae 4–6-ribbed, long-setulose; leaf blades 0.2–1(–2) mm wide; receptacles with hooked, swollen-based hairs</description>
      <determination>1. Amphiachyris amoena</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 30–100(–200) cm; heads in crowded corymbiform arrays; cypselae 7–9-ribbed, short-setulose; leaf blades 0.5–6 mm wide; receptacles glabrous</description>
      <determination>2. Amphiachyris dracunculoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
