<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="1834">CHRYSOMA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 67. 1834</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe astereae;genus CHRYSOMA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chrysos , gold, and - ome , having the condition of; alluding to predominantly yellow-gold heads and corymbs]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, 50–100 cm (evergreen), glabrous, resinous. Stems erect, branched. Leaves cauline; alternate; sessile; blades 1-nerved, oblanceolate to narrowly elliptic (bases sometimes attenuate), margins entire, faces gland-dotted, resinous (covered by reticulum of subisodiametric areoles, each areole surrounded by sunken border). Heads usually radiate, sometimes discoid, in dense (terminal), cymiform arrays. Involucres cylindric, (5–6 ×) 2–2.5 mm. Phyllaries 8–12 in 3–4(–5) series (in vertical ranks), erect, loose, stamineous, 1-nerved (midnerves orange-resinous from bases to apices; flat), lanceolate, unequal, margins scarious. Receptacles flat, shallowly pitted, epaleate. Ray florets (0–)1–2(–3), pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow. Disc florets (2–)3–4(–5), bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubular-funnelform, tubes longer than throats, lobes 5, spreading-recurving, lanceolate; style-branch appendages linear-triangular (closely papillate). Cypselae (brownish) turbinate-oblong, nearly terete, 8–10-ribbed, densely strigoso-sericeous; pappi persistent, of 40–60 tan, unequal, barbellate, apically attenuate bristles in 2–3 series. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States.</description>
  <number>161.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Chrysoma pauciflosculosa was originally described within Solidago; it is distinct in anatomy (F. E. Lloyd 1901; K. Phillips 1963; L. C. Anderson and J. B. Creech 1975) and other features. Chrysoma is recognized by its shrubby habit, areolate-resinous leaves, corymbiform arrays of glomerate, cylindric, few-flowered heads, long disc corolla lobes, and papillate style-branch appendages.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Lloyd, F. E. 1901. Some points in the anatomy of Chrysoma pauciflosculosa. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 28: 445–450.</reference>
    <reference>Phillips, K. 1963. A Taxonomic and Morphological Study of Chrysoma pauciflosculosa (Michx.) Greene. M.S. thesis. University of South Carolina.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
