<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>29.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Solidago</genus_name><species_name>arguta</species_name><species_authority>Aiton</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Hort. Kew.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3: 213. 1789</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Cut-leaf or sharp-leaved or Atlantic goldenrod</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Aster</genus_name><species_name>argutus</species_name><species_authority>(Aiton) Kuntze</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 50–120 cm; caudices branching. Stems 1 usually, erect, round, proximally glabrous, strigose in arrays. Leaves: basal and proximal cauline tapering abruptly to winged, thin petioles, blades broadly ovate, 100–300 × 30–100 mm, margins sharply serrate, apices acute to acuminate, adaxial faces glabrous or slightly scabrous, or sometimes strigose or strigillose; mid to distal cauline sessile, lanceolate, 50–72 × 10–14 mm, reduced distally, becoming entire. Heads 25–250, secund, in open, leafy, paniculiform arrays with recurved branches (sometimes elongate), branches and peduncles hairy. Peduncles 1.5–3 mm, glabrous or moderately short hispido-strigose, bracteoles 1–5, lanceolate-oblong, often grading into phyllaries. Involucres 2.5–4.5(–5) mm. Phyllaries in 3–4 series, unequal; outer ovate, acute, inner linear-oblong, ciliate, obtuse. Ray florets 2–8; laminae 4–4.5 × 0.4–0.6 mm. Disc florets 8–20; corollas 3.5–4 mm, lobes 0.6–1.5 mm. Cypselae 1.5–2 mm, distinctly ridged, glabrous or strigose distally; pappi 3–3.5 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America.</global_distribution><discussion>Solidago arguta is reputedly in Ohio but its presence there is unconfirmed. The species includes a number of regional and ecotypal races investigated by G. H. Morton (1973, 1975). A. Cronquist (1980) is followed here.</discussion><references>
    <reference> Morton, G. H. 1973. The Taxonomy of the Solidago arguta–boottii Complex. Ph.D. dissertation. University of Tennessee.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae glabrous; s Maine to Virginia, w to Kentucky, Tennessee, and s Missouri</statement>
      <determination>29a.1. Solidago arguta var. arguta</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae strigillose (at least distally); Kentucky, Maryland, Virginia, and West Virginia, south.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves relatively firm, the basal usually proximally ± truncate; (shale barrens) e Kentucky, w Maryland, w Pennsylvnia, w Virginia, e WestVirginia</statement>
      <determination>29a.2. Solidago arguta var. harrisii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves less firm, the basal tapering; Virginia to n Florida, w to Kentucky, occasional in Arkansas, Louisiana, and Missouri.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves glabrous; Virginia to n Florida, w to West Virginia, Kentucky and occasionally to s Missouri, Arkansas, Louisiana</statement>
      <determination>29b.1. Solidago arguta var. caroliniana</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves (especially the proximal) strigose or strigillose; (drier places) Alabama to South Carolina, Arkansas, Louisiana, Mississippi, s Missouri, Tennessee</statement>
      <determination>29b.2. Solidago arguta var. boottii</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
