<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rydberg" date="1906">OREOCHRYSUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>33: 152. 1906</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe astereae;genus OREOCHRYSUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek oreios , of mountains, and chrysos , gold]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Haplopappus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Rydberg) H. M. Hall" date="unknown">Oreochrysum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Haplopappus;section Oreochrysum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Solidago</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Rydberg) Semple" date="unknown">Oreochrysum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Solidago;subgenus Oreochrysum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials 15–60(–100) cm; rhizomes long, slender, scale-leaved, thickening, becoming woody. Stems erect, usually simple, minutely puberulous or hirtellous, stipitate-glandular. Leaves basal and cauline (basal and proximal cauline persistent); alternate; petiolate to subpetiolate; basal and proximal cauline blades 1-nerved, spatulate-oblanceolate, mid and distal elliptic to broadly ovate-lanceolate or oblanceolate, margins entire (apices acute to obtuse or rounded), minutely, short-stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted, viscid. Heads radiate, in distinctly flat-topped, tightly corymbiform arrays. Involucres campanulate to hemispheric, 10–11 × 6–8 mm. Phyllaries 15–24 in 3–4 series, mostly appressed, 1-nerved (rarely with lateral pair; convex proximally, flat beyond), outer lanceolate to ovate, inner broadly lanceolate-oblong, strongly unequal to subequal, herbaceous, slender (apices green-tipped and erect to reflexing), glabrous or hirtellous, minutely stipitate-glandular, non-resinous. Receptacles flat, pitted, epaleate. Ray florets 12–20, pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow. Disc florets 25–37, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes shorter than narrowly tubular-funnelform throats, lobes 5, erect to spreading, triangular; style-branch appendages linear. Cypselae fusiform, plump but distinctly compressed, nerves 12–16 (whitish, raised), glabrous; pappi persistent, of 40–60, equal, barbellate, apically attenuate bristles in 2(–3) series. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>164.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Oreochrysum often has been treated as Solidago parryi; J. C. Semple et al. (1999) placed Oreochrysum at subgeneric rank within Solidago. Oreochrysum is separated from Solidago on the basis of its stipitate-glandular vestiture, large heads in strongly corymbiform arrays, herba-ceous phyllaries, prominent rays, narrow disc corollas with relatively short lobes, linear-lanceolate style-branch appendages, and large cypselae. It has no apparent close relatives within Solidago.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
