<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>165.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>COLUMBIADORIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Columbiadoria G. L. Nesom</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>71: 249. 1991</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Columbia (River), and doria , an early name for goldenrods]</etymology><author>Guy L. Nesom</author><description>Subshrubs 30–60 cm; taproots stout, bases woody, branched. Stems strictly erect, mostly simple, glabrous or glabrate to hirtellous. Leaves basal (usually not persistent) and cauline; alternate; sessile; blades oblanceolate, gradually reduced distally, margins entire, 1-nerved (net-nerved), sparsely scabroso-hispidulous, eglandular or obscurely gland-dotted, not resinous. Heads radiate, in racemiform or loosely spiciform to loosely corymbiform arrays. Involucres cylindro-turbinate, 8–11 × 5–6 mm. Phyllaries 35–40 in 5–6 series, 1-nerved (not evident; convex, not keeled or only slightly so on distal 1/2), lanceolate, unequal, proximal 2/3 white-indurate, margins herbaceous, convex, midnerves not evident (apices green), glabrous. Receptacles flat, smooth, epaleate. Ray florets 5–8, pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow (weakly if at all coiling). Disc florets 15–25, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes shorter than narrowly funnelform throats, lobes 5, erect, deltate; style-branch appendages linear-lanceolate (5–6 times longer than stigmatic lines, papillate distally). Cypselae narrowly oblong, slightly compressed, 8-nerved, moderately strigose; pappi persistent, of 40–50, tan, barbellate, attenuate bristles in 1 series.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>nw United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Possibly, Columbiadoria is a member of the Petradoria group (Solidagininae), although it lacks the characteristic linear-lanceolate, parallel-nerveed leaves of those species (G. L. Nesom 1991f).</discussion><references>
    <reference> Nesom, G. L. 1991f. Redefinition of Hesperodoria (Asteraceae: Astereae) and the segregation of Columbiadoria, a new monotypic genus from the western United States. Phytologia 71: 244–251.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
