<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>166.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>EASTWOODIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Eastwoodia Brandegee</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Zoë</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4: 397. 1894</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Alice Eastwood, 1859–1953, western American botanist]</etymology><author>Guy L. Nesom</author><description>Shrubs, rounded, 30–100 cm. Stems erect, branched, glabrous, often resinous. Leaves cauline; alternate; sessile; blades 1-nerved, linear to linear-oblanceolate, margins entire (apices acute), faces glabrous or sparsely hirtellous, gland-dotted (in pits), slightly resinous. Heads discoid, borne singly or in loosely corymbiform arrays. Involucres hemispheric to campanulate, impressed at base, 4–6 × 7–22 mm. Phyllaries 30–45 in 3–5 series, stiffly erect, green on distal 1/2, 1-nerved (midnerves indurate and raised; slightly convex, strongly keeled by midnerves), oblanceolate, unequal, thick, proximally indurate, margins narrowly scarious, (apices acute to apiculate) faces glabrous, resinous. Receptacles flat, pitted, paleate (paleae falling quickly, oblanceolate, chartaceous). Ray florets 0. Disc florets 30–40, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes longer than cylindric to funnel-shaped throats, lobes 5, spreading to reflexing, narrowly lanceolate; style branch appendages triangular-lanceolate. Cypselae (brownish) narrowly obconic, 3–4-angled, strigoso-sericeous (especially on angles); pappi persistent, of 5–8 linear-lanceolate, thick, flat, minutely erose scales in 1 series. x = 9.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>sw United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Eastwoodia is recognized by its white-barked, shrubby habit, linear, gland-dotted, resinous leaves, discoid heads on leafy stems, paleate receptacles, and pappi of long scales.</discussion></treatment>
