<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Lowell E. Urbatsch,Roland P. Roberts,Kurt M. Neubig</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Petradoria Greene" date="unknown">PETRADORIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Erythea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 13. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Astereae;genus PETRADORIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek petros , rock, and doria , an early name for goldenrods]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>168.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Rock goldenrod</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Petradoria had included a second species, Chrysothamnus gramineus H. M. Hall, first described in Chrysothamnus in a broad sense (L. C. Anderson 1963; G. L. Nesom 2000). When effecting its transfer to Petradoria, Anderson gave it the new name P. discoidea because of the earlier combination P. graminea Wooton &amp; Standley, now synonymized with P. pumila var. graminea.</discussion>
  <discussion>L. C. Anderson (1986) subsequently reinstated Petradoria discoidea in the genus Chrysothamnus. After DNA-based investigations indicated that the previously hypothesized alliances of P. discoidea to Petradoria and to Chrysothamnus in the broad sense were unsupported (R. P. Roberts and L. E. Urbatsch 2004), it became the basis for the new, monospecific genus Cuniculotinus. DNA sequence studies supported a close alliance between Cuniculotinus gramineus and Sericocarpus, while Petradoria pumila and a clade consisting of Stenotus acaulis and S. armerioides were shown to be sisters (Roberts and Urbatsch; Roberts 2002). The present treatment of Petradoria is based, in part, on Anderson (1963).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Anderson, L. C. 1963. Studies on Petradoria (Compositae): Anatomy, cytology, taxonomy. Trans. Kansas Acad. Sci. 66: 632–684.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
