<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey &amp; A. Gray" date="unknown">MONOPTILON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Boston J. Nat. Hist.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 106, plate 13, figs. 1–6. 1845</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Astereae;genus MONOPTILON;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek monos , one, and ptilon , soft feather, alluding to pappus of M. bellidiforme , a solitary plumose bristle]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 1–5 cm, herbage hispido-hirsute (hairs long, white), minutely glandular; taprooted. Stems prostrate to decumbent (radiating from base), simple or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; alternate; petiolate; blades 1-nerved, oblong to oblanceolate-spatulate, margins entire (apices rounded to obtuse). Heads radiate, borne singly (usually immediately subtended and surrounded by distal leaves). Involucres campanulate, 4–6 × 6–7 mm. Phyllaries 10–14 in 1(–2) series, appressed (purple-tipped), 1-nerved (midnerves raised-indurate, evident only in proximal 1/2; proximally convex, not keeled), linear-lanceolate, equal, margins herbaceous or scarious, faces hirsute. Receptacles flat, pitted, epaleate. Ray florets 12–21, pistillate, fertile; corollas white or rose- or purple-tinged (strongly coiling). Disc florets 28–40, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow (with prominent orange veins), tubes much shorter than narrowly tubular-funnelform, lobes 5, reflexed, lanceolate; style-branch appendages obtuse to truncate. Cypselae (brownish) obovoid, compressed, 2-ribbed, faces sparsely strigose; pappi persistent, in (1–)2 series, short-toothed cups plus 1 apically plumose bristle or 8–15 inner, tawny white, barbellate, apically attenuate bristles plus outer of short, laciniate paleae. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>180.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Desertstar</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Both species of Monoptilon are decumbent to prostrate, hispid annuals with campanulate involucres, white coiling rays, obovoid compressed cypselae, and chromosome number of 2n = 16. The genus was placed by G. L. Nesom (1994) as sister to Chaetopappa.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems yellow-green; phyllary margins herbaceous; disc corollas loosely strigose proximally; pappi scarious cups 0.1–0.4 mm plus 1 apically plumose bristle usually equaling disc corollas</description>
      <determination>1. Monoptilon bellidiforme</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems often prominently reddish purple; phyllary margins proximally with sharply delimited, white-scarious portions, lacerate-ciliate at base; disc corollas glabrous or nearly so; pappi outer crowns of paleae or narrow squamellae 0.5–1 mm plus 8–15 barbellate inner bristles, length 1 / 3 – 1 / 2 disc corollas</description>
      <determination>2. Monoptilon bellioides</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
