<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Nuttall) Elliott" date="1823">chrysopsis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Small" date="1933">subulata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. S.E. Fl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1338, 1508. 1933</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe astereae;genus chrysopsis;species subulata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Heterotheca</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Nuttall) R. W. Long" date="unknown">hyssopifolia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Small) R. W. Long" date="unknown">subulata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Heterotheca;species hyssopifolia;variety subulata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials, 20–70 cm; taprooted (frequently perennating by rosettes produced at bases of old stems and at ends of short lateral rhizomes and roots). Stems 1–5+, erect (sometimes purple-tinged), often much branched proximally, glabrous to sparsely pilose, eglandular. Leaves: basal blades oblanceolate to linear-oblanceolate, (first season leaves) 50–100 × 4–10 mm, faces densely woolly; cauline blades linear-lanceolate to linear, reduced distally, bases tapering to rounded, margins entire, long-piloso-ciliate, often undulate, apices acute, often twisted, faces sparsely pilose. Heads 10–70 in lax corymbiform arrays. Peduncles 1–10 cm (thin), glabrous or glabrate; bracteoles linear-lanceolate (margins ciliate), glabrous or sparsely pilose, sometimes sparsely stipitate-glandular. Involucres campanulate, 8–10 mm. Phyllaries in 4–5 series, linear, 0.6–0.9 mm wide, unequal, apices long-attenuate, rarely acute (some n Florida collections), tips spreading to reflexed, twisted, faces proximally glabrous or sparsely stipitate-glandular. Ray florets 10–28; laminae 5–8(–10) × 1.5–2 mm. Disc florets 30–45; corollas 5–6 mm, lobes ca. 0.5 mm. Cypselae 1.5–2 mm, 6–10-ridged (ridges yellow to dark red-brown, translucent, clavate), weakly ribbed, faces glabrate to sparsely strigose proximally; pappi in 3 series, outer of linear to linear-triangular scales 0.4–1 mm, inner of 20–25 bristles 6–7 mm, inner moderately clavate. 2n = 10.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering (May–)Jul–Aug(–Sep).</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy open grounds, pine and oak scrub;</description>
  <description type="elevation">10–50 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Scrubland goldenaster</other_name>
  <discussion>Chrysopsis subulata is found on the central to northern peninsula. Early blooming plants may have a second blooming flush in October to December with flowering heads on otherwise brown and dried stems or from short new shoots developing from lower nodes.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of Chrysopsis subulata from Alachua County have acute phyllaries rather than long-attenuate and reflexed, but the leaves have long-pilose margins typical of the species. The number of ridges on the cypselae varies from a few red-brown as in C. linearifolia subsp. dressii to covering nearly the entire body.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
