<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>6.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pityopsis</genus_name><species_name>aspera</species_name><species_authority>(A. Gray) Small</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Man. S.E. Fl.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1341. 1933</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Chrysopsis</genus_name><species_name>graminifolia</species_name><species_authority>(Pursh) Elliott</species_authority><variety_name>aspera</variety_name><variety_authority>A. Gray</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Syn. Fl. N. Amer. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1(2): 121. 1884</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Chrysopsis</genus_name><species_name>aspera</species_name><species_authority>(A. Gray) Shuttleworth ex Small</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Heterotheca</genus_name><species_name>aspera</species_name><species_authority>(A. Gray) Shinners</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials, 20–50 cm; rhizomes 1–20 cm. Stems usually 1, erect, green to brown distally, simple, slender, proximally silky-sericeous, distal 2/3 sometimes densely stipitate-glandular. Leaves: basal overwintering, in rosettes (at ends of short rhizomes), ascending to spreading, blades linear-oblanceolate, 50–250(–350) × 5–10 mm, margins sometimes stipitate-glandular, apices acute, faces sparsely to densely silky-sericeous; cauline ascending, linear, greatly reduced distally, margins sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular, sparsely sericeous, glabrescent, or densely stipitate-glandular; proximal 30–120 × 2–10 mm, distal 20–50 × 1–3 mm, sometimes glabrate. Heads (4–)10–79, in corymbiform arrays. Peduncles 1–7, 1–6 cm, densely stipitate-glandular, glabrescent; bracteoles linear, stipitate-glandular. Involucres turbinate, 4.5–8 mm (shorter than mature pappi). Phyllaries in 5–7 series, margins fimbriate, sparsely piloso-ciliate, moderately so distally (green zones in distal 1/2), apices acute, sometimes long piloso-ciliate distally, faces moderately stipitate-glandular. Ray florets 6–10; laminae 4–6 mm. Disc florets 15–45; corollas 4–5.5 mm, proximal throats glabrate to sparsely short-pilose, lobes 0.5 mm, glabrous to sparsely pilose. Cypselae fusiform, 2–3 mm, ribbed, faces strigose; pappi: outer of linear to linear-triangular scales 0.5–1 mm, inner of 25–35 bristles 5–6 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>se United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Pityopsis aspera grows on the outer coastal plain.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems stipitate-glandular throughout; proximal cauline leaf faces silky-sericeous, mid to distal margins stipitate-glandular, faces usually glabrate; Florida, Georgia</statement>
      <determination>6a. Pityopsis aspera var. aspera</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems sometimes stipitate-glandular distally; cauline leaf margins and faces sericeous; Louisiana to Virginia</statement>
      <determination>6a. Pityopsis aspera var. adenolepis</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
