<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Heterotheca</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Greene) Shinners" date="unknown">fulcrata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Field &amp; Lab.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>19: 71. 1951</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Astereae;genus Heterotheca;species fulcrata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Chrysopsis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene" date="unknown">fulcrata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>25: 119. 1898</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Chrysopsis;species fulcrata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Heterotheca fulcrata is distinguished by the one to several, usually distinctive, ovate-lanceolate bracts subtending at least some heads of the arrays; the bases of the bracts are attenuate to sometimes winged-subpetiolate. In plants with large, ovate distal leaves, the bracts are sometimes hidden by the leaves. Rarely, such bracts are missing below most heads or only one is present, making identification problematic, but the leaf margins usually harbor large hispido-strigose cilia along much of their length. The density of hairs and glands on leaves, the size and shape of leaves, and the number of florets vary greatly within the species. Four varieties are recognized on the basis of differences in those traits and in the frequency of large hispido-strigose hairs along the leaf margins. All four are sympatric along the Mogollon Rim and in the mountains south of the escarpment, in southeastern Arizona and adjacent New Mexico. Intermediate forms occur throughout the range; pure and mixed varietal populations occur in areas of sympatry. Plants in southern Idaho, northern Nevada, and northern Wyoming are atypical and easily misidentified as aberrant forms of H. villosa.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal margins of distalmost leaves abundantly long-hispido-strigose; leaf faces moderately hispido-strigose, moderately stipitate-glandular; Arizona, New Mexico, Texas, adjacent Mexico</description>
      <determination>8d. Heterotheca fulcrata var. senilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal margins of distal leaves sparsely long-hispido-strigose, often more proximal; leaf faces sparsely to densely strigose (rarely whitish), eglandular or sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal cauline leaf faces sparsely to moderately hispido-strigose, moderately stipitate-glandular; leaflike bracts subtending heads not well differentiated from linear-ovate to -lanceolate distal leaves (12–22 mm); involucres 5.7–8.4 mm; ray laminae 7.3–11 mm (averaging 9.6 mm); e Nevada to trans-Pecos Texas, adjacent Mexico</description>
      <determination>8c. Heterotheca fulcrata var. arizonica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal cauline leaf faces sparsely to densely strigose, sparsely to moderately stipitate-glandular or eglandular; leaflike bracts subtending heads ovate, usually large, well differentiated; distal cauline leaves ovate, lanceolate or oblong (18–40 mm); involucres 6.5–10.3 mm (averaging 7.8–8.5), ray laminae (8–)8.5–14.5 mm (averaging 11.5 mm); Front Ranges, Colorado, Wyoming, rare in ne Nevada, mountains of n Utah to se Arizona, trans-Pecos Texas, ne Mexico.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and stems sparsely to moderately hispido-strigose and stipitate-glandular; Front Range, Colorado, se Wyoming, mountains of e Nevada, Utah, n, w Arizona, s New Mexico, n Mexico</description>
      <determination>8a. Heterotheca fulcrata var. fulcrata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and stems moderately to densely short-strigose, eglandular or nearly so (small leaves sometimes nearly white); Colorado, New Mexico, Utah, Wyoming</description>
      <determination>8b. Heterotheca fulcrata var. amplifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
