<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ERIGERON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 863. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 371. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe astereae;genus ERIGERON</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek eri, early, or erio , woolly, and geron, old man, perhaps alluding to pappus, which becomes gray and accrescent in some species, or to solitary, woolly heads of some of species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">Achaetogeron</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Achaetogeron;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Trimorpha</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Trimorpha;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or perennials [subshrubs, shrubs, trees], (0.5–)2–90(–100) cm (taprooted, fibrous-rooted, or rhizomatous and fibrous-rooted, sometimes with simple or branched caudices, sometimes stoloniferous). Stems erect to ascending, decumbent, or prostrate, simple or branched, glabrous or hairy, sometimes glandular (hairs 2-seriate, minute, sometimes stipitate). Leaves basal and/or cauline (basal persistent or not to flowering); alternate; sessile or petiolate; blades 1-nerved (3-nerved), linear to lanceolate, oblanceolate, or spatulate (bases sometimes clasping), margins entire or ± dentate to pinnatifid, faces glabrous or hairy, sometimes glandular. Heads usually radiate, sometimes discoid or disciform (erect, nodding, or arching-pendent in bud), borne singly or in loose, corymbiform or paniculiform arrays. Involucres turbinate to hemispheric, 5–35 mm diam. Phyllaries 30–125(–150) in 2–5 series, 1- or 3-nerved (nerves golden-resinous; usually flat, rarely broadly keeled to convex), narrowly elliptic- to linear-lanceolate, unequal to equal, margins scarious or not, faces hairy or glabrous, sometimes glandular. Receptacles flat to conic, pitted, epaleate. Ray florets 0 or 12–350 in 1(–2+) series, pistillate, fertile; corollas usually white to bluish or purplish to pink, less commonly yellow (coiling from apices, reflexing at tube/lamina junction, or remaining ± straight and spreading). Peripheral florets (disciform heads) 50–200 in 1–4 series, pistillate. Disc florets 25–450, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow (nerves orange-resinous), tubes shorter than usually tubular, sometimes strongly inflated and indurate throats, lobes 5, erect to spreading, deltate; style-branch appendages mostly deltate (papillate). Cypselae (tan) oblong to oblong-obovoid, compressed to flattened, 2(–4)-nerved, or subterete, 5–14-nerved (sect. Wyomingia and some other species), faces glabrous or strigose or sericeous, eglandular; pappi persistent or readily falling, usually of outer setae or scales (0.1–0.4 mm), sometimes connate, plus 5–40(–50), stramineous, barbellate bristles, sometimes pappi only on ray or only on disc cypselae, or 0. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, mostly in temperate regions.</description>
  <number>186.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Fleabane</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">érigéron</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">vergerette</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 390 (173 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The North American and Central American species of Erigeron have been divided into sections (G. L. Nesom 1989c, 1990g, 1994b; Nesom and R. D. Noyes 1999), emphasizing variation in habit (especially taprooted versus rhizomatous and fibrous-rooted), vestiture, arrangement of heads in arrays and orientation before flowering (erect, nodding, or arching-pendent), behavior of ray corolla laminae (straight, reflexing, or coiling), cypsela and pappus morphology, and other morphologic features. The sequence and groupings of species treated here reflect significant modifications of earlier arrangements.</discussion>
  <discussion>G. L. Nesom (1989d) hypothesized that Trimorpha [Erigeron sect. Trimorpha (Cassini) de Candolle] is separate from Erigeron, more closely related to Conyza. Studies by W. Huber and colleagues (e.g., Huber 1993; Huber and Ö. Nilsson 1995) and R. D. Noyes (2000) have shown that Trimorpha species are closely related to those of sect. Erigeron and that both sections are relatively recently derived within the genus. As suggested by Nesom (1994b) and by Huber and Nilsson, and as discussed in detail and experimentally confirmed by Noyes, autogamous breeding systems apparently have arisen independently in groups of Astereae, including Trimorpha and Conyza, where the pistillate florets of a head are greatly increased in number (often outnumbering the bisexual florets), in multiple series, the inner sometimes with filiform, elaminate corollas, and the outer with reduced laminae.</discussion>
  <discussion>In the molecular analysis by R. D. Noyes (2000), Conyzinae comprises Erigeron, American Conyza, the four genera of the South American Leptostelma group, and the North American Aphanostephus; the cladistically basal and terminal taxa of the subtribe are members of Erigeron. Noyes (p. 107) observed that “strictly speaking, although the Conyzinae form a monophyletic group [with caveats regarding Old World Conyza], Erigeron is paraphyletic, as five other genera are derived from within it.” The molecular study included 46 of the 173 species treated here.</discussion>
  <discussion>Polyploidy is common among species of Erigeron, and agamospermy apparently is a common correlate of polyploidy, especially in odd-polyploid plants. Molecular phylogenetic data (R. D. Noyes 2000) indicate that agamospermy has arisen at least three times within the genus.</discussion>
  <discussion>In the descriptions and keys, some characteristics are assumed constant unless otherwise indicated (usually in parentheses); particular application of terms is discussed here. The indumentum of erigerons is often complex; in order to simplify descriptions, glabrous applies here only to absence of non-glandular hairs, eglandular to the absence of glandular hairs; a totally glabrous plant (in the usual sense) would be glabrous and eglandular. Petiole margins are eciliate or sparsely ciliate unless otherwise indicated. Leaf bases of most erigerons are broadened or not, not thickened and white-indurate. Margins of leaves in some erigerons are entire but for tiny callous enations that correspond to the callous tips of teeth on some leaves with serrate margins. Here, margins with such tiny enations are described as denticulate. Heads of some erigerons are “pseudodisciform” in the sense that the outer pistillate florets have relatively small, ± filiform laminae (such florets are technically “ray florets” even though their “rays” are inconspicuous) and the inner pistillate florets have no laminae on their corollas. The distinction between corollas without and those with laminae is sometimes arbitrary. Ray laminae are considered strap-shaped and spreading unless otherwise indicated. Descriptions of ray color as “blue” should be read as lavender-blue.</discussion>
  <discussion>Artificial distinctions are used in the key to groups of species recognized by leafy runners, pinnately lobed or dissected leaves, discoid or disciform heads, and yellow rays. Otherwise, species tend to be identified within natural groups. Couplets that use basal parts for distinction or inference of duration may be difficult if collections lack diagnostic basal parts or if the nature of the basal parts is not clear. Yet, these differences are significant in delimiting species groups and often critical in identification, and the pertinent species otherwise would be scattered widely in a more artificial key.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cronquist, A. 1947. A revision of the North American species of Erigeron, north of Mexico. Brittonia 6: 121–302.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1989c. Infrageneric taxonomy of New World Erigeron (Compositae: Astereae). Phytologia 67: 67–93.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1989d. The separation of Trimorpha (Compositae: Astereae) from Erigeron. Phytologia 67: 61–66.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 1990g. Taxonomy of the Erigeron coronarius group of Erigeron sect. Geniculactis (Asteraceae: Astereae). Phytologia 69: 237–253.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. 2004e. Taxonomic reevaluations in North American Erigeron (Asteraceae: Astereae). Sida 21: 19–40.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. and R. D. Noyes. 1999. Notes on sectional delimitations in Erigeron (Asteraceae: Astereae). Sida 18: 1161–1165.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_head>Key to Groups of Erigeron Species</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads discoid or disciform (pistillate florets 0 or their corollas filiform, lacking laminae)</description>
      <determination>Group 1, p. 260</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads radiate (corollas of pistillate florets bearing laminae, laminae sometimes filiform and hardly surpassing involucres, especially Groups 8 and 11).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants with herbaceous, leafy runners or slender, scale-leaved rhizomes</description>
      <determination>Group 2, p. 261</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants without leafy runners or scale-leaved rhizomes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves pinnately lobed or dissected</description>
      <determination>Group 3, p. 262</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually entire or dentate, rarely with 1–2 pairs of coarse lobes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or short-lived perennials.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pappus bristles absent on ray and/or disc cypselae</description>
      <determination>Group 4, p. 262</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pappus bristles present on ray and disc cypselae.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae nearly filiform, erect.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually in loose, racemiform arrays; pistillate florets in 1 series, all with filiform laminae; pappus bristles not accrescent</description>
      <determination>114. Erigeron lonchophyllus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually in corymbiform arrays; pistillate florets in 2 zones, outer with nearly filiform laminae, inner tubular and essentially elaminate; pappus bristles accrescent (elongating in fruit to ca. 2 times involucres)</description>
      <determination>Group 8 (in part), p. 265</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae strap-shaped, usually spreading.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants fibrous-rooted</description>
      <determination>Group 5, p. 262</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants taprooted</description>
      <determination>Group 6, p. 263</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 3-lobed or 3-dentate at apices; plants usually with relatively slender, rhizomelike caudex branches (rarely in E. compositus )</description>
      <determination>Group 7, p. 264</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not 3-lobed or 3-dentate at apices; plants with or without slender caudex branches.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate florets in 2 zones, outer with nearly filiform, erect laminae, sometimes shorter than involucres, inner tubular and essentially elaminate; pappus bristles accrescent (elongating in fruit to ca. 2 times involucres)</description>
      <determination>Group 8 (in part), p. 265</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate florets all with strap-shaped, spreading laminae, occasionally reduced, nearly filiform and erect (in some arctic, monocephalous species); pappus bristles not accrescent (except in E. uniflorus var. eriocephalus ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rays yellow</description>
      <determination>Group 9, p. 265</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rays white or blue to pink.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants fibrous-rooted (usually rhizomatous, rhizomes sometimes abbreviated or apparently lacking in E. glabellus ) or without an evident taproot (taproot weakly developed or not collected because of extensive rhizome or caudex system).</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes or caudex branches slender (without apparent well-defined central axes); ray laminae strap-shaped</description>
      <determination>Group 10, p. 266</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes thickened (usually evident as single central axes; abbreviated or apparently lacking in E. glabellus ); ray laminae filiform or strap-shaped.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves reduced or present only as scales (cauline largest at midstem); ray laminae not coiling; cypselae 5–6-nerved, glabrous</description>
      <determination>2. Erigeron hyssopifolius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves usually well developed (sometimes withering by flowering); ray laminae usually coiling, often tardily or only at tips (filiform and straight in some species of</description>
      <determination>Group 11); cypselae mostly 2(–4)-nerved (4–7-nerved in E. glacialis and E. howellii ), usually strigose.</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 2–25(–35) cm; leaves mostly basal (bases of cauline not clasping orsubclasping); heads 1–3</description>
      <determination>Group 11, p. 266</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (5–)15–90 cm; leaves basal and cauline or mostly cauline (bases ofcauline usually clasping to subclasping); heads 1–21</description>
      <determination>Group 12, p. 267</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants usually evidently taprooted (sometimes also with branched caudices).</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials (short-lived), caudices usually not branched (stems and leaves arisingfrom near roots)</description>
      <determination>Group 13, p. 269</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials, caudices usually branched.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves all or mostly cauline (basal not markedly larger than cauline, internodes relatively short), blades linear or filiform to narrowly oblong, essentially uniform; California and immediately adjacent areas</description>
      <determination>Group 14, p. 269</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly basal or basal and cauline (if basal withering by flowering, then persistent leaf bases usually evident), oblanceolate, obovate, or spatulate (if linear or filiform then basal larger than cauline and internodes relatively wide); w North America.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal leaves loosely clustered (not in persistent rosettes, usually with evident internodes), blades oblanceolate or linear to filiform; stems and leaves ± strigose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 20–70 cm; leaves oblanceolate; pappi readily falling, of (8–)10–12 bristles; stems not more densely hairy proximally than distally.</description>
      <determination>3. Erigeron neomexicanus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 10–30(–50) cm; leaves linear to filiform; pappi persistent, of 20–30 bristles; stems more densely white-strigose proximally than distally (hairs loosely appressed to ascending, fine)</description>
      <determination>53. Erigeron filifolius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal leaves tightly clustered (usually in persistent rosettes, internodes not readily evident), blades 1- or 3-nerved, linear to oblanceolate, obovate, or spatulate; stems and leaves strigose to hirsute, villous, or lanate-villous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves obovate-spatulate, 5–25 mm wide, cauline little reduced distally or relatively even-sized, bases usually subclasping (except in E. oreganus ); heads usually 1, sometimes 2–5 from proximal axils</description>
      <determination>Group 17, p. 271</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves linear to oblanceolate or spatulate, (0.5–)1–13(–15) mm wide, cauline usually gradually or abruptly reduced distally, bases not clasping or subclasping; heads 1–16.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles prominently ciliate (hairs spreading, thick-based); leaves mostly linear to narrowly oblanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal and cauline or sometimes mostly basal; heads 1–5; ray laminae reflexing (coiling in E. davisii , added to key for contrast with E. engelmannii )</description>
      <determination>Group 15, p. 270</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly basal; heads 1; ray laminae sometimes coiling, not reflexing</description>
      <determination>Group 16, p. 271</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles not prominently ciliate (or if so, hairs thin-based or ascending to loosely appressed); leaves linear to obovate or spatulate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves glabrous or glabrate (minutely glandular in E. nauseosus , sometimes minutely glandular distally in E. arenarioides ); phyllaries minutely glandular, rarely also sparsely strigose or hirsuto-villous (sometimes glabrous, eglandular), often purplish; ray laminae reflexing, coiling, or straight and spreading</description>
      <determination>Group 18, p. 271</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and/or leaves strigose or sericeous to hirsute or villous; phyllaries strigose to hirsute, sometimes glandular, rarely purplish; ray laminae coiling or straight and spreading (reflexing in E. parishii and E. canus ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with spreading hairs</description>
      <determination>Group 19, p. 273</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with appressed hairs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems ascending to decumbent, sometimes purplish proximally; basal leaves (1–)3-nerved, usually linear to oblanceolate, sometimes obovate; stems and leavesstrigose to hirsute</description>
      <determination>Group 20, p. 274</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems mostly erect, usually not purplish proximally; basal leaves linear to oblanceolate or spatulate; stems and leaves usually strigose or sericeous (hairs usually whitish, closely appressed, even-length).</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly spatulate</description>
      <determination>Group 21, p. 275</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear to oblanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases of basal and proximal cauline leaves abruptly widened, thickened, and white-indurate</description>
      <determination>Group 22, p. 275</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases sometimes widened, not thickened and white-indurate</description>
      <determination>Group 23, p. 275</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 1</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal or basal and cauline, cauline reduced distally or bractlike (except in E. lassenianus ); heads discoid or disciform; w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems ascending to decumbent or prostrate-ascending; leaves basal and cauline, cauline usually continuing relatively even-sized nearly to heads; heads (1–)3–7, discoid</description>
      <determination>12. Erigeron lassenianus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually erect to ascending; leaves mostly basal, cauline reduced distally or bractlike; heads usually 1(–4 in E. aphanactis ), discoid or disciform; w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves pinnatifid (lobes linear)</description>
      <determination>92. Erigeron mancus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not pinnatifid, sometimes ternately dissected or lobed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate florets 0 (heads discoid).</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigose or glabrous; leaf bases white-indurate (usually thickened)</description>
      <determination>54. Erigeron bloomeri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely hirsutulous (hairs deflexed to spreading-hirsute) at least proxi-mally; leaf bases greenish, herbaceous (not thickened)</description>
      <determination>81. Erigeron ovinus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate florets 20–100, corollas tubular, laminae absent or not surpassing involucres (heads disciform).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ternately dissected or lobed</description>
      <determination>59. Erigeron compositus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not ternately dissected or lobed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems bracteate; heads 1; disc corolla throats not indurate or inflated; pappus bristles 15–25 (outer pappi of inconspicuous setae; carpopodiayellowish)</description>
      <determination>25. Erigeron chrysopsidis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems leafy to bracteate; heads 1–4; disc corolla throats white-indurate and somewhat inflated; pappus bristles 7–20 (outer pappi of subulate scales or setae; carpopodia whitish).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials; disc corollas conspicuously puberulent</description>
      <determination>32. Erigeron aphanactis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Biennials or short-lived perennials; disc corollas glabrate</description>
      <determination>33. Erigeron calvus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves cauline (basal usually withering by flowering), usually relatively even-sized distally; heads discoid; California, Nevada, Oregon.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries eglandular</description>
      <determination>101. Erigeron inornatus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries minutely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 30–90 cm; stems erect, arising from woody rootcrowns; involucres 5.5–7.5 mm; phyllary apices purplish; pappus bristles 26–38</description>
      <determination>97. Erigeron greenei</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 8–20(–30) cm; stems erect or ascending, usually arising singly from rhizomelike caudex branches; involucres 4–6 mm; phyllary apices greenish orpurplish (var. angustatus ); pappus bristles 20–61</description>
      <determination>99. Erigeron reductus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves oblanceolate to narrowly oblong-oblanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems arising from rhizomelike caudex branches; leaves usually reduced distally; involucres 14–20 mm diam</description>
      <determination>108. Erigeron supplex</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems arising from woody taproots; leaves seldom reduced distally; involucres 7–15 mm diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves eglandular; phyllaries eglandular or sparsely to densely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or sparsely appressed-hairy; phyllaries usually eglandular</description>
      <determination>101. Erigeron inornatus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsutulous to hispido-pilose; phyllaries eglandular or glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely hirsutulous (hairs usually ± deflexed, sometimes loosely antrorsely ascending); phyllaries eglandular or sparsely glandular</description>
      <determination>101. Erigeron inornatus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparsely hispido-pilose, hairs usually stiff, spreading, sometimes antrorsely ascending or appressed; phyllaries densely glandular</description>
      <determination>102. Erigeron petrophilus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems (at least distally) and leaves glandular (variably invested with nonglandular hairs); phyllaries densely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 30–90 cm; stems ascending-erect; leaves 20–40 mm; involucres 12–</description>
      <determination>100. Erigeron biolettii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 5–20(–30) cm; stems ascending to decumbent; leaves 7–25 mm; involucres 7–12 mm diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres (3.5–)4–5 mm</description>
      <determination>103. Erigeron miser</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 5.5–7(–8) mm</description>
      <determination>102. Erigeron petrophilus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 2</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves: bases not clasping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves: margins usually coarsely serrate or crenate (distal teeth 2–5 pairs); involucres 6–8 mm; ray florets 225–350, laminae filiform, tightly coiling; coastal, Louisiana, Texas</description>
      <determination>172. Erigeron procumbens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves: margins entire or shallowly dentate; involucres 3–5(–6) mm; ray florets 40–130, laminae strap-shaped, not coiling; inland, w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely hirsutulous (hairs usually slightly deflexed); stoloniform branches usually without terminal plantlets</description>
      <determination>160. Erigeron tracyi (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigose, often sparsely so, hairs strongly antrorsely appressed to closely ascending; stoloniform branches usually with terminal plantlets</description>
      <determination>161. Erigeron flagellaris (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves: bases clasping to subclasping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually abruptly dilated immediately proximal to heads, villous; leaf marginsusually dentate to denticulate, rarely entire; e United States</description>
      <determination>130. Erigeron pulchellus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems not dilated proximal to heads, nearly glabrous, strigose, or hirsute to hirtellous proximally; leaf margins entire or serrulate to serrate; w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 5–15 cm; stems sparsely pilose (hairs spreading-ascending), strigose near bases, eglandular; involucres 4–5 × 8–10 mm; ray florets 32–45, laminae 8–11 mm; pappus bristles 15–19</description>
      <determination>146. Erigeron kuschei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 15–60 cm; stems hirsute to hirtellous, minutely glandular to eglandular; involucres 6–9 × 9–19 mm; ray florets 40–99, laminae 11–20 mm; pappus bristles 20–32.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous, sometimes sparsely hirsuto-pilose proximal to heads, minutely glandular or eglandular; basal leaves usually persistent, mostly spatulate; phyllaries minutely glandular, otherwise usually glabrous, sometimes sparsely villous at bases</description>
      <determination>144. Erigeron eximius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute to hirtellous (hairs retrorsely spreading), sometimes sparsely glandular; basal leaves usually withering by flowering, elliptic-ovate to spatulate-obovate; phyllaries pilose-hirsute, sometimes minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>142. Erigeron rybius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 3</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and phyllaries sparsely hispido-pilose (hairs spreading, straight), densely stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>155. Erigeron lobatus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and phyllaries densely and evenly puberulous-hirsutulous (hairs spreading, often crinkly), sometimes minutely glandular as well.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely and evenly puberulous-hirsutulous (hairs spreading to spreading-descending or -ascending, often crinkly), minutely glandular at least distally, usu-ally throughout; involucres 3–4 × (5–)7–11 mm; rays 75–150</description>
      <determination>159. Erigeron divergens (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually sparsely strigose, sometimes sparsely hirsutulous distally, sometimes minutely glandular near heads; involucres 2–3.5 × 5.5–7.5 mm; rays 37–85</description>
      <determination>166. Erigeron religiosus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 20–70 cm; heads (1–)5–25(–50); rays white, laminae reflexing; pappi readily falling, of (8–)10–12 bristles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems, leaves, and phyllaries eglandular or glands minute and non-capitate, otherwise usually moderately to densely strigose (hairs sometimes spreading, 0.1–2 mm)</description>
      <determination>3. Erigeron neomexicanus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems, leaves, and phyllaries densely glandular (glands relatively large, capitate), otherwise glabrous or stems sparsely hirsuto-villous (hairs 0.6–2 mm)</description>
      <determination>4. Erigeron oreophilus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (1.5–)2–16(–25) cm; heads 1–4; rays blue to white or pinkish, laminae reflexing or not; pappi persistent, bristles 7–30.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves abruptly reduced distally or nearly absent, usually minutely glandular; heads 1; rays 40–70, corollas usually blue; pappus bristles 25–30; sites at 2700–3700(–4000) m</description>
      <determination>91. Erigeron pinnatisectus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves gradually reduced distally, eglandular; heads 1–4; rays 20–38(–46), corollas usually white to pinkish; pappus bristles 7–19; sites at 1200–3100 m.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudex branches not retaining old leaf bases; ray laminae not reflexing</description>
      <determination>167. Erigeron sionis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudex branches retaining old leaf bases; ray laminae reflexing</description>
      <determination>87. Erigeron pringlei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 4</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pappus bristles absent on ray and disc cypselae</description>
      <determination>168. Erigeron versicolor</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pappus bristles absent on ray cypselae, 8–15 on disc cypselae.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparsely piloso-hispid (hairs spreading), sometimes strigose distally; leaves: basal usually withering by flowering, cauline little reduced proximal to midstem, blades lanceolate to oblong or ovate, margins coarsely serrate to nearly entire</description>
      <determination>169. Erigeron annuus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems ± strigose to strigillose or hirsuto-strigillose (hairs usually ascending, rarely spreading); leaves: basal usually persistent to flowering, blades spatulate to broadly or narrowly oblanceolate to linear, cauline usually gradually reduced distally, margins entire or ± serrate or crenate</description>
      <determination>170. Erigeron strigosus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 5</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads mostly 1, sometimes 2–3.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems greenish proximally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsutulous (hairs spreading-deflexed)</description>
      <determination>160. Erigeron tracyi (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigose (hairs antrorsely appressed)</description>
      <determination>161. Erigeron flagellaris (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually reddish proximally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched mostly on distal 1 / 3 – 1 / 4 , strigose, rarely hirsute proximally</description>
      <determination>171. Erigeron tenuis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched mostly at or proximal to midstem, usually pilose to villous (hairs spreading to spreading-deflexed) proximally, strigose distally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices usually woody, without basal offsets; pappi : outer of setae, inner of (5–)12–17 bristles</description>
      <determination>162. Erigeron modestus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices not woody, with rhizomelike, relatively slender, lignescent, basal offsets 1–7 cm; pappi : outer of scales, inner of 8–11 bristles</description>
      <determination>164. Erigeron vicinus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually 3–50(–100+), sometimes 1 (earliest season).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly basal (usually fleshy-thickened, cauline mostly bractlike), margins entireor denticulate to mucronulate; cypselae 4-nerved, 1.2–1.6 mm</description>
      <determination>5. Erigeron vernus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal and cauline (not fleshy-thickened), margins entire or dentate, serrate, crenate, or pinnately lobed; cypselae 2-nerved, 0.6–1.2 mm or 1.1–1.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots and proximalmost portions of caudices woody</description>
      <determination>162. Erigeron modestus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots and caudices not woody.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually entire, sometimes shallowly dentate; ray laminae tardily coiling; disc corollas 4–5.5 mm; cypselae 1.2–1.5 mm</description>
      <determination>138. Erigeron glabellus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves serrate or crenate to pinnately lobed; ray laminae not coiling; disc corollas 1.5–3.2 mm; cypselae 0.6–1.2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually reddish proximally; cauline leaf bases not clasping orsubclasping; ray corollas 3–5 mm</description>
      <determination>171. Erigeron tenuis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems green proximally; cauline leaf bases clasping to subclasping; ray corollas 4–10 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually leafy to arrays; involucres 4–6 × 6–15 mm; ray florets 150–250(–400), corollas usually white or pinkish, 5–10 mm; pappus bristles 15–20(–30)</description>
      <determination>112. Erigeron philadelphicus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually leafy proximally (leaves 0 or reduced to bracts proximal to arrays); involucres 2.5–4 × 4.5–10 mm; ray florets 100–150, corollas usually blue, sometimes white to pink, 4–6 mm; pappus bristles 10–15</description>
      <determination>113. Erigeron quercifolius</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 6</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems ± strigose (hairs straight) at least distally, sometimes spreading-villous to deflexed-villous proximally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems spreading- to deflexed-villous proximally, ± strigose (hairs straight) distally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals or biennials with thick taproots; stems sometimes lignescent proximally; leaf bases not clasping or subclasping</description>
      <determination>162. Erigeron modestus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals (short-lived) with slender taproots; stems herbaceous; leaf bases commonly clasping to subclasping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems erect; cauline leaf bases sometimes barely subclasping; ray florets 44–70, corollas 3–6 mm; pappus bristles 9–11</description>
      <determination>110. Erigeron geiseri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems initially erect, later ascending to decumbent; cauline leaf bases clasping; ray florets 95–160(–250), corollas 2.5–4 mm; pappus bristles 10–13(–15)</description>
      <determination>111. Erigeron tenellus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigose throughout (sometimes sparsely hirsutulous distally in E. religiosus ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 3–15 cm; stems erect (usually 1 and simple); heads usually 1</description>
      <determination>161. Erigeron flagellaris (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 6–30(–40) cm; stems decumbent-ascending (often multiple from bases, commonly branched from midstems); heads initially 1, sometimes more from axillary branches.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves 10–70 × 2–8(–13) mm, margins usually entire, sometimes dentate or pinnately divided; involucres 2–3.5 mm; cypselae 0.8–1.2 mm; pappus bristles 6–12</description>
      <determination>166. Erigeron religiosus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves 10–30 × 2–6 mm, margins entire; involucres 3.5–4 mm; cypselae 0.7–0.9 mm; pappus bristles 5–8</description>
      <determination>163. Erigeron multiceps (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hispido-pilose, hirsute, hirsutulous (hairs upcurved), or puberulous-hirsutulous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins lobed, often pinnatifid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparsely hispido-pilose, densely stipitate-glandular; pappi of scales and bristles</description>
      <determination>155. Erigeron lobatus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsutulous (hairs upcurved), sometimes minutely glandular; pappi of bristles (lacking outer series of setae)</description>
      <determination>158. Erigeron bellidiastrum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins entire or dentate, uncommonly with 1–2 pairs of coarse, rounded lobes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparsely hispido-pilose (hairs 0.5–2 mm) and minutely stipitate-glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 5–20 cm; stems usually erect, sometimes ascending; leaf margins usually dentate, sometimes entire; involucres 5–7(–9) mm diam.; ray corollas 3.5–5.5mm;disc corollas 1.7–2.4 mm</description>
      <determination>157. Erigeron velutipes</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 15–40 cm; stems procumbent or ascending-decumbent; leaf margins usually entire, rarely 1-toothed; involucres 4–6 mm diam.; ray corollas 3–3.7 mm; disc corollas 1.5–1.8 mm</description>
      <determination>156. Erigeron piscaticus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsutulous or hirsute, sometimes minutely gland-dotted (use lens).</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely hirsutulous (hairs spreading-deflexed, relatively even); heads 1(–3)</description>
      <determination>160. Erigeron tracyi (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsutulous, hirsute, puberuloso-hirsutulous, or spreading-hairy (hairs not all spreading-deflexed and of relatively even lengths); heads usually (1–)5–100.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsutulous (hairs upcurved), eglandular; pappi: outer cartilaginous crowns, inner of bristles; some ray florets positioned among inner phyllaries</description>
      <determination>158. Erigeron bellidiastrum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute to puberuloso-hirsutulous (hairs spreading, spreading-descending or -ascending, sometimes crinkly), usually minutely glandular (use lens); pappi of outer setae or scales and inner bristles; all ray florets interior to inner phyllaries.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems puberuloso-hirsutulous (hairs evenly distributed, bases not thickened); buds nodding; ray laminae remaining relatively straight; cypsela nerves whitish; pappi of outer scales or setae plus 6–9(–12) inner bristles</description>
      <determination>159. Erigeron divergens (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute or hirsuto-hirtellous to hispid (hairs only along ribs, bases thickened); buds erect; ray florets reflexing or downward curving-reflexing; cypsela nerves orange; pappi sometimes of outer scales or setae plus 9–16 inner bristles or only of bristles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 25–50 × 2–5 mm; involucres 5–8 mm diam.; ray florets 125–180, corollas 6–7 mm, laminae reflexing; cypselae 0.7–1 mm; pappi of outer setae or lanceolate scales plus (10–)12–17 inner bristles</description>
      <determination>152. Erigeron arisolius</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 10–30 × 0.5–1.5 mm; involucres 4–6 mm diam.; ray florets (60–)85–130(–195), corollas 3.8–5 mm, laminae downward curving-reflexing; cypselae 0.6–0.7 mm; pappi of outer scales or setae plus 9–14 inner bristles or only of bristles</description>
      <determination>153. Erigeron sceptrifer</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 7</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched (leafy to near heads).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves sparsely strigose, eglandular; ray laminae reflexing</description>
      <determination>87. Erigeron pringlei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves hirsute or hispido-hirsute, minutely glandular; ray laminae not coiling or reflexing.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves spatulate, 15–30 × 1.5–4 mm (reduced to bracts on peduncles), mostly 3-lobed (lobes linear to oblong-oblanceolate, about as wide as central portion of blades); phyllaries glabrous or sometimes sparsely hispid, densely minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>58. Erigeron allocotus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves cuneate to obovate, 150–400 × 10–20 mm (nearly even-sized to near heads), 3-lobed or -dentate (lobes much narrower than central portion of blades); phyllar-ies usually densely villoso-hirsute, minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>63. Erigeron basalticus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems simple (± scapiform, leafy mostly on proximal 1 / 2 , or leaves mostly or distally bractlike).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices simple or branches usually relatively short and thick; leaves (1–)2–3 times ternately lobed or dissected</description>
      <determination>59. Erigeron compositus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudex branches rhizomelike, relatively slender; leaves entire or 1-ternately lobed or toothed (1–2 in E. flabellifolius ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Oldest and largest leaves mostly entire, younger commonly toothed or lobed; Canada, Alaska.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae strap-shaped (relatively broad), spreading; pappi whitish to tawny, bristles often twisted</description>
      <determination>65. Erigeron lanatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae filiform (often involute), usually erect; pappi usually purplish (tawny-white to yellowish in E. pallens ), bristles not twisted.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pappi tawny-white to yellowish; leaves entire or shallowly 3-lobed apically</description>
      <determination>68. Erigeron pallens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pappi usually purplish; leaves entire or toothed or lobed on margins or apically.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 1–5 cm; leaves spatulate to oblanceolate-spatulate, 2–4(–5) mm wide, margins entire or shallowly (2–)3-lobed or -toothed apically, faces moder-ately villous and minutely glandular; phyllaries densely lanate-villous</description>
      <determination>67. Erigeron denalii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (2–)3–9(–14) cm; leaves linear to narrowly oblanceolate, 1–2.5(–3) mm wide, margins entire or (mostly on early leaves) with 1 or 2 shallow, lateral lobes or teeth, faces sometimes sparsely hirsuto-villous, minutelyglandular; phyllaries sparsely pilose or glabrous</description>
      <determination>66. Erigeron purpuratus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Oldest and largest leaves dentate or lobed, younger entire; United States and ( E. trifidus ) s Canada.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems, leaves, and involucres glabrous, glandular; leaf lobes commonly secondarily dentate or lobed</description>
      <determination>64. Erigeron flabellifolius</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems, leaves, and phyllaries hirsute to villoso-hirsute or villous, glandular; leaf lobes not secondarily dentate or lobed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf lobes acute; involucres 8–12 mm; ray corollas 10–15 mm</description>
      <determination>60. Erigeron trifidus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf lobes rounded to obtuse; involucres 5–7 mm; ray corollas 4–10 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants forming dense, compact cushions; leaves 3–16 × 3–6 mm; phyllaries hirsuto-villous to villous (hairs with colored cross walls); ray corollas 6–10 mm</description>
      <determination>61. Erigeron salishii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose, relatively loose; leaves (5–)10–25(–30) × 4–10 mm; phyllaries hirsute to villoso-hirsute (hairs without colored cross walls); ray corollas 4–7 mm</description>
      <determination>62. Erigeron vagus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 8</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries usually sparsely hirsute to villoso-hirsute, eglandular; peduncles straight; leaves mostly 2–6 mm wide</description>
      <determination>117. Erigeron elatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries hairy or glabrous, minutely glandular; peduncles curved; leaves 2–16 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 20–60(–80) cm; sometimes taprooted; heads 1 or 5–35; phyllaries glabrous or sparsely hirsute and glandular; outer pistillate florets 150–250; leaves 3–16 mm wide;pappus bristles (18–)25–35</description>
      <determination>115. Erigeron acris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 5–25(–35) cm; usually fibrous-rooted or weakly short-rhizomatous, sometimes taprooted; heads 1–6(–8); phyllaries sparsely hirsuto-villous or glabrous and glandular; outer pistillate florets 40–70; leaves 2–6(–10) mm wide; pappus bristles (12–)14–21</description>
      <determination>116. Erigeron nivalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 9</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants fibrous-rooted (caudices simple or branched, not taprooted); basal and proximal cauline leaves spatulate to oblanceolate-spatulate</description>
      <determination>118. Erigeron aureus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants taprooted; basal and proximal cauline leaves linear to linear-oblanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigose; leaf bases widened, white-indurate, and sheathing</description>
      <determination>57. Erigeron linearis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigose or hispidulous to hirsute; leaf bases relatively thin, not sheathing.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly basal, in tufts; stems evenly hispidulous to hirsute</description>
      <determination>25. Erigeron chrysopsidis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly cauline (proximal internodes elongate); stems usually strigose (at least on distal 1 / 2 )</description>
      <determination>26. Erigeron piperianus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 10</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves all or mostly cauline (basal relatively small or withering by flowering).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually prostrate to decumbent-trailing, sometimes ascending-erect (taproots commonly not evident or not collected); cypselae 2-nerved, sparsely strigose; pappus bristles18–26</description>
      <determination>107. Erigeron elmeri (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems erect; cypselae 5–6-nerved, glabrous; pappus bristles 25–35.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 50–100 mm; phyllaries in 4–5 series; Arizona, New Mexico</description>
      <determination>1. Erigeron rhizomatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 10–30 mm; phyllaries in 2–3 series; ne United States and Canada</description>
      <determination>2. Erigeron hyssopifolius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal or basal and cauline.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants mat-forming; leaves basal; leaves all basal; rays 10–20</description>
      <determination>86. Erigeron scopulinus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants producing rhizomes or rhizome-like caudex branches, not mat-forming; leaves basal and cauline (basal leaves 10–120); rays 15–100.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bases of stems and basal leaves greenish; cauline leaf bases subclasping (rarely in E. sanctarum ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems ascending, sparsely pilose (hairs spreading-ascending), strigose proximally, eglandular; proximal leaves spatulate; rays 32–45, white; Arizona</description>
      <determination>146. Erigeron kuschei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems erect, sparsely hirsuto-villous (hairs usually retrorse), eglandular; proximal leaves oblanceolate to oblanceolate-spatulate; rays 45–90, blue to purple; California</description>
      <determination>109. Erigeron sanctarum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bases of stems and basal leaves purplish; cauline leaf bases not subclasping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants taprooted (taproots commonly not evident or not collected); involucres 4–6 × 7–13 mm; phyllaries erect, narrowly elliptic, apices appressed, abaxial faces glabrous or sparsely strigose; rays 15–60, laminae reflexing</description>
      <determination>83. Erigeron leiomerus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants fibrous-rooted; involucres 5–7.5 × 9–19 mm; phyllaries often loose, linear-lanceolate, apices spreading, abaxial faces sparsely to moderately villous to hirsuto-villous; rays 30–100, laminae not reflexing or coiling, sometimes tardily coiling.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves 20–120 × 2–11 mm; phyllaries sparsely to moderately villous to hirsuto-villous, densely minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>149. Erigeron ursinus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal and proximal cauline leaves 20–40(–90) × 1–3(–5) mm; phyllaries strigoso-hirsute to strigose (hairs appressed or slightly loose), sometimesminutely glandular</description>
      <determination>150. Erigeron gracilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 11</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae erect, ± filiform, 3–6(–8) mm (0.3–1 mm wide).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hairs of phyllaries and distal stems with dark reddish to blackish-purple cross walls; phyllaries usually dark purple; involucres 10–15(–20) mm diam</description>
      <determination>129. Erigeron humilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hairs of phyllaries with clear or sometimes bright reddish cross walls; phyllaries green or reddish purple; involucres 12–30 mm diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 8–10(–11) mm; phyllaries reddish purple, densely lanate (hairs tangled,soft); pappi accrescent (surpassing disc corollas and involucres in fruit)</description>
      <determination>127. Erigeron uniflorus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 6–8 mm; phyllaries usually green, villous (usually mostly on proximal 1 / 2 ,hairs rigid, usually oriented in single direction); pappi not accrescent</description>
      <determination>128. Erigeron alpiniformis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae spreading, strap-shaped, 5–13 mm (mostly 1–2 mm wide).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and phyllaries densely and closely lanate</description>
      <determination>125. Erigeron muirii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and phyllaries hirsute to villous, villoso-sericeous, woolly-villous, or strigillose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hairs on phyllaries with black or dark purple cross walls.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves hirsute (apices acute to obtuse); disc corollas 3.5–5 mm</description>
      <determination>126. Erigeron hyperboreus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves glabrous or sparsely hirsute (apices rounded to retuse); disc corollas2.4–3.2 mm</description>
      <determination>119. Erigeron melanocephalus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hairs on phyllaries with clear or reddish to reddish purple cross walls.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal leaves narrowly oblanceolate, (10–)40–160 mm; heads 1–2(–4) from branches at midstems</description>
      <determination>124. Erigeron yukonensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal leaves oblong-oblanceolate to oblanceolate, obovate, or spatulate, 10–70(–120) mm; heads 1.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves oblong-oblanceolate to narrowly obovate (apices acute), bases of cauline often subclasping; phyllaries hirsute to hirsuto-villous or villous (hairs whitish, without colored cross walls); ray florets 65–110, corollas 13–17 mm; outer pappi of relatively long setae or scales</description>
      <determination>123. Erigeron porsildii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves oblanceolate to obovate or spatulate (apices rounded), bases of cauline never subclasping; phyllaries ± villous (hairs glassy, often with reddish cross walls); ray florets 20–130, corollas 5–13(–15) mm; outer pappi of relatively short setae.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray florets 25–40, corollas white; basal leaves spatulate (petioles equaling or longerthan blades); phyllaries hirsute to hirsuto-villous</description>
      <determination>121. Erigeron flettii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray florets 25–130, corollas usually blue to pink, rarely white; basal leaves oblanceolate to obovate or spatulate (if spatulate, petioles shorter than or equaling blades); phyllaries hirsute to hirsuto-villous or moderately to densely white-woolly-villous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries hirsute to hirsuto-villous, hairs without colored cross walls</description>
      <determination>120. Erigeron algidus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries moderately to densely woolly-villous, hairs sometimes with reddish cross walls</description>
      <determination>122. Erigeron grandiflorus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 12</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries villoso-lanate or hirsuto-villous (at least basal part of hairs with black or reddish to purple cross walls), minutely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries hirsuto-villous (hair cross walls black)</description>
      <determination>141. Erigeron coulteri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries densely villoso-lanate (hair cross walls reddish to purple)</description>
      <determination>143. Erigeron elatior</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries glandular and/or variously hairy (hair cross walls not distinctly colored).</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems procumbent to decumbent-ascending (plants forming dense colonies); leaves fleshy</description>
      <determination>139. Erigeron glaucus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems erect to ascending (not forming dense colonies); leaves not fleshy.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Primary rhizomes slender, producing scale-leaved runners or stoloniform rhizomes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually abruptly dilated immediately proximal to heads; e United States</description>
      <determination>130. Erigeron pulchellus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems not abruptly dilated; w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 5–15 cm; stems sparsely pilose (hairs spreading-ascending), strigose proximally, eglandular; involucres 4–5 × 8–10 mm; ray florets 32–45, corollas 8–11 mm; pappus bristles 15–19</description>
      <determination>146. Erigeron kuschei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 15–60 cm; stems hirsute to hirtellous, glandular to nearly eglandular; involucres 6–9 × 9–19 mm; ray florets 40–99, corollas 11–20 mm; pappus bristles 20–32.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually glabrous, sometimes sparsely hirsuto-pilose proximal to heads, minutely glandular to nearly eglandular; basal leaves usually persistent, spatulate; phyllaries usually glabrous, sometimes sparselyvillous at bases, minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>144. Erigeron eximius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute to hirtellous (hairs retrorsely spreading), eglandular or sparsely glandular; basal leaves usually withering by flowering, elliptic-ovate to spatulate-obovate; phyllaries piloso-hirsute, sometimes minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>142. Erigeron rybius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Primary rhizomes relatively thick, sometimes woody, fibrous-rooted.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries relatively densely hairy, eglandular or glands essentially obscured by hairs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose (stems from fibrous-rooted rhizomes or caudices with woody, rhizomelike branches); involucres 5–6 × 8–13 mm; phyllaries usually purplish</description>
      <determination>151. Erigeron hessii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not cespitose (caudices simple or branched); involucres 5–9 × 9–22 mm; phyllaries greenish.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants with relatively short and thickened caudices or rhizomes, usually appearing fibrous-rooted; phyllaries hirsute to strigose, eglandular</description>
      <determination>38. Erigeron glabellus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants evidently rhizomatous; phyllaries hirsute to villous, glandular or eglandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries villoso-hirsute, eglandular; alpine habitats, w Canada,Alaska, Oregon, Washington</description>
      <determination>131. Erigeron peregrinus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries hirsute to piloso-hirsute, densely minutely glandular; lower elevation habitats, Rocky Mountains, Alberta, United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigose to strigoso-hirsute or hirsute, eglandular; basal leaves often 3-nerved, margins shallowly serrate, faces loosely strigose; rays 25–80, white; disc corollas 2.9–4 mm</description>
      <determination>140. Erigeron arizonicus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely hirsute to hirsutulous or glabrous, minutely glandular to stipitate-glandular; basal leaves margins entire, faces glabrous or sparsely hirsute; rays 75–150, mostly blue to purple; disc corollas 3.5–4.5 mm</description>
      <determination>145. Erigeron formosissimus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries sometimes sparsely to moderately hirsute to villous (hairs not obscuring glands), glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves often prominently 3-nerved, margins coarsely dentate to shallowly serrate or entire.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins entire or shallowly serrate, faces loosely strigose; phyllaries moderately piloso-hirsute; ray corollas 8–10 mm; Arizona, New Mexico</description>
      <determination>140. Erigeron arizonicus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins usually coarsely dentate (teeth 1–5 pairs), sometimes entire, faces strigose to hirsute; phyllaries glabrous or moderately villous to white-hirsuto-villous (sometimes only at peduncle-involucre region); ray corollas 10–15 mm; California, Oregon, Washington</description>
      <determination>147. Erigeron aliceae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves margins usually entire, sometimes ( E. howellii ) denticulate or shallowly serrate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 1-nerved, strigillose (hairs crinkly) or glabrous distally, eglandular or nearly so; phyllaries glabrous or sparsely hairy, densely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigillose (hairs crinkly) at least distally; ray laminae 1.5–3 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems strigillose, more densely so distally; basal and proximal cauline leaves linear-oblanceolate to broadly lanceolate or spatulate; ray corollas usually blue to rose purple or pink, sometimes white, 8–16(–25) mm; at 1300–3800 m</description>
      <determination>132. Erigeron glacialis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems proximally glabrous, distally strigillose; basal and proximal cauline leaves spatulate; ray corollas white, 13–25 mm; at (60–)500–1200(–1500) m</description>
      <determination>133. Erigeron howellii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous distally; ray laminae ca. 1 mm or 1.5–3 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 30–80(–100) cm; rays 75–150, corollas 8–16 × ca. 1 mm</description>
      <determination>134. Erigeron speciosus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (10–)15–30 cm; rays 20–45, corollas 7–10 × ca. 1.5–3 mm</description>
      <determination>148. Erigeron cervinus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute distally or throughout, glandular or eglandular; phyllaries sometimes hirsute to villous, glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae 1.5–3 mm wide; cypselae 2.5–2.8 mm, (4–)5(–7)-nerved.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllary margins usually ciliate, faces sparsely to moderately villoso-hirsute, usually sparsely gland-dotted apically, rarely throughout</description>
      <determination>131. Erigeron peregrinus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries usually glabrous (rarely outer faces and margins sparsely villous), densely and evenly stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>132. Erigeron glacialis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray laminae ca. 1 mm wide; cypselae (1.3–)1.5–2 mm, 2(–4)-nerved.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems ascending; cauline leaves gradually reduced distally</description>
      <determination>145. Erigeron formosissimus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually erect; cauline leaves usually nearly even-sized, sometimes mid largest.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves ending 1.5–9 cm proximal to heads (peduncles distinct);rays white</description>
      <determination>140. Erigeron arizonicus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves continuing to immediately proximal to heads (peduncles very short); rays mostly blue to purplish.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves prominently and densely stipitate-glandular (glands 0.2–0.5 mm), stems sometimes sparsely pilose (hairs 1–2 mm); pappi: outer of scales, inner of 14–22 bristles</description>
      <determination>137. Erigeron vreelandii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and distal leaves eglandular to minutely glandular or inconspicuously stipitate-glandular (if stipitate, glands 0.1–0.4 mm), stems, leaves, and phyllaries glabrous or hirsute to hirsuto-pilose (hairs 0.5–2 mm); pappi: outer of setae, inner of 20–30 bristles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems moderately to densely hirsute, eglandular; leaves evenly hirsute to strigoso-hirsute, usually eglandular</description>
      <determination>135. Erigeron subtrinervis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or hirsuto-pilose, sometimes minutely glandular; leaves glabrous or sparsely hirsuto-pilose, eglandular or minutely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparsely hirsuto-pilose (hairs 1–2 mm), sometimes minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>136. Erigeron uintahensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or sparsely hirsuto-pilose (hairs 0.5–1 mm), often minutely glandular distally</description>
      <determination>134. Erigeron speciosus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 13</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hispidulous (usually subintricately branched, brittle); involucres 4–5 mm; phyllaries glabrous or outer sparsely hispid, minutely glandular; disc corollas 3.5–4 mm; cypselae 1.5–1.9 mm; pappus bristles 15–18(–23)</description>
      <determination>173. Erigeron bigelovii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems puberulo-hirsutulous to sparsely strigose, glabrate, or glabrous (not subintricately branched, not brittle); involucres 2–4.5 mm; phyllaries hispid, hirtellous, hirsute, hirsuto-villous, or sparsely strigose, usually also minutely glandular, sometimes glabrous or glabrate (in E. karvinskianus ); disc corollas 1.6–3.1 mm; cypselae 0.7–1.4 mm; pappus bristles 5–27.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic to obovate, usually relatively even-sized (with leaf tufts in axils); pappus bristles 15–27</description>
      <determination>154. Erigeron karvinskianus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades oblanceolate or obovate to spatulate, reduced distally (without axillary tufts); pappus bristles 5–17.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems decumbent-ascending to prostrate, erect branches sometimes produced from prostrate ones</description>
      <determination>165. Erigeron lemmonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems erect to ascending.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems puberulo-hirsutulous</description>
      <determination>159. Erigeron divergens (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems closely to loosely strigose or villous, rarely with ascending-spreading hairs as well.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems woody proximally; pappus bristles (5–)12–17</description>
      <determination>162. Erigeron modestus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems herbaceous; pappus bristles 5–12.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices simple; basal and proximal cauline leaves 10–70 × 2–8(–13) mm, margins usually entire, sometimes dentate or pinnately divided; involucres 2–3.5 mm; cypselae 0.8–1.2 mm; pappus bristles 6–12; Arizona, Utah</description>
      <determination>166. Erigeron religiosus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices simple or branched; basal and proximal cauline leaves 10–30 × 2–6 mm, margins entire; involucres 3.5–4 mm; cypselae 0.7–0.9 mm; pappus bristles 5–8; California, Nevada</description>
      <determination>163. Erigeron multiceps (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 14</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely white-strigose (at least proximally), eglandular; leaves linear</description>
      <determination>53. Erigeron filifolius (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or villous, puberulous, hispid, or hirsute, or, if sparsely strigose, then not whitish because of vestiture, glandular or eglandular; leaves mostly narrowly obovate to oblanceolate, oblong, or elliptic, if linear, then stems glabrous or sparsely strigose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparsely villous, minutely stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>104. Erigeron aequifolius</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems puberulous, villous, hispid, hirsute, hirsutulous, sparsely strigose, or glabrous, eglandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems puberulous to villous, hispid, or hirsute to hirsutulous (hairs spreading to spreading-deflexed).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries densely canescent-hirsutulous, minutely glandular; stems puberulous to villosulous (hairs crisped); cypselae glabrous</description>
      <determination>94. Erigeron blochmaniae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries either densely minutely glandular (otherwise glabrous or sparsely hairy) or hispido-hirsute and minutely glandular; stems densely hirsutulous to hirsute, hispidulous, hispido-hirsute, or piloso-hirsute (hairs straight, spreading to deflexed); cypselae strigose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries strigoso- to hispido-hirsute, minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>106. Erigeron breweri (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries glabrous or sparsely hairy, densely glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 7–15 cm; stems prostrate to procumbent or decumbent</description>
      <determination>106. Erigeron breweri (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 6–15(–20) or 20–60 cm; stems usually ascending.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 6–15(–20) cm; caudex branches with lignescent offsets from woody roots; stem hairs spreading, 0.2–1 mm; inner phyllaries lacking green apical areas (margins white, relatively broad, thickened)</description>
      <determination>95. Erigeron klamathensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 12–60 cm; caudex branches rhizomelike, fibrous-rooted; stem hairs slightly to strongly deflexed, 0.1–0.4 mm; inner phyllaries with green apical areas</description>
      <determination>106. Erigeron breweri (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or sparsely strigose (hairs ascending-appressed).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with axillary tufts of smaller leaves at most nodes; margins of inner phyllariesbroadly scarious</description>
      <determination>105. Erigeron mariposanus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems without axillary leaf tufts; margins of inner phyllaries narrowly scarious.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems prostrate to decumbent-trailing; rhizomes relatively slender, fibrous-rooted,or caudex branches rhizomelike; leaves 5–20 mm</description>
      <determination>107. Erigeron elmeri (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems erect or ascending; taproots woody; leaves 10–50(–100) mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mid and distal cauline leaves shorter than internodes, eciliate</description>
      <determination>93. Erigeron oxyphyllus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mid and distal cauline leaves longer than internodes, ciliate (cilia ascending-apressed).</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cilia on leaf margins thick-based; phyllaries glabrous or moderately to densely strigoso-hirsute, sometimes densely and prominently glandular; rays 15–60</description>
      <determination>96. Erigeron foliosus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cilia on leaf margins thin-based; phyllaries glabrate (barely perceptible), densely minutely glandular; rays 9–13</description>
      <determination>98. Erigeron serpentinus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 15</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves strigose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 3.5–6 mm; ray corollas 5–10 mm, laminae 0.8–1.1 mm wide, apparently both coiling at tips and reflexing at tube-lamina junction; disc corollas indurate and inflated beyond tubes, puberulent; cypselae 1.4–1.8 mm, oblong; outer pappi of narrowscales or setae</description>
      <determination>31. Erigeron engelmannii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 5–8 mm; ray corollas 8–14 mm, laminae 1.2–1.8 mm wide, coiling, not reflexing; disc corollas not indurate or inflated, glabrate; cypselae 2.1–2.5 mm, obovoid;outer pappi of setae</description>
      <determination>24. Erigeron davisii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves usually hispid to hirsute or hirtellous, sometimes glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Disc corolla throats not tubular, indurate and inflated; midnerve regions of phyllaries orange to yellowish; outer pappi of setae or scales; heads 1–5(–50).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Disc corollas glabrous or slightly puberulent (hairs glandular-viscid, blunt); pappi: outer of setae or subulate scales 0.1–0.3 mm, inner of 12–27 bristles</description>
      <determination>29. Erigeron pumilus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Disc corollas hirsuto-strigose (hairs sharply pointed); pappi: outer of scales 0.2–0.5 mm, inner of (7–)10–14(–15) bristles</description>
      <determination>30. Erigeron concinnus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Disc corolla throats tubular, not indurate and inflated; midnerve regions of phyllaries greenish; outer pappi of inconspicuous, fine setae; heads 1.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves usually glabrous or sparsely hirsute to villous; rays 30–90; Rocky Mountains</description>
      <determination>28. Erigeron vetensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves usually strigose to hirsutulous or hispid; rays 20–40(–55); Great Basin and Sierra Nevada.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems moderately hirsute to hispidulous (hairs spreading-deflexed), minutely glandular (at least distally); basal leaves 1- or 3-nerved, 20–50(–80) mm; phyllaries greenish; cypselae 1.8–2.5 mm</description>
      <determination>34. Erigeron clokeyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirtellous to sparsely hirsute (hairs straight-spreading, densely minutely glandular; basal leaves 20–35(–45) mm; phyllaries commonly purplish to purplish black, some-times only at tips; cypselae 2.3–2.8 mm</description>
      <determination>35. Erigeron pygmaeus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 16</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rays yellow (sometimes fading).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly basal (in tufts); stems evenly hispidulous to hirsute</description>
      <determination>25. Erigeron chrysopsidis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly cauline (proximal internodes elongate); stems strigose at least on distal 1 / 2</description>
      <determination>26. Erigeron piperianus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rays pink to bluish purple or white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with nonglandular hairs of unequal or equal lengths; stems and leaves moderately to densely minutely glandular; leaves narrowly oblanceolate to spatulate, (20–) 30–80 × 2–6(–12) mm; rays usually pink to blue or purplish, sometimes white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute (hairs unequal); cypselae 2.5–3 mm, densely strigoso-sericeous (facesobscured)</description>
      <determination>23. Erigeron poliospermus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparsely hirsuto-villous (hairs equal); leaves mostly basal, oblanceolate-spatulate to oblanceolate; cypselae 3.5–4.5 mm, sparsely strigose to glabrate (faces not obscured)</description>
      <determination>27. Erigeron latus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with nonglandular hairs of unequal lengths; stems and leaves usually eglandular, sometimes sparsely minutely glandular; leaves linear to linear-oblanceolate, 20–40 × 1–2 mm; rays white or blue.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hispido-hirsutulous to hirsute (hairs spreading, stiff, relatively thick-based); rays usually blue to purplish; disc corollas 3.9–5.5 mm; cypselae 2.2–2.8 mm</description>
      <determination>22. Erigeron nanus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely pilose to hirsuto-villous or loosely strigose; rays usually white; disc corollas 2.8–4 mm; cypselae 1.8–2.2 mm or 2.1–2.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely pilose (hairs usually mixed in orientation); cypselae 1.8–2.2 mm</description>
      <determination>21. Erigeron disparipilus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsuto-villous to loosely strigose (hairs similar in orientation); cypselae 2.1–2.5 mm</description>
      <determination>24. Erigeron davisii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 17</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves usually coarsely dentate or incised; pappus bristles twisted or curled (at least distal 1 / 2 ); stout taproots evident, caudices usually simple</description>
      <determination>20. Erigeron oreganus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves entire or serrate to dentate; pappus bristles not twisted or curled; caudices usually with stout, woody, vertical or horizontal branches 2–10 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and stems glabrous or sparsely villous, sparsely minutely glandular; rays white</description>
      <determination>18. Erigeron cascadensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and stems sparsely to moderately hispidulous to hirsute or hirsuto-villous, minutely glandular to stipitate-glandular; rays usually blue to purplish, sometimes white or pink</description>
      <determination>19. Erigeron leibergii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 18</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves glabrous, minutely glandular; basal leaves usually 3-nerved (sometimes with conspicuously raised primary and secondary venation), cauline little reduced</description>
      <determination>84. Erigeron nauseosus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves glabrous or sparsely and inconspicuously strigose (sparsely villosulous distally in E. evermannii ), eglandular; basal leaves 1-nerved (never with raised venation), cauline reduced distally or essentially absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices with diffuse system of relatively long, slender, rhizomelike branches or basal offsets; taproots usually not evident; ray laminae reflexing.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal and reduced cauline, 15–70 × 2–11(–15) mm; phyllaries in 2–3 series</description>
      <determination>83. Erigeron leiomerus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves all basal, 5–12 × 1–3.5 mm; phyllaries in 3–4(–5) series</description>
      <determination>86. Erigeron scopulinus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices multicipital or with relatively long, thick to relatively slender, lignescent branches; taproots usually evident; ray laminae not reflexing (except in E. kachinensis ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries glabrous; caudex branches relatively short and thick; rays purplish to lavender; New Mexico</description>
      <determination>80. Erigeron subglaber</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries minutely glandular, or sparsely to moderately hirsuto-villous to strigose, or both hairy and glandular; caudex branches short and thick to long and slender; rays mostly white to pink; n to w of New Mexico.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries eglandular or sparsely glandular; ray laminae reflexing; cypselae 1.2–1.6 mm; Arizona.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually apically 3-lobed to pinnatifid with 2–3(–5) pairs of lobes; ray laminae sometimes with abaxial lilac midstripe</description>
      <determination>87. Erigeron pringlei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves entire or (in E. anchana ) with 1(–2) pairs of deep lobes or teeth; ray laminae without midstripe.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear (0.5–0.9 mm wide); pappus bristles 16–21</description>
      <determination>90. Erigeron heliographis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear-oblanceolate to spatulate; pappus bristles 9–15 or 19–26.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 7–22 cm; basal leaves spatulate, (30–)40–90 × 4–8 mm, margins entire or with 1(–2) pairs of lobes or teeth (petioles about 2 times blade lengths); phyllary midnerves orange-resinous, slightly swollen; disc corollas with prominent orange-resinous veins; pappus bristles 19–26</description>
      <determination>88. Erigeron anchana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants mostly 3–5 cm; basal leaves linear-oblanceolate to slightly spatulate, 10–30 × 0.5–2(–3) mm, margins entire (petioles, when distinct, about equaling blades); phyllary midnerves greenish yellow, not swollen; disc corollas veins not orange-resinous; pappus bristles 9–13(–15)</description>
      <determination>89. Erigeron saxatilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries minutely glandular; ray laminae reflexing or not; cypselae 1.5–3.5 mm; n to ne of Arizona.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves filiform or linear to linear-oblanceolate; cypselae 1.5–2.2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 4–6 × 7–10 mm; rays blue, 4–8 mm</description>
      <determination>36. Erigeron arenarioides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 3–3.5 × 5–6 mm; rays white, 8–9 mm</description>
      <determination>37. Erigeron salmonensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves oblanceolate to spatulate; cypselae 1.8–3.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not folding along midveins; ray corollas 7–13 mm; pappus bristleswhite-shiny</description>
      <determination>79. Erigeron garrettii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves commonly folding along midveins; ray corollas 3.5–10 mm; pappus bristles stramineous, dull.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads 1–4; rays 10–15, laminae reflexing; pappus bristles 12–14;cypselae 1.8–2 mm</description>
      <determination>85. Erigeron kachinensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads 1(–2); rays 13–40, laminae not reflexing; pappus bristles 25–35; cypselae 2–3.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal and reduced cauline; phyllaries glabrous, minutelyglandular; ray corollas 4–6 mm; disc corollas 2.8–4 mm</description>
      <determination>73. Erigeron watsonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves nearly all basal; phyllaries sparsely to moderately hirsuto-villous, sometimes minutely glandular; ray corollas 6–10 mm; disccorollas 3.6–4.5 mm</description>
      <determination>74. Erigeron evermannii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 19</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves spatulate, bases of blades abruptly contracted to petioles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems villous to hirsuto-villous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries eglandular or sparsely glandular near apices and along midregion; stems and leaves eglandular; leaf faces strigose to hirsuto-villous, less densely so abaxially;cypselae 1.3–1.8 mm</description>
      <determination>76. Erigeron uncialis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries evenly and densely glandular; stems and leaves glandular; leaf faces equallyhirsuto-canescent; cypselae 1–1.2 mm</description>
      <determination>77. Erigeron cavernensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute to hirtellous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems moderately to densely hirtellous (hairs deflexed), eglandular; leaves folding along midnerves; rays deep blue or violet to rose-purple; disc corollas 4.2–6.3 mm</description>
      <determination>78. Erigeron asperugineus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely hirsute (hairs spreading), minutely glandular; leaves not folding alongmidnerves; rays white to pink; disc corollas 2.5–3 mm</description>
      <determination>82. Erigeron maguirei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades linear to lanceolate, oblanceolate, or oblanceolate-spatulate, bases usually attenuate to petioles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf faces glabrous or glabrate abaxially, hairy adaxially (both faces hairy in E. parryi ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries densely glandular, villous hairs with blackish purple crosswalls; rays purple to lavender; leaf apices acute; pappus bristles 15–24</description>
      <determination>43. Erigeron lackschewitzii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries sparsely and inconspicuously glandular, non-glandular hairs with or without colored crosswalls; rays white to pink or bluish; leaf apices obtuse to rounded or (in E. ochroleucus ) acute; pappus bristles (6–)7–15 or 15–25.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute; leaves 10–25 mm, faces hirsute to hirsuto-strigose</description>
      <determination>40. Erigeron parryi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsutulous to villous, lanate-villous, or villosulous; leaves 10–90(–120) mm, abaxial faces essentially glabrous, adaxial strigose or sparsely villous .</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems finely hirsutulous to villosulous; leaf apices obtuse to rounded; rays 15–35, bluish to purplish, rarely white; pappus bristles 15–20</description>
      <determination>39. Erigeron rydbergii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems loosely strigose to puberulo-strigose or villous; leaf apices acute or obtuse to rounded; rays (12–)20–62(–85), white to pinkish, bluish, or lavender; pappus bristles (6–)7–15.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems (1–)2–6(–12) cm, strigose to short-villous, usually arising from short, thickened caudex branches; leaves (5–)10–50(–60) mm, apices obtuse to rounded, adaxial faces sparsely loosely strigose, abaxial glabrate or glabrous, shiny; involucres (3–)4–6(–8) mm; phyllary hairs usually with colored crosswalls; rays (12–)20–44(–85); pappus bristles (6–)7–11</description>
      <determination>41. Erigeron radicatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems (2–)8–18(–30) cm, usually loosely strigose, arising from a nearly common point near apices of thick taproots, caudices usually simple; leaves (20–)40–90(–120) mm, apices acute, faces usually strigose at least on proximal 1 / 3 – 3 / 4 of blade, adaxial glabrous distally; involucres 5.5–7 mm; phyllary hairs usually without colored crosswalls; rays 30–62; pappus bristles 12–15</description>
      <determination>42. Erigeron ochroleucus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf faces hairy.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices acute; basal leaves (30–)50–160 mm; stems usually purplish proximally; heads 1–10(–18).</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves usually smaller than basal; heads 1–4(–7)</description>
      <determination>10. Erigeron eatonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves gradually or little reduced from basal, usually continuing relatively even-sized nearly to heads; heads 1–10(–18).</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries flat, densely hirsute to hirsuto-villous, sometimes sparsely minutely glandular; rays 35–65, corollas 7–13 mm, laminae coiling at apices; disc corollas 4–5.3 mm; pappus bristles 20–30</description>
      <determination>6. Erigeron corymbosus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries commonly strongly keeled to nearly folded, moderately hirsuto-villous or villous, densely minutely glandular; rays 12–36, corollas 4.5–8 mm, laminae slightly coiling or not; disc corollas 2.5–3.5 mm; pappus bristles 12–24</description>
      <determination>12. Erigeron lassenianus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices usually rounded to obtuse; basal leaves mostly (15–)20–90 mm; stems greenish proximally (except E. jonesii ); heads 1–5.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 3-nerved.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems greenish proximally; phyllaries densely hirsuto-canescent to hirtellous; raylaminae coiling</description>
      <determination>14. Erigeron caespitosus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems purplish proximally; phyllaries sparsely to moderately hirsute; ray laminae not coiling or reflexing</description>
      <determination>13. Erigeron jonesii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 1-nerved.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute (hairs spreading, not deflexed), densely minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>82. Erigeron maguirei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute or hirsutulous to hirtellous (hairs deflexed or not), eglandular or glandular only distally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem hairs spreading to ascending; leaves 10–25(–50) × 0.8–2 mm</description>
      <determination>40. Erigeron parryi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem hairs deflexed; leaves 15–70 × 2–6(–8).</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries hirsute to hirsuto-villous, eglandular; involucres 5–7 mm; raycorollas 6–10 mm, blue; pappus bristles 20–25</description>
      <determination>16. Erigeron goodrichii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries strigose to strigulose or finely hirsuto-villous, minutely glandular; involucres 3.7–5.2 mm; ray corollas 5–6 mm, blue to pink or white;pappus bristles 12–20</description>
      <determination>15. Erigeron abajoensis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 20</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly linear.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves persistent (old leaf bases persistent, chaffy, fibrous); cauline leaves graduallyor abruptly reduced from basals; heads 1(–3); involucres 5–7 × 10–13 mm</description>
      <determination>11. Erigeron canaani</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves present at, or withering by flowering (old leaf bases not persistent); cauline leaves gradually or little reduced from basals; heads (1–)2–7(–18); involucres 4.2–8.5 × 6–18 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 9–20(–35) cm; cauline leaves relatively unreduced distally; involucres 4.2–5.6 × 6–10(–12) mm</description>
      <determination>12. Erigeron lassenianus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (5–)15–60 cm; cauline leaves reduced distally; involucres (4.5–)5–8.5 × 9–12 or 12–18 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants colonial (caudex branches rhizomelike); involucres (4.5–)5–6 × 9–12 mm; phyllaries linear-lanceolate, apices linear-acuminate; disc corollas 3–3.5 mm; cypselae 1.2–1.6 mm</description>
      <determination>7. Erigeron decumbens (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not colonial (caudex branches not rhizomelike); involucres 6–8.5 × (12–) 14–20 mm; phyllaries narrowly oblanceolate to lanceolate, apices acute or abruptly acuminate; disc corollas 3.5–4.5 mm; cypselae (1.8–)2–3.2 mm</description>
      <determination>8. Erigeron robustior (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly oblanceolate to narrowly oblanceolate or narrowly obovate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal cells of stem hairs erect, hairs attenuate; leaves 1- or 3-nerved.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly 3-nerved, hirtellous; phyllaries densely hirsuto-canescent to hirtellous</description>
      <determination>14. Erigeron caespitosus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly strigose to loosely hirsutulous; phyllaries strigose to strigulose or hirsuto-villous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems loosely strigose (hairs ascending); involucres 3.7–5.2 mm; pappus bristles 12–20</description>
      <determination>15. Erigeron abajoensis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems mostly hirsute to hirtellous (hairs deflexed), sometimes proximally strigose (hairs ascending); involucres 5–7 mm; pappus bristles 20–25</description>
      <determination>16. Erigeron goodrichii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal cells of stem hairs inclined, often sharply, hairs even-width until apex; leaves mostly 3-nerved (1- or 3-nerved in E. lassenianus ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves persistent; cauline leaves usually smaller than basal; heads 1–4(–7)</description>
      <determination>10. Erigeron eatonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves persistent at, or withering by flowering; cauline leaves gradually or little reduced from basal; heads (1–)2–7(–18).</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants colonial (caudex branches rhizomelike); involucres 9–12 mm wide; cypselae 1.2–1.6 mm</description>
      <determination>7. Erigeron decumbens (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not colonial (caudices essentially simple); involucres 6–10(–12) mm wide (in E. lassenianus ) or (9–)12–20 mm wide; cypselae (1.5–)2–3.2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries densely, minutely glandular; involucres 4–5.5 × 6–10(–12) mm</description>
      <determination>12. Erigeron lassenianus (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries essentially eglandular; involucres 6–8.5 × (9–)12–20 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (15–)25–55 cm; taproots relatively thin, 2–3 mm wide; basal leaves linear to very narrowly oblanceolate; cauline leaves ending proximal to heads; involucres 6–8.5 × (12–)14–20 mm; phyllaries narrowly oblanceolate to lanceolate, acute-acuminate</description>
      <determination>8. Erigeron robustior (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 10–22(–27) cm; taproots relatively thick, (3–)5–8 mm wide; basal leaves oblanceolate to spatulate-oblanceolate; cauline leaves usually continuing to near heads; involucres (5–)6–7 × 9–12(–14) mm; phyllaries elliptic-oblanceolate to oblong-oblanceolate, abruptly acuminate</description>
      <determination>9. Erigeron maniopotamicus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 21</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 5–13 mm wide, silvery, densely strigoso-sericeous; involucres 9–14 mm diam</description>
      <determination>71. Erigeron tweedyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 1–7 mm wide, gray-green and strigose or strigillose, or green and sparsely strigose to glabrate or glabrous; involucres 5–12 mm diam.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices sharply acute; rays blue to purple</description>
      <determination>70. Erigeron tener</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices rounded to obtuse; rays mostly white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants mostly occurring singly (caudices simple or branches relatively slender); rays (8–)11–12</description>
      <determination>72. Erigeron wilkenii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants mat-forming or cespitose (caudices multicipital, branches usually relatively thick); rays 10–30.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants mat-forming (from lignescent rhizomes and branched caudices); stems and leaves grayish-strigillose; pappus bristles 20–25; New Mexico</description>
      <determination>69. Erigeron acomanus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants usually cespitose; stems and leaves greenish, strigose; pappus bristles 12–22; Utah, Nevada, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems closely strigose; leaves narrowly oblanceolate to oblanceolate–spatulate; rays 10–20(–25); disc corollas 2.4–3.4 mm</description>
      <determination>75. Erigeron cronquistii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems loosely strigose to hirsuto-villous; leaves spatulate (laminae elliptic-obovate to suborbiculate); rays 22–30; disc corollas 2–2.4 mm</description>
      <determination>76. Erigeron uncialis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 22</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves narrowly oblanceolate, 1.5–5 mm wide; involucres 5.5–9 × 13–18 mm</description>
      <determination>55. Erigeron barbellulatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear to linear-oblanceolate, basal 0.5–3 mm wide; involucres 3.5–7 × 6–13 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 0.5–1 mm wide; involucres 3.5–5 × 6–11 mm; rays 15–25, blue to pale lavenderor pinkish; pappus bristles 20–30</description>
      <determination>56. Erigeron elegantulus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 0.5–3 mm wide; involucres 4–7 × 8–13 mm; rays 25–38, usually bright yellow,sometimes cream to nearly white; pappus bristles 10–20</description>
      <determination>57. Erigeron linearis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <key>
    <key_head>Group 23</key_head>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal and cauline (basal mostly withering by flowering, not forming conspicuous tufts); heads 1–5(–10).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems silvery white; phyllaries glabrous or sparsely strigose proximally, minutely gland-ular; ray laminae reflexing; outer pappi of setae or conspicuous scales</description>
      <determination>50. Erigeron parishii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems greenish to gray-green; phyllaries usually strigose to hirsuto-strigose, often minutely glandular; ray laminae coiling; outer pappi of inconspicuous setae.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves gradually reduced distally, ending well proximal to heads; heads 1–3(–5); involucres 5–7 × 7–12(–15 mm); rays 28–40, corollas 10–18(–20) mm; disc corollas sparsely strigoso-villous (hairs needlelike); flowering mid Apr–Jun(–Jul)</description>
      <determination>48. Erigeron utahensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves reduced to linear bracts relatively even-sized beyond midstem and continuing to immediately proximal to heads; heads (1–)3–10; involucres 3–5 × 5–8 mm; rays 10–14(–20), corollas 4–8 mm; disc corollas viscid-puberulent (hairs multicellular, blunt); flowering Jun–Sep</description>
      <determination>49. Erigeron sparsifolius</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly basal or basal and cauline (basal usually persistent); heads 1 or 1–5(–10).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves 0 or restricted to proximal 1 / 4 (– 1 / 2 ) of stems.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cypselae (8–)10–14-nerved, glabrous; ray laminae reflexing, sometimes tardily, never coiling</description>
      <determination>51. Erigeron canus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cypselae 2-nerved, hairy at least on nerves; ray laminae coiling.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves oblanceolate to spatulate, 2–7 mm wide; cypsela faces and margins strigose to strigoso-sericeous, margins densely ciliate</description>
      <determination>17. Erigeron untermannii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly linear, 0.5–1.5 mm wide; cypsela faces glabrous, margins sparsely to densely velutinous-ciliate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries strigose (hairs thin-based); rays 15–32; ray corolla tubes andbases of laminae glabrous or glabrate; pappus bristles 30–40</description>
      <determination>44. Erigeron compactus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Phyllaries hispido-hirsutulous (hairs relatively thick-based); rays 30–55; ray corolla tubes and bases of laminae densely strigoso-hirsute; pappus bristles 15–25(–35)</description>
      <determination>45. Erigeron consimilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves often little reduced on at least proximal 1 / 2 stems.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems, leaves, and phyllaries gray-green to silvery, densely strigose to hirsute or villoso-hirsute; cypselae (2–)4(–5)- or 6–8-nerved; pappus bristles 25–40 or 32–50.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves silvery to gray-green; phyllaries silvery-strigose (hairs closelyappressed); cypselae 6–8-nerved; pappus bristles 25–40</description>
      <determination>46. Erigeron argentatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves gray-green; phyllaries hirsute to villoso-hirsute; cypselae (2–)4(–5)-nerved; pappus bristles 32–50</description>
      <determination>47. Erigeron pulcherrimus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems, leaves, and phyllaries greenish, closely to loosely strigose; cypselae 2(–3)-nerved; pappus bristles 12–27.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices multicipital, rarely branched; stems loosely strigose to puberulo-strigose; pappus bristles 12–15</description>
      <determination>42. Erigeron ochroleucus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Caudices with relatively short, thick branches; stems closely strigose; pappus bristles 15–27.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly 12–30 mm (persistent portions of basal leaves relatively short and broad); phyllaries relatively thinly herbaceous; cypsela faces glabrous, margins sparsely ciliate; Arizona, New Mexico</description>
      <determination>52. Erigeron sivinskii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly (20–)30–80 mm (persistent portions of basal leaves relatively long and slender-fibrous); phyllary margins thickened; cypsela faces and margins villoso-hirsute, more densely so on nerves; Colorado, Utah, Wyoming</description>
      <determination>38. Erigeron nematophyllus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
