<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>32.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Erigeron</genus_name><species_name>aphanactis</species_name><species_authority>(A. Gray) Greene</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Francisc.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>389. 1897</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Erigeron</genus_name><species_name>concinnus</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker &amp; Arnott) Torrey &amp; A. Gray</species_authority><variety_name>aphanactis</variety_name><variety_authority>A. Gray</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts </publication_title><place_in_publication>6: 540. 1865 (as concinnum)</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials, 2–20(–30) cm; taprooted, caudices branched. Stems erect to slightly decumbent-ascending, canescent-hirsute, densely stipitate-glandular. Leaves basal (persistent) and cauline (petioles prominently ciliate, at least on proximal portions, hairs thick-based, spreading); basal blades linear-oblanceolate to spatulate, 20–80 × 2–7 mm, cauline gradually or abruptly reduced distally, sometimes bractlike (stems scapiform), margins entire, faces canescent-hirsute, densely stipitate-glandular (hairs finer). Heads (disciform) 1–4. Involucres 4–6 × 7–15 mm. Phyllaries in 2–3 series, coarsely hirsute, densely minutely glandular. Ray (pistillate) florets 30–45; corollas usually tubular, lacking laminae, or laminae shorter than involucres. Disc corollas 2.8–4.5 mm (throats white-indurate and inflated, conspicuously puberulent). Cypselae 1.5–1.8 mm, 2-nerved, faces sparsely strigose (carpopodia whitish); pappi: outer of scales or setae, inner of 7–20 bristles.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Erigeron aphanactis is distinguished from E. austiniae by its conspicuously puberulent (versus essentially glabrous) disc corollas and white (versus yellow) carpopodia; it also is similiar in habit and vestiture to E. concinnus, which has conspicuous white to pinkish rays.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems leafy; heads usually 2–3; disc corolla lobes usually yellowish</statement>
      <determination>32a. Erigeron aphanactis var. aphanactis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems scapiform; heads 1; disc corolla lobes sometimes becoming reddish or purplish</statement>
      <determination>32b. Erigeron aphanactis var. congestus</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
