<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>106.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Erigeron</genus_name><species_name>breweri</species_name><species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>6: 541. 1866</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Brewer’s fleabane</common_name><description>Perennials, 7–75 cm; taprooted (taproots usually not collected, often weakly developed), roots and caudices woody, branches rhizomelike (3–15 cm; fibrous-rooted), relatively slender, leafless, ascending. Stems usually ascending, sometimes prostrate to procumbent or decumbent (var. jacinteus) (often purple, distal branches stiff, spreading-ascending), hispid (hairs spreading-deflexed, 0.1–0.4 mm), mostly eglandular. Leaves cauline; (ascending) blades narrowly oblong-lanceolate to narrowly obovate, 10–40 × 2–5 mm, margins entire, relatively evenly spaced and sized, hispid, mostly eglandular. Heads 1 or 2–5(–10) in loosely corymbiform arrays. Involucres mostly 4–6 × 9–14 mm. Phyllaries in 3–5 series (all but outermost with stramineous margins and distal, greenish-herbaceous, narrowly rhomboid areas), strigoso- to hispido-hirsute or essentially glabrous, densely minutely glandular. Ray florets 20–62; corollas white or pink, often drying blue, 4–7 mm, laminae weakly coiling. Disc corollas 3.5–5.5 mm (throats slightly indurate, not inflated). Cypselae 2–3 mm, 2-nerved, faces sparsely strigose; pappi: outer of setae, inner of (15–)20–35(–50) bristles.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 5 (5 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Erigeron breweri is treated as a member of E. sect. Linearifolii in G. L. Nesom (1992b), where all of the varieties are mapped in detail.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries glabrous or sparsely hairy, densely glandular.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants usually 12–40 or 30–60 cm; stems ascending-erect; leaves usually 15–35 mm</statement>
      <determination>106d. Erigeron brewerivar. breweri</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 7–15 cm; stems prostrate to procumbent or decumbent; leaves 5–12 mm</statement>
      <determination>106e. Erigeron brewerivar. jacinteus</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries strigoso- to hispido-hirsute, sometimes slightly glandular.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants 20–30 cm; stems often wiry and brittle; phyllaries hispido-hirsute (hairs translucent, spreading, stiff, relatively thick-based), glandular</statement>
      <determination>106c. Erigeron brewerivar. porphyreticus</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants (30–)40–75 cm; stems not wiry or brittle; phyllaries strigoso- or hispido-hirsute (hairs ascending to ascending-appressed, white), eglandular.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries strigoso-hirsute (hairs relatively thin-based, ascending-appressed, gradually and slightly reduced in density from outer to inner phyllaries), eglandular</statement>
      <determination>106a. Erigeron brewerivar. bisanctus</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries hispido-hirsute (hairs relatively thick-based, ascending, dense on outermost phyllaries, much less so on mid and inner), eglandular</statement>
      <determination>106b. Erigeron brewerivar. covillei</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
