<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>131.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Erigeron</genus_name><species_name>peregrinus</species_name><species_authority>(Banks ex Pursh) Greene</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3: 166. 1897</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Wandering fleabane</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Aster</genus_name><species_name>peregrinus</species_name><species_authority>Banks ex Pursh</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 556. 1813</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials, 5–55(–70) cm; rhizomatous, fibrous-rooted, caudices usually simple, thick. Stems erect to basally ascending, hirsute to hirsuto- or strigoso-villous (hairs loosely appressed, slightly crinkled), sometimes loosely strigose distally (var. thompsonii), eglandular. Leaves basal (persistent) and cauline; basal blades linear-oblanceolate to broadly lanceolate or spatulate, (30–)50–100 × 5–25 mm, cauline gradually reduced distally (bases distinctly subclasping, except when greatly reduced), margins entire, faces hirsute, hirsuto-villous, sparsely villosulous, glabrate, or glabrous, eglandular. Heads 1. Involucres 5–9(–12) × 10–22(–25) mm. Phyllaries in 2–3(–4) series (margins usually ciliate), abaxially sparsely to moderately villoso-hirsute, usually eglandular, sometimes sparsely gland-dotted apically, rarely sparsely so over adaxial faces (especially in var. thompsonii). Ray florets 30–80; corollas usually blue to rose purple or pink, sometimes white to pale blue, 12–20(–25) mm (mostly 1.5–3 mm wide), laminae coiling. Disc corollas 3.5–4.5 mm. Cypselae 2.5–2.8 mm, (4–)5(–7)-nerved, faces sparsely strigose; pappi: outer of setae, inner of 20–32 bristles.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>nw North America.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries moderately to densely hirsute to hirsuto-villous; rays purplish to pink or white</statement>
      <determination>131a. Erigeron peregrinus var. peregrinus</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries sparsely hirsuto-villous to glabrate; rays white</statement>
      <determination>131b. Erigeron peregrinus var. thompsonii</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
