<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">astereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">erigeron</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene" date="1898">formosissimus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>25: 121, plate 332, figs. 3, 4. 1898</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe astereae;genus erigeron;species formosissimus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, 10–40(–55) cm; rhizomatous, fibrous-rooted, rhizomes variably thick. Stems ascending, densely hirsute to hirsutulous or glabrous, minutely glandular to stipitate-glandular. Leaves basal (persistent) and cauline; basal blades oblanceolate to oblanceolate-spatulate, 20–100(–150) × 4–10(–15) mm, margins entire, closely ciliate, faces glabrous or sparsely hirsute, sometimes sparsely glandular; cauline blades becoming ovate to lanceolate, gradually reduced distally (bases clasping). Heads 1–6. Involucres 5–8 × 10–20 mm. Phyllaries in 2–3 series (greenish), glabrous or hirsuto-villous, densely minutely glandular to stipitate-glandular (glands sometimes obscured by hairs in var. formosissimus). Ray florets 75–150; corollas blue to purple, rarely pink to white, 8–15 mm (ca. 1 mm wide), laminae coiling at tips or not at all. Disc corollas 3.5–4.5 mm. Cypselae (1.3–)1.6–1.9 mm, 2-nerved, faces sparsely strigose; pappi: outer of setae, inner of 15–25 bristles.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora): w United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>145.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Beautiful fleabane</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Variation in vestiture of Erigeron formosissimus is complex, ranging from stems and heads glabrous and densely stipitate-glandular to stems and heads densely hairy and essentially eglandular; intermediates are found over the range of the species. The taxonomic solution of recognizing broadly sympatric varieties within a single species is biologically untenable, and some have treated this as a single entity; the variation is greater than typically occurs within a single species of Erigeron (see comments following 3. E. neomexicanus, where the situation with E. oreophilus is similar).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres moderately to densely hirsute, minutely glandular; distal leaves hirsuto-villous, eglandular or sometimes sparsely glandular</description>
      <determination>145a. Erigeron formosissimus var. formosissimus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres glabrous or sparsely hirsuto-villous, densely minutely glandular; distal leaves usually glabrous, sometimes sparsely villoso-hirsute, minutely glandular</description>
      <determination>145b. Erigeron formosissimus var. viscidus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
