<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>155.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Erigeron</genus_name><species_name>lobatus</species_name><species_authority>A. Nelson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Amer. J. Bot.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>21: 580. 1934</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Lobed fleabane</common_name><description>Annuals, mostly 10–40(–50) cm; taprooted. Stems erect, sparsely hispido-pilose (hairs spreading, straight, 0.6–2) mm), densely stipitate-glandular. Leaves basal (persistent) and cauline; basal and proximal cauline blades obovate-spatulate, 50–100(–150) × 4–25 mm, cauline gradually reduced (lobing distally), margins pinnatifid or bipinnatifid with (1–)2–4 pairs of rounded to acute lobes, faces sparsely hispido-pilose, stipitate-glandular. Heads 1–5 (peduncles long, ebracteate). Involucres 3–4 × 6–10 mm. Phyllaries in 2–3 series (sometimes basally connate, broad, thin) sparsely hispido-pilose, stipitate glandular. Ray florets 85–110; corollas white, drying dark blue, 6–9 mm, laminae not coiling or reflexing. Disc corollas 1.8–2.9 mm. Cypselae 1.2–1.4 mm, 2-nerved, faces sparsely strigose; pappi: outer of scales (sometimes connate, forming crowns), inner of 11–12 bristles.</description><phenology>jan</phenology><phenology>winter</phenology><phenology>feb</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><habitat>stream banks</habitat><habitat>sandy lake shores</habitat><habitat>dry washes</habitat><habitat>desert or riparian scrub</habitat><habitat>sometime with creosote bush</habitat><elevation>300–1200 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Sonora).</global_distribution><discussion>Erigeron lobatus is characterized by persistent basal and proximal cauline leaves with rounded to acute lobes, vestiture of stipitate glands and sparse, spreading, hispido-pilose hairs, heads on relatively long, ebracteate peduncles, and broad, thin phyllaries. Erigeron divergens often is similar; its glandularity is not stipitate and its nonglandular hairs are shorter and denser.</discussion></treatment>
