<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Dieteria</genus_name><species_name>asteroides</species_name><species_authority>Torrey</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in W. H. Emory, Not. Milit. Reconn.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>141. 1848</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Machaeranthera</genus_name><species_name>asteroides</species_name><species_authority>(Torrey) Greene</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Biennials or short-lived perennials. Stems, branches, and peduncles usually hairy, puberulent, or canescent, often sparsely stipitate-glandular (glabrous or densely stipitate-glandular in var. glandulosa). Leaf blades lanceolate to oblanceolate, mid 20–100 × (2–)6–20 mm, margins entire to irregularly serrate, faces puberulent or canescent, often sparsely short-stipitate-glandular (densely, stiffly long-stipitate-glandular in var. glandulosa); distal bases cordate to auriculate, clasping. Involucres broadly turbinate to hemispheric. Phyllaries in 5–12 series, spreading to reflexed, apices acute to long-acuminate, 1–6 mm, herbaceous, faces puberulent or canescent throughout (on both indurate bases and foliaceous apices), sometimes sparsely stipitate-glandular (moderately to densely stipitate-glandular in var. glandulosa). Receptacles 3.5–7 mm diam. Ray florets pistillate, fertile; laminae white to purple, 10–20 × 0.8–1.5 mm. Disc corollas 5–8 mm. Cypselae glabrous or moderately appressed-hairy.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>sw United States</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems glabrous or stipitate-glandular; leaves stiffly stipitate-glandular</statement>
      <determination>1b. Dieteria asteroides var. glandulosa</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems hairy, puberulent, or canescent, sometimes sparsely stipitate-glandular; leaves puberulent or canescent, sometimes sparsely stipitate-glandular.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Mid leaf blades 6–20 mm wide, margins usually serrate or serrulate; involucres hemispheric; phyllary apices long-acuminate, 3–6 mm</statement>
      <determination>1a. Dieteria asteroides var. asteroides</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Mid leaf blades 2–6 mm wide, margins entire or slightly serrulate; involucres usually broadly turbinate, rarely hemispheric; phyllary apices acute to acuminate, 1–3 mm</statement>
      <determination>1c. Dieteria asteroides var. lagunensis</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
