<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pyrrocoma</genus_name><species_name>clementis</species_name><species_authority>Rydberg</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>27: 625. 1900</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Tranquil goldenweed</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Haplopappus</genus_name><species_name>clementis</species_name><species_authority>(Rydberg) S. F. Blake</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 3–18(–40) cm. Stems 1–5, ascending or decumbent, pale and often red-tinged, sparsely villous, sometimes tomentose. Leaves (persistent, thick, ± fleshy); basal petiolate, blades lanceolate to narrowly oblanceolate, 50–140 × 9–16 mm, margins usually entire, sometimes slightly undulate, sometimes denticulate, sparsely ciliate, apices acute to obtuse, faces usually glabrous, sometimes puberulent or villous, eglandular; cauline sessile, lanceolate to ovate, 20–40 × 5–10 mm, bases clasping, auriculate. Heads usually borne singly, terminal, sometimes 2–3 smaller proximally, not subtended by leaflike bracts. Peduncles 0.5–1 cm. Involucres broadly campanulate, 8–15 × 20–35 mm. Phyllaries in 3–4 series, green with white margins, sometimes yellowish, lanceolate to oblanceolate, 6–12 mm, unequal, margins entire, ciliate, apices obtuse to acute or acuminate, faces villous. Ray florets 21–55; corollas 10–18 mm. Disc florets 100+; corollas 6–8 mm. Cypselae subfusiform, not compressed, 4–7 mm, 4-angled, faces striate, sericeous or glabrous; pappi tawny, 6–8 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Pyrrocoma clementis is recognized by its villous to tomentose stems, villous and ciliate phyllaries, and high elevation habitat, often well above tree-line. It is similar to P. uniflora, which has narrower heads, finer floccose-tomentose pubescence, and grows at lower elevations.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries narrowly obovate, abruptly acute; cypselae sericeous</statement>
      <determination>3a. Pyrrocoma clementisvar. clementis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries narrowly lanceolate, apices attenuate; cypselae glabrous</statement>
      <determination>3b. Pyrrocoma clementisvar. villosa</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
