<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cucurbitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">BRYONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1012. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Bryony [Greek bruein , to burgeon or sprout, alluding to rapid growth of herbaceous stems produced annually from large perennial roots] I</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 442 [as Bronia]. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cucurbitaceae;genus BRYONIA</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, usually dioecious, rarely monoecious, climbing or sprawling; stems &lt;annual&gt;, hispidulous to glabrate; roots tuberous; tendrils unbranched. Leaves: blade orbiculate to ovate or hastate, 3–5-angled, or palmately 3–5-lobed, lobes ovate to deltate or triangular, margins coarsely toothed, surfaces eglandular. Inflorescences: staminate flowers 4–16 in axillary racemes or fascicles; pistillate flowers [1–]2–6(–10) in axillary corymboid to racemoid panicles; bracts absent. Flowers: hypanthium campanulate to shallowly campanulate; sepals 5, lanceolate to deltate; petals 5, distinct, white to cream, greenish white, or yellowish green, or yellowish, usually green-throated and faintly green-lined, oblong-ovate to ovate-lanceolate, 3–7 mm, glabrate, corolla broadly funnelform-campanulate to nearly rotate. Staminate flowers: stamens 5, 2 connate in pairs, 1 distinct, appearing as 3 stamens; filaments inserted near hypanthium rim, distinct; thecae distinct, C-curved to S-curved, connective broadened and sheetlike; pistillodes absent. Pistillate flowers: ovary 1-locular, ovoid to broadly ellipsoid; ovules 3–10 per locule; style 1, slender-columnar; stigmas 3, 2-lobed; staminodes 3–5 or absent or vestigial. Fruits berrylike, red to orange or black, globose, smooth, &lt;glabrous&gt;, indehiscent. Seeds 2–8, ovoid or oblong, compressed, not arillate, margins thickened-corrugated or not differentiated, surface roughened.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Europe, Asia, Africa, Pacific Islands.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 12 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Jeffrey, C. 1969. A review of the genus Bryonia L. (Cucurbitaceae). Kew Bull. 23: 441–461.</reference>
    <reference>Volz, S. M. and S. S. Renner. 2009. Phylogeography of the ancient Eurasian medicinal plant genus Bryonia (Cucurbitaceae) inferred from nuclear and chloroplast sequences. Taxon 58: 550–560.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
