<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Richard ex Kunth" date="unknown">podostemaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">PODOSTEMUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 164, plate 44 [as Podostemon]. 1803</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Threadfood , riverweed , orchid-of-the-waterfall</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family podostemaceae;genus PODOSTEMUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek podos , foot, and stemon , stamen, alluding to stamens elevated on foot-stalk (andropodium)]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Roots green, photosynthetic; haptera (fleshy disclike or fingerlike outgrowths) arising along flanks of roots serving as anchorage. Leaves with 1–2 basal sheaths; stipules extensions of boat-shaped leaf base; petiole round to elliptic; blade symmetric, ultimate divisions linear, awl-shaped, or spatulate, apex rounded, blunt, acute, or apiculate. Inflorescences apical or lateral, 1–12-flowered, pedicellate; spathella clavate, smooth or papillate, apex rounded or with nipple, rupturing apically into 1–6 irregular segments. Pedicels expanded at apex, elongating during anthesis. Flowers zygomorphic; tepals scalelike, 2 at base of ovary on either side of andropodium (lateral tepals), shorter than ovary, 1 (andropodial tepal) arising at top of andropodium from fork between 2 stamen filaments; anthers basifixed, quadrangular; thecae equal or inner longer than outer, apices rounded, distinct, dehiscence introrse; ovary oriented obliquely on pedicel, 2-locular, ellipsoidal; ovules 25–200; placentation axile; stigmas distinct, simple, bent toward anthers prior to spathella rupture, divergent and elongating during anthesis. Capsules 2-locular, persistent valve oriented obliquely on pedicel, each valve 3-ribbed, suture margins thickened, riblike. Seeds 0–42[–203].</description>
  <description type="distribution">c, e North America, Mexico, West Indies (Dominican Republic), Central America, South America.</description>
  <discussion>Species 11 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Philbrick, C. T. 1984. Aspects of floral biology, breeding system, and seed and seedling biology in Podostemum ceratophyllum Michx. (Podostemaceae). Syst. Bot. 9: 166–174.</reference>
    <reference>Philbrick, C. T. and G. E. Crow. 1983. Distribution of Podostemum ceratophyllum Michx. (Podostemaceae). Rhodora 85: 325–341.</reference>
    <reference>Philbrick, C. T. and G. E. Crow. 1992. Isozyme variation and population structure in Podostemum ceratophyllum Michx. (Podostemaceae): Implications for colonization of glaciated North America. Aquatic Bot. 43: 311–325.</reference>
    <reference>Philbrick, C. T. and A. Novelo R. 2004. Monograph of Podostemum. Syst. Bot. Monogr. 70: 1–106.</reference>
    <reference>Rutishauser, R. et al. 2003. Developmental morphology of roots and shoots of Podostemum ceratophyllum (Podostemaceae–Podostemoideae). Rhodora 105: 337–353.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
