<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cucurbitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cogniaux" date="1890">BRANDEGEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Calif. Acad. Sci., ser.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 3: 58. 1890</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cucurbitaceae;genus BRANDEGEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Townshend Stith Brandegee, 1843 – 1925, California botanist, explorer and collector, civil engineer, topographer]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual (sometimes short-lived perennial), monoecious, sprawling, trailing, or climbing; stems &lt;annual&gt;, glabrate; taprooted or roots slender-fibrous; tendrils unbranched. Leaves: blade hastate, 4–5-angular, or suborbiculate, shallowly to deeply palmately 3(–5)-lobed, lobes triangular or ovate to linear-oblong, central lobe usually longest, margins entire, surfaces eglandular. Inflorescences: staminate flowers (1–)2(–3) in axillary racemes or racemoid panicles; pistillate flowers solitary in same axils as staminate, irregularly produced; &lt;peduncles erect at apex&gt;; bracts absent. Flowers: hypanthium cupulate; sepals 5, barely differentiated as apiculae; petals 5, distinct or nearly so, white, triangular to ovate or narrowly oblong-triangular with acute apices, 1–1.5[–3] mm, glabrous, corolla rotate to shallowly cupulate. Staminate flowers: stamens 3–5 (appearing 1–3 from connation); filaments inserted at hypanthium base, connate; thecae connate, forming a head but not fused into ring, horseshoe-shaped, twisted-contorted, connective broad; pistillodes absent. Pistillate flowers: ovary 1-locular, broadly fusiform-rostrate; ovules 1(–2) per locule; styles 1–3, columnar; stigmas 1, depressed-globose to hemispheric, sometimes 2-lobed; staminodes absent. Fruits capsular, light tan, obovoid to suborbicular, gibbous, slightly compressed, beaked, dry, thin-walled, sparsely short-echinate or subaculeate, spinules thick-based, antrorsely upturned, irregularly dehiscent. Seeds 1(–2), subcylindric-clavate to obdeltoid, compressed, not arillate, margins not differentiated, surface muriculate to warty.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>J. N. Rose (1897b) recognized five species of Brandegea (without a key to distinguish them). Of the five, B. minima (S. Watson) Rose was later transferred to Cyclanthera (D. M. Kearns and E. C. Jones 1992); the others have been relegated to synonymy of B. bigelovii.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
