<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cucurbitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey &amp; A. Gray" date="unknown">ECHINOCYSTIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 542. 1840</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Wild or wild mock cucumber , wild balsam apple [Greek echinos , hedgehog, and kystis , bladder, alluding to prickly, hollow fruits] E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cucurbitaceae;genus ECHINOCYSTIS</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, monoecious, climbing or trailing; stems glabrate; taprooted with branching secondary roots or roots slender-fibrous; tendrils 3-branched. Leaves: blade depressed-orbiculate to suborbiculate or ovate, palmately (3–)5(–7)-lobed, lobes triangular to oblong-triangular, margins entire or serrulate-cuspidate, surfaces eglandular, &lt;glabrous or scabrous&gt;. Inflorescences: staminate flowers 50–200 in axillary racemes or racemoid panicles; pistillate flowers 1(–3) from same axils as staminate, &lt;peduncles erect at apex&gt;; bracts absent. Flowers: hypanthium shallowly cupulate; sepals (5–)6, filiform, almost pricklelike; petals (5–)6, connate 1/4 length, white to greenish white, narrowly triangular to linear-lanceolate or oblong-lanceolate, 3–6 mm, minutely glandular-puberulent, corolla rotate. Staminate flowers: stamens 3; filaments inserted at corolla base, connate, &lt;column 0.4 mm&gt;; thecae connate, forming subsessile capitate androecium but not fused into single ring, sigmoid-flexuous, connective broad; pistillodes absent. Pistillate flowers: ovary 2-locular, subglobose; ovules 2 per locule; style 1, nearly vestigial; stigma 3, forming a subglobose head; staminodes absent. Fruits pepos, light green to blue-green, globose-ovoid to ovoid or ellipsoid, bladdery-inflated, symmetric, &lt;dry, thin-walled&gt;, surface moderately to densely echinate, &lt;spinules weak, flexible, whitish-glaucous with green mottling at bases&gt;, dehiscence apically irregularly lacerate, sometimes explosively. Seeds 4, broadly oblong-ellipsoid, strongly flattened, not arillate, margins not differentiated, surface slightly pitted-roughened. x = 32.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
