<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Batsch" date="unknown">violaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">viola</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kellogg" date="unknown">purpurea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pacific (San Francisco),</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2 Feb. 1855: unnumb. 1855</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>F</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family violaceae;genus viola;species purpurea</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>51.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, caulescent, not stoloniferous, 1.5–25 cm. Stems 1–5(–7), decumbent or spreading to erect, leafy proximally and distally, ± glabrous, puberulent, canescent, or tomentose, on caudex from subligneous rhizome. Leaves basal and cauline; basal: 1–6; stipules adnate to petiole, forming 2 linear, membranous wings, wing margins entire or laciniate, each wing with lanceolate to ± deltate projection, margins entire or laciniate, apex acute to long-acuminate; petiole 1.8–14.5 cm, puberulent to tomentose; blade purplish, purple-tinted, or gray-green abaxially, gray, green, or gray-green adaxially, sometimes shiny adaxially, ovate, orbiculate, oblong, deltate, or lanceolate, 0.8–5.3 × 0.4–4.1 cm, often fleshy, base cordate, subcordate, truncate, or attenuate, oblique or not, margins usually ± crenate, serrate, dentate, or coarsely or irregularly repand-dentate, sometimes entire, usually ciliate, apex acute to obtuse or rounded, surfaces glabrous, puberulent, or tomentose; cauline similar to basal except: stipules linear, lanceolate, oblanceolate, or ± oblong to ovate, margins entire, lacerate, or laciniate, usually ciliate, apex sometimes divided into 2–3 filiform processes or obtuse; petiole 0.3–19.7 cm, glabrous or puberulent; blade ovate, oblong, elliptic, deltate, or lanceolate, 0.9–5.2 × 0.2–2.9 cm, length 0.8–7.1 times width, margins crenate, serrate, dentate, repand-denticulate, undulate-denticulate, sinuate, undulate, or entire, abaxial surface puberulent, canescent, or tomentose, adaxial surface glabrous, sparsely pubescent, puberulent, canescent, or tomentose. Capsules ovoid to ± spherical, 4–7 mm, puberulent. Seeds light to dark brown or mottled gray and brown, 2–3.1 mm. 2n = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 7 (7 in the flora): w North America, nw Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 7 (7 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w North America, nw Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Varieties 7 (7 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Varieties of Viola purpurea are variable and intergrade. All are found in California; six occur in other western states, one in Mexico, and one in British Columbia. Mature plants are needed for determination.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants 3–25 cm. Stems spreading to erect, usually not buried, usually elongated by end of season, ± glabrous or puberulent. Leaves: basal: 1–5; petiole 4–11 cm, puberulent; blade purple-tinted abaxially, green adaxially, often shiny, ± orbiculate to widely ovate, 1.6–4.6(–5.3) × 1.6–4.1 cm, ± fleshy, base usually attenuate, sometimes subcordate or truncate, margins irregularly crenate, apex acute to obtuse, abaxial surface glabrous or puberulent, hairs sometimes only on veins, adaxial surface usually glabrous, sometimes sparsely puberulent; cauline: petiole 1.5–19.7 cm, usually puberulent; blade ovate, deltate, or lanceolate, 1.2–4.5 × 0.8–2.5 cm, length 1–2.3 times width, base usually attenuate, sometimes ± cordate or truncate, margins crenate-serrate, abaxial surface puberulent (or along veins), adaxial surface glabrous or sparsely pubescent. Peduncles 4.5–10 cm, usually puberulent, sometimes glabrous. Lowest petals 10–12 mm. Capsules 5–6 mm. Seeds dark brown, 2.1–2.3 mm.</discussion>
  <discussion>Flowering Mar–Jul. In openings or beneath shrubs, usually in yellow pine (Pinus ponderosa) forests or higher; 200–2900 m; Calif., Oreg.; Mexico (Baja California).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
