<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Batsch" date="unknown">violaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">viola</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="M. S. Baker &amp; J. C. Clausen" date="unknown">tomentosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Leafl. W. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 142. 1949</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Woolly or felt-leaved or feltleaf violet E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family violaceae;genus viola;species tomentosa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>65</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, caulescent, not stoloniferous, 7–10 cm. Stems 1–3(–5), prostrate or decumbent to erect, leafy proximally and distally, densely white-tomentose, from usually vertical, subligneous rhizome. Leaves basal and cauline; basal: 1–6; stipules linear to broadly ovate-oblong, margins entire, sometimes with scattered glandular hairs, apex acute to obtuse; petiole 2–6 cm, densely white-tomentose; blade ± oblanceolate to elliptic, 1.5–5 × 1.4–2.1 cm, base attenuate, usually oblique, margins usually entire, rarely crenate distally, ciliate, apex acute to usually obtuse, mucronulate, surfaces densely white-tomentose abaxially, strigose adaxially; cauline similar to basal except: stipules ovate, lanceolate, oblanceolate, or oblong, margins entire or toothed, densely ciliate with white hairs; petiole 1.5–3.5 cm; blade 1.8–4 × 0.6–1.1 cm. Peduncles 1–4 cm, densely white-tomentose. Flowers: sepals lanceolate, margins ciliate-tomentose, auricles 0.5–1 mm; petals deep lemon-yellow adaxially, upper 2 often brownish purple abaxially, lower 3 dark brown- to brownish purple-veined, lateral 2 bearded, lowest 6–11 mm, spur yellow, gibbous, 0.5–1.5 mm; style head bearded; cleistogamous flowers absent. Capsules ± spherical, 4–5 mm, densely white-tomentose. Seeds brown with lighter brown mottling, 2.5–2.8 mm. 2n = 12.</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="phenology">aug</description>
  <description type="habitat">dry gravelly places open ponderosa jeffrey lodgepole pine forests</description>
  <description type="habitat">gravelly places</description>
  <description type="habitat">open ponderosa</description>
  <description type="habitat">Jeffrey</description>
  <description type="habitat">lodgepole pine forests</description>
  <description type="elevation">1500–2000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering May–Aug. Dry, gravelly places, open ponderosa, Jeffrey, lodgepole pine forests; 1500–2000 m; Calif.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering May–Aug.</phenology>
      <habitat>Dry, gravelly places, open ponderosa, Jeffrey, lodgepole pine forests;</habitat>
      <elevation>1500–2000 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Calif.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Viola tomentosa occurs in El Dorado, Nevada, Placer, Plumas, and Sierra counties. M. S. Baker (1949) reported that nearly every leaf axil of V. tomentosa produces a flower bud and that these buds produce chasmogamous flowers late in season instead of cleistogamous flowers, as do other members of the V. nuttallii complex.</discussion>
  <discussion>Viola tomentosa hybridizes with V. purpurea; the hybrids appeared sterile (M. S. Baker 1949). J. Clausen (1964) reported a putative hybrid between V. tomentosa and V. sheltonii from one location in Sierra County.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
