<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Kunth ex de Candolle" date="unknown">turneraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">TURNERA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 271. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Turnera</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 131. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family turneraceae;genus TURNERA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For William Turner, 1515 – 1568, English botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, subshrubs, or shrubs [trees], hairs glandular and simple [stellate], glandular hairs sessile-capitate or microcapitate. Leaves petiolate or sessile, often with nectaries; stipules present or absent. Inflorescences axillary; peduncle free or adnate to petiole (flowers epiphyllous); prophylls persistent. Pedicels absent. Flowers mostly distylous; sepals at least 1/3 connate; petals yellow or white [salmon, pink, orange, or red], sometimes with dark basal spot; corona absent; filaments often with nectaries; anthers dorsifixed or basifixed. Capsules granulose, rugose, or verrucose [smooth]. Seeds reticulate [striate]. x = 5, 7, (13).</description>
  <description type="distribution">sc, se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Africa.</description>
  <discussion>Species 142 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>I. Urban (1883) divided Turnera into nine series, and M. M. Arbo (2008) added two. Phylogenetic studies (S. Truyens et al. 2005; Arbo and S. M. Espert 2009) indicate that it is monophyletic.</discussion>
  <discussion>Turnera subulata Smith, with a dark basal spot in the yellow petals, has been collected twice, probably as a garden escape, in Miami-Dade County, southern Florida.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves: petiole without nectaries, blade margins revolute; inflorescences 0.5 – 0.8 cm, not epiphyllous; filaments adnate for 0.2 mm to base of floral tube, anther pockets absent; anthers dorsifixed</description>
      <determination>1. Turnera diffusa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves: petiole with nectaries, blade margins not revolute; inflorescences 2 – 4 cm, epiphyllous; proximal part of filaments adnate by margins to floral tube forming 5 nectar pockets; anthers basifixed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers distylous; petals white</description>
      <determination>2. Turnera coerulea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers homostylous; petals yellow</description>
      <determination>3. Turnera ulmifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <references>
    <reference>Arbo, M. M. 2000. Estudios sistemáticos en Turnera (Turneraceae). II. Series Annulares, Capitatae, Microphyllae y Papilliferae. Bonplandia (Corrientes) 10: 1–82.</reference>
    <reference>Arbo, M. M. 2005. Estudios sistemáticos en Turnera (Turneraceae). III. Series Anomalae y Turnera. Bonplandia (Corrientes) 14: 115–318.</reference>
    <reference>Arbo, M. M. 2008. Estudios sistemáticos en Turnera (Turneraceae). IV. Series Leiocarpae, Conciliatae y Sessilifoliae. Bonplandia (Corrientes) 17: 107–334.</reference>
    <reference>Arbo, M. M. and S. M. Espert. 2009. Morphology, phylogeny and biogeography of Turnera L. (Turneraceae). Taxon 58: 457–467.</reference>
    <reference>Arbo, M. M. and S. M. Mazza. 2011. The major diversity centre for neotropical Turneraceae. Syst. Biodivers. 9: 203–210.</reference>
    <reference>Truyens, S., M. M. Arbo, and J. S. Shore. 2005. Phylogenetic relationships, chromosome and breeding system evolution in Turnera (Turneraceae): Inferences from ITS sequence data. Amer. J. Bot. 92: 1749–1758.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
