<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu ex Roussel" date="unknown">passifloraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">passiflora</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">pallida</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 955. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Corkystem passionflower</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family passifloraceae;genus passiflora;species pallida</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>5.</number>
  <description type="morphology">lobes rounded to acute, margins entire; abaxial fine veins moderately to prominently raised, abaxial nectaries absent. Floral bracts absent or minute. Flowers: floral tube absent; sepals green, often becoming purple, 4–8 × 2–3 mm; petals absent; corona filament whorls 2, outer filaments green, green-white, or purple basally, yellow apically, linear, terete, 2–4 mm. Berries blue-black, globose to ovoid, 5–13 × 5–10 mm. 2n = 24.</description>
  <description type="phenology">mar</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">oct</description>
  <description type="phenology">fall</description>
  <description type="phenology">nov</description>
  <description type="phenology">dec</description>
  <description type="phenology">winter</description>
  <description type="habitat">subtropical to tropical woodlands shrublands pine forests scrub and disturbed areas in rocky loamy to sandy soil often calcareous</description>
  <description type="habitat">shrublands</description>
  <description type="habitat">pine forests</description>
  <description type="habitat">scrub and disturbed areas</description>
  <description type="habitat">in rocky</description>
  <description type="habitat">loamy to sandy soil</description>
  <description type="habitat">often calcareous</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–60 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies (Bahamas)</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies (Greater and Lesser Antilles)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Bermuda</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America (Venezuela)</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced in s Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Indian Ocean Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">w Pacific Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Australia.</description>
  <discussion>The leaves of Passiflora pallida show variation in lobe number, from juvenile to adult plants, and within and among individuals, with both unlobed and three-lobed leaf forms most common. In Texas, leaves on mature plants are always symmetrically three-lobed; in Florida, leaves can be unlobed, symmetrically three-lobed, or asymmetrically two- to three-lobed. Passiflora pallida is also self-compatible, an unusual feature in the genus.</discussion>
  <discussion>In peninsular Florida, Passiflora pallida is widespread and locally common to occasionally weedy. In Texas, it is relatively uncommon, known only from the extreme southernmost part of the state and from a single disjunct population about 150 miles northward in Refugio County (S. R. Hill 1981).</discussion>
  <discussion>Traditionally synonymized under Passiflora suberosa in our region (for example, D. S. Correll and M. C. Johnston 1970; R. L. Hammer 2002; R. P. Wunderlin and B. F. Hansen 2003), P. pallida is closely related to the larger-flowered P. suberosa and commonly is treated as conspecific with it worldwide. The hypanthium of P. pallida generally is 3–4 mm in diameter, with inner coronal filaments usually less than 1.5 mm and outer filaments less than 4 mm, whereas in P. suberosa the hypanthium generally is 4–8.8 mm in diameter, with inner coronal filaments usually 1.5–3.9 mm and outer filaments (2.5–)3–8.1 mm. Passiflora suberosa is native in</discussion>
  <discussion>Mexico, the West Indies, and Central and South America, and has been widely introduced in tropical regions (weedy in Hawaii), but does not occur in the flora area. In regions where the two species naturally co-occur, P. pallida generally is found at lower elevations than P. suberosa. These two species and close relatives were reviewed by K. E. Porter-Utley (2003).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
