<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu ex Roussel" date="unknown">passifloraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">passiflora</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Aiton" date="unknown">ciliata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hort. Kew.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 310. 1789</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>I</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family passifloraceae;genus passiflora;species ciliata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Passiflora</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">foetida</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Aiton) Masters" date="unknown">ciliata</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Stems terete to longitudinally ridged, glabrous or densely hairy. Leaves not or weakly pungent, glabrous or densely hairy, glandular-ciliate; stipules pectinate, 5–6 × 2–4 mm, with glandular bristles or hairs; petiole with glandular bristles or hairs; blade roughly symmetric, 3–10(–12) × 3–8(–10) cm, moderately 3(–5)-lobed, middle lobe much longer than lateral lobes, margins weakly serrulate to nearly entire; abaxial fine veins weakly raised, abaxial nectaries absent. Floral bracts pinnatifid, 20–30 × 15–25 mm, margins serrate to nearly entire, with glandular bristles or hairs. Flowers: floral tube cuplike, 4–6 mm deep; sepals white, 18–25 × 7–9 mm; petals purple to white, 20–25 × 8–10 mm;</description>
  <description type="habitat">corona filament whorls 5–6 outer 2 whorls purple basally white medially pale purple apically linear terete to transversely compressed 16–20 mm. berries bright red to crimson ovoid to broadly ellipsoid 30–35 × 20–25 mm</description>
  <description type="habitat">outer 2 whorls purple basally</description>
  <description type="habitat">white medially</description>
  <description type="habitat">pale purple apically</description>
  <description type="habitat">linear</description>
  <description type="habitat">terete to transversely compressed</description>
  <description type="habitat">16–20 mm. Berries bright red to crimson</description>
  <description type="habitat">ovoid to broadly ellipsoid</description>
  <description type="habitat">30–35 × 20–25 mm.</description>
  <discussion>Flowering Aug–Dec. Warm-temperate to subtropical woodlands, shrublands, or disturbed areas, in moist to dry, loamy to sandy soil, 10–200 m; introduced; Fla., Tex.; Mexico; West Indies; Central America.</discussion>
  <discussion>Passiflora ciliata is relatively uncommon and apparently introduced in the flora area and probably is spreading. Nearly all plants in Florida (for example, R. P. Wunderlin and B. F. Hansen 2003) and some in Texas identified as P. foetida are actually P. ciliata. E. P. Killip (1938) noted the presence of P. foetida var. riparia (C. Wright ex Grisebach) Killip in Florida, which we include in P. ciliata.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of this species within the flora area can be either entirely glabrous or densely hairy throughout; otherwise, they are essentially identical morphologically. The description provided here best reflects its variation within our region, and the species is more variable outside of our range. We treat this species broadly to include many members of sect. Dysosmia that have mature leaves unscented to weakly pungent when bruised and that have bright red to scarlet fruits, characteristics that seem to be consistently associated.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
