<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">corchorus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">aestuans</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Nat. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10, 2: 1079. 1759</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* East Indian or West African mallow IW</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus corchorus;species aestuans</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Corchorus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lamarck" date="unknown">acutangulus</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants herbs, annual or short-lived perennial. Stems erect to decumbent or ascending, 2–13(–20) dm, puberulent in lines, hairs simple, arched, downturned to irregularly oriented. Leaves: petiole 5–30(–36) mm; blade ovate or broadly ovate to ovate-elliptic, 2–8 cm, base rounded-truncate, margins serrate, one or both of basal pair of teeth sometimes prolonged into caudate-setaceous point 3–5 mm, apex short-acuminate or acute, surfaces sparsely pilose to strigose on veins and lamina. Inflorescences usually solitary flowers, sometimes fasciculate or cymose, 2–3-flowered. Pedicels 2–3 mm. Flowers: sepals narrowly oblong, 3–5 mm, awned, glabrous; petals 4–6 mm; stamens 10–20. Capsules cylindric, wing-angled, wings to 2 mm wide, 3(–4)[–5]-valved, each valve terminated by bifurcate awn 1.5–3 mm, 15–25(–40) × 4–5 mm, glabrous. 2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jul–Sep(–Oct).</description>
  <description type="habitat">Roadsides, fallow fields, vacant lots, abandoned road beds, concrete cracks, edges of scrub oak thickets and pine-oak woodlands, lake edges, shady woodlands;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–50 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Ala., Fla., Ga., La.; Asia (India); Africa; introduced also in West Indies, Central America, South America, elsewhere in Asia (Japan, Pakistan, Singapore), Pacific Islands (Papua New Guinea), Australia.</description>
  <discussion>Apparently the first and perhaps only record of Corchorus aestuans for Alabama is an 1891 collection from ballast ground in Mobile County.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
