<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">TRIUMFETTA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 444. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Burrbark</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 203. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus TRIUMFETTA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Giovanni Battista Triumfetti, 1658 – 1708, Italian botanist, director of the botanical garden in Rome]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Bartramia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>name rejected</publication_title>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>6.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, subshrubs, [trees], taprooted. Stems erect, usually much-branched, hairy, hairs stellate or 1-rayed and apparently simple. Leaves petiolate; stipules subpersistent, linear-lanceolate to lanceolate; blade ovate or broadly ovate to oblong-elliptic, lanceolate-elliptic, or ovate-elliptic, rhombic-ovate, or suborbiculate, often palmately 3–5-lobed, herbaceous, margins serrate to dentate, surfaces usually stellate-pubescent, palmately 3–7-veined. Inflorescences axillary or terminal, cymose [solitary flowers or fasciculate], 2 or 3(–5)-flowered, simple or ultimately 1–4-branched, clusters leaf-opposed at axils, sometimes appearing subspicate. Flowers: sepals 5, [triangular-lanceolate] narrowly oblong to linear, valvate, often cucullate, commonly with hornlike subapical apiculum, stellate-pubescent to glabrate; petals 5 [absent or relatively small], yellow, narrowly oblanceolate to oblong or linear-oblong, usually with basal, adaxial glands; stamens 5–25[–60], on androgynophore; staminodes 0; ovary 2–4[or 5]-locular; ovules 1 or 2 per locule; styles 1, simple, short-cylindric; stigmas 2–5-lobed. Capsules globose to ovoid-globose or ovoid, 2–3[–6]-valved, spiny, spines uncinate [straight], glabrous or hairy, indehiscent [dehiscence loculicidal]. Seeds 1–2 per locule, irregularly ovoid to obovoid or pyriform, smooth. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa.</description>
  <discussion>Species 100–150 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of Triumfetta vary in habit, in leaf size, shape, and vestiture, and in some floral features. Leaves are shed or smaller during stress (R. G. Collevatti et al. 1998). Fruits usually are necessary for unambiguous identification.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fryxell, P. A. 1998. A synopsis of the neotropical species of Triumfetta (Tiliaceae). In: P. Matthew and M. Sivadasan, eds. 1998. Diversity and Taxonomy of Tropical Flowering Plants. Calicut. Pp. 167–192.</reference>
    <reference>Lay, K. K. 1950. The American species of Triumfetta L. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 37: 315–395.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
