<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Janice G. Saunders</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">WALTHERIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 673. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5. 304. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus WALTHERIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Augustin Friedrich Walther, 1688 – 1746, German physician, anatomist, and botanist at Leipzig University]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>10.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs [herbs, shrubs], prostrate to erect, taprooted. Stems unarmed, hairy, hairs stellate and/or simple, sometimes also glandular. Leaves petiolate; stipules deciduous, narrowly triangular or linear-triangular; blade: margins dentate, serrate, or crenate. Inflorescences axillary, cincinni in double or compound dichasial clusters, glomerulate, or paniculiform, 5–40-flowered; epicalyx absent; bracts 4, unilateral subtending floral pair, unequal or subequal. Flowers sweet-smelling, sessile or subsessile, homostylous [mostly distylous]; sepals connate 1/2–2/3 length, nectary present; petals late-deciduous, pale yellow, bright yellow, or yellow-orange, usually darker in corolla throat, spatulate, clawed [rarely not clawed], lamina obovate, oblong, oblanceolate, or obtriangular; androgynophore absent or present, to 0.7 mm; stamens connate most of length [connate basally to entirely]; anthers 2-thecate, oblong or ovate; staminodes 0; ovary 1-locular, obovoid or obconic, stipitate or not; ovules 2 per locule; styles included, cylindric; stigmas 10–40-branched, apex slightly exserted above stamen apices and corolla. Fruits capsules, 1-locular, obconic, obovoid, or oblique, apically hairy, dehiscence partially or completely loculicidal. Seeds 1(or 2) per locule, brown or black, slightly laterally compressed, obovoid, obconic, or oblique, smooth or minutely granulate; endosperm present; cotyledons oblate [widely elliptic to elliptic, circular]. x = 5, 6, 7, 10, 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Bermuda</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Atlantic Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Indian Ocean Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical areas.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 60 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Waltheria albicans Turczaninow and W. rotundifolia Schrank are found in Mexico, and apparent hybrids of them with W. indica in the broad sense occur in the United States.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Köhler, E. 1971. Zur Pollenmorphologie der Gattung Waltheria L. (Sterculiaceae). Feddes Repert. 82: 125–153. Köhler, E. 1976. Pollen dimorphism and heterostyly in the genus Waltheria L. (Sterculiaceae). In: I. K. Ferguson and I. Muller, eds. The Evolutionary Significance of the Exine. London. Pp. 147–161.</reference>
    <reference>Saunders, J. G. 1995. Systematics and Evolution of Waltheria (Sterculiaceae). Ph.D. dissertation. University of Texas.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
