<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">waltheria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Britton" date="1903">bahamensis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Torreya</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 105. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus waltheria;species bahamensis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 6(–10) dm, resinous, appearing subglabrous but microscopically densely sessile-glandular, usually sparsely and very minutely stellate-puberulent. Stems 1–3 mm wide, nodes knobby, joints exserted 0.8–1 mm. Leaves: stipules linear-triangular, to 5 mm; petiole 1–12(–20) × 0.4–0.6 mm, with low tubercles; blade concolor, dark brown, bronze, or coppery, drying brownish olive, usually broadly oblong to oblong, ovate-oblong, or obovate-oblong, sometimes ovate, to 5 × 3 cm, resinous, base widely cuneate to slightly cordate, margins sharply dentate or sharply crenate-dentate,</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering and fruiting year-round.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Dry, pineland regions (Big Pine Key), pine barrens, hammocks, everglades, savannas, coastal rocky ground, sandy beaches;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.; West Indies (Bahamas).</description>
  <discussion>Flowering and fruiting year-round. Dry, pineland regions (Big Pine Key), pine barrens, hammocks, everglades, savannas, coastal rocky ground, sandy beaches; 0 m; Fla.; West Indies (Bahamas).</discussion>
  <discussion>Waltheria bahamensis has been considered endemic to the Bahamas. Plants of W. bahamensis are found in Florida from Camp Jackson, Frostproof, Miami, Pine Crest, and Sanibel Island.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some Florida collections previously called Waltheria indica are attributable to W. bahamensis or W. bahamensis × W. glabra; other specimens are hybrids of W. bahamensis and W. indica (J. G. Saunders 1995).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
