<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Paul A. Fryxell†,Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Malvoideae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Outlines Bot.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>816, 1094, 1118. 1835</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;subfamily Malvoideae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, subshrubs, shrubs, or trees, erect or procumbent, often stellate-hairy, sometimes with glandular hairs, generally mucilaginous, inner bark tough-fibrous. Leaves usually cauline, alternate, also distichous in Krapovickasia, Malvella, Meximalva, and some species of Sida, subsessile or sessile in some Herissantia, Horsfordia, Sida, Sidastrum, and Sphaeralcea; blade usually symmetric, asymmetric in Malvella, sometimes asymmetric in Pavonia, usually unlobed, sometimes palmately lobed or dissected, margins serrate or entire, primary veins often palmate (except in Lagunaria), without nectaries (except in Gossypium, Hibiscus, Talipariti, Thespesia, and Urena). Inflorescences terminal or axillary, umbels, spikes, racemes, or panicles or solitary</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide; mostly in tropical areas.</description>
  <other_name type="past_name">Malvidae</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 110, species ca. 1800 (42 genera, 220 species in the flora): nearly worldwide; mostly in tropical areas.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some ornamental malvaceous trees have been introduced to California, none of which is known in the flora area outside of cultivation. These include the Mexican Robinsonella cordata Rose &amp; Baker f. and, from Australia and New Zealand, Hoheria glabrata Sprague, Plagianthus divaricatus J. R. Forster &amp; G. Forster, and P. regius (Poiteau) Hochreutiner. Malope trifida Cavanilles from the Mediterranean region, and the subshrubs Alyogyne Alefeld from Australia, species of Anisodontea C. Presl from South Africa, and Lavatera species from the Mediterranean are sometimes grown as ornamentals; they are not naturalized in the flora area.</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 110, species ca. 1800 (42 genera, 220 species in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fryxell, P. A. 1978. Neotropical segregates from Sida L. (Malvaceae). Brittonia 30: 447–462.</reference>
    <reference>Fryxell, P. A. 1979. The Natural History of the Cotton Tribe. College Station. Fryxell, P. A. 1988. Malvaceae of Mexico. Syst. Bot. Monogr. 25. Fryxell, P. A. 1997. The American genera of Malvaceae—II. Brittonia 49: 204–269.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
