<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Paul A. Fryxell†,Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cavanilles" date="1785">ANODA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Diss.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 38, plate 10, fig. 3</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>plate</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11, figs. 1, 2. 1785</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus ANODA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Ceylonese vernacular name for a species of Abutilon ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Medikus" date="unknown">Cavanillea</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(A. Gray) Wooton &amp; Standley" date="unknown">Sidanoda</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Anoda</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(B. L. Robinson &amp; Greenman) B. L. Robinson &amp; Greenman" date="unknown">caudatifolia</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">A.</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="L. Riley" date="unknown">urophylla</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>16.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs or subshrubs, annual. Stems erect to decumbent, hispid or stellate-hairy to glabrescent. Leaves: stipules deciduous, inconspicuous, usually linear; blade usually linear, lanceolate, oblong, or ovate to triangular, sometimes lobed, base truncate, cordate, or cuneate, margins dentate to entire. Inflorescences axillary solitary flowers or terminal racemes or panicles; involucel absent. Flowers: calyx accrescent or not, not inflated, ribbed or not, base rounded, lobes ovate to triangular, apex acute or acuminate; corolla yellow, lavender, or purplish, rarely white; staminal column included; style 5–19-branched; stigmas usually abruptly capitate. Fruits schizocarps, erect, not inflated, oblate, not indurate, hairy; mericarps 5–19, 1-celled, with or without spur at dorsal angle, lateral walls usually disintegrating at maturity, irregularly dehiscent. Seeds 1 per mericarp, sometimes enclosed in persistent reticulate endocarp. x = 15.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Australia.</description>
  <discussion>Species 23 (7 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Anoda is predominantly Mexican in both distribution and maximum diversity, the South American occurrences being predominantly of the weedy A. cristata.</discussion>
  <discussion>Subshrubs, branching principally in inflorescence, 1 m. Stems erect, with simple hairs 0.5–1 mm and shorter glandular hairs. Leaves: petiole subequal to blade or shorter upward, with simple hairs 0.5–1 mm and shorter glandular hairs; blade concolorous, broadly ovate, gradually reduced and narrower upward, to 12 cm, membranous, base cordate, margins dentate, apex acuminate, surfaces minutely tomentose. Inflorescences usually panicles. Pedicels 1–5 cm. Flowers: calyx 5–7 mm, lobes with dark midrib, apex ± acuminate, tomentose; petals pale yellow, drying reddish, 10 mm, prominently bearded on claw; staminal column with recurved hairs; style 5-branched; stigmas glabrous. Schizocarps 6 mm diam., minutely hairy; mericarps 5, dorsally rounded. Seeds without enclosing endocarp. 2n = 30.</discussion>
  <discussion>Flowering spring–fall. Dry, open shrublands; 1000–1500 m; Ariz.; Mexico (Chihuahua, Jalisco, Sinaloa, Sonora).</discussion>
  <discussion>Anoda abutiloides is found in Pima and Santa Cruz counties.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bates, D. M. 1987. Chromosome numbers and evolution in Anoda and Periptera (Malvaceae). Aliso 11: 523–531.</reference>
    <reference>Fryxell, P. A. 1987. Revision of the genus Anoda (Malvaceae). Aliso 11: 485–522.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
