<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Laurence J. Dorr</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="1821">CALLIRHOe</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 181. 1821</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Poppy mallow , wine cup , wild hollyhock</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus CALLIRHOe</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Derivation uncertain; possibly Greek kallos , beautiful, and rhoias , corn poppy, alluding to resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>20.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual, perennial, or sometimes biennial, hairy, hairs stellate, 4-rayed, and/or simple, or plants glabrous and glaucous. Stems erect, ascending, or decumbent. Leaves: stipules persistent, caducous, or tardily deciduous, ovate, linear-lanceolate to subulate, auriculate, or rhombic-ovate; blade often pedate, suborbiculate, cordate, ovate, triangular, or hastate, palmately cleft or entire and crenate, base truncate, cordate, or sagittate to hastate, margins 1 per carpel; styles 10–28-branched; stigmas introrsely decurrent, filiform. Fruits schizocarps, erect, not inflated, oblate or depressed-discoid, indurate, reticulate and rugose, strigose or glabrous, indehiscent or dehiscent (annual species only); mericarps 10–28, 2-celled, prominently obtusely beaked or not, drying tan or brown, distal locule sterile, lower 1-seeded. Seeds 1 per locule, reniform or reniform-pyriform (annual species only), glabrous. x = 14, 15.</description>
  <description type="distribution">United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 9 (9 in the flora): United States, n Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 9 (9 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>United States, n Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 9 (9 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Several species of Callirhoe are gynodioecious; populations of C. alcaeoides, C. involucrata, and C. leiocarpa have individuals with either bisexual or functionally pistillate (that is, male-sterile) flowers. In these species the functionally pistillate flowers can be recognized by their reduced number of anther sacs, failure of these anther sacs to dehisce, stigmatic lobes often conspicuous at early anthesis, reduced petal size, and in C. alcaeoides shorter calyx lobe length. A few populations of C. pedata in Arkansas exhibit a corolla size dimorphism suggesting that this species too may be gynodioecious. Several species of Callirhoe are cultivated and may escape. All taxa of this genus occur within the flora area except C. involucrata var. tenuissima Palmer ex Baker f., which is wholly Mexican.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bates, D. M., L. J. Dorr, and O. J. Blanchard. 1989. Chromosome numbers in Callirhoe (Malvaceae). Brittonia 41: 143–151.</reference>
    <reference>Dorr, L. J. 1990. A revision of the North American genus Callirhoe (Malvaceae). Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 56: 1–75.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
