<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David M. Bates</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="D. M. Bates" date="unknown">FRYXELLIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Brittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>26: 95, fig. 1A. 1974 * [For Paul Arnold Fryxell, 1927 – 2011</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>American student of Malvaceae] C</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus FRYXELLIA</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>23.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, stellate-hairy. Stems cespitose. Leaves: stipules persistent, filiform to subulate; petiole subequal to or somewhat shorter than blade; blade ovate to oblong-lanceolate, unlobed, base subcordate to obtuse, margins toothed, apex acute or obtuse, without foliar nectaries. Inflorescences axillary, solitary flowers, ± equaling leaves; apex; filaments terminal and subterminal; ovary 12-carpellate; ovules 1 in each lower carpel cell, pendulous; styles 12-branched, (branches equal in number to carpels); stigmas capitate. Fruits schizocarps, not inflated, discoid, moderately indurate, stellate-hairy; mericarps 12, 1-celled, divided internally by endoglossum; distal cell reduced, barren, smooth-walled, hairy, each valve armed with suberect dorsal spur; proximal cell enclosing pendulous seed, reticulate-fenestrate, indehiscent, joined to columella by single median basal-dorsal vein. Seeds 1 per mericarp, puberulent about raphe. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Texas</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: Texas, n Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>Texas, n Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fryxell, P. A. and J. Valdés R. 1991. Observations of Fryxellia pygmaea (Malvaceae). Sida 14: 399–404.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
