<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">hibiscus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Harvey ex A. Gray" date="unknown">coulteri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(5): 23. 1852</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Desert rose-mallow F</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus hibiscus;species coulteri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>3.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, to 2 m, herbage with appressed-stellate and simple hairs throughout. Stems: stellate hairs of younger stems dense, appressed, 4-armed, arms approximate in pairs, aligned with stem axis, lines of fine, curved hairs absent or obscured; older growth grayish, rough, glabrescent. Leaves: stipules linear-subulate, 3–10 mm; petiole primarily in distal 1/2, sometimes themselves shallowly pinnately lobed, surfaces scabridulous, hairs appressed-stellate, obscure nectary present abaxially on midvein near base. Inflorescences solitary flowers in axils of distal leaves. Pedicels jointed below apices, to 17 cm, usually much exceeding subtending leaves; involucellar bractlets 8–14, linear-subulate, 1–2 cm, margins ciliate. Flowers erect or ascending; calyx divided 3/4+ length, funnelform, 1.4–2.2 cm, equaling or slightly exceeding involucel, lobes narrowly lanceolate-triangular, margins ciliate, apices attenuate, nectaries absent; corolla rotate, petals yellow to cream, usually with dark to obscure maroon lines basally, asymmetrically obovate to broadly obovate, 1.6–4 × 1–3.5 cm, margins ± entire, sparingly hairy abaxially where exposed in bud; staminal column straight, yellow or cream, 0.6–1.4 cm, bearing filaments throughout, free portion of filaments not secund, 1–3 mm; pollen yellow-orange; styles cream, 1.5–5 mm; stigmas maroon or cream. Capsules pale olivaceous gray with darker median stripe on each valve, ovoid or ellipsoid, 0.7–1.7 cm, to 2/3 calyces, apex rounded, hairy near apex or glabrous throughout. Seeds dark brown, angulately reniform-ovoid, 2.4–3 mm, silky-hairy ± throughout.</description>
  <description type="habitat">desert rocky slopes</description>
  <description type="habitat">rocky slopes</description>
  <description type="elevation">600–1600 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Baja California).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Chihuahua).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Coahuila).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Durango).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Nuevo León).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Sonora).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Zacatecas).</description>
  <discussion>Hibiscus coulteri has been recorded in the southern half of Arizona; in Otero County, New Mexico; and in the region west of the Pecos River in Texas.</discussion>
  <discussion>A naturally occurring hybrid between Hibiscus coulteri and H. denudatus (Hibiscus ×sabei Weckesser) has recently been documented from western Texas (W. Weckesser 2011).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
