<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">LAVATERA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 690. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Rose mallow [For Lavater family, 17th-century physicians and naturalists of Zurich] I</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 308. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus LAVATERA</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Medikus" date="unknown">Olbia</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Stegia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Candolle" date="unknown">de</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>32.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, subshrubs, or shrubs, perennial or annual [biennial], stellate-hairy or glabrate. Stems erect. Leaves: stipules early-deciduous, narrowly triangular, lanceolate, oblanceolate, or linear; blade lanceolate or ovate to orbiculate, narrower above, base rounded to wide-cuneate, unlobed</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; s Europe (Mediterranean regions), sw Asia (to Kashmir), Africa (Ethiopia), Atlantic Islands (Canary Islands); introduced also widely.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 12–25 (3 in the flora): introduced; s Europe (Mediterranean regions), sw Asia (to Kashmir), Africa (Ethiopia), Atlantic Islands (Canary Islands); introduced also widely.</discussion>
  <discussion>Lavatera has traditionally been distinguished from Malva by its cuplike, basally fused involucellar bractlets. Based on molecular evidence, Lavatera and Malva are nearly indistinguishable, and while still accepted here based upon different criteria, Lavatera taxa eventually may be combined with Malva. Lavatera arborea Linnaeus, L. assurgentiflora Kellogg, and L. cretica Linnaeus of previous treatments have been transferred to Malva, and some epithet changes were necessary.</discussion>
  <discussion>Lavatera cachemiriana Cambessèdes is commonly cultivated and may escape; it is similar to L. thuringiaca but has denser, long-stellate indument and the involucellar bractlets are two-thirds as long as the calyx, are broadly ovate with acute apices, fused at base into a cup about 1 cm long, barely appressed to the calyx, and are accrescent in fruit.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 12–25 (3 in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ray, M. F. 1995. Systematics of Lavatera and Malva (Malvaceae, Malveae)—A new perspective. Pl. Syst. Evol. 198: 29–53.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
