<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David M. Bates</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Greene" date="1906">MALACOTHAMNUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Leafl. Bot. Observ. Crit.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 208. 1906</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Chaparral mallow , bushmallow</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus MALACOTHAMNUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek malakos , soft, or malache , mallow, and thamnos , shrub, alluding to habit]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>34.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs or shrubs, sometimes root-suckering, glabrate to densely hairy, hairs various, simple or bifurcate, simple-glandular, and stellate, ca. 6–30-armed. Stems erect or ascending, ultimate branches strict to diffuse. Leaves: stipules ± persistent, filiform to subulate; blade ovate to round, rhombic, or reniform, unlobed or palmately 3-, 5-, or 7-lobed, base cordate to truncate or cuneate, margins usually toothed. Inflorescences usually axillary, rarely terminal, flowers solitary or in clusters in dense to open heads, spikes, racemes, or panicles; involucellar bractlets persistent, 3, distinct (basally connate in M. aboriginum). Flowers: calyx not accrescent, not inflated, lobes triangular to ovate, not ribbed; corolla exceeding calyx, campanulate to subrotate, usually rose to pale pink, pinkish mauve, or mauve, rarely white; staminal column ± included; filaments terminal and subterminal; ovary 7–14-carpellate; ovules 1 per cell; styles 7–14-branched, (branches equal in number to carpels); stigmas capitate. Fruits schizocarps, erect, not inflated, disclike, subglobose-obovate in lateral view, not indurate, fragile, apically minutely stellate-hairy; mericarps 7–14, drying tan, 1-celled, asymmetrically suborbicular to obovoid-reniform, smooth-walled, without dorsal spur, apex muticous, dehiscence loculicidal, walls falling away as 2 fragile valves. Seeds 1 per mericarp, ascending, brown or black, obovoid-reniform, usually papillate-stellate or minutely stellate-hairy or rarely glabrous. x = 17.</description>
  <description type="distribution">California</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <discussion>Species 11 (10 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Most species of Malacothamnus are locally common in early burn successions of chaparral and adjacent vegetation types in California and northern Baja California. Malacothamnus foliosus (S. Watson) Kearney is the only species restricted to Mexico; it is found in northern Baja California.</discussion>
  <discussion>Major morphological variants in Malacothamnus have been recognized as species, as treated by T. H. Kearney (1951). Insofar as known, most taxa are interfertile and in some instances intergrade in areas of proximity. Interpopulational variation within most species in indument and inflorescence characters is high and of moderately complex patterning.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bates, D. M. 1963. The Genus Malacothamnus. Ph.D. dissertation. University of California, Los Angeles. Benesh, D. L. and W. J. Elisens. 1999. Morphological variation in Malacothamnus fasciculatus (Torrey &amp; A. Gray) E. Greene (Malvaceae) and related species. Madroño 46: 142–152.</reference>
    <reference>Kearney, T. H. 1951. The genus Malacothamnus Greene (Malvaceae). Leafl. W. Bot. 6: 113–140.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
