<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">MALVA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 687. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Mallow , mauve</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 308. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus MALVA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin name derived from Greek malacho , to soften, alluding to emollient qualities of some species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(de Candolle) Alefeld" date="unknown">Axolopha</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Medikus" date="unknown">Bismalva</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Webb &amp; Berthelot" date="unknown">Saviniona</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>35.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual, biennial, or perennial, subshrubs, or shrubs, glabrous or hairy, hairs stellate or simple. Stems erect, ascending, or trailing. Leaves: stipules persistent or deciduous, linear, lanceolate, triangular, or ovate to ± falcate; blade orbiculate or reniform, unlobed or palmately 3–7(–9)-lobed or divided, base cordate to truncate, margins crenate to dentate. Inflorescences usually axillary, flowers usually in fascicles, sometimes solitary, sometimes terminal racemes; involucel present, bractlets persistent, 3, distinct or basally connate. or recurved pedicel), not inflated, oblate-discoid, usually depressed in center, around broad axis, without persistent swollen style base, ± indurate, glabrous or hairy; mericarps 6–15(–20), drying tan or brown, 1-celled, wedge-shaped (triangular in cross section), oblong to reniform, beak or cusp absent, sides thin and papery or thicker, margins usually edged, apex rounded, indehiscent. Seeds 1 per mericarp, adherent to mericarp wall, usually not readily separated from it, reniform-rounded, notched, glabrous. x = 21.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa (especially Mediterranean region)</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced nearly worldwide.</description>
  <discussion>Species 30–40 (11 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Some species of Malva are weedy; five or six in the flora area generally occur in cultivation as ornamentals or as vegetables and occasionally escape. Some species previously treated within Lavatera (see M. F. Ray 1995, 1998) are here included in Malva based upon molecular evidence. Traditionally, Lavatera and Malva were separated by the presence of partially connate relatively wide involucellar bractlets in the former and distinct generally narrow bractlets in the latter. The annual species of Althaea (sect. Hirsutae Iljin ex Olyanitskaya &amp; Tzvelev) may also belong within Malva, but have been kept separate here. Nomenclature in Althaea, Lavatera, and Malva is still in flux and a satisfactory classification is not yet available. Intergeneric hybrids among some species of all three genera suggest a close relationship.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ray, M. F. 1995. Systematics of Lavatera and Malva (Malvaceae, Malveae)—A new perspective. Pl. Syst. Evol. 198: 29–53.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
