<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">MALVASTRUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Amer. Acad. Arts, n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 21. 1849</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* False mallow</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus MALVASTRUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Malva and Latin -astrum , incomplete resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">Sidopsis</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>36.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, or subshrubs, hairy, hairs closely appressed or tufted, sometimes pustular-based, (2–)4–10[–12]-rayed, stellate, sometimes bilateral, infrequently sublepidote or simple. Stems erect or ascending to decumbent. Leaves: stipules persistent [deciduous], lanceolate to linear [wide-ovate], usually subfalcate or falcate; blade wide-ovate to lanceolate, unlobed or sometimes obscurely 3-lobed, base rounded, slightly cordate, nearly truncate, to cuneate, margins crenate-dentate to dentate-serrate or denticulate. Inflorescences axillary solitary flowers, terminal racemes or spikes in distal 1/2 of plant; involucel present, bractlets</description>
  <description type="distribution">United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, ne Australia.</description>
  <discussion>Species 15 (6 in the flora): United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, ne Australia.</discussion>
  <discussion>Two or three species of Malvastrum have been widely introduced worldwide in tropical and warm-temperate regions; none is usually cultivated; several are considered to be quite weedy. At least one species (M. coromandelianum) has some medicinal use.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 15 (6 in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hill, S. R. 1982. A monograph of the genus Malvastrum A. Gray (Malvaceae: Malveae). Rhodora 84: 1–83, 159–264, 317–409.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
