<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Brian R. Keener</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. E. Fries" date="1908">PSEUDABUTILON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Kongl. Svenska Vetensk. Acad. Handl., n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>43: 96, plate 5, fig. 2</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>plate</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7, figs. 19 – 27. 1908</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus PSEUDABUTILON</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pseud- , false, and genus Abutilon ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>43.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs or shrubs. Stems erect or rarely decumbent, setose or stellate-hairy, not viscid. Leaves: stipules persistent, linear to lanceolate; blade ovate to broadly ovate, unlobed or sometimes shallowly 3-lobed, not dissected, base cordate, margins crenate to serrate. Inflorescences axillary umbels or solitary flowers, sometimes aggregated in terminal inflorescences; involucel absent. Flowers: calyx accrescent, subequal to mature fruit, not inflated, lobes unribbed, triangular to ovate, basally rounded; corolla rotate or shallowly campanulate, yellow; staminal column included; ovary 5–8[–10]-carpellate; ovules (2 or)3 per cell; styles 5–8[–10]-branched; stigmas capitate. Fruits schizocarps, erect to weakly ascending, not inflated, oblate, slightly indurate, hairy; mericarps 5–8[–10], 1-celled sometimes with endoglossum which partially divides chamber into upper and lower portions (this may be interpreted as 2 cells), apex rounded, with divergent apical distal spines, lateral walls usually disintegrating at maturity, dehiscent. Seeds (2 or)3 per mericarp, turbinate, papillate, glabrous. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sc, sw United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</description>
  <discussion>Species 18 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fryxell, P. A. 1997b. A revision and redefinition of Pseudabutilon (Malvaceae). Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 21: 175–195.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
