<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Paul A. Fryxell†,Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">SIDA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 683. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Fanpetals , wireweed</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 306. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus SIDA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek side , name used by Theophrastos for plants now called Nymphaea alba Linnaeus]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Wight" date="unknown">Dictyocarpus</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Boehmer" date="unknown">Malvinda</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(K. Schumann) Monteiro" date="unknown">Pseudomalachra</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>45.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, subshrubs, or shrubs. Stems erect, ascending, or reclining to procumbent, glabrous or hairy, sometimes viscid (S. glabra). Leaves spirally arranged (distichous in S. planicaulis and S. ulmifolia), petiolate or subsessile; stipules persistent, usually linear to lanceolate or falcate; blade usually unlobed (lobed with maplelike leaves in S. hermaphrodita), base cuneate, cordate, subcordate, truncate, or rounded, margins crenate, dentate, serrate, or entire. Inflorescences axillary solitary (sometimes paired or clustered) often plicate in bud, usually 1/2 divided, often 10-ribbed at base (unribbed in S. hermaphrodita) or angulate, lobes acute or acuminate to triangular or ovate; corolla white, cream, yellow, yellow-orange, salmon-pink, red-orange, or reddish [purplish], sometimes with dark-red center; staminal column included; style 5–14-branched; stigmas capitate. Fruits developed or muticous, reticulate, glabrous or hairy, lateral walls usually persistent, indehiscent below with well-differentiated dorsal wall, indehiscent or partially dehiscent apically. Seeds 1 per mericarp, glabrous. x = 7, 8.</description>
  <description type="habitat">in the flora area sida linifolia cavanilles flax-leaved sida is known from a single collection (alabama mobile introduced from west indies on ballast sep 1886 mohr s.n. f) and treated here as a waif</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sida linifolia Cavanilles</description>
  <description type="habitat">flax-leaved sida</description>
  <description type="habitat">is known from a single collection (Alabama</description>
  <description type="habitat">Mobile</description>
  <description type="habitat">introduced from West Indies on ballast</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sep 1886</description>
  <description type="habitat">Mohr s.n.</description>
  <description type="habitat">F) and treated here as a waif</description>
  <description type="distribution">it is distinguished from other sidas in North America by its entire leaf margins. Sida cordata (Burman f.) Borssum Waalkes has been reported in Maryland (Baltimore City)</description>
  <description type="distribution">it is a generally prostrate herb with cordate leaves and filiform pedicels that are nearly the same length as the leaves</description>
  <description type="distribution">no vouchers have been found</description>
  <description type="distribution">if it was present</description>
  <description type="distribution">it can be regarded as a waif. Reports of S. aggregata K. Presl</description>
  <description type="distribution">a variable and rather common Neotropical species</description>
  <description type="distribution">have not been verified</description>
  <description type="distribution">no vouchers have been located. Sida acuta Burman f. and S. carpinifolia Linnaeus f. are names often used for ballast specimens of plants found in temperate seaports that have not persisted.</description>
  <discussion>Most sidas have apical spines on the fruits that adhere to fur, wool, and clothing, and therefore it may be difficult to pinpoint their native ranges versus the areas to which they have been introduced. Some are considered to be pan-tropical roadside weeds.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fryxell, P. A. 1985. Sidus sidarum V. The North and Central American species of Sida. Sida 11: 62–91.</reference>
    <reference>Kearney, T. H. 1954. A tentative key to the North American species of Sida L. Leafl. W. Bot. 7: 138–150.</reference>
    <reference>Krapovickas, A. 2003b. Sida sección Distichifolia (Monteiro) Krapov. comb. nov., stat. nov. (Malvaceae–Malveae). Bonplandia (Corrientes) 12: 83–121.</reference>
    <reference>Krapovickas, A. 2007. Las especies de Sida secc. Malachroideae del Cono Sur de Sudamérica. Bonplandia (Corrientes) 16: 209–225.</reference>
    <reference>Siedo, S. J. 1999. A taxonomic treatment of Sida sect. Ellipticifolia (Malvaceae). Lundellia 2: 100–127.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
