<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="1849">SIDALCEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Amer. Acad. Arts, n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 18. 1849</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Checkerbloom , checker mallow</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus SIDALCEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Generic names Sida and Alcea , alluding to resemblances]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Greene" date="unknown">Hesperalcea</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>46.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, or subshrubs, sometimes glaucous, usually hairy, sometimes glabrate, hairs stellate or simple or both, with taproot, clustered fleshy roots, caudex, or adventitious roots, sometimes with shallow, elongated or compact rhizomes often termed rootstocks. Stems erect or ascending, reclining to decumbent at base, these often rooting, stolonlike stems sometimes present.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America; n Mexico.</description>
  <discussion>Species 31 (31 in the flora): w North America; n Mexico.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some species of Sidalcea are cultivated for ornament. The common name checkerbloom comes from the pattern of veins on the petals of some species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some species of Sidalcea are similar and difficult to distinguish; details of the plant habit and fruits are generally necessary for identification. Most Sidalcea species, especially those in the S. oregana group and S. malviflora group, show great plasticity. The presence of gynodioecy is widespread in Sidalcea, and pistillate and bisexual flowers often have different sizes within a population (the pistillate being smaller). As with most other mallows that have schizocarps, the mericarp features usually are not evident until full dry maturity. The inflorescences are generally rather congested initially and later may elongate; both alternatives in the key should be considered. Inflorescence descriptions in the key are for plants in full flower; staminal column measurements are for bisexual flowers only.</discussion>
  <discussion>There is some difficulty in applying the term rhizome in Sidalcea, although it has widespread traditional use in keys to the species; most structures called rhizomes are at or near the soil surface and may be decumbent rooting stems; rhizomes are best developed in S. calycosa subsp. rhizomata, S. gigantea, and S. hirtipes.</discussion>
  <discussion>The rank subspecies is widely used in this treatment in accordance with C. L. Hitchcock (1957) and S. R. Hill (2012b). Varieties were distinguished within some of the subspecies in past treatments. See Hitchcock for more information on the published varieties.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 31 (31 in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Andreasen, K. and B. G. Baldwin. 2001. Unequal evolutionary rates between annual and perennial lineages of checker mallows (Sidalcea, Malvaceae): Evidence from 18S-26S rDNA internal and external transcribed spacers. Molec. Biol. Evol. 18: 936–944.</reference>
    <reference>Andreasen, K. and B. G. Baldwin. 2003. Reexamination of relationships, habital evolution, and phylogeography of checker mallows (Sidalcea, Malvaceae) based on molecular phylogenetic data. Amer. J. Bot. 90: 436–444.</reference>
    <reference>Andreasen, K. and B. G. Baldwin. 2003b. Nuclear ribosomal DNA sequence polymorphism and hybridization in checker mallows (Sidalcea, Malvaceae). Molec. Phylogen. Evol. 29: 563–581.</reference>
    <reference>Halse, R. R., B. A. Rottink, and R. Mishaga. 1989. Studies in Sidalcea taxonomy. NorthW. Sci. 63: 154–161.</reference>
    <reference>Hill, S. R. 1993. Sidalcea. In: J. C. Hickman, ed. 1993. The Jepson Manual. Higher Plants of California. Berkeley, Los Angeles, and London. Pp. 755–760.</reference>
    <reference>Hill, S. R. 2012b. Sidalcea. In: B. G. Baldwin et al., eds. 2012. The Jepson Manual: Vascular Plants of California, ed. 2. Berkeley. Pp. 887–896.</reference>
    <reference>Hitchcock, C. L. 1957. A Study of the Perennial Species of Sidalcea. Seattle. [Univ. Wash. Publ. Biol. 18.] Roush, E. M. F. 1931. A monograph of the genus Sidalcea. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 18: 117–244.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
