<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="1849">sidalcea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene" date="unknown">multifida</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cybele Columb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 34. 1914</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Cut-leaf checkerbloom E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus sidalcea;species multifida</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>20.</number>
  <description type="morphology">ternately lobed, lobes linear to filiform, narrowest on distalmost leaves, somewhat fleshy, surfaces hairy, hairs appressed, stellate; distalmost leaf lobes unlobed. Inflorescences erect, open, calyces not conspicuously overlapping except sometimes in bud, usually unbranched, usually 3–9(–15)-flowered, elongate, 1-sided, to 7–25 cm; bracts usually paired, linear or lanceolate to narrowly ovate, proximal divided to base, distalmost 2-fid or simple, 5 mm, shorter to longer than pedicels. Pedicels 3–8(–10) mm; involucellar bractlets absent. Flowers usually bisexual or, infrequently, unisexual and pistillate, plants gynodioecious; calyx (6–)7–10 mm, slightly enlarged in fruit, uniformly minutely stellate-puberulent; petals pink to rose, pale-veined at least when dry, 9–20(–25) mm, pistillate shortest; staminal column 3.3–7.5 mm, sparsely stellate-hairy; anthers pale yellowish to white; stigmas 6 or 7.</description>
  <description type="habitat">schizocarps 5–7 mm diam</description>
  <description type="elevation">mericarps 6 or 7, 3.5–4.3 mm, roughened, back finely glandular-puberulent, sides and back coarsely reticulate-veined, pitted, mucro 0.5–1 mm. Seeds 1.5–2 mm. 2n = 20.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering May–Jul(–Sep). Dry places, sagebrush scrub, pinyon-juniper or pine forests; (1200–)2000–2500(–2900) m; Calif., Nev.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering May–Jul(–Sep).</phenology>
      <habitat>Dry places, sagebrush scrub, pinyon-juniper or pine forests;</habitat>
      <elevation>(1200–)2000–2500(–2900) m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Calif., Nev.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Flowering May–Jul(–Sep). Dry places, sagebrush scrub, pinyon-juniper or pine forests; (1200–)2000–2500(–2900) m; Calif., Nev.</discussion>
  <discussion>Sidalcea multifida is generally a low-growing plant of high elevations, and usually can be distinguished by its highly glaucous, waxy, generally erect stems and leaves, and the generally basal and persistent seven- to nine-lobed leaf blades with pinnate or ternate lobes. It has been confused with S. glaucescens, to which it appears to be closely related and of which it may be found to be a variant or subspecies; as in S. glaucescens, the narrow inflorescence is often slightly curved between flowers. Sidalcea multifida can generally be distinguished from S. glaucescens by its seven- to nine-lobed leaf blades with more finely divided, ternate lobes, persisting basal leaves, range, and more erect habit. It occurs in Alpine, Mono, and Tulare counties in California, and from Lyon to Washoe counties in Nevada.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
