<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John La Duke</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. St.-Hilaire in A. St.-Hilaire et al." date="1825">SPHAERALCEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. St.-Hilaire et al., Fl. Bras. Merid.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(fol.): 163. 1825</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Globemallow</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus SPHAERALCEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek sphaera , sphere, and alkea , mallow, alluding to arrangement of mericarps in a spherical head]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>48.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial. Stems erect or decumbent to ascending, stellate-canescent to stellate-silvery-lepidote, rarely glabrous. Leaves petiolate or sessile; stipules persistent or deciduous, linear; blade linear, lanceolate, orbiculate, or ovate to triangular, trullate, or cordate, unlobed or pedately dissected, base tapered, cuneate, or truncate to cordate, margins entire or crenate to serrate. Inflorescences terminal, racemes or panicles, or flowers sometimes fascicled or in axillary cymose racemes; involucel absent or present, involucellar bractlets inflated, cylindric, ovoid, flattened-spheric, flattened-spheric-conic, hemispheric, widely conic, truncate-conic, spheric, truncate-ovoid, ellipsoid, short-urceolate, helmet-shaped, or truncate-spheric, indurate, hairy; mericarps [7–]9–30, drying tan to brown, 1- or 2-celled, without dorsal spur, distally extended or not, usually smooth, apex cuspidate, truncate, or acute, with or without seeds, proximally usually rugose-reticulate and indehiscent, distally ± dehiscent, often remaining attached to fruit axis after maturity by threadlike extension of dorsal vein. Seeds 1 or 2(or 3) per mericarp, glabrous or slightly pubescent. x = 5.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w, c North America, Mexico, South America (Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile, Paraguay).</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (26 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Sphaeralcea is often collected and somewhat difficult to identify. The species boundaries are not always sharp because there is frequent hybridization, polyploidy, and morphological variation in response to environmental conditions, particularly rainfall. Plants growing in Arizona are particularly difficult to identify.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kearney, T. H. 1935. The North American species of Sphaeralcea subgenus Eusphaeralcea. Univ. Calif. Publ. Bot. 19: 1–128.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
