<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Steven R. Hill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">malvaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">URENA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 692. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* [Malayalam ooren , to loosen or soak, alluding to retting process to extract fibers from stem tissues of U. lobata ] I</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 309. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family malvaceae;genus URENA</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>51.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, subshrubs, or shrubs, stellate-hairy or glabrate. Stems erect. Leaves: stipules early-deciduous, subulate; blade variable, sometimes ovate, [oblong or lanceolate], often 3–5-angled, -lobed, or –parted, base truncate to cordate, margins crenate [serrate], surfaces minutely stellate-hairy, with 1+ prominent, foliar nectaries (glands) on abaxial side at base of central vein. Inflorescences axillary solitary flowers or fascicles, [terminal racemes]; involucel present, bractlets persistent, 5, basally connate. Pedicels 1.5–7 mm. Flowers: calyx not accrescent, not inflated, lobes keeled, 1-veined, lanceolate, elliptic to ovate, usually acute, usually obscured by involucel; corolla shallowly campanulate to rotate, rose-pink, drying lavender; staminal column included; ovary 5-carpellate; ovules 1 per cell; style 10-branched, 2 per carpel; stigmas capitellate. Fruits schizocarps, erect, not inflated, oblate, unwinged, slightly indurate; mericarps 5, 1-celled, without dorsal spur, apex rounded, dorsal surface prominently glochidiate [smooth], otherwise hirtellous or glabrous, flat lateral surfaces striate, indehiscent. Seeds 1 per mericarp, obovoid or reniform, glabrous. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced;</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide in tropical and warm regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species 6 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
