<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Lorin I. Nevling Jr.,Kerry Barringer</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">THYMELAEACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>Family THYMELAEACEAE</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs or shrubs, deciduous or evergreen. Stems flexible; wood usually poorly lignified; bark ring; disc usually present (minute or absent in Thymelaea), surrounding gynoecium; stamens usually diplostemonous; anthers introrse, 4-sporangiate; ovary 1-locular, 1(–5)-carpellate;</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">ne Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">s</description>
  <description type="distribution">c Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">e</description>
  <description type="distribution">se Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Genera ca. 46, species ca. 450 (4 genera, 7 species in the flora): North America, ne Mexico, s, c Europe, e, se Asia, n Africa, Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Genera ca. 46, species ca. 450 (4 genera, 7 species in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, ne Mexico, s, c Europe, e, se Asia, n Africa, Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 46, species ca. 450 (4 genera, 7 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Classification of Thymelaeaceae within the dicotyledons is uncertain. It was placed in Myrtales, near Elaeagnaceae, because of its internal phloem and prominent hypanthium; that treatment is not supported by embryological and genetic data. Euphorbiaceae and Flacourtiaceae also have been suggested as possible relatives based on similarities in pollen and biochemistry. Other classifications place Thymelaeaceae in the Malvanae, either in its own order, Thymelaeales, or in Malvales.</discussion>
  <discussion>All species are poisonous to mammals, containing tricyclic daphnane and tiglane diterpenes, esters of daphnetoxin, and coumarins. The bark and fruit can be extremely irritating to mucous membranes even after drying and cause contact dermatitis in sensitive individuals.</discussion>
  <discussion>A dozen species of Daphne are grown for their sweet-scented flowers and early bloom. Species of Pimelea Banks ex Gaertner and Dais cotinifolia Linnaeus also are cultivated as ornamentals in warm climates.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Domke, F. W. 1934. Untersuchungen über die systematische und geographische Gliederung der Thymelaeaceen. Biblioth. Bot. 27: 1–151.</reference>
    <reference>Fuchs, A. 1938. Beiträge zur Embryologie der Thymelaeaceae. Oesterr. Bot. Z. 87: 1–41.</reference>
    <reference>Gilg, E. 1894. Thymelaeaceae. In: H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl, eds. 1887–1915.</reference>
    <reference>Die natürlichen Pflanzenfamilien.... 254 fascs. Leipzig. Fasc. 106[III,6a], pp. 217–245.</reference>
    <reference>Nevling, L. I. Jr. 1962. Thymelaeaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 43: 428–434.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
