<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CISTACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>Family CISTACEAE</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, subshrubs, or shrubs, &lt;usually hairy&gt;. Leaves alternate, opposite, or whorled, usually estipulate, sometimes stipulate (Tuberaria), &lt;stipules caducous&gt;, petiolate or sessile; blade 1- or 3- [5-]veined from base, not lobed, &lt;sometimes scalelike&gt;, margins entire [crenate, serrate], sometimes revolute and/or undulate. Inflorescences usually corymbose, cymose, paniculate, racemose, thyrsiform, or umbellate, seldom solitary flowers. Pedicels present or absent; bracts present or absent. Flowers chasmogamous or cleistogamous; sepals &lt;persistent or tardily falling&gt;, 3–5; petals &lt;usually caducous [marcescent]&gt;, usually 3–5, &lt;sometimes 0 in cleistogamous flowers, imbricate, distinct, crumpled in bud&gt;, green, dark red, pink, purple, red, white, or yellow; stamens (3–)5–150+; &lt;filaments distinct or basally connate&gt;; ovaries superior, 2-, 3-, 5-, or 6–12-carpellate; placentation parietal; styles 0 or 1; stigmas 1 or 3; ovules orthotropous [anatropous], bitegmic, crassinucellate. Fruits capsular, dehiscence loculicidal [septifragal]. Seeds (1–)3–800+ per capsule, &lt;often with thin outer integument&gt;.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly of temperate areas.</description>
  <discussion>Genera 8, species 170–180 (5 genera, 40 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Affinities of Cistaceae are evidently with Malvales. Members of Cistaceae are widely cultivated, especially cultivars of hybrids and species of Cistus, Crocanthemum, Halimium (Dunal) Spach, and Helianthemum Miller.</discussion>
  <discussion>Hairs on Cistaceae plants may be simple or stellate (comprising tight clusters or tufts of simple, unbranched hairs) and glandular or eglandular.</discussion>
  <discussion>Two species of Cistaceae have been collected in the flora area as waifs. Helianthemum nummularium Miller is known from Colorado, Missouri, and Oregon; it differs from species of Crocanthemum by the combination of glabrous abaxial surfaces of sepals and stellate-tomentose ovaries. Helianthemum salicifolium (Linnaeus) Miller is known from New York; it differs from species of Crocanthemum by its opposite leaves and erect, curved pedicels.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Arrington, J. M. 2004. Systematics of the Cistaceae. Ph.D. dissertation. Duke University. Arrington, J. M. and K. Kubitzki. 2003. Cistaceae. In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 10+ vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 5, pp. 62–70.</reference>
    <reference>Guzmán, B. and P. Vargas. 2009. Historical biogeography and character evolution of Cistaceae (Malvales) based on analysis of plastid rbcL and trnL-trnF sequences. Organisms Diversity Evol. 9: 83–99.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
