<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cucurbitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Silva Manso" date="unknown">CAYAPONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Subst. Braz.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>31. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cucurbitaceae;genus CAYAPONIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Derivation uncertain, perhaps from Caiapó, river or native tribe of Amazonian Brazil]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>22.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, usually monoecious, sometimes dioecious, climbing; stems &lt;annual or perennial&gt;, puberulent or glabrous; roots tuberous; tendrils unbranched or 2[–3]-branched. Leaves: blade [subquadrangular] pentagonal, deltate, or ovate, unlobed or 3–5-lobed, lobes broadly triangular or deltate to ovate-deltate, oblong-oblanceolate, or elliptic, margins denticulate or serrulate, surfaces sometimes with disc-shaped glands abaxially near base or bracts filiform or absent. Flowers: hypanthium campanulate; sepals 5, deltate to triangular or linear [ovate-lanceolate, oblong-lanceolate, or linear-subulate]; petals 5, connate 1/2–2/3 length, white, cream, or pale green [orange to yellow], oblong-lanceolate to linear-oblong, 5–10 mm, glabrous or puberulent or tomentose adaxially, corolla rotate to campanulate. Staminate flowers: stamens 3; filaments inserted near hypanthium rim, distinct; thecae distinct or connate, forming a head, sigmoid-replicate,</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 60 (2 in the flora): se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</discussion>
  <discussion>A discussion of plasticity of inflorescence morphology in Cayaponia was provided by R. McVaugh (2001b)––a flowering branch apparently constitutes a complex branching system, potentially producing solitary flowers, groups of flowers, or new branches from any node. Although these observations pertain directly only to C. attenuata (Hooker &amp; Arnott) Cogniaux, they perhaps also apply to the two species included here.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 60 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Duchen, P. and S. S. Renner. 2010. The evolution of Cayaponia (Cucurbitaceae): Repeated shifts from bat to bee pollination and long-distance dispersal to Africa 2–5 million years ago. Amer. J. Bot. 97: 1129–1141.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
