<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Desvaux" date="unknown">frankeniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">FRANKENIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 331. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 154. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family frankeniaceae;genus FRANKENIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Johann Frankenius, 1590 – 1661, Swedish botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Branches articulated, often swollen at nodes, usually differentiated into long and short shoots, hairs simple. Leaves petiolate or sessile, salt crystals usually present on leaf surfaces, sometimes forming solid crust, short-shoot leaves in axillary fascicles; petiole sometimes inconspicuous,</description>
  <description type="habitat">narrow to broad distally margins usually ciliate. inflorescences: floral bracts leaflike usually connate basally into verticels of 4 clasping calyx base (rarely adnate to calyx base). flowers: calyx tube cylindric [campanulate] strongly rounded-ribbed</description>
  <description type="habitat">margins usually ciliate. Inflorescences: floral bracts leaflike</description>
  <description type="habitat">usually connate basally into verticels of 4</description>
  <description type="habitat">clasping calyx base (rarely adnate to calyx base). Flowers: calyx tube cylindric [campanulate]</description>
  <description type="habitat">strongly rounded-ribbed</description>
  <description type="elevation">4–6[–7]-lobed, petals white, pink, violet, or blue-purple, oblong-oblanceolate to spatulate, claw linear, broadening slightly at apex, to narrowly cuneate, limb apex truncate or rounded, erose-denticulate to sinuous, glabrous;</description>
  <description type="distribution">anthers yellow or red to yellowish pink to purplish red</description>
  <description type="distribution">ovary with [1–]2–60[–100] ovules</description>
  <description type="distribution">funiculi ascending and bearing erect ovules or deflexed and bearing pendulous ovules</description>
  <description type="distribution">usually free</description>
  <description type="distribution">infrequently adnate to carpel wall for part of their lengths. Seeds ivory to golden brown</description>
  <description type="distribution">ovoid-conic or elongate-ovoid to oblong- or ovoid-ellipsoid or ellipsoid. x = 5.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 70 (5 in the flora): United States, Mexico, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Australia; introduced in West Indies.</discussion>
  <discussion>Frankenia species vary in the degree of revoluteness of the leaf margins. This is most easily determined on fresh or softened material; loosely revolute margins will often tend to become somewhat more revolute on drying but can still be distinguished from tightly revolute margins that are not readily unrolled.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Whalen, M. A. 1987. Systematics of Frankenia (Frankeniaceae) in North and South America. Syst. Bot. Monogr. 17: 1–93.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
