<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cucurbitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">CUCURBITA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1010. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Squash , gourd</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 441. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cucurbitaceae;genus CUCURBITA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin name for gourd]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cucurbita</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(E. James) A. Gray" date="unknown">perennis</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pepo</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Kunth) Britton" date="unknown">foetidissima</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>23.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants sometimes shrublike in cultivated forms of C. melopepo, annual or perennial, monoecious, procumbent and trailing or climbing; stems &lt;annual, often sulcate or angled&gt;, hairy; roots tuberous or fibrous or a taproot; tendrils 2–7-branched or absent. Leaves: blade suborbiculate to broadly ovate, ovate-lanceolate, reniform, or triangular, usually deeply to shallowly palmately (3–)5(–7)-lobed, sometimes unlobed or 2-lobed, lobes depressed-ovate, ovate, broadly or narrowly triangular, or obovate to lanceolate, oblanceolate, oblong-lanceolate, or subrhombic, &lt;base truncate to cordate&gt;, margins serrate to denticulate or mucronulate, surfaces eglandular or glandular, glands scattered, sessile or stipitate to peltate. Inflorescences: staminate flowers solitary [in axillary fascicles]; pistillate flowers solitary, from different axils than staminate; floral bracts absent. Flowers: hypanthium campanulate, cylindric, or cupulate; sepals 5, &lt;straight, erect&gt;, subulate-linear to lanceolate [spatulate]; petals 5, &lt;often recurving&gt;, connate 1/2 length, cream or</description>
  <description type="habitat">yellow to orange broadly ovate to oblong-ovate oblong-elliptic triangular triangular-ovate or lanceolate-ovate 25–90[–120] mm pubescent to puberulent corolla campanulate. staminate flowers: stamens 3</description>
  <description type="habitat">broadly ovate to oblong-ovate</description>
  <description type="habitat">oblong-elliptic</description>
  <description type="habitat">triangular</description>
  <description type="habitat">triangular-ovate</description>
  <description type="habitat">or lanceolate-ovate</description>
  <description type="habitat">25–90[–120] mm</description>
  <description type="habitat">pubescent to puberulent</description>
  <description type="habitat">corolla campanulate. Staminate flowers: stamens 3</description>
  <description type="elevation">filaments inserted at hypanthium base, distinct or slightly connate; thecae connate, forming central oblong body, sigmoid-flexuous, connective narrow; margins differentiated or not in thickness, texture, and color, surface smooth or slightly rough to punctate-sculptured. x = 20.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 14–22 (9 in the flora): North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America; introduced nearly worldwide.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 14–22 (9 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America; introduced nearly worldwide.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 14–22 (9 in the flora): North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America; introduced nearly worldwide.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species of Cucurbita have long provided fruits that are staples of the world’s diet. Radiocarbon dates for C. pepo from Guilá Naquitz Cave in subtropical central Oaxaca, Mexico, document the earliest known cultivation of a squash––between 10,000 to 8000 calendar years ago (B. D. Smith 1997)––predating the appearance of maize, beans, and other directly dated domesticates in the Americas by about 4000 years. The oldest known cultivated maize cobs also have come from Guilá Naquitz Cave, dated about 6250 calendar years ago. Cultivated cucurbits were introduced into the Old World quickly after the discovery of the New World (H. S. Paris et al. 2006), and since the 17th century they have spread over the tropics and subtropics and temperate regions. After its introduction to the Old World, C. pepo apparently underwent secondary diversification in Europe and/or Asia Minor (J. R. Harlan 1951).</discussion>
  <discussion>Cucurbita has been divided into two groups (T. W. Whitaker and W. P. Bemis 1975): the arid-zone perennials with tuberous storage roots, and the more mesophytic annuals or short-lived perennials without storage roots. Four of the domesticated species (C. argyrosperma K. Koch, C. maxima, C. moschata, and C. pepo) plus one wild species (C. ecuadoriensis Cutler &amp; Whitaker) comprise the mesophytic lineage (O. I. Sanjur et al. 2002). One other among the mesophytic domesticated species, C. ficifolia, is outside the mesophytic clade and basal to it.</discussion>
  <discussion>Uncertainty about the number of species in the genus reflects two areas of subjectivity: some domesticated species are commonly treated as conspecific with a wild species when a derivative-progenitor relationship is indicated––the domesticated Cucurbita maxima arose from the wild C. andreana Naudin of South America; and, the taxonomic status of some entities is not unambiguously resolved––C. digitata was treated by M. Nee (1990) to include four taxa, three of which are sometimes treated as distinct species. In any case, the geography and morphology of all the entities potentially treated at specific rank is fairly well understood. Additionally, Nee has noted that a wild ancestor of C. moschata, from reports from Colombia, may remain to be discovered and described; similarly, he has predicted that the wild ancestor of C. ficifolia exists somewhere in the Andes.</discussion>
  <discussion>Four of the domesticated species are treated here because they sometimes are encountered in the flora area outside of cultivation; in most cases, these plants can be characterized as waifs, as they apparently do not maintain themselves in persistent populations for more than one or a few years.</discussion>
  <discussion>Cucurbita argyrosperma K. Koch (Japanese pie pumpkin, white cushaw) is currently grown in the United States and known to have been in cultivation in eastern North America since pre-Columbian times (G. J. Fritz 1994); it has not been reported to grow outside of cultivation in the flora area.</discussion>
  <discussion>Identification of species among plants of domesticated Cucurbita often is difficult (especially among C. maxima, C. melopepo, C. moschata, and C. pepo) because habit, vestiture, leaf shape, and floral characters commonly show parallel variation, and fruit shape and size are highly variable.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants perennial; roots tuberous. Stems prostrate, sometimes rooting adventitiously at nodes, ca. 2–10 m, puberulent to scabrous with pustulate-based hairs; tendrils 3–7-branched 3–6 cm above base, hirsute, eglandular. Leaves: petiole 3–12 cm, coarsely hispid to hispidulous with puberulent understory of gland-tipped hairs; blade narrowly triangular or triangular-acuminate to triangular-lanceolate, unlobed or shallowly 2-lobed, (10–)12–30(–40) × (6–)8–20(–30) cm, longer than broad, base hastate-cordate to truncate, margins coarsely and widely mucronulate to denticulate, surfaces densely short-hirsute-pilose abaxially, short strigose-hirsute to hispid-hirsute adaxially, eglandular or minutely sessile-glandular. Peduncles in fruit 5-ribbed, slightly expanded or not at point of fruit attachment, hardened, woody. Flowers: hypanthium broadly campanulate, 10–18 mm; sepals narrowly lanceolate to linear-oblong or filiform-subulate, 10–25 mm; corolla golden yellow, campanulate to cylindric-campanulate, 6–10 cm; anther filaments usually sparsely short-villous with viscid-glandular hairs; ovary hirsute to short-villous. Pepos green with white stripes, white-mottled, evenly yellowish to orange-yellow at full maturity, depressed-globose to globose or oblong-globose, 5–10 cm, smooth. Seeds tan to cream or yellowish, oblong-ovate to ovate-elliptic, 9–13 mm, margins thickened-raised, surface smooth. 2n = 40, 42.</discussion>
  <discussion>Flowering May–Aug. Sandy fields and hills, sandsage prairies, dunes, gypsum hills, rocky soil, calcareous clay loam, grasslands, mesquite scrub, pinyon-juniper, floodplain woods, vacant lots, roadsides, railroad banks; 100–2000 m; Ariz., Ark., Calif., Colo., Fla., Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., Mich., Mo., Nebr., Nev., N.Mex., Ohio, Okla., Tex., Utah, Va., Wyo.; Mexico (Chihuahua, Coahuila, Nuevo León, San Luis Potosí, Sonora, Zacatecas); introduced in Europe (Germany).</discussion>
  <discussion>Records of Cucurbita foetidissima in localities east of Missouri apparently represent adventives outside of the native range. The single known locality in Florida (Marion County) was where hay from the Midwest was thrown.</discussion>
  <discussion>Cucurbita foetidissima has been studied as a source of root starch and seed oil and is a potentially productive crop adapted to arid and semiarid regions. The tuberous roots of an individual average 50 kilograms in weight in three to four growing seasons (J. S. DeVeaux and E. B. Shultz 1985).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bailey, L. H. 1943. Species of Cucurbita. Gentes Herb. 6: 266–322.</reference>
    <reference>Bemis, W. P. and T. W. Whitaker. 1969. The xerophytic Cucurbita of northwestern Mexico and southwestern United States. Madroño 20: 33–41.</reference>
    <reference>Decker, D. S., T. W. Walters, and U. Posluszny. 1990. Genealogy and gene flow among annual domesticated species of Cucurbita. Canad. J. Bot. 68: 782–789.</reference>
    <reference>Nee, M. 1990. The domestication of Cucurbita (Cucurbitaceae). Econ. Bot. 44(3,suppl.): 56–68.</reference>
    <reference>Rhodes, A. M. et al. 1968. Numerical taxonomic study of Cucurbita. Brittonia 20: 251–266.</reference>
    <reference>Sanjur, O. I. et al. 2002. Phylogenetic relationships among domesticated and wild species of Cucurbita (Cucurbitaceae) inferred from a mitochondrial gene: Implications for crop plant evolution and areas of origin. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 99: 535–540.</reference>
    <reference>Whitaker, T. W. and W. P. Bemis. 1975. Origin and evolution of the cultivated Cucurbita. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 102: 362–368.</reference>
    <reference>Wilson, H. D. 1990. Gene flow in squash species. BioScience 40: 449–455.</reference>
    <reference>Wilson, H. D., J. Doebley, and M. Duvall. 1992. Chloroplast DNA diversity among wild and cultivated members of Cucurbita (Cucurbitaceae). Theor. Appl. Genet. 84: 859–865.</reference>
  </references>
  <references>
    <reference>Bemis, W. P. et al. 1978. The feral buffalo gourd, Cucurbita foetidissima. Econ. Bot. 32: 87–95.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
