<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cucurbitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">cucurbita</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Small) L. H. Bailey" date="unknown">okeechobeensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="[C E]" date="unknown">okeechobeensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cucurbitaceae;genus cucurbita;species okeechobeensis;subspecies okeechobeensis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4a.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual; roots fibrous. Stems prostrate or climbing, sometimes rooting adventitiously at nodes, to 12 m, usually coarsely hirsute to villous with flattened, vitreous hairs to glabrate or glabrous, rarely sparsely short-hispid, without pustulate-based hairs; tendrils 3-branched 1–3 cm above base, glabrous, eglandular. Leaves: petiole 5–15 cm, sparsely hispid to pilose-hirsute or glabrous or glabrate; blade orbiculate to suborbiculate or reniform, shallowly to deeply 5–7-lobed, 4.5–15 × 8–20 cm, usually broader than long or equally so, base cordate, lobes triangular to acuminate-triangular or subrhombic, midveins of leaf lobes not distinctly elongate-whitened, margins closely mucronulate to denticulate, sometimes irregularly toothed, surfaces hispid to hispid-hirsute or villous-hirsute to sparsely hirsute-villous or glabrate, sometimes mottled with silvery-green adaxially, eglandular. Peduncles in fruit shallowly 5-ribbed, abruptly expanded at point of fruit attachment, hardened, woody. Flowers: hypanthium campanulate, 5–6 mm; sepals lanceolate to subulate, 5–8 mm; corolla cream to pale creamy yellow, campanulate, 6–9 cm (staminate shorter); anther filaments glabrous; ovary densely pubescent. Pepos light green with pale white stripes at maturity, green-streaked or flecked with white or dark green, tan to brown when dry, globose to broadly ovoid, (5–)7–9(–11) cm, surface smooth; &lt;flesh intensely bitter&gt;. Seeds whitish to light gray, ovate, 7–12 mm, margins thickened-raised, surfaces smooth. 2n = 40.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Mar–Nov.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Pond-apple swamps, floodplain forests, power-line cuts through cypress-hardwood swamps, hardwood swamp edges, spoil islands, climbing on pond apple, elderberry, and buttonbush, often associated with alligator nests, canal and ditch banks, wet road shoulders;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–20 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
