<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cucurbitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">cucurbita</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pepo</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="[I]" date="unknown">pepo</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cucurbitaceae;genus cucurbita;species pepo;subspecies pepo</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cucurbita</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Willdenow" date="unknown">aurantia</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">C.</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">pepo</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Alefeld" date="unknown">medullosa</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>5a.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual; roots taproots or fibrous. Stems creeping or climbing, rooting adventitiously at nodes, to 3 m, hispid with persistent, strongly pustulate-based hairs and a hispidulous-hirsutulous understory; tendrils 2–7-branched 1–5 cm above base, hispidulous to hirsutulous, eglandular. Leaves: petiole 5–20(–24) cm, pustulate-hispid (pustulate-based) and hispidulous-hirsutulous; blade &lt;sometimes white-spotted at vein junctions&gt;, broadly ovate-cordate to triangular-cordate or reniform, shallowly to deeply palmately (3–)5–7-lobed, 20–30 × 20–35 cm, usually broader than long or equally so, base cordate, lobes ovate-deltate to obovate or obovate-rhombic, midveins of leaf lobes not distinctly elongate-whitened, margins denticulate to serrate-denticulate, surfaces hirsute, hirsute-strigillose, villous-strigose, or hispidulous-scabrous, eglandular. Peduncles in fruit 5-ribbed, not or very gradually expanded at point of fruit attachment, hardened, woody. Flowers: hypanthium campanulate, 8–12 mm; sepals linear to subulate-linear, 8–25 mm; corolla yellow to golden yellow or orange, tubular-campanulate, 4–10 cm; anther filaments glabrous; ovary villous. Pepos wholly light to dark green, green with white stripes, or minutely cream- or green-speckled to yellow, orange, or bicolored green and yellow, globose or depressed-globose to ovoid, obovoid, ellipsoid-ovoid, broadly ellipsoid, slightly pyriform, cushion-shaped, or cylindric, 5–10(–25) cm, usually smooth or ribbed, rarely verrucose, &lt;flesh whitish to yellowish or pale orange, soft, not bitter&gt;. Seeds whitish to cream or tawny, narrowly to broadly elliptic to obovate, rarely orbiculate, 7–15(–26) mm, margins raised-thickened, surface ± smooth. 2n = 40.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jun–Oct.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Vacant lots, trash heaps, roadsides, disturbed sites;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Ala., Calif., Conn., Kans., Ky., La., Mass., Mich., Nev., N.H., N.Mex., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., S.C., Tenn., Utah, Va.; Mexico; South America; introduced also in West Indies, Central America, Eurasia, Atlantic Islands.</description>
</bio:treatment>
