<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>12.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eupatorium</genus_name><species_name>leucolepis</species_name><species_authority>(de Candolle) Torrey &amp; A. Gray</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 84. 1841</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Justiceweed</common_name><common_name>white-bracted thoroughwort</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Eupatorium</genus_name><species_name>glaucescens</species_name><species_authority>Elliott</species_authority><variety_name>leucolepis</variety_name><variety_authority>de Candolle</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr. </publication_title><place_in_publication>5: 177. 1836</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials, 40–100+ cm. Stems (from short caudices or stout rhizomes) single, sparsely branched distally, puberulent throughout (more densely distally and among heads). Leaves usually opposite (distal sometimes alternate, ascending to vertical); sessile; blades pinnately nerved, lance-oblong to linear-oblong, 20–60 × 4–10(–15) mm, bases rounded to cuneate (not connate-perfoliate), margins entire or serrate, apices acute, faces villous (abaxial), scabrous (adaxial), gland-dotted. Heads in corymbiform arrays. Phyllaries 8–10 in 2–3 series, narrowly elliptic, 2.5–8 × 0.8–1.2 mm, acuminate to attenuate, mucronate, abaxial faces puberulent, gland-dotted. Florets 5; corollas 3–3.5 mm. Cypselae 2–3 mm; pappi of 30–40 bristles 4.5–5 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>e North America.</global_distribution><discussion>Eupatorium leucolepis is distinct morphologically by its acuminate to attenuate phyllaries, linear and usually plicate leaves, and phyllotaxy that is almost always strictly opposite to the arrays, with well-separated nodes. Eupatorium leucolepis has recently been shown to include two distinct species, an unnamed diploid that is endemic to Carolina Bay habitats and a series of relatively widespread and mostly polyploid, apomictic populations that include the type. It was recognized after preparation of this treatment that E. novae-angliae (E. leucolepis var. novae-angliae) was derived from hybridization between the unnamed diploid and E. perfoliatum, and is here recognized as a distinct species; it is not directly related genetically to E. leucolepis and thus is not appropriately classified as a variety of it.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades strongly folded along midribs, curved, 4–10 mm wide.</statement>
      <determination>12a. Eupatorium leucolepis var. leucolepis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades weakly folded along midribs, not curved, 10–15 mm wide.</statement>
      <determination>12b. Eupatorium leucolepis var. novae-angliae</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
