<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Eric E. Lamont</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">eupatorieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="1838">EUTROCHIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>New Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 78. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe eupatorieae;genus EUTROCHIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek eu- , well, truly, and trocho- , wheel-like, alluding to whorled leaves]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. M. King &amp; H. Robinson" date="unknown">Eupatoriadelphus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eupatoriadelphus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Eupatorium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">Verticillatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eupatorium;section Verticillatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, 30–350+ cm. Stems (sometimes ± purple, sometimes glaucous, internodes usually shorter than leaves) erect, unbranched. Leaves mostly cauline; mostly whorled (3–7 per node), rarely opposite; petiolate; blades pinnately veined or ± 3-nerved from at or near bases, deltate-ovate, lance-elliptic, lanceolate, lance-ovate, or ovate (bases gradually or abruptly tapered), margins serrate (usually with gland at apex of each tooth, apices acuminate), abaxial faces usually gland-dotted and hirsute, puberulent, pubescent, scabrous, or stipitate-glandular, sometimes glabrate, adaxial faces mostly puberulent to scabrous-hirsute and glabrescent, sometimes glabrate or glabrous. Heads discoid, in (flat-topped or convex to rounded) compound, corymbiform arrays. Involucres cylindric, 2.5–7 mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 10–22 in 5–6 series, (pale pink to purple, rarely white, tightly appressed) striate or 1-nerved, mostly lance-ovate to lanceolate, unequal (outer 2–3 obtuse, densely pubescent or glabrescent, often gland-dotted, innermost glabrous or glabrescent). Receptacles flat or convex, epaleate. Florets 4–22; corollas usually purplish or pinkish, rarely white, throats funnelform, lobes 5, ovate to deltate; styles: bases enlarged, puberulent, branches ± filiform to clavate (slightly dilated or flattened distally, papillose). Cypselae (dark brown to black or yellowish brown) prismatic, 5-ribbed, usually gland-dotted, sometimes scabrellous on ribs; pappi persistent, of 25–40 (cream to pinkish purple) barbellate bristles in 1 series. x = 10.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <number>393.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Joepyeweed</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">eupatoire</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 5 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Detailed distribution maps for taxa of Eutrochium are available but treated as taxa under Eupatorium (E. E. Lamont 1995).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Lamont, E. E. 1995. Taxonomy of Eupatorium section Verticillata (Asteraceae). Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 72: 1–66.</reference>
    <reference>Mackenzie, K. K. 1920. Scientific names applicable to our purple-flowered eupatoriums. Rhodora 22: 157–165.</reference>
    <reference>Wiegand, K. M. and C. A. Weatherby. 1937. The nomenclature of the verticillate eupatoria. Rhodora 39: 297–306.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually ± 3-nerved and bases of blades abruptly contracted to petioles; florets (4–)5–9(–10) (near coast from South Carolina to New Hampshire and Nova Scotia).</description>
      <determination>1. Eutrochium dubium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves either pinnately veined or bases of blades gradually narrowed to petioles or both; florets 4–10 or 8–22.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads in ± flat-topped arrays; florets 8–22</description>
      <determination>2. Eutrochium maculatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads in convex to rounded arrays; florets 4–10.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually glandular-pubescent throughout, sometimes densely puberulent and sparingly glandular; abaxial leaf faces ± glandular-pubescent and sparsely hirsute; s Appalachian Mountains of sw Virginia, e Kentucky, e Tennessee, and w NorthCarolina</description>
      <determination>3. Eutrochium steelei</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous proximal to heads; abaxial leaf faces sparingly and minutely gland-dotted; relatively widespread in e North America.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems purple at nodes, usually solid, rarely ± hollow near bases</description>
      <determination>4. Eutrochium purpureum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems purplish throughout (and glaucous), hollow</description>
      <determination>5. Eutrochium fistulosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
