<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eutrochium</genus_name><species_name>purpureum</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) E. E. Lamont</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sida</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>21: 902. 2004</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Sweetscented or sweet joepyeweed</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Eupatorium</genus_name><species_name>purpureum</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 838. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Eupatoriadelphus</genus_name><species_name>purpureus</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) R. M. King &amp; H. Robinson</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 30–200 cm. Stems usually dark purple at nodes, usually otherwise greenish, rarely purplish green, usually solid, rarely ± hollow near bases, glabrous proximally, ± glandular-puberulent distally and among heads. Leaves mostly in 3s–4s(–5s); petioles 5–15(–20) mm, glabrous or sparingly puberulent, rarely ciliate; blades pinnately veined, lance-ovate or ovate to deltate-ovate, mostly (7–)9–26(–30) × (2.5–)3–15(–18) cm, bases abruptly or gradually tapered, margins coarsely serrate, abaxial faces sparingly and minutely gland-dotted and densely pubescent to glabrate, adaxial faces sparingly puberulent and glabrescent or glabrous. Heads in loose, convex, compound corymbiform arrays. Involucres often purplish, 6.5–9 × 2.5–5 mm. Phyllaries usually glabrous, sometimes sparsely hairy. Florets (4–)5–7(–8); corollas usually pale pinkish or purplish, 4.5–7 mm. Cypselae 3–4.5 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America.</global_distribution><discussion>Eutrochium purpureum is morphologically variable and is known to hybridize with all other species in the genus (E. E. Lamont 1995). Historically, more than a dozen infraspecific taxa have been recognized; the extent of intergradation and the lack of correlation among varying traits tend to make recognition of more than two varieties impractical.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves: abaxial faces usually glabrous, sometimes sparsely to densely hairy along major veins (hairs fine, simple, 1-cellular); s New Hampshire to n Florida, w to se Minnesota, Iowa, and e Oklahoma.</statement>
      <determination>4a. Eutrochium purpureum var. purpureum</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves: abaxial faces densely and persistently puberulent to villous; s Minnesota, Iowa, and ne Kansas to s Wisconsin, n Illinois, and n Missouri.</statement>
      <determination>4b. Eutrochium purpureum var. holzingeri</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
