<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>19.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Rudbeckia</genus_name><species_name>hirta</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 907. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Black-eyed Susan</common_name><description>Annuals, biennials, or perennials, to 100 cm (taprooted or roots fibrous). Stems hispid to hirsute (hairs spreading, 1+ mm). Leaves: blades elliptic, lanceolate, or ovate (not lobed), bases attenuate to cuneate, margins entire or serrate, apices acute, faces hispid to hirsute; basal petiolate, blades 8–30 × 0.5–7 cm; cauline petiolate or sessile, blades (sometimes pandurate) 3–20 × 0.4–4 cm. Heads borne singly or (2–5) in loose, corymbiform arrays. Phyllaries to 3 cm (faces hispid to hirsute). Receptacles hemispheric to ovoid; paleae 4–6 mm, apices acute, often attenuate, abaxial tips hirsute to hispid. Ray florets 8–16; laminae (usually uniformly yellow to yellow-orange or with a basal maroon splotch, sometimes mostly maroon) elliptic to oblong or oblanceolate, 15–45 × 5–10 mm, abaxially hispid to hirsute. Discs 12–22 × 10–20 mm. Disc florets 250–500+; corollas proximally yellowish green, distally brown-purple, 3–4.2 mm; style branches ca. 1.5 mm, apices subulate. Cypselae 1.5–2.7 mm; pappi 0.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>e North America.</global_distribution><discussion>Some strains of Rudbeckia hirta are cultivated and/or used in seed mixes for “re-naturalization” and erosion control.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals, biennials, or perennials; stems branched at bases or proximal to or at or near mid heights, leafy mostly toward bases (leaves smaller distally); peduncles usually at least 1 / 2 plant heights (Gulf Coastal Plain, Florida to Texas).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems branched mostly at or near mid heights; basal leaves oblanceolate, faces hispid to ± sericeous; Georgia to Texas19a . Rudbeckia hirta var. angustifolia</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems branched at or near bases (plants often scapiform); basal leaves obovate to nearly orbiculate, faces scabrous to hirsute; c, s Florida</statement>
      <determination>19b. Rudbeckia hirta var. floridana</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Biennials or perennials; stems branched mostly beyond mid heights, leafy ± throughout; peduncles to 1 / 3 plant heights.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves: basal blades broadly ovate to broadly elliptic, 2.5–7 cm wide (lengths mostly 2 times widths), margins coarsely toothed; cauline (sometimes sessile) lanceolate, ovate, or pandurate (mostly Appalachian Highlands toIllinois)</statement>
      <determination>19c. Rudbeckia hirta var. hirta</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves: basal blades lanceolate to oblanceolate, 1–2.5(–5) cm wide (lengths 3–5 times widths), margins entire or serrulate; cauline blades spatulate, oblanceolate, or broadly linear</statement>
      <determination>19d. Rudbeckia hirta var. pulcherrima</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
