<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Eupatorieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. M. King &amp; H. Robinson" date="unknown">BRICKELLIASTRUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>24: 63. 1972</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Eupatorieae;genus BRICKELLIASTRUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Generic name Brickellia and Latin - astrum , indicating inferiority or an incomplete resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials or subshrubs, 30–80+ cm (plants not viscid). Stems decumbent to erect, much branched from bases. Leaves cauline; mostly opposite (distal sometimes alternate); petiolate; blades usually 3-nerved, deltate to ovate, margins crenate-dentate, faces pubescent or glabrous, sometimes gland-dotted. Heads discoid, in loose, corymbiform to paniculiform arrays. Involucres ± campanulate, 4–7 mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 20–25 in 3–4 series, 2- or 4-nerved, lance-ovate to lanceolate, unequal (herbaceous to chartaceous). Receptacles convex, epaleate. Florets 25–35; corollas white or yellowish white, throats funnelform (lengths 2.5–4 times diams.); styles: bases not enlarged, glabrous, branches narrowly clavate. Cypselae prismatic, 5(–7)-ribbed, puberulent; pappi readily falling or fragile, of ca. 25 barbellate bristles in 1 series. x = 10.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>404.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>B. L. Turner (1988c, 1994c, 1996+) placed Brickelliastrum, Asanthus, and the Mexican genus Dyscritogyne R. M. King &amp; H. Robinson within Steviopsis R. M. King &amp; H. Robinson. All four are essentially segregates of Brickellia, distinguished especially by their lack of pubescent swellings at bases of stylar shafts. As noted by Turner, this aggregate forms a heterogeneous group; the finer division is followed here until further evidence indicates a better taxonomic disposition.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
