<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>10.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Liatris</genus_name><species_name>elegans</species_name><species_authority>(Walter) Michaux</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 91. 1803</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Pinkscale or elegant gayfeather</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Staehelina</genus_name><species_name>elegans</species_name><species_authority>Walter</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. Carol., </publication_title><place_in_publication>202. 1788</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 30–120 cm. Corms depressed-globose or globose to napiform. Stems puberulent to hirsute-puberulent. Leaves: (basal on relatively distant internodes usually withering before flowering) proximal cauline 1-nerved, narrowly oblanceolate, 60–200(–300) × 3–8 mm, gradually or abruptly reduced distally (becoming slightly to strongly deflexed), essentially glabrous or sparsely puberulent, gland-dotted. Heads in dense, spiciform arrays. Peduncles usually 0, sometimes 1–5(–10) mm. Involucres turbinate-cylindric, 12–20 × 4–6 mm. Phyllaries in 3–4 series, narrowly lanceolate-triangular, unequal, strigose to strigoso-hispid, margins with hyaline borders, apices (at least inner) prolonged, spreading, ± dilated, petaloid (pink, purplish, white, or yellow). Florets 4–5; corolla tubes glabrous inside. Cypselae 3.5–5(–6) mm; pappi: lengths ± equaling corollas, bristles plumose.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>s United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Variety elegans extends across the geographic range of the species; the other three varieties form local enclaves essentially imbedded within var. elegans and sporadically intergrading with it at points of contact (see further comments under 10d. var. kralii).</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary apices petaloid, blue, lavender, magenta, or pink, ± elongate and recurving, petaloid portions short relative to herbaceous bases.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Corms depressed-globose</statement>
      <determination>10a. Liatris elegans var. elegans</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Corms elongate, tapering</statement>
      <determination>10b. Liatris elegans var. carizzana</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary apices petaloid, usually yellowish to creamy white, rarely pale lavender to rose, recurving to slightly flaring or nearly straight, petaloid portions elongate or relatively short relative to bases.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads usually crowded (peduncles 0); phyllary apices creamy white (rarely pale lavender), sometimes initially lemon yellow fading to creamy white, elongate and recurving, petaloid portions short relative to herbaceous bases</statement>
      <determination>10c. Liatris elegans var. bridgesii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Heads well spaced; phyllary apices light yellow or cream (rarely pale lavender), flaring-divergent slightly or not at all, petaloid portions elongate relative to herbaceous bases</statement>
      <determination>10d. Liatris elegans var. kralii</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
