<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>262.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>RATIBIDA</genus_name><genus_authority>Ratibida Rafinesque</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Ludov.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>73. 1817</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Derivation unknown]</etymology><common_name>Prairie coneflower</common_name><common_name>Mexican-hat</common_name><author>Lowell E. Urbatsch</author><author>Patricia B. Cox</author><description>Perennials, 15–120 cm. Stems 1–12+, erect, branched from bases, throughout, or only among heads, strigoso-hirsute, gland-dotted. Leaves basal and cauline; alternate; petiolate (petioles relatively shorter distally); blades lanceolate to ovate or oblanceolate to obovate or oblong, pinnately lobed to 1–2-pinnatifid (lobes usually rounded), ultimate margins entire or serrate, faces usually strigoso-hirsute, usually gland-dotted. Heads radiate, borne singly or in loose, corymbiform arrays. Involucres ± rotate, 8–16 mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 5–15 in 2 series (usually reflexed in fruit, unequal, outer longer). Receptacles subspheric to columnar, paleate (paleae conduplicate, linear to oblong-oblique, chartaceous proximally, herbaceous distally, apices truncate, usually densely strigose and gland-dotted, each margin usually with an adaxial resin gland; receptacles plus paleae and florets = discs, 5–70 × 5–18 mm). Ray florets 3–15+, neuter; corollas yellow, bicolor (maroon/yellow), or wholly maroon. Disc florets 50–400+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellowish green, often purplish distally, tubes shorter than cylindric throats, lobes 5, obovate to triangular (gland-dotted and, sometimes, hairy abaxially). Cypselae (black) strongly compressed, linear-oblanceolate to oblong-oblique, margins (at least abaxial) usually ciliate or pectinate-fimbriate, apices truncate and, often, ciliate, faces glabrous or sparsely hairy; pappi of 1–2 toothlike projections, or coroniform, or 0. x = 16.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 7 (4 in flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico.</global_distribution><references>
    <reference> Jackson, S. W. 1963. Hybridization among three species of Ratibida. Univ. Kansas Sci. Bull. 44: 3–27.</reference>
    <reference> Richards, E. L. 1968. A monograph of the genus Ratibida. Rhodora 70: 348–393.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted; leaves 2-pinnately lobed; peduncles to 6.5 cm (ribs not prominent; heads held just beyond leaves); discs subspheric to ovoid, 5–15 mm; pappi coroniform (of connatescales 0.2–1.5 mm)</statement>
      <determination>4. Ratibida tagetes</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants fibrous rooted or taprooted; leaves 1–2-pinnatifid or -pinnately lobed; peduncles (1.5–)6.5–48+ cm (ribs tan; heads held well beyond leaves); discs columnar, ellipsoid-globular, or ovoid, 10–70 mm; pappi 0, or of 1–2 toothlike projections.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants fibrous rooted; discs ellipsoid to globular or ovoid, 10–25 mm; pappi 0, or of 1–2 toothlike projections</statement>
      <determination>3. Ratibida pinnata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants taprooted; discs columnar, 10–70 mm; pappi usually of 1–2 toothlike projections, sometimes 0.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Style branches ca. 1.8 mm, proximal 1 / 2 stigmatic, apices subulate; cypselae: abaxial margins narrowly winged to fimbriate or pectinate-fimbriate, adaxial margins pectinate-fimbriate</statement>
      <determination>2. Ratibida peduncularis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Style branches 1–2.5 mm, proximal 2 / 3 – 3 / 4 stigmatic, apices rounded; cypselae: abaxial margins glabrous, adaxial margins glabrous or ciliate</statement>
      <determination>1. Ratibida columnifera</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
