<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>417.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>MIKANIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Willdenow</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3: 1742. 1803</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Josef Gottfried Mikan, 1743–1814, professor, University of Prague]</etymology><conserved_name>name conserved</conserved_name><common_name>Climbing hempweed</common_name><author>Walter C. Holmes</author><description>Vines (perennial, sometimes suffrutescent) [non-viney perennials, shrubs], to 300[–1500+] cm. Stems usually twining to scrambling (terete, striate, or [4-] 6-angled, sometimes winged), branched. Leaves cauline; opposite [whorled]; petiolate [sessile]; blades palmately 3[–7]-nerved [pinnately nerved], ± ovate or deltate-ovate to triangular [linear], margins entire or undulate to dentate or toothed to lobed, faces glabrous or puberulent to tomentose, often gland-dotted. Heads discoid, in corymbiform [paniculiform, racemiform, spiciform, thyrsiform] arrays. Involucres ± cylindric, [1–]2–3[–4] mm diam. (usually each subtended by 1 bractlet). Phyllaries persistent, 4 in ± 2 series (outer pair imbricate over inner pair), not notably nerved, lanceolate, linear, or oblong (bases often swollen), ± equal. Receptacles flat (glabrous), epaleate. Florets 4; corollas usually white, sometimes pink to rose or purplish, throats funnelform or campanulate, lobes 5, linear or triangular to deltate; styles: bases slightly, if at all, enlarged, glabrous, branches ± filiform [weakly clavate]. Cypselae ± prismatic, [4–]5[–10]-ribbed, glabrous or puberulent, sometimes gland-dotted; pappi persistent, of [20–]30–60 (white, buff, pinkish, or purplish) barbellulate to barbellate bristles in 1–2 series (distinct or basally connate). x = 16–20.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 450 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>overwhelmingly neotropical (9 species in the Old World tropics)</global_distribution><global_distribution>some temperate North American and South American.</global_distribution><discussion>All species of Mikania in the flora belong to M. sect. Mikania in the sense of W. C. Holmes (1996).</discussion><references>
    <reference> Holmes, W. C. 1981. Mikania (Compositae) of the United States. Sida 9: 147–158.</reference>
    <reference>Holmes, W. C. 1993. The Genus Mikania (Compositae: Eupatorieae) in the Greater Antilles. Fort Worth. [Sida Bot. Misc. 9.] Holmes, W. C. 1996. A proposed sectional classification for Mikania (Eupatorieae). In: D. J. N. Hind et al., eds. 1996. Proceedings of the International Compositae Conference, Kew 1994. 2 vols. Kew. Vol. 1, pp. 621–626.</reference>
    <reference> Robinson, B. L. 1934. Mikania scandens and its near relatives. Contr. Gray Herb. 104: 55–71.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems 6-angled, gray-tomentulose to tomentose; leaf blades ovate to deltate; heads 7–10 mm; phyllaries 6–8 mm; corolla lobes linear; cypselae 3–4 mm</statement>
      <determination>1. Mikania cordifolia</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems terete to obscurely 6-angled, glabrate to densely pilose; leaf blades triangular to triangular-ovate; heads 4–7 mm; phyllaries 3–6 mm; corolla lobes triangular to deltate; cypselae 1.8–2.2 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves (membranous): apices tapering; phyllaries linear-lanceolate, 5–6 mm; corollasusually pinkish to purplish, 3.5–4 mm; e United States</statement>
      <determination>2. Mikania scandens</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves (subcoriaceous to ± fleshy): apices acute to acuminate; phyllaries lanceolate tonarrowly ovate, 3–4 mm; corollas white, ca. 3 mm; s Florida</statement>
      <determination>3. Mikania batatifolia</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
