<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>275.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>WYETHIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Wyethia Nuttall</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>J. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>7: 39, plate 5. 1834</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Nathaniel Jarvis Wyeth, 1802–1856, early western American explorer]</etymology><common_name>Mules-ears</common_name><author>William A. Weber</author><description>Perennials, 15–60(–100) cm (taproots relatively massive; caudices seldom branched). Stems erect (or bending erect from bases), branched mostly from bases. Leaves basal and cauline; alternate; usually petiolate (basal), sometimes sessile; blades (usually pinnately nerved, basal larger than cauline) ± deltate, elliptic-ovate, lanceolate, lance-elliptic, lance-linear, or oblong-ovate, bases truncate to cuneate, margins usually entire, rarely dentate to serrate (sometimes ciliate), faces glabrous or hairy (sometimes gland-dotted or finely stipitate-glandular). Heads radiate, borne singly or 2–5(–8+) in ± corymbiform to racemiform arrays. Involucres hemispheric to campanulate or turbinate, 12–60+ mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 12–36(–48) in 2–3+ series (subequal to unequal, outer sometimes foliaceous, much larger than inner). Receptacles flat to convex, paleate (paleae conduplicate, at least bases, papery). Ray florets 5–25+, pistillate, fertile; corollas mostly yellow (cream to white in W. helianthoides). Disc florets 35–150+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes much shorter than cylindric throats; lobes 5, ± deltate to lanceolate (style branches stigmatic in 2 barely distinct lines, appendages ± filiform). Cypselae ± prismatic, weakly 3–4-angled (faces glabrous or hairy); pappi 0, or persistent, coroniform (usually lacerate) or of 1–4+ ovate to subulate, erose to lacerate (often basally connate) scales. x = 19.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 8 (8 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w North America.</global_distribution><discussion>Some species formerly included in Wyethia are here treated in Agnorhiza and Scabrethia. Balsamorhiza is closely related to Wyethia.</discussion><references>
    <reference> Weber, W. A. 1946. A taxonomic and cytological study of the genus Wyethia, family Compositae, with notes on the related genus Balsamorhiza. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 35: 400–452.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres 35–60+ mm diam.; outer phyllaries (30–)40–80+ mm (± foliaceous, much surpassing discs).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades: faces glabrous or finely stipitate-glandular, sometimes sparsely pilosulous as well (usually shining); cypselae 10–13 mm</statement>
      <determination>1. Wyethia glabra</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades: faces densely tomentose to tomentulose (usually gland-dotted as well), glabrescent; cypselae 12–15 mm</statement>
      <determination>2. Wyethia helenioides</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres 10–30(–40) mm diam.; outer phyllaries 15–30(–40) mm (not foliaceous, seldom surpassing discs).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades: faces tomentose to tomentulose (at least when young, glabrescent, usuallygland-dotted)</statement>
      <determination>3. Wyethia mollis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades: faces glabrous, glabrate, hirsute, hirsutulous, hirtellous, pilose, pilosulous, scabrellous, or strigillose (not tomentose to tomentulose, often gland-dotted or stipitate-glandular).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades: faces glabrous or glabrate (gland-dotted); phyllary margins not ciliate; cypselae glabrous.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves: blades lance-elliptic or oblong-lanceolate to lanceolate; rays 8–21(–25), laminae 25–60 mm; cypselae 8–9 mm</statement>
      <determination>4. Wyethia amplexicaulis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves: blades narrowly oblong-lanceolate to lance-linear; rays 5–8+, lami-nae 18–30 mm; cypselae 6–8 mm</statement>
      <determination>5. Wyethia longicaulis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades: faces usually hirsute, hirsutulous, hirtellous, pilose, pilosulous, scabrellous, or strigillose (sometimes vernicose, rarely finely stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted), sometimes glabrate; phyllary margins ± ciliate; cypselae strigillose or glabrous</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves: blades lanceolate to lance-linear; cypselae 7–8 mm, ± strigillose</statement>
      <determination>6. Wyethia angustifolia</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaves: blades elliptic-ovate, lanceolate, or lance-elliptic; cypselae 9–11 mm, strigillose or glabrous.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries 36–48; rays 13–25, laminae (cream to white) 25–45 mm; cypselae strigillose distally and on margins</statement>
      <determination>7. Wyethia helianthoides</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries 16–34; rays 11–12, laminae (yellow) 25–50 mm; cypselaeglabrous</statement>
      <determination>8. Wyethia arizonica</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
