<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Lessing" date="1831">ecliptinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Gaertner" date="1791">SYNEDRELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fruct. Sem. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 456, plate 171, fig. 7. 1791</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe ecliptinae;genus SYNEDRELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Etymology not clear; perhaps alluding to clustering of heads]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 10–80+ cm. Stems erect or ascending, branched from bases or ± throughout. Leaves cauline; opposite; petiolate; blades (usually 3-nerved) ovate to elliptic, bases cuneate to rounded, margins toothed, faces ± scabrous. Heads radiate, (sessile or subsessile) in axillary glomerules or borne singly. Involucres cylindric to campanulate, 3–6 mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 2–5+ in 1(–2) series (lanceolate, herbaceous to chartaceous). Receptacles convex, paleate (paleae lance-linear, scarious, flat or weakly cupped at bases). Ray florets 2–9+ (in 1–2 series), pistillate, fertile; corollas yellowish. Disc florets 4–12+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellowish, tubes about equaling slightly ampliate, cylindric throats, lobes 4, rounded-deltate. Cypselae dimorphic, strongly obcompressed or flattened, narrowly oval and winged (ray, wings laciniate) or linear-cuneate and not winged (disc); pappi persistent, of 2 triangular scales (ray) or 2–3 subulate scales or awns (disc). x = 20?</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America; also introduced in Asia, Africa, Pacific Islands, Australia.</description>
  <number>287.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
