<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Cassini ex Dumortier" date="1827">helianthinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">helianthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Nuttall" date="1821">petiolaris</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 115. 1821</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe helianthinae;genus helianthus;species petiolaris</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 40–200 cm. Stems erect, usually densely canescent, hispid, or strigillose, rarely ± hirsute or glabrate. Leaves mostly cauline; mostly alternate; petioles 2–4 cm; blades (often bluish green) lanceolate to deltate-ovate or ovate, 4–15 × 1–8 cm, bases subcordate or truncate to cuneate, margins entire or ± serrate, abaxial faces strigose, sparsely to densely, or not at all, gland-dotted. Heads 1–5. Peduncles 4–15(–40) cm. Involucres ± hemispheric, 10–24 mm diam. Phyllaries 14–25, lance-linear to lanceolate to lance-ovate, 10–14 × 1–4(–5) mm, (margins sometimes ciliate) apices short-attenuate, abaxial faces usually hispidulous, rarely sparsely hirsute to glabrate. Paleae 4.5–7.5 mm, 3-toothed, middle teeth ± ciliate or bearded, hairs whitish, 0.5–0.7 mm. Ray florets 10–30; laminae 15–20 mm. Disc florets 50–100+; corollas 4.5–6 mm, lobes usually reddish, rarely yellow; anthers reddish to purplish, appendages purplish (style branches reddish). Cypselae 3–4.5 mm, ± villous; pappi of 2 aristate scales 1.5–3 mm plus 0–2 erose scales 0.3–0.5 mm. 2n = 34.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora): w North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>9.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Prairie sunflower</other_name>
  <discussion>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Helianthus petiolaris is adventive beyond western North America.</discussion>
  <discussion>A third subspecies has yet to be named at that rank in Helianthus petiolaris; it has been called H. petiolaris var. canescens A. Gray. It differs in having stems, leaves, and phyllaries densely canescent and abaxial faces of leaves densely gland-dotted. It is additionally characterized by peduncles usually ebracteate, phyllaries 1–2 mm wide, disc corolla throats gradually narrowed distal to slight, not densely hairy basal bulges, and 2n = 34. It flowers late spring through late summer and grows on sandy soils in open areas at (10–)1000–2300 m in Arizona, California, Nevada, New Mexico, and Texas and in Mexico. It was treated as H. niveus (Bentham) Brandegee subsp. canescens (A. Gray) Heiser by C. B. Heiser et al. (1969); molecular and morphologic data appear to favor a placement within H. petiolaris.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually hispidulous to strigillose; peduncles usually bractless; phyllaries 3–5 mm wide; disc corollas: throats abruptly narrowed distal to densely hairy basal bulbs</description>
      <determination>9a. Helianthus petiolaris subsp. petiolaris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually ± hispid; peduncles usually each with leafy bract subtending head; phyllaries 2–3.5 mm wide; disc corollas: throats gradually narrowed distal to slight, not densely hairy, basal bulges</description>
      <determination>9b. Helianthus petiolaris subsp. fallax</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
