<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Lessing" date="1830">ambrosiinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey &amp; A. Gray in W. H. Emory" date="1859">DICORIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. H. Emory, Rep. U.S. Mex. Bound.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(1): 86, plate 30. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe ambrosiinae;genus DICORIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek di , two, and koris , bug, alluding to the two, “buglike” cypselae of the original species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, perennials, or subshrubs [shrubs], 10–90+ cm. Stems erect, virgately to divaricately branched. Leaves cauline; proximally opposite (first 2–10+ pairs in early growth, Feb–Apr), otherwise alternate; petiolate; blades (3-nerved) lance-linear to lanceolate (proximal) or ± deltate or ovate to elliptic or lanceolate (distal), margins entire or toothed, faces sericeous to strigillose, sometimes with coarser, erect hairs, usually gland-dotted as well. Heads disciform or discoid (then functionally staminate), in (mostly ebracteate) racemiform to paniculiform arrays [borne singly or loosely aggregated in 2s or 3s]. Involucres ± cup-shaped to saucer-shaped, 3–5+ mm diam. Phyllaries persistent (outer) or tardily falling, distinct, outer (4–)5(–7) in 1 series, ± herbaceous, inner 0–4 (each subtending a pistillate floret), scarious to membranous (accrescent, ultimately ovate to elliptic in fruit). Receptacles convex; paleae cuneiform to linear, membranous, ± villous to hispid distally, sometimes wanting. Pistillate florets (0–)1–4; corollas 0. Functionally staminate florets 5–15+; corollas whitish, funnelform, lobes 5, erect, reflexed, or incurved (anthers distinct or weakly coherent). Cypselae strongly obcompressed, often slightly cucullate, ± obovate to elliptic, margins corky-winged, irregularly toothed, faces smooth or warty, sometimes gland-dotted; pappi 0 (cypselae often each with apical tuft of white hairs). x = 18.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America, nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>248.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Traits that have been used to distinguish species and/or infraspecific taxa of dicorias in the flora (presence/absence of erect hairs on stems, shape, size, and toothing of distal leaves, size of cypselae, and relative development of inner phyllaries; A. Cronquist 1994) vary and combine so capriciously that I find no justification for recognition of more than a single, polymorphic species in the flora area.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
