<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Justin W. Allison</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Lessing" date="1830">coreopsidinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cavanilles" date="1795">HETEROSPERMA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Icon.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 34. 1795</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe coreopsidinae;genus HETEROSPERMA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek, heteros , differing, and sperma , seed; probably alluding to the contrasting outer and inner cypselae]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 10–40(–70+) cm (taprooted). Stems 1 (bases relatively thick), ascending to erect, branched distally or ± throughout (striate). Leaves mostly cauline; opposite; obscurely petiolate or sessile; blades mostly pinnately lobed [undivided] (lobes 3–5, usually linear to filiform, sometimes lanceolate), ultimate margins usually entire, sometimes denticulate (often ciliate, at least proximally, apices acute), faces glabrous [hairy]. Heads radiate, borne singly or in loose, cymiform arrays. Calyculi of (1–)3–5+ erect, narrowly spatulate or linear to filiform, herbaceous bractlets (often surpassing phyllaries, margins usually hispid-ciliate). Involucres cylindric to obconic, 2–5 mm diam. (larger in fruit). Phyllaries 3–5+ in ± 2 series, distinct, erect, mostly oblong or ovate, equal, membranous. Receptacles concave to flat, paleate; paleae similar to phyllaries, oblong or oval to lanceolate or linear (± embracing cypselae, ± hyaline with brown striae, apices obtuse, apiculate). Ray florets 1–3[–8], pistillate, fertile; corollas pale yellow [orange]. Disc florets 3–10[–20+], bisexual, fertile; corollas ± yellow (at least distally), tubes shorter than funnelform throats, lobes 5, deltate. Cypselae (± dimorphic) outer obcompressed, ellipsoid or obovoid, winged (wings ± corky, often cucullate and/or pectinate), faces often corky-tuberculate, glabrous, inner ± obovoid, usually some (innermost) tapered to ± barbellate beaks; pappi 0, or persistent or tardily falling, of (1–)2–3 spreading to reflexed, retrorsely barbellate awns. x = 25.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States, Mexico, Central America, South America; introduced in West Indies.</description>
  <number>313.</number>
  <discussion>Species 5–10 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
