<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Calycadenia</genus_name><species_name>truncata</species_name><species_authority>de Candolle</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5: 695. 1836</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Calycadenia</genus_name><species_name>truncata</species_name><subspecies_name>scabrella</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Drew) D. D. Keck</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 20–120 cm (sometimes robust); self-incompatible (herbage glaucescent, acrid-scented). Stems (usually reddish) usually branched (branches 1–15+, remote, arcuate-ascending, slender, arising mostly distal to midpoints of main stems), glabrous or ± scabrous distally. Leaves mostly alternate, 2–10 cm (at least proximal), hispidulous to hispid and± long-hairy (at least margins and adaxial faces), sometimes with tack-glands. Heads in spiciform arrays (usually l–3 per node). Peduncular bracts ± narrowly elliptic, 1–12 mm (± glabrous or hispidulous to hispid, sometimes ± bristly and/or pectinate-fimbriate), apices ± truncate, tack-glands (0–) 1 (terminal). Phyllaries 5–10 mm, abaxial faces glabrous or sparsely strigose and/or long-straight-hairy, especially distally, shaggy-long hairy on distal margins, tack-glands usually 0. Paleae 5–10 mm (tack-glands 0). Ray florets 3–6; corollas yellow, tubes ca. 2.5 mm, ± papillate, throats sometimes with red “eyes,” laminae (4–)5–12 mm (central lobes smaller than laterals, symmetric, widest at bases, laterals asymmetric, sinuses less than 1/3 laminae). Disc florets 3–25 (ovaries often sterile or of low fertility); corollas yellow, 4–6 mm (sometimes papillate distally, lobes± hirsute; anthers yellow, light brown, or dark purple). Ray cypselae ca. 3 mm, rough-wrinkled, glabrous. Disc cypselae 2–4 mm, glabrous or ± appressed-hairy; pappi 0 or of 7–12 oblong, fimbriate scales, to 1 mm. 2n = 14.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><phenology>nov</phenology><habitat>dry, open hillsides</habitat><habitat>rocky ridges</habitat><habitat>talus</habitat><elevation>50–1500 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><discussion>Calycadenia truncata is the most widespread of all of the taxa. It ranges from Jackson and Josephine counties in southwestern Oregon [reported by D. D. Keck (1960b) from Douglas County] in the Coast Range to San Luis Obispo County, California, and in the Sierra Nevada foothills south to Fresno County. It is also localized in sites in the Sacramento Valley.</discussion></treatment>
