<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority=")" date="unknown">Heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Bentham &amp; Hooker f." date="unknown">Madiinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Calycadenia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">pauciflora</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. H. Emory, Rep. U.S. Mex. Bound.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(1): 100. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Heliantheae;subtribe Madiinae;genus Calycadenia;species pauciflora;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>10.</number>
  <discussion>Calycadenia pauciflora is variable and closely related to and intergrades with C. fremontii. It is found mostly in the foothills of the Coast Ranges from Tehama County to Lake, Napa, and Yolo counties. It is also known from one location on the valley floor in Butte County.</discussion>
  <discussion>The morphologic and chromosomal similarity of some populations of Calycadenia ciliosa to C. fremontii led R. L. Carr and G. D. Carr (1983) to merge the two species. Traditional treatments of these taxa and C. pauciflora have placed together populations that are far from homogeneous and may vary from one another in morphology and chromosome number and structure. For instance, C. fremontii and C. pauciflora are each known to include at least six different chromosome races. In this treatment, we have chosen to recognize the larger-headed members of C. pauciflora in the sense of G. D. Carr (1975) as C. fremontii. This reflects the current state of our knowledge, including molecular studies (B. G. Baldwin and S. Markos 1998). Molecular studies have provided a separate means of assessing relationships and insights into the evolution of the genus. Providing a practical taxonomic framework that reflects what is now known about the complicated morphologic and chromosomal patterns of variation of C. pauciflora and C. fremontii has proved to be an elusive goal.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
