<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Bruce G. Baldwin,John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority=")" date="unknown">Heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Bentham &amp; Hooker f." date="unknown">Madiinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Greene" date="unknown">HOLOZONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9: 122. 1882</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Heliantheae;subtribe Madiinae;genus HOLOZONIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek holos , whole or entire, and zona , belt or girdle; alluding to each phyllary fully (or mostly) investing a ray ovary (cypsela), in contrast to the half-invested cypselae of Hemizonia ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, 30–150 cm (rhizomatous). Stems (aerial) ± erect. Leaves mostly cauline; proximal opposite (basally connate), distal alternate; sessile; blades lanceolate to linear, margins entire, faces hirsute and (distal leaves) glandular-hirtellous (glands cup-shaped). Heads radiate, borne singly or in loose, corymbiform arrays (peduncles filiform). Peduncular bracts: pit-glands, tack-glands, and/or spines 0. Involucres ± obconic or turbinate, 2–4+ mm diam. Receptacles flat to convex, glabrous or setulose, paleate (paleae falling, in 1 series between rays and discs, connate). Phyllaries 4–10 in 1 series (each mostly or wholly enveloping a ray ovary, ± lance-linear, herbaceous, abaxially hirsute, sometimes glandular-hirtellous, glands cup-shaped). Ray florets 4–10, pistillate, fertile; corollas whitish (abaxially purplish-veined). Disc florets 9–28, functionally staminate; corollas white (pubescent), tubes shorter than funnelform throats, lobes 5, deltate (anthers ± dark purple; styles glabrous proximal to branches). Cypselae (black) obcompressed, ± clavate (basal attachments centered, apices beakless, areolae broadly cupulate, faces glabrous); pappi (rays) 0 or coroniform (0.1–0.3 mm), or (discs) 0 or (readily falling) of 1–5 subulate scales. x = 14.</description>
  <description type="distribution">California.</description>
  <number>343.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Holozonia has been treated as congeneric with Hemizonia and with Lagophylla. Like Lagophylla, Holozonia has functionally staminate disc florets, cup-shaped glands, and obcompressed cypselae, each completely or mostly invested by a phyllary. Additional morphologic considerations and biosystematic studies led W. C. Thompson (1983) to reject the hypothesis of a close relationship between Holozonia and Lagophylla. Molecular phylogenetic data are in keeping with a closer relationship of Holozonia to other continental tarweeds with white corollas and x = 14 (i.e., Blepharizonia and Hemizonia), than to Lagophylla (S. Carlquist et al. 2003).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Thompson, W. C. 1983. A Biosystematic Study of Lagophylla (Compositae: Heliantheae) and Related Taxa. Ph.D. dissertation. University of California, Davis.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
