<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Rydberg in N. L. Britton et al." date="1914">Hymenopappinae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in N. L. Britton et al., N. Amer. Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>34: 43. 1914</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe Hymenopappinae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or perennials, (5–)20–150 cm. Leaves mostly basal or basal and cauline; alternate; petiolate or sessile; blades deltate to lanceolate overall, usually 1–2-pinnately or palmati-pinnately lobed, lobes usually filiform, ultimate margins entire or toothed, faces glabrous or hairy, often tomentose, usually gland-dotted. Heads usually discoid, rarely radiate, usually in ± corymbiform arrays. Calyculi 0. Involucres obconic to hemispheric. Phyllaries persistent or tardily falling, 5–13+ in 2+ series (distinct, often yellowish, whitish, or purplish, orbiculate to lance-linear, subequal, often ± petaloid, margins usually notably membranous or scarious). Receptacles flat or convex, usually epaleate (paleae scarious, conduplicate, each ± investing subtended floret in H. newberryi). Ray florets usually 0, sometimes 8, pistillate, fertile; corollas white or whitish. Disc florets 12–70+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow or whitish to purplish, tubes longer than or about equaling funnelform or abruptly dilated, campanulate throats, lobes 5, ± deltate (reflexed at anthesis); anther thecae pale; stigmatic papillae in 2 lines. Cypselae obconic to obpyramidal, usually 4-angled and 12–16-ribbed, glabrous or hairy; pappi 0 or of 12–22 orbiculate to spatulate scales.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico.</description>
  <number>187m.19.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">Hymenopappanae</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 5, species 28 (1 genus, 10 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>H. Robinson (1981) suggested that Hymenopappinae is related to Gaillardiinae and other “core” groups of traditional Helenieae.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
