<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>354c.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Lasthenia</genus_name><genus_authority>Cassini</genus_authority><section_name>Hologymne</section_name><section_authority>(Bartling) Nuttall</section_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Trans. Amer. Philos. Soc., n. s.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>7: 383. 1841</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><section_name>Hologymne</section_name><section_authority>Bartling</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Index Seminum (Göttingen) </publication_title><place_in_publication>1837: 4. 1837</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><section_name>Crockeria</section_name><section_authority>Greene ex A. Gray</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Annuals. Leaves entire (blades ± fleshy, bases sometimes connate and sheathing). Involucres hemispheric. Phyllaries persistent, connate 2/3+ their lengths (forming cups, glabrous but for distinct apices). Receptacles ± conic, papillate or warty, glabrous or sparsely hairy. Ray corollas yellow, laminae 4–14 mm, floral pigments remaining yellow in dilute aqueous alkali. Disc corolla lobes 5; anther appendages deltate or broadly ovate; style apices deltate with apical tufts of hairs and subapical fringes of shorter hairs. Cypselae 2–3.5 mm; epappose. 2n = 14.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><us_distribution>California.</us_distribution><discussion>Members of sect. Hologymne have a high salt tolerance and usually occur in moderately to strongly alkaline habitats, such as coastal salt marshes, around vernal pools, and in wet areas around alkali flats (i.e., hard-packed, poorly aerated, saline clays). The herbage of these plants also becomes succulent in response to increasing soil salinity as the soil dries up. All three species show a narrow range of morphologic characteristics except for their variable cypselae.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae black, strongly flattened, obovoid, margins ciliate (hairs stiff, blunt), faces glabrous or scabrous</statement>
      <determination>7. Lasthenia chrysantha</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae black, ± flattened and obovate to oblong, or gray, ± clavate or obovoid, margins sometimes ciliate, faces glabrous or hairy (sometimes papillate).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae ± flattened and obovate to oblong, to 2.5 mm, faces ± hairy (hairs curved) and papillate</statement>
      <determination>8. Lasthenia ferrisiae</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cypselae ± clavate or obovoid, to 3.5 mm, faces glabrous or hairy and papillate (papil-lae rusty or yellowish, wartlike)</statement>
      <determination>9. Lasthenia glabrata</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
