<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>354e.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Lasthenia</genus_name><genus_authority>Cassini</genus_authority><section_name>Ornduffia</section_name><section_authority>R. Chan</section_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>48: 38. 2001</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Annuals. Leaves usually pinnatifid, sometimes entire. Involucres hemispheric or obconic. Phyllaries persistent, usually distinct (connate 1/4–1/2 their lengths in L. conjugens). Receptacles conic or dome-shaped, glabrous or hairy. Ray corollas yellow, laminae 5–10 mm, floral pigments remaining yellow in dilute aqueous alkali. Disc corolla lobes 5; anther appendices linear, obovate, or ovate (style apices deltate with apical tufts of hairs and subapical fringes of shorter hairs). Cypselae to 1.5 mm; epappose or pappose. 2n = 12.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><us_distribution>California.</us_distribution><discussion>Members of sect. Ornduffia are morphologically similar; they can be distinguished by pappus and phyllary differences. They are typically found in vernal pools; the plants may start growing as submerged aquatics and flower as succulent xerophytes. Leaves of this section are usually pinnatifid; undivided leaves are sometimes produced in crowded conditions with poor light.</discussion><discussion>R. Ornduff (1966b) originally included the three members of Lasthenia sect. Ornduffia in sect. Ptilomeris. Molecular studies (R. Chan 2000) showed that the three species form a distinct, monophyletic group.</discussion><references>
    <reference> Crawford, D. J. and R. Ornduff. 1989. Enzyme electrophoresis and evolutionary relationships among three species of Lasthenia (Asteraceae: Heliantheae). Amer. J. Bot. 76: 289–296.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries 12–18 (connate 1 / 4 – 1 / 2 their lengths)</statement>
      <determination>12. Lasthenia conjugens</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries 7–16 (distinct).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi usually of 1(–2) aristate scales plus 3–6+ shorter, ± subulate scales</statement>
      <determination>11. Lasthenia burke</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pappi usually of (3–)4(–5) subulate, aristate scales plus 3–5+ shorter, ± subulate scalesor teeth, rarely of aristate scales only or 0</statement>
      <determination>13. Lasthenia fremontii</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
