<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Bruce G. Baldwin,John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Bentham &amp; Hooker f." date="unknown">baeriinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="B. G. Baldwin" date="2000">CONSTANCEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>46: 159. 2000</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe baeriinae;genus CONSTANCEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Lincoln Constance, 1909–2001, Californian botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, 50–150(–200) cm. Stems decumbent to ± erect, branched from bases or throughout (densely white-tomentose to glabrate). Leaves cauline; alternate; petiolate; blades broadly ovate, 1–2-pinnately lobed (lobes oblong or oblanceolate to linear), ultimate margins entire (somewhat revolute, apices ± rounded), faces white-tomentose (adaxial often glabrescent). Heads radiate, (50–100+) in corymbiform or paniculiform arrays. Involucres cylindric to campanulate, 3–5 mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 8–16 in ± 2 series (± erect in fruit, distinct, oblong to linear, ± herbaceous, ± keeled). Receptacles flat to convex, shallowly pitted, glabrous, epaleate. Ray florets 4–9, pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow. Disc florets 10–25+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes shorter than campanulate or narrowly funnelform throats, lobes 5, deltate. Cypselae (blackish, dull) obpyramidal to clavate, ± scabrellous to glabrate; pappi persistent, of 2–6+ unequal (or 2 opposite, longer, and ± equal), basally connate, oblong to subulate scales (tips acute to erose). x = 19.</description>
  <description type="distribution">California.</description>
  <number>360.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Recognition of Constancea is based on morphologic, cytologic, and molecular evidence for polyphyly of Eriophyllum if E. nevinii is included. Constancea has characteristics found in other, closely related x = 19 “helenioid” genera that are unusual or absent in the clade represented by Eriophyllum, Pseudobahia, and Syntrichopappus, such as leaves with well-developed petioles, phyllaries in more than one series and more than the number of ray florets, and pappus scales unequal or a longer pair opposite and ± equal. The previously suggested close relationship between Constancea and another coastal subshrub, E. staechadifolium, is untenable.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
