<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>367.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>SCHKUHRIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Roth</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Catal. Bot.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 116. 1797</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Christian Schkuhr, 1741–1811, German botanist]</etymology><conserved_name>name conserved</conserved_name><author>John L. Strother</author><description>Annuals, 5–50+ cm. Stems erect, simple or branched (usually distally). Leaves mostly cauline; mostly opposite (distal sometimes alternate); petiolate or sessile; blades linear to filiform or 1–2-pinnately lobed (lobes 3–7+, linear to filiform), ultimate margins entire, faces sparsely hairy (hairs bulbous, conic, or fusiform, 0.1–0.3 mm), glabrescent, usually gland-dotted. Heads radiate or discoid, usually in loose, corymbiform to paniculiform arrays. Involucres obconic-obpyramidal to ± turbinate or hemispheric, 3–6 mm diam. (subtended by 0–3 bractlets). Phyllaries persistent, 4–6+ in 1–2 series (spreading or reflexed in fruit, distinct, obovate to oblanceolate, subequal, thin-herbaceous to membranous, margins membranous, often purplish or yellowish). Receptacles convex, pitted, epaleate. Ray florets 0 or 1–2, pistillate, fertile; corollas yellow or white. Disc florets 2–8(–30+), bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow to yellowish, sometimes red-tipped (± stipitate-glandular), tubes shorter than or about equaling campanulate to funnelform throats, lobes 5, deltate. Cypselae narrowly obpyramidal, 4-angled, finely nerved, ± hirsutulous to villous (at least at bases and/or on angles); pappi persistent, of 8+ spatulate to lanceolate (basally and/or medially thickened, distally and/or laterally scarious) scales (all, some, none, or the alternate ones ± aristate). x = 11.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 or perhaps more (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>sw United States</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution>South America.</global_distribution><discussion>According to B. G. Baldwin et al. (2002), among others, Schkuhria is closely related to Achyropappus Kunth and to Bahia.</discussion><references>
    <reference> Heiser, C. B. 1945. A revision of the genus Schkuhria. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 32: 265–278.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries ± hirsutulous and gland-dotted; ray florets 0; disc florets 15–30</statement>
      <determination>1. Schkuhria multiflora</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries gland-dotted, otherwise usually glabrous; ray florets usually 1–2, sometimes 0; disc florets 2–6(–8+)</statement>
      <determination>2. Schkuhria pinnata</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
