<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Craig C. Freeman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Meisner" date="unknown">MUEHLENBECKIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pl. Vasc. Gen.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 316</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>2: 227. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus MUEHLENBECKIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for H. G. Muehlenbeck, 1798–1845, Swiss physician]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, vinelike, perennial; rhizomatous. Stems suberect, prostrate, or scandent,
    glabrous or puberulent, sometimes papillose. Leaves deciduous, cauline, alternate, usually
    petiolate; ocrea usually deciduous, sometimes persistent, chartaceous; petiole base articulated,
    extrafloral nectaries present; blade linear to orbiculate, panduriform, or
    triangular-lanceolate, margins entire or irregularly wavy. Inflorescences terminal and axillary,
    spikelike, essentially not pedunculate. Pedicels prescent. Flowers bisexual and unisexual, with
    staminate, pistillate, or sometimes both sexes occurring with bisexual flowers on the same
    plant, 1–2(–5) per ocreate fascicle, base stipelike; perianth accrescent, white to greenish
    white, campanulate, glabrous; tepals 5, connate proximally, sepaloid, dimorphic, outer slightly
    larger than inner. Staminate flowers: stamens 8 (9); filaments distinct, adnate to base of
    perianth tube, glabrous; anthers yellow or pink to purple, ovate to elliptic; pistil
    rudimentary. Pistillate flowers: tube white or reddish purple to black in fruit, becoming
    fleshy; stamens rudimentary; styles 3, spreading, connate proximally; stigmas fimbriate. Achenes
    completely or partly included in fleshy perianth, black or dark brown, unwinged, 3-gonous to
    subglobose, glabrous. Seeds: embryo straight. x = 10.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (New Zealand)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 23 (2 in the flora): introduced; Central America, South America, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 23 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; Central America, South America, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>23.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Wirevine</other_name>
  <discussion>species 23 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Brandbyge, J. 1992. The genus Muehlenbeckia (Polygonaceae) in South and Central
      America. Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 114: 349–416.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubes of pistillate flowers white in fruit; distal branches of stems
        brownish-puberulent; leaf blades ovate-oblong to suborbiculate or panduriform</description>
      <determination>1. Muehlenbeckia complexa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubes of pistillate flowers reddish purple to black in fruit; distal branches of
        stems glabrous; leaf blades triangular-lanceolate</description>
      <determination>2. Muehlenbeckia hastulata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
