<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26c.1.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Rumex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <subgenus_name>Rumex</subgenus_name>
    <section_name>Axillares</section_name>
    <section_authority>Rechinger f.</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Publ. Field Mus. Nat. Hist., Bot. Ser.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 6. 1937</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants not developing basal rosette of leaves, sometimes with long-creeping rhizomes.
    Stems erect, ascending, procumbent, or decumbent, normally with regular, leafy axillary shoots
    that tend to develop 2d-order axillary inflorescences (often overtopping 1st-order ones). Leaf
    blades mostly lanceolate, elliptic, ovate-lanceolate, or ovate-elliptic, base cuneate, or in
    some species broadly cuneate, rounded, truncate-cuneate, or indistinctly cordate. Inner tepals
    with margins entire, rarely minutely erose-denticulate.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 40 (21) in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>South America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Pacific Islands (Hawaii).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>North american representatives of this section (except Rumex venosus, a distinctive
    species) form a polymorphic complex consisting of often interfertile races (N. M. Sarkar 1958).
    In most cases those races are separated morphologically and restricted geographically. They may
    be arranged into at least three aggregates (groups) that approximate the subsections described
    by K. H. Rechinger (1937): R. verticillatus aggr. (subsect. Verticillati Rechinger f.), R.
    altissimus aggr. (subsect. Salicifolii Rechinger f., in part), and R. salicifolius aggr.
    (subsect. Salicifolii, in part). In case of difficulty with identification, inevitable with
    immature or intermediate specimens, determination to the aggregate level is recommended. Those
    preferring more broadly circumscribed species may use existing infrageneric combinations (see J.
    C. Hickman 1984). Attempts have been made to submerge various “microspecies” (especially in the
    R. salicifolius group) into more broadly circumscribed taxa, usually R. salicifolius and R.
    mexicanus, and various combinations at subspecific and varietal ranks have been proposed (see
    Hickman). In my opinion, results of this approach are inconsistent (e.g., some taxa are treated
    as varieties while others, not less distinct, are accepted as species or subspecies) and in most
    cases less convincing than the original treatment by Rechinger and the thorough study by Sarkar.
    I agree with Sarkar (p. 993) that “any drastic taxonomic revision of the species of the
    Axillares section of Rumex should be postponed until more complete cytogenetic data have
    accumulated concerning the interrelationships of all the taxa in this section.”</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Sarkar, N. M. 1958. Cytotaxonomic studies on Rumex sect.
      Axillares. Canad. J. Bot. 36: 947–996.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>
