<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>16.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Rumex</genus_name><species_name>ellipticus</species_name><species_authority>Greene</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4: 234. 1901</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Elliptic tall dock</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Rumex</genus_name><species_name>altissimus</species_name><species_authority>Alph. Wood</species_authority><subspecies_name>ellipticus</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Greene) Á. Löve</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, glabrous, with vertical rootstock. Stems ascending or decumbent, usually producing axillary shoots below 1st-order inflorescence or at proximal nodes, 40–70 cm. Leaf blades lanceolate or broadly lanceolate, 5–10(–15) × 2–3(–4) cm, usually ca. 3–4 times as long as wide, widest in proximal 1/2, rarely near middle, thick, often subcoriaceous, base cuneate, margins entire, flat, apex acute or attenuate. Inflorescences terminal and axillary, terminal usually occupying distal 1/5–1/3 of stem, rather dense or interrupted in proximal 1/2, usually narrowly paniculate (branches simple and comparatively short). Pedicels articulated in proximal 1/2 almost near base, thickish, 3–6(–7) mm, usually approximately as long as or slightly shorter than inner tepals, articulation indistinctly swollen. Flowers 12–20 in whorls; inner tepals ovate or cordate-triangular, occasionally almost orbiculate, 5–6 × 4–5 mm, base truncate or indistinctly cordate, margins entire, apex obtuse or subacute; tubercles absent or 1 inner tepal with indistinctly swollen midvein. Achenes brown, 2.7–3.2 × 1.8–2.5 mm. 2n = 20.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>sandy, gravelly, and muddy shores of rivers and streams</habitat><elevation>10–1000 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution><discussion>Rumex ellipticus is closely related to R. altissimus and is sometimes regarded as a subspecies of it (Á. Löve 1986).</discussion></treatment>
