<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>28.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Rumex</genus_name><species_name>subarcticus</species_name><species_authority>Lepage</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Naturaliste Canad.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>82: 191. 1955</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Subarctic or subarctic willow dock</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Rumex</genus_name><species_name>pallidus</species_name><species_authority>Bigelow</species_authority><subspecies_name>subarcticus</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Lepage) Á. Löve</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, glabrous, with vertical rootstock. Stems usually procumbent, rarely ascending, usually producing axillary shoots below 1st-order inflorescence or at proximal nodes, 30–60 cm. Leaf blades narrowly linear-lanceolate, 6–17 × 1–3 cm, usually ca. 7–10 times as long as wide, widest near middle, usually thick, not coriaceous or subcoriaceous, base cuneate, margins entire, usually strongly undulate and/or crenulate, apex acute. Inflorescences terminal and axillary, terminal usually occupying distal 1/5–1/3 of stem, rather dense towards apex, distinctly interrupted in proximal 1/2, usually broadly paniculate (branches almost at right angles to main axis, simple or with few 2d-order branches). Pedicels articulated in proximal 1/3, filiform, 4–7 mm, not more than 2–2.5 times as long as inner tepals, articulation slightly swollen. Flowers 10–20 in whorls; inner tepals, broadly deltoid or deltoid-ovate, 3–4 × 3.2–4(–4.5) mm, base truncate, margins entire or indistinctly crenulate, apex obtuse or subacute; tubercles absent, rarely small and indistinct. Achenes brown or dark reddish brown, 2–3 × 1.5–2 mm. 2n = 20.</description><phenology>early summer</phenology><habitat>mostly coastal and alluvial habitats: sea beaches</habitat><habitat>shores of rivers and streams</habitat><habitat>wet meadows</habitat><elevation>0–200 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>Nunavut.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution><discussion>Some specimens of Rumex subarcticus have well-developed tubercles similar to those of R. pallidus (N. M. Sarkar 1958), to which it is closely related and of which it may be regarded as a northwestern subspecies or variety (see Á. Löve 1986).</discussion></treatment>
