<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>36.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Rumex</genus_name><species_name>alpinus</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 334. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><conserved_name>name proposed for conservation</conserved_name><common_name>Monk’s-rhubarb</common_name><common_name>butter or Alpine dock</common_name><description>Plants perennial, glabrous or minutely papillose-pubescent, with stout, creeping rhizome. Stems erect, branched above middle, 60–100 cm. Leaves: ocrea mostly deciduous or sometimes partially persistent at maturity; blade usually ovate-orbiculate, sometimes orbiculate or broadly ovate, 20–40 × 20–35 cm, base deeply and widely cordate, margins entire, flat or slightly undulate, apex obtuse. Inflorescences terminal, occupying distal 1/2 of stem, rather dense, widely paniculate to fusiform. Pedicels articulated at middle or in proximal 1/3, filiform, 3–9 mm, articulation distinctly swollen. Flowers 10–20 in whorls; inner tepals ovate or ovate-triangular, 4–5(–6) × 3–5 mm, base truncate or slightly cordate, margins entire or subentire, apex obtuse or subobtuse; tubercles absent. Achenes brown to brownish green, 2.5–3.5 × 1–2 mm. 2n = 20.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>waste places: roadsides</habitat><habitat>old fields and gardens</habitat><habitat>disturbed meadows</habitat><elevation>0–1500 m;</elevation><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>N.S</global_distribution><us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution><us_distribution>Vt.</us_distribution><global_distribution>c</global_distribution><global_distribution>s Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution>w Asia.</global_distribution><discussion>Rumex alpinus belongs to subsect. Alpini Rechinger f. The name R. alpinus has been proposed for nomenclatural conservation (S. Cafferty and S. Snogerup 2000).</discussion><discussion>This species was first reported from North America in Nova Scotia (M. L. Fernald 1921; K. H. Rechinger 1937). It remains uncommon in the United States and Canada. Rumex alpinus never has been reported as being a serious invasive weed; however, it may persist at a site for a very long time. Previously, the species was culti-vated widely, mostly for medicinal and veterinary purposes.</discussion></treatment>
