<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>27.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>OXYRIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Hill</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Veg. Syst.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>10: 24, plate 24, fig. 2. 1765</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek oxys , sour, and -aria , possession, alluding to acidic leaves]</etymology><common_name>Mountain-sorrel</common_name><common_name>oxyrie</common_name><author>Craig C. Freeman</author><author>John G. Packer</author><description>Herbs, perennial; roots fibrous; rhizomes present or not. Stems erect, glabrous. Leaves deciduous, basal, rarely also cauline, alternate, petiolate; ocrea sometimes deciduous, chartaceous; blade reniform to orbiculate-cordate, margins entire to obscurely wavy. Inflorescences terminal, paniclelike or racemelike, pedunculate. Pedicels present. Flowers bisexual, (1–)3–7 per ocreate fascicle, base stipelike; perianth nonaccrescent, greenish to reddish brown, campanulate, glabrous; tepals 4, in 2 whorls of 2, distinct, sepaloid, dimorphic, outer 2 narrower than inner 2; stamens (2–)6; filaments distinct, free, glabrous; anthers white to red or deep purple, elliptic to ovate; styles 2, spreading, distinct; stigmas penicillate. Achenes exserted, yellowish to tan, winged, lenticular, glabrous. Seeds: embryo straight or curved. x = 7.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 4 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>arctic and alpine</global_distribution><global_distribution>n</global_distribution><global_distribution>w North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution>e Asia.</global_distribution><references>
    <reference>Chrtek, J. and M. Šourková. 1992. Variation in Oxyria digyna. Preslia 64: 207–210.</reference>
    <reference>Mooney, H. A. and W. D. Billings. 1961. Comparative physiological ecology of arctic and alpine populations of Oxyria digyna. Ecol. Monogr. 31: 1–29.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
