<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>6.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Polygonum</genus_name><species_name>glaucum</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 254. 1818</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Seabeach knotweed</common_name><description>Plants silvery, homophyllous. Stems prostrate to ascending, branched from base, not wiry, 20–70 cm. Leaves: ocrea persistent, 7–15 mm, proximal part cylin-dric, pruinose, distal parts silvery, margins overlapping, entire or lacerate; petiole 0.5–3 mm; blade bluish green, lanceolate, 10–30 × 2–8 mm, coriaceous, margins revolute, apex obtuse or acute, rugulose when fresh, markedly rugulose when dried, glaucous; middle stem leaves slightly larger than adjacent branch leaves, distal leaves overtopping flowers they subtend. Inflorescences axillary; cymes uniformly distributed, 1–3-flowered. Pedicels enclosed in ocreae, 3–5 mm. Flowers semi-open; perianth (2–)3–4 mm; tube 12–26% of perianth length; tepals ± recurved, overlapping, white, margins white or pink, petaloid, not keeled, oblong-obovate to spatulate, not cucullate; midvein usually unbranched; stamens 8. Achenes exserted from perianth, reddish brown to dark brown, ovate, 3-gonous, 2.5–3(–4) mm, faces subequal, apex not beaked, edges straight, shiny, smooth; late-season achenes common, 3–5 mm. 2n = 40.</description><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><phenology>nov</phenology><habitat>coastal beaches</habitat><habitat>sand dunes</habitat><habitat>margins of salt ponds</habitat><elevation>0–10 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Conn.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Del.</us_distribution><us_distribution>D.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mass.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.J.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution>R.I.</us_distribution><us_distribution>S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution><discussion>Polygonum glaucum is restricted to maritime beaches along the Atlantic coast from Massachusetts south to Georgia. Over most of its range it is rare and declining; populations on coastal islands of Massachusetts and along the shore of Long Island appear to be secure. Seabeach knotweed appears to be related to P. oxyspermum.</discussion></treatment>
