<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">polygonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Small" date="1893">sawatchense</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20: 213, plate 156. 1893</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus polygonum;species sawatchense</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs. Stems erect, green to brownish, simple or branched from base, not wiry, 4–50 cm, glabrous or papillose-scabrid-ulous. Leaves uniformly distrib-uted, articulated to ocreae, basal leaves persistent or caducous, distal leaves abruptly or gradually reduced to bracts; ocrea 4–10 mm, glabrous or papillose-scabridulous, proximal part cylindric, distal part lacerate or disintegrating into a few persistent fibers; petiole 0.1–2 mm; blade 1-veined, not pleated, linear or narrowly oblong to oblanceolate, 8–45 × 2–8(–12) mm, margins revolute or flat, smooth or papillose-denticulate, apex acute, mucronate, rarely obtuse. Inflorescences axillary or axillary and terminal, spikelike, elongate; cymes widely spaced along branches, 2–4-flowered. Pedicels enclosed in or exserted from ocreae, erect, 1–4 mm. Flowers closed or at least some open; perianth (2.5–)4 mm; tube 20–40% of perianth length; tepals overlapping, greenish or reddish, sometimes flushed with purple, with white or pink margins, sepaloid or petaloid, oblong or oblong-elliptic, cucullate, navicular, apex rounded; midveins unbranched or with few branches at base; stamens 3–8. Achenes enclosed in perianth, black, elliptic or ovate, 2.5–3.3 mm, faces subequal, shiny, smooth.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <number>25.</number>
  <discussion>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and ocreae glabrous; leaf blades linear-lanceolate to narrowly oblong or oblanceolate, margins smooth; flowers closed</description>
      <determination>25a. Polygonum sawatchense subsp. sawatchense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and ocreae papillose-scabridulous; leaf blades elliptic or oblong-elliptic, margins papillose-denticulate; at least some flowers open</description>
      <determination>25b. Polygonum sawatchense subsp. oblivium</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
