<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Alan R. Smith</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">plumbaginaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">PLUMBAGO</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 151. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 75. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family plumbaginaceae;genus PLUMBAGO</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin plumbago , a leadlike ore, alluding to historical use as a cure for lead
    poisoning]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial shrubs or suffrutescent herbs; roots not known. Stems erect,
    prostrate, or climbing, ribbed. Leaves cauline, sessile or short-petiolate (petiole usually less
    than 1.5 cm); blade elliptic to oblanceolate or spatulate, base narrowed, margins entire, apex
    acute, acuminate, or obtuse, membranaceous. Inflorescences terminal or axillary spikelike
    racemes or panicles. Pedicels 2-bracteolate, short. Flowers sometimes heterostylous,
    short-pedicellate; bracts absent; calyx persistent, 5-ribbed, tubular, with stalked,
    capitate-glandular protuberances along ribs; lobes triangular, 1–2 mm; corolla salverform,
    evenly to somewhat unevenly 5-lobed, lobes spreading, obovate, round, or truncate, mucronate;
    stamens included or exserted, free from corolla; style 1 included or exserted; stigmas 5,
    linear. Fruits capsules, included, brownish, long-beaked; valves coherent at apex. x =
    7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical regions, North America, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Leadwort</other_name>
  <discussion>species 12 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
  <discussion>Several species of Plumbago are cultivated, including P. auriculata. The entire plant
    of that species, especially the root, contains plumbagin, a toxic naphthoquinone derivative (oil
    of plumbago), which may cause severe skin irritation or blistering in humans and may also be
    toxic to other animals (T. C. Fuller and E. McClintock 1986).</discussion>
  <discussion>The remarkable glands on the calyces of Plumbago are often called “glandular hairs,”
    but they are not true hairs, being much more massive and multicellular structures with enlarged,
    capitate apices.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corollas pale blue, tube 2 or more times length of calyx; calyces with stipitate,
        glandlike protuberances and hairs; inflorescences compact, 2.5–3(–5) cm; plants cultivated
        and locally naturalized in Florida</description>
      <determination>1. Plumbago auriculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corollas white, tube mostly less than 2 times length of calyx; calyces with
        stipitate, glandlike protuberances, true hairs absent; inflorescences elongate, 3–15(–30)
        cm; plants native</description>
      <determination>2. Plumbago zeylanica</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
