<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">plumbaginaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">plumbago</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">zeylanica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 151. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family plumbaginaceae;genus plumbago;species zeylanica</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Plumbago</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">scandens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Plumbago;species scandens;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants herbaceous. Stems prost-rate, climbing, or erect, glabrous. Leaves petiolate (to 1.5 cm) or sessile; blade ovate, lance-elliptic, or spatulate to oblanceolate, (3–)5–9(–15) × (1–)2.5–4(–7) cm, base attenuate, apex acute, acuminate, or obtuse. Inflorescences 3–15(–30) cm, rachises glandular, viscid; floral bracts lanceolate, 3–7 × 1–2 mm. Flowers heterostylous; calyx 7–11(–13) mm, tube glabrous but with stalked glands along length of ribs; corolla white, 17–33 mm, tube 12.5–28 mm (less than 2 times length of calyx), lobes 5–12 × 3–3.5 mm; stamens included. Capsules 7.5–8 mm. Seeds reddish brown to dark brown, 5–6 mm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">palm groves</description>
  <description type="habitat">thickets</description>
  <description type="habitat">shady hummocks</description>
  <description type="habitat">shell mounds</description>
  <description type="habitat">rocky places in open areas</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–50 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Doctorbush</other_name>
  <discussion>Plumbago zeylanica and P. scandens, both Linnaean species, have heretofore been treated as distinct, the former name applied exclusively to Old World plants, the latter to New World specimens. John Edmondson (pers. comm.) indicates that he believes this “could be a classic case of New World and Old World taxonomists each doing their own thing.” Plants in herbaria under these two names appear indistinguishable.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference_discussion>Robert W. Kiger, Editor</reference_discussion>
    <reference_discussion>This is a consolidated list of all works cited in volume 5, whether as selected references, in text, or in nomenclatural contexts. In citations of articles, both here and in the taxonomic treatments, and also in nomenclatural citations, the titles of serials are rendered in the forms recommended in G. D. R. Bridson and E. R. Smith (1991). When those forms are abbreviated, as most are, cross references to the corresponding full serial titles are interpolated here alphabetically by abbreviated form. In nomenclatural citations (only), book titles are rendered in the abbreviated forms recommended in F. A. Stafleu and R. S. Cowan (1976–1988) and F. A. Stafleu and E. A. Mennega (1992+). Here, those abbreviated forms are indicated parenthetically following the full citations of the corresponding works, and cross references to the full citations are interpolated in the list alphabetically by abbreviated form. Two or more works published in the same year by the same author or group of coauthors will be distinguished uniquely and consistently throughout all volumes of Flora of North America by lower-case letters (b, c, d, ...) suffixed to the date for the second and subsequent works in the set. The suffixes are assigned in order of editorial encounter and do not reflect chronological sequence of publication. The first work by any particular author or group from any given year carries the implicit date suffix “a”; thus, the sequence of explicit suffixes begins with “b”. There may be citations in this list that have dates suffixed “b” but that are not preceded by citations of “[a]” works for the same year, or that have dates suffixed “c,” “d,” “e,” or “f” but that are not preceded by citations of “[a],” “b,” “c,” “d,” and/or “e” works for that year. In such cases, the missing “[a],” “b,” “c,” “d,” and/or “e” works are ones cited (and encountered first from) elsewhere in the Flora that are not pertinent in this volume.</reference_discussion>
    <reference>A. S. B. Bull. = A S B Bulletin.</reference>
    <reference>Abrams, L. and R. S. Ferris. 1923–1960. Illustrated Flora of the Pacific States: Washington, Oregon, and California. 4 vols. Stanford. (Ill. Fl. Pacific States)</reference>
    <reference>Abuhadra, M. N. 2000. Taxonomic studies on the Arenaria serpyllifolis group (Caryophyllaceae). Fl. Medit. 10: 185–190.</reference>
    <reference>Acta Bot. Neerl. = Acta Botanica Neerlandica.</reference>
    <reference>Acta Phytotax. Sin. = Acta Phytotaxonomica Sinica. [Chih Wu Fen Lei Hsüeh Pao.]</reference>
    <reference>Acta Univ. Lund. = Acta Universitatis Lundensis. Nova Series. Sectio 2, Medica, Mathematica, Scientiae Rerum Naturalium. [Lunds Universitets Årsskrift N.F., Avd. 2.]</reference>
    <reference>Acta Univ. Upsal., Symb. Bot. Upsal. = Acta Universitatis Upsaliensis. Symbolae Botanicae Upsalienses.</reference>
    <reference>Adanson, M. 1763[–1764]. Familles des Plantes. 2 vols. Paris. [Vol. 1, 1764; vol. 2, 1763.] (Fam. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Aiton, W. and W. T. Aiton. 1810–1813. Hortus Kewensis; or a Catalogue of the Plants Cultivated in the Royal Botanic Garden at Kew. 5 vols. London. (Hortus Kew.)</reference>
    <reference>Akeroyd, J. R. 1991. A new subspecific combination in Rumex acetosella L. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 106: 97–99.</reference>
    <reference>Akeroyd, J. R. 1993. Herniaria. In: T. G. Tutin et al., eds. 1993+. Flora Europaea, ed. 2. 1+ vol. Cambridge and New York. Vol. 1, pp. 182–184.</reference>
    <reference>Alph. Aufz. Gew.—See: G. Heynhold 1846[–1847]</reference>
    <reference>Amer. Anthropol. = American Anthropologist.</reference>
    <reference>Amer. J. Bot. = American Journal of Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Amer. J. Sci. Arts = American Journal of Science, and Arts.</reference>
    <reference>Amer. Midl. Naturalist = American Midland Naturalist; Devoted to Natural History, Primarily That of the Prairie States.</reference>
    <reference>Amer. Naturalist = American Naturalist....</reference>
    <reference>Anales Inst. Bot. Cavanilles = Anales del Instituto Botánico A. J. Cavanilles.</reference>
    <reference>Anales Inst. Segunda Enseñ. = Anales del Instituto de Segunda Enseñanza de la Habana.</reference>
    <reference>Anales Jard. Bot. Madrid = Anales del Jardín Botánico de Madrid.</reference>
    <reference>Anales Soc. Ci. Argent. = Anales de la Sociedad Científica Argentina.</reference>
    <reference>Anales Univ. Chile, I, Mem. Ci. Lit. = Anales de la Universidad de Chile. I. Memorias Cientificas i Literarias.</reference>
    <reference>Andersen, R. N., W. E. Lueschen, and J. R. Zaremba. 1985. Prickly smartweed (Polygonum bungeanum), a new weed in North America. Weed Sci. 33: 805–806.</reference>
    <reference>Anderson, L. C. 1991. Paronychia chartacea ssp. minima (Caryophyllaceae): A new subspecies of a rare Florida endemic. Sida 14: 435–441.</reference>
    <reference>Animadv. Bot. Spec. Alt.—See: P. Arduino 1764</reference>
    <reference>Ann. A. C. F. A. S. = Annales de l’A C F A S.</reference>
    <reference>Ann. Amélior. Pl. = Annales de l’Amélioration des Plantes.</reference>
    <reference>Ann. Bot. (Oxford) = Annals of Botany. (Oxford.)</reference>
    <reference>Ann. Lyceum Nat. Hist. New York = Annals of the Lyceum of Natural History of New York.</reference>
    <reference>Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. = Annals of the Missouri Botanical Garden.</reference>
    <reference>Ann. Nat. Hist. = Annals of Natural History; or, Magazine of Zoology, Botany and Geology.</reference>
    <reference>Ann. Sci. Nat., Bot. = Annales des Sciences Naturelles. Botanique.</reference>
    <reference>Ann. Wiener Mus. Naturgesch. = Annalen des Wiener Museums der Naturgeschichte.</reference>
    <reference>Annuaire Conserv. Jard. Bot. Genève = Annuaire du Conservatoire et Jardin Botaniques de Genève.</reference>
    <reference>Anthropol. Rec. = Anthropological Records.</reference>
    <reference>Arcangeli, G. 1882. Compendio della Flora Italiana.... Turin. (Comp. Fl. Ital.)</reference>
    <reference>Arch. Naturwiss. Landesdurchf. Böhmen. = Archiv für die naturwissenschaftliche Landesdurchforschung von Böhmen.</reference>
    <reference>Archibald, J. K., P. G. Wolf, V. J. Tepedino, and J. Bair. 2001. Genetic relationships and population structure of the endangered Steamboat buckwheat, Eriogonum ovalifolium var. williamsiae (Polygonaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 88: 608–615.</reference>
    <reference>Arduino, P. 1764. Animadversionum Botanicarum Specimen Alterum. Venice. (Animadv. Bot. Spec. Alt.)</reference>
    <reference>Ark. Bot. = Arkiv för Botanik Utgivet av K. Svenska Vetenskapsakademien.</reference>
    <reference>Ascherson, P. F. A. et al. 1896–1939. Synopsis der mitteleuropäischen Flora. 12 vols., some in parts. Leipzig. (Syn. Mitteleur. Fl.)</reference>
    <reference>Atlantic J. = Atlantic Journal, and Friend of Knowledge.</reference>
    <reference>Austral. J. Bot. = Australian Journal of Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Austral. Syst. Bot. = Australian Systematic Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Baad, M. F. 1969. Biosystematic Studies of the North American species of Arenaria, Subgenus Eremogone (Caryophyllaceae). Ph.D. dissertation. University of Washington.</reference>
    <reference>Bailey, J. P., L. E. Child, and A. P. Conolly. 1996. A survey of the distribution of Fallopia ×bohemica (Chrtek &amp; Chrtková) J. Bailey (Polygonaceae) in the British Isles. Watsonia 21: 187–198.</reference>
    <reference>Bailey, J. P. and C. A. Stace. 1992. Chromosome number, morphology, pairing, and DNA values of species and hybrids in the genus Fallopia (Polygonaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 180: 29–52.</reference>
    <reference>Baileya = Baileya; a Quarterly Journal of Horticultural Taxonomy.</reference>
    <reference>Baker, H. G. 1953b. Dimorphism and monomorphism in the Plumbaginaceae II. Pollen and stigmata in the genus Limonium. Ann. Bot. (Oxford), n. s. 17: 433–445.</reference>
    <reference>Bakker, K. 1957. Revision of the genus Polycarpaea (Caryoph.) in Malaysia. Acta Bot. Neerl. 6: 48–53.</reference>
    <reference>Ball, P. W. and V. H. Heywood. 1964. A revision of the genus Petrorhagia. Bull. Brit. Mus. (Nat. Hist.), Bot. 3: 121–172.</reference>
    <reference>Barkoudah, Y. I. 1962. A revision of Gypsophila, Bolanthus, Ankyropetalum and Phryna. Wentia 9: 1–203.</reference>
    <reference>Barneby, R. C. and E. C. Twisselman. 1970. Notes on Loeflingia (Caryophyllaceae). Madroño 20: 398–408.</reference>
    <reference>Barrett, S. A. and E. W. Gifford. 1933. Miwok material culture. Bull. Public Mus. Milwaukee 2(4): 119–376.</reference>
    <reference>Barrows, D. P. 1900. The Ethno-botany of the Coahuilla Indians of Southern California. Chicago. [Reprinted 1978, New York.]</reference>
    <reference>Bartonia = Bartonia; a Botanical Annual.</reference>
    <reference>Baskin, C. C., P. L. Chesson, and J. M. Baskin. 1993. Annual seed dormancy cycles in two desert winter annuals. J. Ecol. 81: 551–556.</reference>
    <reference>Baskin, J. M. and C. C. Baskin. 1990. The role of light and alternating temperatures on germination of Polygonum aviculare seeds exhumed on various dates. Weed Res. 30: 397–402.</reference>
    <reference>Bastard, T. 1812. Supplément à l’Essai sur la Flore du Département de Maine-et-Loire. Angers. (Suppl. Fl. Maine-et-Loire)</reference>
    <reference>Baumgarten, J. C. G. 1816–1846. Enumeratio Stirpium Magno Transsilvaniae.... 4 vols. + suppl. + index. Vienna and Hermannstadt. (Enum. Stirp. Transsilv.)</reference>
    <reference>Beena, K. R., K. Ananda, and K. R. Sridhar. 2000. Fungal endophytes of three sand dune species of west coast of India. Sydowia 52: 1–9.</reference>
    <reference>Beerling, D. J., J. P. Bailey, and A. P. Conolly. 1994. Fallopia japonica (Houtt.) Ronse Decraene. J. Ecol. 82: 959–979.</reference>
    <reference>Behnke, H.-D. 1982. Geocarpon minimum: Sieve-element plastids as additional evidence for its inclusion in the Caryophyllaceae. Taxon 31: 45–47.</reference>
    <reference>Behnke, H.-D. and T. J. Mabry, eds. 1994. Caryophyllales: Evolution and Systematics. Berlin.</reference>
    <reference>Beih. Bot. Centralbl. = Beihefte zum Botanischen Centralblatt. Original Arbeiten.</reference>
    <reference>Beitr. Naturk.—See: J. F. Ehrhart 1787–1792</reference>
    <reference>Bentham, G. 1839[–1857]. Plantas Hartwegianas Imprimis Mexicanas.... London. [Issued by gatherings with consecutive signatures and pagination.] (Pl. Hartw.)</reference>
    <reference>Bentham, G. 1844[–1846]. The Botany of the Voyage of H.M.S. Sulphur, under the Command of Captain Sir Edward Belcher...during the Years 1836–1842. 6 parts. London. [Parts paged consecutively.] (Bot. Voy. Sulphur)</reference>
    <reference>Berher, E.-L. 1887. La Flore des Vosges. Épinal. [Vol. 2 of L. Louis, Le Département des Vosges: Description, Histoire, Statistique.] (Fl. Vosges)</reference>
    <reference>Bernis, F. 1952. Revisión del género Armeria Willd. con especial referencia a los grupos Ibéricos. Anales Inst. Bot. Cavanilles 11(2): 5–287.</reference>
    <reference>Besser, W. S. J. G. von. 1822. Enumeratio Plantarum.... Vilna. (Enum. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Bigelow, J. 1824. Florula Bostoniensis. A Collection of Plants of Boston and Its Vicinity..., ed. 2. Boston. (Fl. Boston. ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Bigelow, J. 1840. Florula Bostoniensis. A Collection of Plants of Boston and Its Vicinity..., ed. 3. Boston. (Fl. Boston. ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Biochem. Syst. &amp; Ecol. = Biochemical Systematics and Ecology.</reference>
    <reference>Biol. J. Linn. Soc. = Biological Journal of the Linnean Society.</reference>
    <reference>Biol. Skr. = Biologiske Skrifter.</reference>
    <reference>Bishop Mus. Occas. Pap. = Bishop Museum Occasional Papers.</reference>
    <reference>Bittrich, V. 1993. Caryophyllaceae. In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 4+ vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 2, pp. 206–236.</reference>
    <reference>Blackwell, W. H. 1990. Poisonous and Medicinal Plants. Englewood Cliffs.</reference>
    <reference>Bluff, M. J., C. A. Fingerhuth, and C. F. W. Wallroth. 1825–1833. Compendium Florae Germaniae. 4 vols. Nuremberg. (Comp. Fl. German.)</reference>
    <reference>Bocek, B. R. 1984. Ethnobotany of Costanoan Indians, based on collections by John P. Harrington. Econ. Bot. 38: 240–255.</reference>
    <reference>Böcher, T. W. 1963. Experimental and cytological studies on plant species. VIII. Racial differentiation in amphi-Atlantic Viscaria alpina. Biol. Skr. 11(6).</reference>
    <reference>Böcher, T. W. 1977. Cerastium alpinum and C. arcticum, a mature polyploid complex. Bot. Not. 130: 303–309.</reference>
    <reference>Bocquet, G. 1969. Revisio Physolychnidum (Silene Sect. Physolychnis).... Lehre.</reference>
    <reference>Bogle, A. L., T. Swain, R. D. Thomas, and E. D. Kohn. 1971. Geocarpon: Aizoaceae or Caryophyllaceae? Taxon 20: 473–477.</reference>
    <reference>Boissiera = Boissiera; Mémoires des Conservatoire et de l’Institut de Botanique Systématique de l’Université de Genève (later Mémoires des Conservatoire et Jardin Botaniques de la Ville de Genève). Supplement de Candollea.</reference>
    <reference>Boivin, B. 1954. Les variations du Stellaria humifusa Rottboell. Ann. A. C. F. A. S. 20: 97–98.</reference>
    <reference>Boivin, B. 1956. Stellaria sectio Umbellatae Schischkin (Caryophyllaceae). Svensk Bot. Tidskr. 50: 113–114.</reference>
    <reference>Borbás, V. von. 1884. Temes Megye Vegetiója (Flora Comitatus Temesiensis).... Temesvárott. (Fl. Comit. Temesiensis)</reference>
    <reference>Boreau, A. 1857. Flore du Centre de la France..., ed. 3. 2 vols. Angers. (Fl. Centre France ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Borodina, A. E. 1977. O vidakh roda Rumex L. Evropeyshoy chasti SSSR. 1. Subgen. Rumex sect. Rumex subsect. Maritimi Rech. f. (De generis Rumex L. speciebus in parte Europaea URSS crescentibus. 1. Subgen. Rumex sect. Rumex subsect. Maritimi Rech. f.) Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast. 14: 64–72.</reference>
    <reference>Boston J. Nat. Hist. = Boston Journal of Natural History.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Beechey Voy.—See: W. J. Hooker and G. A. W. Arnott [1830–]1841</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Cab. = Botanical Cabinet; Consisting of Coloured Delineations of Plants from All Countries.... [Edited by G. Loddiges.]</reference>
    <reference>Bot. California—See: W. H. Brewer et al. 1876–1880</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Dict. ed. 4—See: A. Eaton 1836</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Gaz. = Botanical Gazette; Paper of Botanical Notes.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Helv. = Botanica Helvetica.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. J. Linn. Soc. = Botanical Journal of the Linnean Society.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Jahrb. Syst. = Botanische Jahrbücher für Systematik, Pflanzengeschichte und Pflanzengeographie.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Mag. = Botanical Magazine; or, Flower-garden Displayed.... [Edited by Wm. Curtis.] [With vol. 15, 1801, title became Curtis’s Botanical Magazine; or....]</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Mag. (Tokyo) = Botanical Magazine. [Shokubutsu-gaku Zasshi.] (Tokyo.)</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Mus. Leafl. = Botanical Museum Leaflets. [Harvard University.]</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Not. = Botaniska Notiser.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Not., Suppl. = Botisker Notiser. Supplement.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Tidsskr. = Botanisk Tidsskrift.</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Voy. Sulphur—See: G. Bentham 1844[–1846]</reference>
    <reference>Bot. Zhurn. (Moscow &amp; Leningrad) = Botanicheskii Zhurnal. (Moscow and Leningrad.)</reference>
    <reference>Botanical Society of America 2001. Botany 2001 Abstracts. Columbus.</reference>
    <reference>Botanical Society of America 2002. Botany 2002 Abstracts. Columbus.</reference>
    <reference>Botany (Fortieth Parallel)—See: S. Watson 1871</reference>
    <reference>Bowerman, M. L. 1944. The Flowering Plants and Ferns of Mount Diablo, California; Their Distribution and Association into Plant Communities. Berkeley. (Fl. Pl. Ferns Mt. Diablo)</reference>
    <reference>Bowlin, W. R., V. J. Tepedino, and T. L. Griswold. 1993. The reproductive biology of Eriogonum pelinophilum (Polygonaceae). In: R. C. Sivinski and K. Lightfoot, eds. 1993. Southwestern Rare and Endangered Plants: Proceedings of the...Conference. Santa Fe. Pp. 296–300.</reference>
    <reference>Brandbyge, J. 1992. The genus Muehlenbeckia (Polygonaceae) in South and Central America. Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 114: 349–416.</reference>
    <reference>Brandbyge, J. 1993. Polygonaceae. In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 4+ vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 2, pp. 531–544.</reference>
    <reference>Brenckle, J. F. 1941. Notes on Polygonum (Avicularia). Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 68: 491–495.</reference>
    <reference>Brewer, W. H. et al. 1876–1880. Geological Survey of California.... Botany.... 2 vols. Cambridge, Mass. (Bot. California)</reference>
    <reference>Bridson, G. D. R. and E. R. Smith. 1991. B-P-H/S. Botanico-Periodicum-Huntianum/Supplementum. Pittsburgh.</reference>
    <reference>Britten, J. 1890. Buda v. Tissa. J. Bot. 28: 295–297.</reference>
    <reference>Britton, N. L. et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. [Vols. 1–34, 1905–1957; ser. 2, parts 1–13+, 1954+.]</reference>
    <reference>Brittonia = Brittonia; a Journal of Systematic Botany....</reference>
    <reference>Brown, L. E. and S. J. Marcus. 1998. Notes on the flora of Texas with additions and other significant records. Sida 18: 315–324.</reference>
    <reference>Brown, R. 1810. Prodromus Florae Novae Hollandiae et Insulae van-Diemen.... London. (Prodr.)</reference>
    <reference>Browne, P. 1756. The Civil and Natural History of Jamaica.... London. (Civ. Nat. Hist. Jamaica)</reference>
    <reference>Brummitt, R. K. and C. E. Powell, eds. 1992. Authors of Plant Names. A List of Authors of Scientific Names of Plants, with Recommended Standard Forms of Their Names, Including Abbreviations. Kew.</reference>
    <reference>Brysting, A. K. and R. Elven. 2000. The Cerastium alpinum–C. arcticum complex (Caryophyllaceae): Numerical analyses of morphological variation and a taxonomic revision of C. arcticum Lange s.l. Taxon 49: 189–216.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Acad. Int. Géogr. Bot. = Bulletin de l’Académie Internationale de Géographie Botanique.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Bot. Surv. India = Bulletin of the Botanical Survey of India.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Brit. Mus. (Nat. Hist.), Bot. = Bulletin of the British Museum (Natural History). Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Calif. Acad. Sci. = Bulletin of the California Academy of Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Cl. Phys.-Math. Acad. Imp. Sci. Saint-Pétersbourg = Bulletin de la Classe Physico-mathématique de l’Académie Impériale des Sciences de Saint-Pétersbourg.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Herb. Boissier = Bulletin de l’Herbier Boissier.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Natl. Mus. Canada = Bulletin of the National Museum of Canada.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. New York Bot. Gard. = Bulletin of the New York Botanical Garden.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. New York State Mus. Sci. Serv. = Bulletin of the New York State Museum and Science Service.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Ohio Biol. Surv. = Bulletin of the Ohio Biological Survey.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Public Mus. Milwaukee = Bulletin of the Public Museum of Milwaukee.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. S. Calif. Acad. Sci. = Bulletin of the Southern California Academy of Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Soc. Hist. Nat. Afrique N. = Bulletin de la Société d’Histoire Naturelle de l’Afrique du Nord.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Soc. Imp. Naturalistes Moscou = Bulletin de la Société Impériale des Naturalistes de Moscou.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Soc. Roy. Bot. Belgique = Bulletin de la Société Royale de Botanique de Belgique.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club = Bulletin of the Torrey Botanical Club.</reference>
    <reference>Bull. Univ. Utah, Biol. Ser. = Bulletin of the University of Utah. Biological Series.</reference>
    <reference>Burleigh, J. G. and T. P. Holtsford. 2003. Molecular systematics of the eastern North American Silene (Caryophyllaceae): Evidence from nuclear ITS and chloroplast trnL intron sequences. Rhodora 105: 76–90.</reference>
    <reference>Burnat, E., J. I. Briquet, and F. G. Cavillier. 1892–1931. Flore des Alpes Maritimes.... 7 vols. Geneva, Basel, and Lyon. (Fl. Alpes Marit.)</reference>
    <reference>Byull. Moskovsk. Obshch. Isp. Prir., Otd. Biol. = Byulleten’ Moskovskogo Obshchestva Ispytatelei Prirody. Otdel Biologicheskii.</reference>
    <reference>Cafferty, S. and S. Snogerup. 2000. Proposal to conserve the name Rumex alpinus L. (Polygonaceae) with a conserved type. Taxon 49: 571–572.</reference>
    <reference>Callihan, R. H., S. L. Carson, and R. T. Dobbins. 1995. NAWEEDS, Computer-aided Weed Identification for North America. Illustrated User’s Guide plus Computer Floppy Disk. Moscow, Idaho.</reference>
    <reference>Camazine, S. and R. A. Bye. 1980. A study of the medical ethnobotany of the Zuni Indians of New Mexico. J. Ethnopharmacol. 2: 365–388.</reference>
    <reference>Campbell, C. G. 1997. Buckwheat. Fagopyrum esculentum Moench. Gatersleben and Rome. [Promoting the Conservation and Use of Underutilized and Neglected Crops 19.]</reference>
    <reference>Campderá, F. 1819. Monographie des Rumex.... Paris etc. (Monogr. Rumex)</reference>
    <reference>Canad. Field-Naturalist = Canadian Field-Naturalist.</reference>
    <reference>Canad. J. Bot. = Canadian Journal of Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Canad. J. Genet. Cytol. = Canadian Journal of Genetics and Cytology.</reference>
    <reference>Canad. J. Pl. Sci. = Canadian Journal of Plant Science.</reference>
    <reference>Candolle, A. P. de. 1813b. Catalogus Plantarum Horti Botanici Monspeliensis.... Monpellier, Paris, and Strasbourg. (Cat. Pl. Hort. Monsp.)</reference>
    <reference>Candolle, A. P. de and A. L. P. P. Candolle, eds. 1823–1873. Prodromus Systematis Naturalis Regni Vegetabilis.... 17 vols. Paris etc. [Vols. 1–7 edited by A. P. de Candolle, vols. 8–17 by A. L. P. P. de Candolle.] (Prodr.)</reference>
    <reference>Candollea = Candollea; Organe du Conservatoire et du Jardin Botaniques de la Ville de Genève.</reference>
    <reference>Caratt. Nuov. Gen.—See: C. S. Rafinesque 1810</reference>
    <reference>Carlquist, S. 2003. Wood anatomy of Polygonaceae: Analysis of a family with exceptional wood diversity. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 141: 25–51.</reference>
    <reference>Carlquist, S. and C. J. Biggs. 1996. Wood anatomy of Plumbaginaceae. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 123: 135–147.</reference>
    <reference>Carlson, G. G. and V. H. Jones. 1940. Some notes on uses of plants by the Comanche Indians. Pap. Michigan Acad. Sci. 25: 517–542.</reference>
    <reference>as. Nár. Muz. Praze Rada Prír. = Casopis Národního Muzea v Praze. Rada Prírodovedný.</reference>
    <reference>Castanea = Castanea; Journal of the Southern Appalachian Botanical Club.</reference>
    <reference>Cat. N. Amer. Pl.—See: A. A. Heller 1898</reference>
    <reference>Cat. Pl. Hort. Monsp.—See: A. P. de Candolle 1813b</reference>
    <reference>Cat. Pl. Upper Louisiana—See: T. Nuttall 1813</reference>
    <reference>Cattaneo, C. 1844. Notizie Naturali e Civili su la Lombardia. Milan. (Not. Nat. Civ. Lombardia)</reference>
    <reference>Cavanilles, A. J. 1791–1801. Icones et Descriptiones Plantarum, Quae aut Sponte in Hispania Crescunt, aut in Hortis Hospitantur. 6 vols. Madrid. (Icon.)</reference>
    <reference>Chamberlin, R. V. 1911. The ethno-botany of the Gosiute Indians of Utah. Mem. Amer. Anthropol. Assoc. 2: 331–405.</reference>
    <reference>Chambers, K. L. 1992. Choosing the correct name for Aconogonon (Polygonum sect. Aconogonon) in Alaska. Rhodora 94: 319–322.</reference>
    <reference>Chapman, A. W. 1860. Flora of the Southern United States.... New York. (Fl. South. U.S.)</reference>
    <reference>Chapman, A. W. 1897. Flora of the Southern United States..., ed. 3. Cambridge, Mass. (Fl. South. U.S. ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Chase, M. W. et al. 1993. Phylogenetics of seed plants: An analysis of nucleotide sequences from the plastid gene rbcL. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 80: 528–580.</reference>
    <reference>Chater, A. O. and G. Halliday. 1993. Arenaria. In: T. G. Tutin et al., eds. 1993+. Flora Europaea, ed. 2. 1+ vol. Cambridge and New York. Vol. 1, pp. 140–148.</reference>
    <reference>Chaudhri, M. N. 1968. A revision of the Paronychiinae. Meded. Bot. Mus. Herb. Rijks Univ. Utrecht 285: 306–397.</reference>
    <reference>Chestnut, V. K. 1902. Plants used by the Indians of Mendocino County, California. Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 7: 295–408.</reference>
    <reference>Chin, T. C. and H. W. Youngken. 1947. The cytotaxonomy of Rheum. Amer. J. Bot. 34: 401–407.</reference>
    <reference>Chinnappa, C. C. 1985. Studies on the Stelleria longipes complex (Caryophyllaceae): Interspecific hybridization. I. Triploid meiosis. Canad. J. Genet. Cytol. 27: 318–321.</reference>
    <reference>Chinnappa, C. C. 1992. Stellaria porsildii, sp. nov., a new member of the S. longipes complex (Caryophyllaceae. Syst. Bot. 17: 29–32.</reference>
    <reference>Chinnappa, C. C. and J. K. Morton. 1974. The cytology of Stellaria longipes. Canad. J. Genet. Cytol. 16: 499–514.</reference>
    <reference>Chinnappa, C. C. and J. K. Morton. 1976. Studies on the Stellaria longipes Goldie complex—Variation in wild populations. Rhodora 78: 488–501.</reference>
    <reference>Chinnappa, C. C. and J. K. Morton. 1984. Studies on the Stellaria longipes Goldie complex (Caryophyllaceae): Biosystematics. Syst. Bot. 9: 60–73.</reference>
    <reference>Chinnappa, C. C. and J. K. Morton. 1991. Studies on the Stellaria longipes complex (Caryophyllaceae): Taxonomy. Rhodora 93: 129–135.</reference>
    <reference>Chowdhuri, P. K. 1957. Studies in the genus Silene. Notes Roy. Bot. Gard. Edinburgh 22: 221–278.</reference>
    <reference>Christman, S. P. and W. S. Judd. 1990. Notes on plants endemic to Florida scrub. Florida Sci. 53: 52–73.</reference>
    <reference>Chrtek, J. and M. Šourková. 1992. Variation in Oxyria digyna. Preslia 64: 207–210.</reference>
    <reference>Chung, H. S. et al. 1999. Flavonoid constituents of Chorizanthe diffusa with potential cancer chemo-preventive activity. J. Agric. Food Chem. 47: 36–41.</reference>
    <reference>Civ. Nat. Hist. Jamaica—See: P. Browne 1756</reference>
    <reference>Clairville, J. P. de. 1811. Manuel d’Herborisation en Suisse et en Valais.... Winterthur. (Man. Herbor. Suisse)</reference>
    <reference>Class-book Bot. ed. 2—See: A. Wood 1847</reference>
    <reference>Class-book Bot. ed. s.n.(b)—See: A. Wood 1861</reference>
    <reference>Clute, O. and O. Palmer. 1893. Spurry (Spergula arvensis). Michigan Agric. Exp. Sta. Bull. 91: 3–8.</reference>
    <reference>Coker, P. D. 1962. Corrigiola litoralis L. J. Ecol. 50: 833–840.</reference>
    <reference>Comp. Fl. German.—See: M. J. Bluff et al. 1825–1833</reference>
    <reference>Comp. Fl. Ital.—See: G. Arcangeli 1882</reference>
    <reference>Consaul, L. L., S. I. Warwick, and J. McNeill. 1991. Allozyme variation in the Polygonum lapathifolium complex. Canad. J. Bot. 69: 2261–2270.</reference>
    <reference>Conservation Genet. = Conservation Genetics.</reference>
    <reference>Consp. Fl. Eur.—See: C. F. Nyman 1878–1890</reference>
    <reference>Consp. Fl. Groenland.—See: J. M. C. Lange 1880[–1894]</reference>
    <reference>Consp. Regn. Veg.—See: H. G. L. Reichenbach 1828</reference>
    <reference>Contr. Gray Herb. = Contributions from the Gray Herbarium of Harvard University. [Some numbers reprinted from (or in?) other periodicals, e.g. Rhodora.]</reference>
    <reference>Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. = Contributions from the University of Michigan Herbarium.</reference>
    <reference>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. = Contributions from the United States National Herbarium.</reference>
    <reference>Contr. W. Bot. = Contributions to Western Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Cooperrider, T. S. 1995. The Dicotyledoneae of Ohio: Linaceae through Campanulaceae. Columbus. [The Vascular Flora of Ohio, vol. 2(2).]</reference>
    <reference>Core, E. L. 1939. A taxonomic revision of the genus Siphonychia. J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. 55: 339–345.</reference>
    <reference>Core, E. L. 1940. Notes on the mid-Appalachian species of Paronychia. Virginia J. Sci. 1: 110–116.</reference>
    <reference>Core, E. L. 1941. The North American species of Paronychia. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 26: 369–397.</reference>
    <reference>Correll, D. S. and M. C. Johnston. 1970. Manual of the Vascular Plants of Texas. Renner, Tex.</reference>
    <reference>Costea, M. and F. J. Tardif. 2003. Nomenclatural changes in the genus Polygonum, section Polygonum (Polygonaceae). Sida 20: 987–997.</reference>
    <reference>Costea, M. and F. J. Tardif. 2003b. Does Polygonum patulum (Polygonaceae) grow in North America? Sida 20: 1707–1708.</reference>
    <reference>Costea, M. and F. J. Tardif. 2005. Taxonomy of the Polygonum douglasii (Polygonaceae) complex with a new species from Oregon. Brittonia 57: 1–27.</reference>
    <reference>Courtney, A. D. 1968. Seed dormancy and field emergence in Polygonum aviculare. J. Appl. Ecol. 5: 675–684.</reference>
    <reference>Coville, F. V. 1897. Notes on the plants used by the Klamath Indians of Oregon. Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 5: 87–110.</reference>
    <reference>Crépin, F. 1866. Manuel de la Flore de Belgique..., ed. 2. Brussels. (Man. Fl. Belgique ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Cronquist, A. 1981. An Integrated System of Classification of Flowering Plants. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Crow, G. E. 1978. A taxonomic revision of Sagina (Caryophyllaceae) in North America. Rhodora 80: 1–91.</reference>
    <reference>Crow, G. E. 1979. The systematic significance of seed morphology in Sagina (Caryophyllaceae) utilizing SEM. Brittonia 31: 52–63.</reference>
    <reference>Cuénoud, P. et al. 2002. Molecular phylogenetics of Caryophyllales based on nuclear 18S rDNA and plastid rbcL, atpB, and matK DNA sequences. Amer. J. Bot. 89: 132–144.</reference>
    <reference>Curr. Topics Pl. Sci.—See: J. E. Gunckel 1969</reference>
    <reference>Curtis, W. [1775–]1777–1798. Flora Londinensis.... 2 vols. in 6 fasc. and 72 nos. London. (Fl. Londin.)</reference>
    <reference>Cusick, A. W. 1983. Spergularia (Caryophyllaceae) in Ohio. Michigan Bot. 22: 69–71.</reference>
    <reference>Cycl.—See: A. Rees [1802–]1819–1820</reference>
    <reference>Cytologia = Cytologia; International Journal of Cytology.</reference>
    <reference>Dalci, M. 1972. The Taxonomy of Section Persicaria (Tourn.) L. in the Genus Polygonum (Tourn.) L. (Polygonaceae) in the United States East of the Rocky Mountains. Ph.D. dissertation. University of Nebraska.</reference>
    <reference>Darwent, A. L. 1975. The biology of Canadian weeds. 14. Gypsophila paniculata. Canad. J. Pl. Sci. 55: 1049–1058.</reference>
    <reference>Davis, L. and R. J. Sherman. 1990. The rediscovered Sonoma spineflower at Point Reyes National Seashore. Fremontia 18(1): 17–18.</reference>
    <reference>Davis, L. and R. J. Sherman. 1992. Ecological study of the rare Chorizanthe valida (Polygonaceae) at Point Reyes National Seashore, California. Madroño 39: 271–280.</reference>
    <reference>Davis, R. J. 1952. Flora of Idaho. Dubuque. (Fl. Idaho)</reference>
    <reference>Dawson, J. E. 1979. A Biosystematic Study of Rumex Section Rumex in Canada and the United States. Ph.D. thesis. Carleton University.</reference>
    <reference>DeDecker, M. 1974. Redescription of Eriogonum hoffmannii, a Death Valley endemic. Madroño 5: 265–267.</reference>
    <reference>Delarbre, A. 1800. Flore d’Auvergne..., ed. 2. 2 vols. Riom and Clermont. (Fl. Auvergne ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>den Nijs, J. C. M. 1974. Biosystematic studies of the Rumex acetosella complex. I. Angiocarpy and chromosome numbers in France. Acta Bot. Neerl. 23: 655–675.</reference>
    <reference>den Nijs, J. C. M. 1976. Biosystematic studies of the Rumex acetosella complex. II. The Alpine region. Acta Bot. Neerl. 25: 417–447.</reference>
    <reference>den Nijs, J. C. M. 1984. Biosystematic studies of the Rumex acetosella complex. VIII. A taxonomic revision. Feddes Repert. 95: 43–66.</reference>
    <reference>den Nijs, J. C. M., H. Hooghiemstra, and P. H. Schalk. 1980. Biosystematic studies of the Rumex acetosella complex. IV. Pollen morphology and the possibilities of identification of cytotypes in pollen analysis. Phyton (Horn) 20: 307–323.</reference>
    <reference>den Nijs, J. C. M. and T. Panhorst. 1980. Biosystematic studies of the Rumex acetosella complex. III. A note on the systematic position of “R. tenuifolius (Wallr.) Löve.” Acta Bot. Neerl. 29: 179–192.</reference>
    <reference>den Nijs, J. C. M., K. Sorgdrager, and J. Stoop. 1985. Biosystematic studies of the Rumex acetosella complex. IX. Cytogeography of the complex in the Iberian Peninsula and taxonomic discussion. Bot. Helv. 95: 141–156.</reference>
    <reference>Descr. Pl. Nouv.—See: É. P. Ventenat [1800–1803]</reference>
    <reference>Desert Pl. = Desert Plants; a Quarterly Journal Devoted to Broadening Our Knowledge of Plants Indigenous or Adaptable to Arid and Sub-arid Regions.</reference>
    <reference>Desfontaines, R. L. [1798–1799.] Flora Atlantica sive Historia Plantarum, Quae in Atlante, Agro Tunetano et Algeriensi Crescunt. 2 vols. in 9 parts. Paris. (Fl. Atlant.)</reference>
    <reference>Deut. Excurs.-Fl.—See: K. F. W. Jessen 1879</reference>
    <reference>Deut. Fl.—See: H. Karsten 1880–1883</reference>
    <reference>Deutschl. Fl.—See: G. F. Hoffmann [1791–1804]</reference>
    <reference>Deutschl. Fl. ed. 2—See: J. Sturm et al. 1900–1907</reference>
    <reference>Deutschl. Fl. ed. 3—See: J. C. Röhling et al. 1823–1839</reference>
    <reference>Dodge, C. K. 1915. The flowering plants, ferns and fern allies growing without cultivation in Lambton County, Ontario. Rep. (Annual) Michigan Acad. Sci. 16: 132–200.</reference>
    <reference>Don, D. 1825. Prodromus Florae Nepalensis.... London. (Prodr. Fl. Nepal.)</reference>
    <reference>Don, G. 1831–1838. A General History of the Dichlamydeous Plants.... 4 vols. London. (Gen. Hist.)</reference>
    <reference>Dorn, R. D. 1988. Vascular Plants of Wyoming. Cheyenne. (Vasc. Pl. Wyoming)</reference>
    <reference>Dorn, R. D. 2001. Vascular Plants of Wyoming, ed. 3. Cheyenne. (Vasc. Pl. Wyoming ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Downie, S. R., D. S. Katz(-Downie), and K. J. Cho. 1997. Relationships in the Caryophyllales as suggested by phylogenetic analyses of partial chloroplast DNA ORF2280 homolog sequences. Amer. J. Bot. 84: 253–273.</reference>
    <reference>Duke, J. A. 1961. Preliminary revision of the genus Drymaria. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 48: 173–268.</reference>
    <reference>Dumortier, B. C. J. 1827. Florula Belgica.... Tournay. (Fl. Belg.)</reference>
    <reference>Dunn, D. B. 1982. Problems in “keeping up” with the flora of Missouri. Trans. Missouri Acad. Sci. 16: 95–98.</reference>
    <reference>Eaton, A. 1836. Eaton’s Botanical Grammar and Dictionary..., ed. 4. Albany. (Bot. Dict. ed. 4)</reference>
    <reference>Ecol. Monogr. = Ecological Monographs.</reference>
    <reference>Ecology = Ecology, a Quarterly Journal Devoted to All Phases of Ecological Biology.</reference>
    <reference>Econ. Bot. = Economic Botany; Devoted to Applied Botany and Plant Utilization.</reference>
    <reference>Edinburgh J. Bot. = Edinburgh Journal of Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Edinburgh Philos. J. = Edinburgh Philosophical Journal.</reference>
    <reference>Edwards’s Bot. Reg. = Edwards’s Botanical Register....</reference>
    <reference>Ehrhart, J. F. 1787–1792. Beiträge zur Naturkunde.... 7 vols. Hannover and Osnabrück. (Beitr. Naturk.)</reference>
    <reference>Elliott, S. [1816–]1821–1824. A Sketch of the Botany of South-Carolina and Georgia. 2 vols. in 13 parts. Charleston. (Sketch Bot. S. Carolina)</reference>
    <reference>Elmore, F. A. 1943. Ethnobotany of the Navajo. Albuquerque. [Reprinted 1978, New York.]</reference>
    <reference>Elven, R., Ö. Nilsson, and S. Snogerup. 2000. Rumex. In: B. Jonsell and T. Karlsson, eds. 2000+. Flora Nordica. 2+ vols. Stockholm. Vol. 1, pp. 281–318.</reference>
    <reference>Emery, R. J. N. and C. C. Chinnappa. 1994. Morphological variation among members of the Stellaria longipes complex: S. longipes, S. longifolia and S. porsildii (Caryophyllaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 190: 69–78.</reference>
    <reference>Emory, W. H. 1848. Notes of a Military Reconnoissance, from Fort Leavenworth, in Missouri, to San Diego, in California, Including Part of the Arkansas, Del Norte, and Gila Rivers.... Made in 1846–7, with the Advanced Guard of the “Army of the West.” Washington. (Not. Milit. Reconn.)</reference>
    <reference>Emory, W. H. 1857–1859. Report on the United States and Mexican Boundary Survey, Made under the Direction of the Secretary of the Interior. 2 vols. in parts. Washington. (Rep. U.S. Mex. Bound.)</reference>
    <reference>Encycl.—See: J. Lamarck et al. 1783–1817</reference>
    <reference>Encycl. Brit. ed. 7—See: M. Napier 1830–1842</reference>
    <reference>Endlicher, S. L. 1836–1840[–1850] Genera Plantarum Secundum Ordines Naturales Disposita. 18 parts + 5 suppls. in 6 parts. Vienna. [Paged consecutively through suppl. 1(2); suppls. 2–5 paged independently.] (Gen. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Engler, H. G. A. et al., eds. 1924+. Die natürlichen Pflanzenfamilien..., ed. 2. 26+ vols. Leipzig and Berlin. (Nat. Pflanzenfam. ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Enum. Pl.—See: W. S. J. G. von Besser 1822; C. L. Willdenow 1809–1813[–1814]</reference>
    <reference>Enum. Pl. Corea—See: T. Mori 1922</reference>
    <reference>Enum. Pl. Nov.—See: F. E. L. von Fischer and C. A. von Meyer 1841–1842</reference>
    <reference>Enum. Stirp. Transsilv.—See: J. C. G. Baumgarten 1816–1846</reference>
    <reference>Enum. Stirp. Vindob.—See: N. J. Jacquin 1762</reference>
    <reference>Enum. Syst. Pl.—See: N. J. Jacquin 1760</reference>
    <reference>Eriogonum—See: S. G. Stokes 1936</reference>
    <reference>Értek. Term. Köréb. Magyar Tud. Akad. = Értekezések a Természettudományi Köréböl; Kiadja a Magyar Tudományos Akadémia.</reference>
    <reference>Ertter, B. 1980. A revision of the genus Oxytheca (Polygonaceae). Brittonia 32: 70–102.</reference>
    <reference>Ertter, B. 1996. Saga of the Santa Cruz spineflower. Fremontia 24(4): 8–11.</reference>
    <reference>Erythea = Erythea; a Journal of Botany, West American and General.</reference>
    <reference>Escamilla, M. and V. Sosa. 2000. Características de la semilla en las series del género Drymaria (Caryophyllaceae). Kurtziana 28: 259–274.</reference>
    <reference>Evol. Trends Pl. = Evolutionary Trends in Plants.</reference>
    <reference>Evolution = Evolution, International Journal of Organic Evolution.</reference>
    <reference>Fam. Pl.—See: M. Adanson 1763[–1764]</reference>
    <reference>Fassett, N. C. 1949. The variations of Polygonum punctatum. Brittonia 6: 369–393.</reference>
    <reference>Favarger, C. and M. Krähenbühl. 1996. Nombre chromosomique et affinities probables d’un Cerastium (Caryophyllaceae) des Balkans. Anales Jard. Bot. Madrid 54: 155–165.</reference>
    <reference>Feddes Repert. = Feddes Repertorium.</reference>
    <reference>Feddes Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg. = Feddes Repertorium Specierum Novarum Regni Vegetabilis.</reference>
    <reference>Felger, R. S. 2000. Flora of the Gran Desierto and Río Colorado of Northwestern Mexico. Tucson.</reference>
    <reference>Fenzl, E. 1833. Versuch einer Darstellung der geographischen Verbreitungs- und Vertheilungs-Verhältnisse der natürlichen Familie der Alsineen.... Vienna. (Vers. Darstell. Alsin.)</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1919. The unity of the genus Arenaria. Rhodora 21: 1–7.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1921. The Gray Herbarium expedition to Nova Scotia, 1920. Rhodora 23: 89–111, 153–171, 223–245.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1922c. Notes on the flora of western Nova Scotia 1921. Rhodora 24: 157–180, 201–208.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1936c. Notes on Paronychia, Anychia. Rhodora 38: 416–421.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1940b. Some spermatophytes of eastern North America. Rhodora 42: 239–276.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1943f. Virginian botanizing under restrictions. Part I. Field studies of 1942 and 1943. Rhodora 45: 357–413.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1950. Gray’s Manual of Botany, ed. 8. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Fewkes, J. W. 1896. A contribution to ethnobotany. Amer. Anthropol. 9: 14–21.</reference>
    <reference>Field &amp; Lab. = Field &amp; Laboratory.</reference>
    <reference>Firbank, L. G. 1988. Biological flora of the British Isles. 165. Agrostemma githago L. (Lychnis githago (L.) Scop.). J. Ecol. 76: 1232–1246.</reference>
    <reference>Fischer, F. E. L. von and C. A. von Meyer. 1841–1842. Enumeratio...Plantarum Novarum.... 2 parts. St. Petersburg and Leipzig. [Parts paged independently.] (Enum. Pl. Nov.)</reference>
    <reference>Fishbein, M. 1993. Noteworthy collections: Mexico. Rumex orthoneurus Rech. f. (Polygonaceae). Madroño 40: 271.</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Alaska Yukon—See: E. Hultén 1941–1950</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Aleut. Isl.—See: E. Hultén 1937</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Alpes Marit.—See: E. Burnat et al. 1892–1931</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Altaica—See: C. F. von Ledebour 1829–1833</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Amer. Sept.—See: F. Pursh [1813] 1814</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Angl.—See: W. Hudson 1762</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Arct. URSS—See: A. I. Tolmatchew 1960–1987</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Atlant.—See: R. L. Desfontaines [1798–1799]</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Auvergne ed. 2—See: A. Delarbre 1800</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Belg.—See: B. C. J. Dumortier 1827</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Bor.-Amer.—See: W. J. Hooker [1829–]1833–1840; A. Michaux 1803</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Boston. ed. 2—See: J. Bigelow 1824</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Boston. ed. 3—See: J. Bigelow 1840</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Bras.—See: C. F. P. von Martius et al. 1840–1906</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Bras. Merid.—See: A. St.-Hilaire et al. 1824[–1833]</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Brit.—See: J. E. Smith 1800–1804</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Calif.—See: W. L. Jepson 1909–1943</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Carol.—See: T. Walter 1788</reference>
    <reference>Fl. ech.—See: J. S. Presl and C. B. Presl 1819</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Centre France ed. 3—See: A. Boreau 1857</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Chil.—See: C. Gay 1845–1854</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Colorado—See: P. A. Rydberg 1906</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Comit. Temesiensis—See: V. von Borbás 1884</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Dan.—See: G. C. Oeder et al. [1761–]1764–1883</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Env. Paris ed. 2—See: J. L. Thuillier 1799</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Franç. ed. 3—See: J. Lamarck and A. P. de Candolle 1805[–1815]</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Francisc.—See: E. L. Greene 1891–1897</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Helv.—See: J. Gaudin 1828–1833</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Idaho—See: R. J. Davis 1952</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Ital.—See: F. Parlatore 1848–1896</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Lapp.—See: G. Wahlenberg 1812</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Londin.—See: W. Curtis [1775–]1777–1798</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Ludov.—See: C. S. Rafinesque 1817</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Maine et Loire—See: J. P. Guépin 1838</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Medit. = Flora Mediterranea; Acta Herbarii Mediterranei Panormitani sub Auspiciis Societatis Botanicorum Mediterraneorum “Optima” Nuncupata Edita.</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Montpellier—See: H. Loret and A. Barrandon 1876</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Murmansk. Obl.—See: B. N. Gorodkov and A. I. Pojarkova 1953–1966</reference>
    <reference>Fl. N. Amer.—See: J. Torrey and A. Gray 1838–1843</reference>
    <reference>Fl. N. Mitt.-Deutschland ed. 9—See: C. A. F. Garcke 1869</reference>
    <reference>Fl. N.W. Amer.—See: T. J. Howell 1897–1903</reference>
    <reference>Fl. N.W. Coast—See: C. V. Piper and R. K. Beattie 1915</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Palouse Reg.—See: C. V. Piper and R. K. Beattie 1901</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Pl. Ferns Mt. Diablo—See: M. L. Bowerman 1944</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Rocky Mts.—See: P. A. Rydberg 1917</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Ross.—See: C. F. von Ledebour [1841]1842–1853</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Scand. Prodr. ed. 2—See: A. J. Retzius 1795</reference>
    <reference>Fl. S.E. U.S.—See: J. K. Small 1903</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Sicul.—See: C. B. Presl 1826</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Sicul. Prodr.—See: G. Gussone 1827–1843</reference>
    <reference>Fl. South. U.S.—See: A. W. Chapman 1860</reference>
    <reference>Fl. South. U.S. ed. 3—See: A. W. Chapman 1897</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Taur.-Caucas.—See: F. A. Marschall von Bieberstein 1808–1819</reference>
    <reference>Fl. URSS—See: V. L. Komarov et al. 1934–1964</reference>
    <reference>Fl. Vosges—See: E.-L. Berher 1887</reference>
    <reference>Fl. W. Calif.—See: W. L. Jepson 1901</reference>
    <reference>Flexner, S. B. and L. C. Hauck, eds. 1987. The Random House Dictionary of the English Language, ed. 2 unabridged. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Flora = Flora; oder (allgemeine) botanische Zeitung. [Vols. 1–16, 1818–33, include “Beilage” and “Ergänzungsblätter”; vols. 17–25, 1834–42, include “Beiblatt” and “Intelligenzblatt.”]</reference>
    <reference>Florida Sci. = Florida Scientist.</reference>
    <reference>Folia Geobot. Phytotax. = Folia Geobotanica et Phytotaxonomica.</reference>
    <reference>Foreman, D. B., N. G. Walsh, and T. J. Entwisle, eds. 1993–1999. Flora of Victoria. 4 vols. Melbourne and Sydney.</reference>
    <reference>Fors. Oecon. Plantel. ed. 3—See: J. W. Hornemann 1821–1837</reference>
    <reference>Fox, G. A. 1989. Consequences of flowering-time variation in a desert annual: Adaptation and history. Ecology 70: 1294–1306.</reference>
    <reference>Fox, G. A. 1990. Components of flowering time variation in a desert annual. Evolution 44: 1404–1423.</reference>
    <reference>Fox, G. A. 1990b. Perennation and the persistence of annual life histories. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 135: 829–840.</reference>
    <reference>Franklin, J. et al. 1823. Narrative of a Journey to the Shores of the Polar Sea, in the Years 1819, 20, 21 and 22. London. [Richardson: Appendix VII. Botanical appendix, pp. [729]–778, incl. bryophytes by Schwägrichen, algae and lichens by Hooker. Brown: Addenda [to Appendix VII], pp. 779–784.] (Narr. Journey Polar Sea)</reference>
    <reference>Frémont, J. C. 1843–1845. Report of the Exploring Expedition to the Rocky Mountains in the Year 1842, and to Oregon and North California in the Year 1843–44. 2 parts. Washington. [Parts paged consecutively.] (Rep. Exped. Rocky Mts.)</reference>
    <reference>Fremontia = Fremontia: Journal of the California Native Plant Society.</reference>
    <reference>Fries, E. M. 1832–1845. Novitiarum Florae Suecicae Mantissa.... 3 vols. Lund. (Novit. Fl. Suec. Mant.)</reference>
    <reference>Fruct. Sem. Pl.—See: J. Gaertner 1788–1791[–1792]</reference>
    <reference>Fuller, T. C. and E. McClintock. 1986. Poisonous Plants of California. Berkeley.</reference>
    <reference>Gaertner, J. 1788–1791[–1792]. De Fructibus et Seminibus Plantarum.... 2 vols. Stuttgart and Tübingen. [Vol. 1 in 1 part only, 1788. Vol. 2 in 4 parts paged consecutively: pp. 1–184, 1790; pp. 185–352, 353–504, 1791; pp. 505–520, 1792.] (Fruct. Sem. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Gaertner, P. G., B. Meyer, and J. Scherbius. 1799–1802. Oekonomisch-technische Flora der Wetterau. 3 vols. Frankfurt am Main. [Vols. 1 and 2 paged independently, vol. 3 in 2 parts paged independently.] (Oekon. Fl. Wetterau)</reference>
    <reference>Gagnepain, F. 1908. Contribution à la connaissance du genre Polycarpaea Lamk. J. Bot. (Morot), sér. 2, 1: 275–280.</reference>
    <reference>Garcke, C. A. F. 1869. Flora von Nord- und Mittel-Deutschland..., ed. 9. Berlin. (Fl. N. Mitt.-Deutschland ed. 9)</reference>
    <reference>Gard. Dict. ed. 8—See: P. Miller 1768</reference>
    <reference>Gard. Dict. Abr. ed. 4—See: P. Miller 1754</reference>
    <reference>Gartenflora = Gartenflora; Monatsschrift für deutsche und schweizerische Garten- und Blumenkunde.</reference>
    <reference>Gasquez, J. et al. 1978. Essai de taxonomie d’une espèce adventice annuelle: Polygonum aviculare L. Ann. Amélior. Pl. 28: 565–577.</reference>
    <reference>Gaudin, J. 1828–1833. Flora Helvetica.... 7 vols. Zürich. (Fl. Helv.)</reference>
    <reference>Gay, C. 1845–1854. Historia Física y Política de Chile.... Botánica [Flora Chilena]. 8 vols., atlas. Paris. (Fl. Chil.)</reference>
    <reference>Gen. Hist.—See: G. Don 1831–1838</reference>
    <reference>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.—See: T. Nuttall 1818</reference>
    <reference>Gen. Pl.—See: S. L. Endlicher 1836–1840[–1850]; N. M. Wolf 1776</reference>
    <reference>Gen. Pl. ed. 5—See: C. Linnaeus 1754</reference>
    <reference>Gen. Sp. Pl.—See: M. Lagasca y Segura 1816b</reference>
    <reference>Genes Genet. Systems = Genes and Genetic Systems.</reference>
    <reference>Gentes Herb. = Gentes Herbarum; Occasional Papers on the Kinds of Plants.</reference>
    <reference>Geobios (Jodhpur) = Geobios; an International (Bimonthly) Journal of Life Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Ges. Naturf. Freunde Berlin Mag. Neuesten Entdeck. Gesammten Naturk. = Der Gesellschaft naturforschender Freunde zu Berlin Magazin für die neuesten Entdeckungen in der gesammten Naturkunde.</reference>
    <reference>Ges. Naturf. Freunde Berlin Neue Schriften = Der Gesellschaft naturforschender Freunde zu Berlin, neue Schriften.</reference>
    <reference>Gifford, E. W. 1936. Northeastern and western Yavapai. Univ. Calif. Publ. Amer. Archaeol. Ethnol. 34: 247–345.</reference>
    <reference>Gilbert, M. G. 1987. The taxonomic position of the genera Telephium and Corrigiola. Taxon 36: 47–49.</reference>
    <reference>Gleason, H. A. 1952. The New Britton and Brown Illustrated Flora of the Northeastern United States and Adjacent Canada. 3 vols. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Good, D. A. 1984. Revision of the Mexican and Central American species of Cerastium. Rhodora 86: 339–379.</reference>
    <reference>Goodman, G. J. 1934. A revision of the North American species of the genus Chorizanthe. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 21: 1–102.</reference>
    <reference>Goodman, G. J. 1957. The genus Centrostegia, tribe Eriogoneae. Leafl. W. Bot. 8: 125–128.</reference>
    <reference>Gorodkov, B. N. and A. I. Pojarkova, eds. 1953–1966. Flora Murmanskoi Oblasti. 5 vols. Moscow. (Fl. Murmansk. Obl.)</reference>
    <reference>Graham, S. A. and C. E. Wood Jr. 1965. The genera of Polygonaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 46: 91–113.</reference>
    <reference>Gray, A. 1867. A Manual of the Botany of the Northern United States..., ed. 5. New York and Chicago. [Pteridophytes by D. C. Eaton.] (Manual ed. 5)</reference>
    <reference>Gray, A., S. Watson, and J. M. Coulter. 1890. A Manual of the Botany of the Northern United States..., ed. 6. New York and Chicago. (Manual ed. 6)</reference>
    <reference>Gray, S. F. 1821. A Natural Arrangement of British Plants.... 2 vols. London. (Nat. Arr. Brit. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Great Basin Naturalist Mem. = Great Basin Naturalist Memoirs.</reference>
    <reference>Great Plains Flora Association 1977. Atlas of the Flora of the Great Plains. Ames.</reference>
    <reference>Great Plains Flora Association 1986. Flora of the Great Plains. Lawrence, Kans.</reference>
    <reference>Greene, E. L. 1891–1897. Flora Franciscana. An Attempt to Classify and Describe the Vascular Plants of Middle California. 4 parts. San Francisco. [Parts paged consecutively.] (Fl. Francisc.)</reference>
    <reference>Greuter, W. 1995. Silene (Caryophyllaceae) in Greece—A subgeneric and sectional classification. Taxon 44: 542–581.</reference>
    <reference>Grinnell, G. B. 1923. The Cheyenne Indians: Their History and Ways of Life. 2 vols. New Haven and London. [Reprinted 1972, Lincoln, Nebr.]</reference>
    <reference>Grønland—See: H. J. Rink 1852–1857</reference>
    <reference>Guépin, J. P. 1838. Flore de Maine et Loire.... Paris. (Fl. Maine et Loire)</reference>
    <reference>Gunckel, J. E., ed. 1969. Current Topics in Plant Science. New York. (Curr. Topics Pl. Sci.)</reference>
    <reference>Gussone, G. 1827–1843. Florae Siculae Prodromus.... 2 vols. + suppl. Naples. (Fl. Sicul. Prodr.)</reference>
    <reference>Gustafson, D. J., G. Romano, R. E. Latham, and J. K. Morton. 2003. Amplified fragment length polymorphism analysis of genetic relationships among the serpentine barrens endemic Cerastium velutinum Rafinesque var. villosissimum Pennell (Caryophyllaceae) and closely related Cerastium species. J. Torrey Bot. Soc. 130: 218–223.</reference>
    <reference>Hall, C. A. Jr. and V. Doyle-Jones, eds. 1988. Plant Biology of Eastern California. Los Angeles.</reference>
    <reference>Hammer, K., P. Hanelt, and H. Knupffer. 1982. Vorarbeiten zur monographischen Darstellung von Wildpflanzensortimenten: Agrostemma L. (Studies towards a monographic treatment of wild plant collections: Agrostemma L.) Kulturpflanze 30: 45–96.</reference>
    <reference>Handb. Nat. Pfl.-Syst.—See: H. G. L. Reichenbach 1837</reference>
    <reference>Handb. Skand. Fl.—See: C. J. Hartman 1820</reference>
    <reference>Handbuch—See: J. H. F. Link 1829–1833</reference>
    <reference>Hannover. Mag. = Hannoverisches Magazin worin kleine Abhandlungen...gesamlet (gesammelt) und aufbewahret sind.</reference>
    <reference>Haraldsen, K. B. and J. Wesenberg. 1993. Population genetic analysis of an amphi-Atlantic species: Lychnis alpina (Caryophyllaceae). Nordic J. Bot. 13: 377–387.</reference>
    <reference>Haraldson, K. 1978. Anatomy and taxonomy in Polygonaceae subfam. Polygonoideae Meisn. emend. Jaretzky. Acta Univ. Upsal., Symb. Bot. Upsal. 22: 1–93.</reference>
    <reference>Hardham, C. B. 1989. Chromosome numbers of some annual species of Chorizanthe and related genera (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae). Phytologia 66: 89–94.</reference>
    <reference>Harriman, N. A. 1981b. In: IOPB chromosome number reports LXX. Taxon 30: 68–80.</reference>
    <reference>Harrington, H. D. 1954. Manual of the Plants of Colorado. Denver.</reference>
    <reference>Harris, S. K. 1965. Notes on the flora of Coös County, New Hampshire. Rhodora 67: 195–197.</reference>
    <reference>Harris, W. 1969. Seed characters and organ size in the cytotaxonomy of Rumex acetosella L. New Zealand J. Bot. 7: 125–141.</reference>
    <reference>Harris, W. 1973. Leaf form and panicle height variability in Rumex acetosella L. New Zealand J. Bot. 11: 115–144.</reference>
    <reference>Hart, J. A. 1981. The ethnobotany of the Northern Cheyenne Indians of Montana. J. Ethnopharmacol. 4: 1–55.</reference>
    <reference>Hartman, C. J. 1820. Handbok i Skandinaviens Flora, Innefettande Sveriges och Norriges Vexter, till och med Mossorna. Stockholm. (Handb. Skand. Fl.)</reference>
    <reference>Hartman, R. L. 1971. The Family Caryophyllaceae in Wyoming. M.S. thesis. University of Wyoming.</reference>
    <reference>Hartman, R. L. 1972. [Flora of Wyoming] Caryophyllaceae. Res. J. Wyoming Agric. Exp. Sta. 64: 14–45.</reference>
    <reference>Hartman, R. L. 1974. Rocky Mountain species of Paronychia (Caryophyllaceae): A morphological, cytological, and chemical study. Brittonia 26: 256–263.</reference>
    <reference>Hartman, R. L. 1979. Cerastium clawsonii (Caryphyllaceae): A synonym of Linum hudsonioides (Linaceae). Rhodora 81: 283.</reference>
    <reference>Hartman, R. L. 1993. Arenaria. In: J. C. Hickman, ed. 1993. The Jepson Manual. Higher Plants of California. Berkeley, Los Angeles, and London. Pp. 478–480.</reference>
    <reference>Hartman, R. L. and R. K. Rabeler. 2004. New combinations in North American Caryophyllaceae. Sida 21: 753–754.</reference>
    <reference>Harvard Pap. Bot. = Harvard Papers in Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Hawkes, C. V. and E. S. Menges. 1995. Density and seed production of a Florida endemic, Polygonella basiramia, in relation to time since fire and open sand. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 133: 138–149.</reference>
    <reference>Hedberg, O. 1997. The genus Koenigia L. emend. Hedberg (Polygonaceae). Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 124: 295–330.</reference>
    <reference>Hedges, K. 1986. Santa Ysabel Ethnobotany. San Diego. [Ethnic Technol. Notes 20.]</reference>
    <reference>Heide, O. M., K. Pederson, and E. Dahl. 1990. Environmental control of flowering and morphology in the high arctic Cerastium regelii, and the taxonomic status of C. jenisejense. Nordic J. Bot. 10: 141–147.</reference>
    <reference>Heldreich, T. [1851.] Plantae Atticae, a. 1848. N.p. [Indelible autograph list.] (Pl. Atticae)</reference>
    <reference>Heller, A. A. 1898. Catalogue of North American Plants North of Mexico, Exclusive of the Lower Cryptogams. [Lancaster, Pa.] (Cat. N. Amer. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Herman, K. D. 1996. Gypsophila paniculata. Baby’s-breath. In: J. M. Randall and J. Marinelli, eds. 1996. Invasive Plants: Weeds of the Global Garden. Brooklyn. P. 78.</reference>
    <reference>Hermann, F. 1937. Übersicht über die Herniaria-Arten des Berliner Harbars. Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg. 42: 203–224.</reference>
    <reference>Hess, W. J. and J. L. Reveal. 1976. A revision of Eriogonum (Polygonaceae) subgenus Pterogonum. Great Basin Naturalist 36: 281–333.</reference>
    <reference>Heynhold, G. 1846[–1847]. Alphabetische und synonymische Aufzählung der...Gewächse.... Dresden and Leipzig. (Alph. Aufz. Gew.)</reference>
    <reference>Hickman, J. C. 1971. Arenaria, section Eremogone (Caryophyllaceae) in the Pacific Northwest: A key and discussion. Madroño 21: 201–207.</reference>
    <reference>Hickman, J. C. 1984. Nomenclatural changes in Polygonum, Persicaria and Rumex (Polygonaceae). Madroño 31: 249–252.</reference>
    <reference>Hickman, J. C., ed. 1993. The Jepson Manual. Higher Plants of California. Berkeley, Los Angeles, and London.</reference>
    <reference>Hickman, J. C. 1993b. Geographic subdivisions of California. In: J. C. Hickman, ed. 1993. The Jepson Manual. Higher Plants of California. Berkeley, Los Angeles, and London. Pp. 37–46.</reference>
    <reference>Hickman, J. C. 1993c. Polygonaceae. In: J. C. Hickman, ed. 1993. The Jepson Manual. Higher Plants of California. Berkeley, Los Angeles, and London. Pp. 854–895.</reference>
    <reference>Hickman, J. C. and C. S. Hickman. 1978. Polygonum perfoliatum: A recent Asiatic adventive. Bartonia 45: 18–23.</reference>
    <reference>Hiitonen, H. I. A. [1933.] Suomen Kasvio.... Helsinki. (Suom. Kasvio)</reference>
    <reference>Hill, J. 1759–1775. The Vegetable System.... 26 vols. London. (Veg. Syst.)</reference>
    <reference>Hill, J. 1768. Hortus Kewensis. London. (Hort. Kew.)</reference>
    <reference>Hinds, H. R. 1995. Nomenclatural changes in Polygonum, Persicaria, and Aconogonon (Polygonaceae). Novon 5: 165–166.</reference>
    <reference>Hinds, H. R. 2000. Flora of New Brunswick..., ed. 2. Fredericton.</reference>
    <reference>Hinton, L. 1975. Notes on La Huerta Diegueno ethnobotany. J. Calif. Anthropol. 2: 214–222.</reference>
    <reference>Hist. Nat. Vég.—See: E. Spach 1834–1848</reference>
    <reference>Hist. Pl. Dauphiné—See: D. Villars 1786–1789</reference>
    <reference>Hitchcock, C. L. 1964. Polygonaceae. In: C. L. Hitchcock et al. 1955–1969. Vascular Plants of the Pacific Northwest. 5 vols. Seattle. Vol. 2, pp. 102–182.</reference>
    <reference>Hitchcock, C. L. and A. Cronquist. 1973. Flora of the Pacific Northwest: An Illustrated Manual. Seattle.</reference>
    <reference>Hitchcock, C. L., A. Cronquist, M. Ownbey, and J. W. Thompson. 1955–1969. Vascular Plants of the Pacific Northwest. 5 vols. Seattle. [Univ. Wash. Publ. Biol. 17.] (Vasc. Pl. Pacif. N.W.)</reference>
    <reference>Hitchcock, C. L. and B. Maguire. 1947. A Revision of the North American Species of Silene. Seattle. [Univ. Wash. Publ. Biol. 13.] (Revis. N. Amer. Silene)</reference>
    <reference>Hocking, G. M. 1956. Some plant materials used medicinally and otherwise by the Navaho Indians in the Chaco Canyon, New Mexico. Palacio 56: 146–165.</reference>
    <reference>Hoffmann, G. F. [1791–1804.] Deutschland Flora oder botanisches Taschenbuch.... 4 vols. Erlangen. (Deutschl. Fl.)</reference>
    <reference>Hong, S. P. 1991. A revision of Aconogonon (= Polygonum sect. Aconogonon, Polygonaceae) in North America. Rhodora 93: 322–346.</reference>
    <reference>Hong, S. P. 1993. Reconsideration of the generic status of Rubrivena (Polygonaceae, Persicarieae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 186: 95–122.</reference>
    <reference>Hong, S. P., L.-P. Ronse Decraene, and E. Smets. 1998. Systematic significance of tepal surface morphology in tribes Persicarieae and Polygoneae (Polygonaceae). Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 127: 91–116.</reference>
    <reference>Hooker, W. J. [1829–]1833–1840. Flora Boreali-Americana; or, the Botany of the Northern Parts of British America.... 2 vols. in 12 parts. London, Paris, and Strasbourg. (Fl. Bor.-Amer.)</reference>
    <reference>Hooker, W. J. and G. A. W. Arnott. [1830–]1841. The Botany of Captain Beechey’s Voyage; Comprising an Account of the Plants Collected by Messrs Lay and Collie, and Other Officers of the Expedition, during the Voyage to the Pacific and Bering’s Strait, Performed in His Majesty’s Ship Blossom, under the Command of Captain F. W. Beechey...in the Years 1825, 26, 27, and 28. 10 parts. London. [Parts paged and plates numbered consecutively.] (Bot. Beechey Voy.)</reference>
    <reference>Hooker’s J. Bot. Kew Gard. Misc. = Hooker’s Journal of Botany and Kew Garden Miscellany.</reference>
    <reference>Hornemann, J. W. 1821–1837. Forsøg til en Dansk Oeconomisk Plantelaere, ed. 3. 2 vols. Copenhagen. (Fors. Oecon. Plantel. ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Hort. Kew.—See: J. Hill 1768</reference>
    <reference>Horton, J. H. 1963. A taxonomic revision of Polygonella (Polygonaceae). Brittonia 15: 177–203.</reference>
    <reference>Horton, J. H. 1972. Studies of the southeastern United States flora. IV. Polygonaceae. J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. 88: 92–102.</reference>
    <reference>Hortus Kew.—See: W. Aiton and W. T. Aiton 1810–1813</reference>
    <reference>Houttuyn, M. 1773–1783. Natuurlijke Historie of Uitvoerige Beschrijving der Dieren, Planten en Mineraalen, Volgens het Samenstel van den Heer Linnaeus. Met Naauwkeurige Afbeeldingen. Tweede Deels [Planten].... 14 fasc. Amsterdam. (Nat. Hist.)</reference>
    <reference>Howard, R. A. 1958. A history of the genus Coccoloba in cultivation. Baileya 6: 204–212.</reference>
    <reference>Howell, J. T. 1941. Notes on Polycarpon. Leafl. W. Bot. 3: 80.</reference>
    <reference>Howell, J. T., P. H. Raven, and P. Rubtzoff. 1958. A flora of San Francisco, California. Wasmann J. Biol. 16: 1–157.</reference>
    <reference>Howell, T. J. 1897–1903. A Flora of Northwest America. 1 vol. in 8 fasc. Portland. [Fasc. 1–7 (text) paged consecutively, fasc. 8 (index) independently.] (Fl. N.W. Amer.)</reference>
    <reference>Hudson, W. 1762. Flora Anglica.... London. (Fl. Angl.)</reference>
    <reference>Hultén, E. 1937. Flora of the Aleutian Islands and Westernmost Alaska Peninsula with Notes on the Flora of Commander Islands.... Stockholm. (Fl. Aleut. Isl.)</reference>
    <reference>Hultén, E. 1941–1950. Flora of Alaska and Yukon. 10 vols. Lund and Leipzig. [Vols. paged consecutively and designated as simultaneous numbers of Lunds Univ. Årsskr. (= Acta Univ. Lund.) and Kungl. Fysiogr. Sällsk. Handl.] (Fl. Alaska Yukon)</reference>
    <reference>Hultén, E. 1943. Stellaria longipes and its allies. Bot. Not. 1943: 251–270.</reference>
    <reference>Hultén, E. 1956. The Cerastium alpinum complex. A case of world-wide introgressive hybridization. Svensk Bot. Tidskr. 50: 411–495.</reference>
    <reference>Hultén, E. 1964. Remarkable range extension for Minuartia groenlandica (Retz.) Ostenf. Svensk Bot. Tidskr. 58: 432–435.</reference>
    <reference>Hultén, E. 1968. Flora of Alaska and Neighboring Territories: A Manual of the Vascular Plants. Stanford.</reference>
    <reference>Hultén, E. 1973. Supplement to Flora of Alaska and Neighboring Territories. A study in the flora of Alaska and the transberingian connections. Bot. Not. 126: 459–512.</reference>
    <reference>Hutchinson, J. 1973. The Families of Flowering Plants, ed. 3. Oxford.</reference>
    <reference>Icon.—See: A. J. Cavanilles 1791–1801</reference>
    <reference>Ikonnikov, S. S. 1973. Zametki o gvozdichnykh (Caryophyllaceae). I. O rode Eremogone Fenzl. Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast. 10: 136–142.</reference>
    <reference>Ill. Fl. Pacific States—See: L. Abrams and R. S. Ferris 1923–1960</reference>
    <reference>Index Kew.—See: B. D. Jackson et al. [1893–]1895+</reference>
    <reference>Index Seminum (Berlin), App. = Index Seminum (Berlin), Appendix.</reference>
    <reference>Index Seminum (Dorpat) = Index Seminum Horti Academici Dorpatensis.</reference>
    <reference>Index Seminum (St. Petersburg) = Index Seminum, Quae Hortus Botanicus Imperialis Petropolitanus pro Mutua Commutatione Offert.</reference>
    <reference>Ives, J. C. 1861. Report upon the Colorado River of the West, Explored in 1857 and 1858 by Lieutenant Joseph C. Ives.... 5 parts, appendices. Washington. (Rep. Colorado R.)</reference>
    <reference>J. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia = Journal of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.</reference>
    <reference>J. Agric. Food Chem. = Journal of Agricultural and Food Chemistry.</reference>
    <reference>J. Appl. Ecol. = Journal of Applied Ecology.</reference>
    <reference>J. Arnold Arbor. = Journal of the Arnold Arboretum.</reference>
    <reference>J. Bot. = Journal of Botany, British and Foreign.</reference>
    <reference>J. Bot. (Morot) = Journal de Botanique. [Edited by L. Morot.]</reference>
    <reference>J. Calif. Anthropol. = Journal of California Anthropology.</reference>
    <reference>J. Ecol. = Journal of Ecology.</reference>
    <reference>J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. = Journal of the Elisha Mitchell Scientific Society.</reference>
    <reference>J. Ethnopharmacol. = Journal of Ethnopharmacology; Interdisciplinary Journal Devoted to Bioscientific Research on Indigenous Drugs.</reference>
    <reference>J. Hist. Nat. = Journal d’Histoire Naturelle.</reference>
    <reference>J. Jap. Bot. = Journal of Japanese Botany.</reference>
    <reference>J. Lepid. Soc. = Journal of the Lepidopterists’ Society.</reference>
    <reference>J. Linn. Soc., Bot. = Journal of the Linnean Society. Botany.</reference>
    <reference>J. Pl. Biol. = Journal of Plant Biology.</reference>
    <reference>J. Range Managem. = Journal of Range Management.</reference>
    <reference>J. Torrey Bot. Soc. = Journal of the Torrey Botanical Society.</reference>
    <reference>J. Wash. Acad. Sci. = Journal of the Washington Academy of Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Jackson, B. D. et al., comps. [1893–]1895+. Index Kewensis Plantarum Phanerogamarum.... 2 vols. + 21+ suppls. Oxford. (Index Kew.)</reference>
    <reference>Jacquin, N. J. 1760. Enumeratio Systematica Plantarum, Quas in Insulis Caribaeis Vicinaque Americes Continente Detexit Novas.... Leiden. (Enum. Syst. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Jacquin, N. J. 1762. Enumeratio Stirpium Plerarumque, Quae Sponte Crescunt in Agro Vindobonensi, Montibusque Confinibus. Vienna. (Enum. Stirp. Vindob.)</reference>
    <reference>Jahrb. Wiss. Bot. = Jahrbücher für wissenschaftliche Botanik.</reference>
    <reference>Jaretzky, R. 1928. Histologische und karyologische Studien an Polygonaceen. Jahrb. Wiss. Bot. 69: 357–490.</reference>
    <reference>Jepson, W. L. 1901. A Flora of Western Middle California.... Berkeley. (Fl. W. Calif.)</reference>
    <reference>Jepson, W. L. 1909–1943. A Flora of California.... 3 vols. in 12 parts. San Francisco etc. [Pagination consecutive within each vol.; vol. 1 page sequence independent of part number sequence (chronological); part 8 of vol. 1 (pp. 1–32, 579–index) never published.] (Fl. Calif.)</reference>
    <reference>Jepson, W. L. [1923–1925.] A Manual of the Flowering Plants of California.... Berkeley. (Man. Fl. Pl. Calif.)</reference>
    <reference>Jessen, K. F. W. 1879. Deutsche Excursions-Flora. Hannover. (Deut. Excurs.-Fl.)</reference>
    <reference>Johnston, A. 1987. Plants and the Blackfoot. Lethbridge, Alta.</reference>
    <reference>Jones, D. M. and T. R. Mertens. 1970. A taxonomic study of genus Polygonum employing chromatographic methods. Proc. Indiana Acad. Sci. 80: 422–430.</reference>
    <reference>Jonsell, B. 2001. Arenaria. In: B. Jonsell and T. Karlsson, eds. 2000+. Flora Nordica. 2+ vols. Stockholm. Vol. 2, pp. 99–104.</reference>
    <reference>Jonsell, B. and T. Karlsson, eds. 2000+. Flora Nordica. 2+ vols. Stockholm.</reference>
    <reference>Judd, W. S. 1983. The taxonomic status of Stipulicida filiformis (Caryophyllaceae). Sida 10: 33–36.</reference>
    <reference>Jurtzev, B. A. et al. 1975. Floristicheskie nakhodki v Chukotskoy tundre, 2. (Novitates pro flora Terrae Tschuktschorum, 2.) Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast. 12: 301–324.</reference>
    <reference>Kalmia = Kalmia; Botanic Journal.</reference>
    <reference>Kan, T. M. 1992. The Distribution and Ecology of the Narrow Endemic Eriogonum umbellatum var. torreyanum. M.S. thesis. University of California, Davis.</reference>
    <reference>Karlsson, T. 2000. Polygonum. In: B. Jonsell and T. Karlsson, eds. 2000+. Flora Nordica. 2+ vols. Stockholm. Vol. 1, pp. 255–273.</reference>
    <reference>Karsten, H. 1880–1883. Deutsche Flora. Pharmaceutisch-medicinische Botanik.... 13 Lieferungen. Berlin. (Deut. Fl.)</reference>
    <reference>Kartesz, J. T. 1987. A Flora of Nevada. Ph.D. thesis. 3 vols. University of Nevada, Reno.</reference>
    <reference>Kartesz, J. T. and K. N. Gandhi. 1990. Nomenclatural notes for the North American flora, II. Phytologia 68: 421–427.</reference>
    <reference>Kartesz, J. T. and C. A. Meacham. 1999. Synthesis of the North American Flora, ver. 1.0. Chapel Hill. [CD-ROM.]</reference>
    <reference>Kaul, R. B. 1986. Polygonaceae. In: Great Plains Flora Association. 1986. Flora of the Great Plains. Lawrence, Kans. Pp. 214–235.</reference>
    <reference>Kearney, T. H. and R. H. Peebles. 1960. Arizona Flora, ed. 2. Berkeley.</reference>
    <reference>Ketzner, D. M. 1996. Crepis pulchra (Asteraceae) and Moenchia erecta (Caryophyllaceae) in Illinois. Trans. Illinois State Acad. Sci. 89: 21–23.</reference>
    <reference>Kew Bull. = Kew Bulletin.</reference>
    <reference>Khalaf, M. K. and C. A. Stace. 2001. The distinction between Cerastium tomentosum Linnaeus and C. biebersteinii Candolle (Caryophyllaceae), and their occurrence in the wild in Britain. Watsonia 23: 481–491.</reference>
    <reference>Kharkevich, S. S., ed. 1985+. Plantae Vasculares Orientis Extremi Sovietici. 7+ vols. Leningrad.</reference>
    <reference>Kiger, R. W. and D. M. Porter. 2001. Categorical Glossary for the Flora of North America Project. Pittsburgh.</reference>
    <reference>Kim, J. Y. and C. W. Park. 2000. Morphological and chromosomal variation in Fallopia section Reynoutria (Polygonaceae) in Korea. Brittonia 52: 34–48.</reference>
    <reference>Kim, M. H., J. H. Park, and C. W. Park, C. W. 2000. Flavonoid chemistry of Fallopia section Fallopia (Polygonaceae). Biochem. Syst. &amp; Ecol. 28: 433–441.</reference>
    <reference>Kim, S. T., M. H. Kim, and C. W. Park. 2000. A systematic study on Fallopia section Fallopia (Polygonaceae). Korean J. Pl. Taxon. 30: 35–54.</reference>
    <reference>Kitchener, G. D. 2002. Rumex ×xenogenus Rech. fil. (Polygonaceae), the hybrid between Greek and patience docks, found in Britain. Watsonia 24: 209–213.</reference>
    <reference>Komarov, V. L., B. K. Schischkin, and E. Bobrov, eds. 1934–1964. Flora URSS.... 30 vols. Leningrad. (Fl. URSS)</reference>
    <reference>Kongl. Svenska Vetensk. Acad. Handl. = Kongl[iga]. Svenska Vetenskaps Academiens Handlingar.</reference>
    <reference>Kongl. Vetensk. Acad. Nya Handl. = Kongl[iga]. Vetenskaps Academiens Nya Handlingar.</reference>
    <reference>Korean J. Pl. Taxon. = Korean Journal of Plant Taxonomy.</reference>
    <reference>Kozhevnikov, Y. P. 1985. De Caryophyllaceis notae criticae. Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast. 22: 95–114.</reference>
    <reference>Kral, R., ed. 1983. A Report on Some Rare, Threatened, or Endangered Forest-related Vascular Plants of the South. 2 vols. Washington. [U.S.D.A. Forest Serv., Techn. Publ. R8-TP 2.]</reference>
    <reference>Kruckeberg, A. R. 1961. Artificial crosses of western North American silenes. Brittonia 13: 305–333.</reference>
    <reference>Kruckeberg, A. R. 1962. Intergeneric hybrids in the Lychnideae (Caryophyllaceae). Brittonia 14: 311–321.</reference>
    <reference>Kubitzki, K. et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 4+ vols. Berlin etc.</reference>
    <reference>Kulturpflanze = Kulturpflanze. Berichte und Mitteilungen aus dem Institut für Kulturpflanzenforschung der Deutschen Akademie der Wissenschaften zu Berlin in Gatersleben Krs. Aschersleben.</reference>
    <reference>Kuntze, O. 1891–1898. Revisio Generum Plantarum Vascularium Omnium atque Cellularium Multarum.... 3 vols. Leipzig etc. (Revis. Gen. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Kurtto, A. 2001. Silene [in part]. In: B. Jonsell and T. Karlsson, eds. 2000+. Flora Nordica. 2+ vols. Stockholm. Vol. 2, pp. 183–188.</reference>
    <reference>Kurtto, A. 2001b. Honckenya. In: B. Jonsell and T. Karlsson, eds. 2000+. Flora Nordica. 2+ vols. Stockholm. Vol. 2, pp. 106–109.</reference>
    <reference>Kuyper, K. F., U. Yandell, and R. S. Nowak. 1997. On the taxonomic status of Eriogonum robustum (Polygonaceae), a rare endemic in western Nevada. Great Basin Naturalist 57: 1–10.</reference>
    <reference>Kuzmina, M. L. 2002. The sections Macrolepides (F. N. Williams) Klok. and Barbulatum F. N. Williams of the genus Dianthus L. (Caryophyllaceae) in East Europe and the Caucasus. Komarovia 2: 29–54.</reference>
    <reference>Kuzmina, M. L. 2003. The sections Carthusiani and Armerium of the genus Dianthus (Caryophyllaceae) in East Europe and the Caucasus. Komarovia 3: 85–102.</reference>
    <reference>Lagasca y Segura, M. 1816b. Genera et Species Plantarum.... Madrid. (Gen. Sp. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Lakela, O. 1962. Occurrence of species of Polycarpaea Lam. (Caryophyllaceae) in North America. Rhodora 64: 179–182.</reference>
    <reference>Lakela, O. 1963. Annotation of North American Polycarpaea. Rhodora 6: 35–44.</reference>
    <reference>Lamarck, J. et al. 1783–1817. Encyclopédie Méthodique. Botanique.... 13 vols. Paris and Liège. [Vols. 1–8, suppls. 1–5.] (Encycl.)</reference>
    <reference>Lamarck, J. and A. P. de Candolle. 1805[–1815]. Flore Française, ou Descriptions Succinctes de Toutes les Plantes Qui Croissent Naturellement en France..., ed. 3. 5 tomes in 6 vols. Paris. [Tomes 1–4(2), 1805; tome 5, 1815.] (Fl. Franç. ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Lamarck, J. and J. Poiret. 1791–1823. Tableau Encyclopédique et Méthodique des Trois Règnes de la Nature. Botanique.... 6 vols. Paris. [Vols. 1–2 = tome 1; vols. 3–5 = tome 2; vol. [6] = tome 3. Vols. paged consecutively within tomes.] (Tabl. Encycl.)</reference>
    <reference>Lamb Frye, A. S. and K. A. Kron. 2003. rbcL phylogeny and character evolution in Polygonaceae. Syst. Bot. 28: 326–332.</reference>
    <reference>Lambinon, J. 1981. Proposition de rejet Spergularia media (L.) C. Presl, Fl. Sic. 1: 161. 1826 (Caryophyllaceae). Taxon 30: 364.</reference>
    <reference>Landry, G. P., W. D. Reese, and C. M. Allen. 1988. Stellaria parva Pederson new to North America. Phytologia 64: 497.</reference>
    <reference>Lange, J. M. C. 1880[–1894]. Conspectus Florae Groenlandicae. 3 parts. Copenhagen. [Parts paged consecutively.] (Consp. Fl. Groenland.)</reference>
    <reference>Laubengayer, R. A. 1937. Studies in the anatomy and morphology of the polygonaceous flower. Amer. J. Bot. 24: 329–343.</reference>
    <reference>Lawrence, G. H. M. 1940. Armerias, native and cultivated. Gentes Herb. 4: 391–418.</reference>
    <reference>Lawrence, G. H. M. 1947. The genus Armeria in North America. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 37: 751–779.</reference>
    <reference>Leafl. Bot. Observ. Crit. = Leaflets of Botanical Observation and Criticism.</reference>
    <reference>Leafl. W. Bot. = Leaflets of Western Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Ledebour, C. F. von. 1829–1833. Flora Altaica. 4 vols. Berlin. (Fl. Altaica)</reference>
    <reference>Ledebour, C. F. von. [1841]1842–1853. Flora Rossica sive Enumeratio Plantarum in Totius Imperii Rossici Provinciis Europaeis, Asiaticis, et Americanis Hucusque Observatarum.... 4 vols. Stuttgart. (Fl. Ross.)</reference>
    <reference>Lefèbvre, C. 1974. Population variation and taxonomy in Armeria maritima with special reference to heavy-metal tolerant populations. New Phytol. 73: 209–219.</reference>
    <reference>Lefèbvre, C. and X. Vekemans. 1995. A numerical taxonomic study of Armeria maritima (Plumbaginaceae) in North America and Greenland. Canad. J. Bot. 73: 1583–1595.</reference>
    <reference>Lehr, J. H. 1978. A Catalogue of the Flora of Arizona. Phoenix.</reference>
    <reference>Leslie, A. C. 1983. The International Dianthus Register, ed. 2. London.</reference>
    <reference>Lewis, Mont E. 1973. Wheeler Peak Area: Species List.... N.p.</reference>
    <reference>Lewis, P. O. 1991. Allozyme Variation and Evolution in Polygonella (Polygonaceae). Ph.D. dissertation. Ohio State University.</reference>
    <reference>Lewis, P. O. 1991b. Allozyme variation in the rare Gulf Coast endemic Polygonella macrophylla Small (Polygonaceae). Pl. Spec. Biol. 6: 1–10.</reference>
    <reference>Lewis, P. O. and D. J. Crawford. 1995. Pleistocene refugium endemics exhibit greater allozymic diversity than widespread congeners in the genus Polygonella (Polygonaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 82: 141–149.</reference>
    <reference>Lex. Gen. Phan.—See: T. E. von Post and O. Kuntze 1903</reference>
    <reference>Li, H. L. 1952b. The genus Tovara (Polygonaceae). Rhodora 50: 19–25.</reference>
    <reference>Libert, B. and R. Englund. 1989. Present distribution and ecology of Rheum rhaponticum (Polygonaceae). Willdenowia 19: 91–98.</reference>
    <reference>Link, J. H. F. 1829–1833. Handbuch zur Erkennung der nutzbarsten und am häufigsten vorkommenden Gewächse.... 3 vols. Berlin. (Handbuch)</reference>
    <reference>Linnaea = Linnaea. Ein Journal für die Botanik in ihrem ganzen Umfange.</reference>
    <reference>Linnaeus, C. 1753. Species Plantarum.... 2 vols. Stockholm. (Sp. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Linnaeus, C. 1754. Genera Plantarum, ed. 5. Stockholm. (Gen. Pl. ed. 5)</reference>
    <reference>Linnaeus, C. 1758[–1759]. Systema Naturae per Regna Tria Naturae..., ed. 10. 2 vols. Stockholm. (Syst. Nat. ed. 10)</reference>
    <reference>Linnaeus, C. 1762–1763. Species Plantarum..., ed. 2. 2 vols. Stockholm. (Sp. Pl. ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Linnaeus, C. 1766–1768. Systema Naturae per Regna Tria Naturae..., ed. 12. 3 vols. Stockholm. (Syst. Nat. ed. 12)</reference>
    <reference>Linnaeus, C. 1767[–1771]. Mantissa Plantarum. 2 parts. Stockholm. [Mantissa [1] and Mantissa [2] Altera paged consecutively.] (Mant. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Little, E. L. Jr., R. O. Woodbury, and F. H. Wadsworth. 1969. Common Trees of Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands. 2 vols. Washington. [Agric. Handb. 249.]</reference>
    <reference>Lledó, M. D. et al. 1998. Systematics of Plumbaginaceae based upon cladistic analysis of rbcL sequence data. Syst. Bot. 23: 21–29.</reference>
    <reference>Loret, H. and A. Barrandon. 1876. Flore de Montpellier.... 2 vols. Montpellier and Paris. [Vols. paged consecutively.] (Fl. Montpellier)</reference>
    <reference>Lousley, J. E. 1953. Rumex cuneifolius and a new hybrid. Watsonia 2: 394–397.</reference>
    <reference>Lousley, J. E. and D. H. Kent. 1981. Docks and Knotweeds of the British Isles. London.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. 1941. Rumex tenuifolius (Wallr.) Löve, spec. nova. Bot. Not. 1941: 99–101.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. 1944. The dioecious forms of Rumex subgenus Acetosa in Scandinavia. Bot. Not. 1944: 237–254.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. 1983. The taxonomy of Acetosella. Bot. Helv. 93: 145–168.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. 1986. In: IOPB chromosome number reports XCII. Taxon 35: 610–613.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and V. Everson. 1967. The taxonomic status of Rumex paucifolius. Taxon 16: 423–425.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and B. M. Kapoor. 1967. New combinations in Acetosa and Bucephalophora. Taxon 16: 519–522.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and B. M. Kapoor. 1968. A chromosome atlas of the collective genus Rumex. Cytologia 32: 328–342.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and D. Löve. 1957. Rumex thyrsiflorus new to North America. Rhodora 59: 1–5.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and D. Löve. 1975. Nomenclatural notes on Arctic plants. Bot. Not. 128: 497–523.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and D. Löve. 1975b. Cytotaxonomical Atlas of the Arctic Flora. Vaduz.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and D. Löve. 1982. In: IOPB chromosome number reports LXXIV. Taxon 31: 119–128.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and D. Löve. 1988. In: IOPB chromosome number reports XCIX. Taxon 37: 396–399.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and P. Sarkar. 1957. Chromosomes and relationships of Koenigia islandica. Canad. J. Bot. 35: 507–514.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, D. and J.-P. Bernard. 1958. Rumex stenophyllus in North America. Rhodora 60: 54–57.</reference>
    <reference>Luteyn, J. L. 1976. Revision of Limonium (Plumbaginaceae) in eastern North America. Brittonia 28: 303–317.</reference>
    <reference>Luteyn, J. L. 1990. The Plumbaginaceae in the flora of the southeastern United States. Sida 14: 169–178.</reference>
    <reference>Macloskie, G. 1903–1914. Reports of the Princeton University Expeditions to Patagonia 1896–1899...Botany.... 2 vols. + suppl. Princeton and Stuttgart. [Vols. 1 and 2 paged consecutively; suppl. paged independently.]</reference>
    <reference>Madroño = Madroño; Journal of the California Botanical Society [from vol. 3: a West American Journal of Botany].</reference>
    <reference>Maguire, B. 1947. Studies in the Caryophyllaceae. III. A synopsis of the North American species of Arenaria sect. Eremogone Fenzl. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 74: 38–56.</reference>
    <reference>Maguire, B. 1950. Studies in the Caryophyllaceae. IV. A synopsis of the North American species of the subfamily Silenoideae. Rhodora 52: 233–245.</reference>
    <reference>Maguire, B. 1951. Studies in the Caryophyllaceae. V. Arenaria in America north of Mexico. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 46: 493–511.</reference>
    <reference>Maguire, B. 1958. Arenaria rossii and some of its relatives in America. Rhodora 60: 44–53.</reference>
    <reference>Maguire, B. 1960. Arenaria. In: T. H. Kearney and R. H. Peebles. 1960. Arizona Flora, ed. 2. Berkeley. Pp. 295–298.</reference>
    <reference>Man. Fl. Belgique ed. 2—See: F. Crépin 1866</reference>
    <reference>Man. Fl. Pl. Calif.—See: W. L. Jepson [1923–1925]</reference>
    <reference>Man. Herbor. Suisse—See: J. P. de Clairville 1811</reference>
    <reference>Man. Higher Pl. Oregon—See: M. E. Peck 1941</reference>
    <reference>Man. S. Calif. Bot.—See: P. A. Munz 1935</reference>
    <reference>Mant. Pl.—See: C. Linnaeus 1767[–1771]</reference>
    <reference>Manual ed. 5—See: A. Gray 1867</reference>
    <reference>Manual ed. 6—See: A. Gray et al. 1890</reference>
    <reference>Marschall von Bieberstein, F. A. 1808–1819. Flora Taurico-Caucasica.... 3 vols. Charkow. (Fl. Taur.-Caucas.)</reference>
    <reference>Martin, W. C. and C. R. Hutchins. 1980. A Flora of New Mexico. 2 vols. Vaduz.</reference>
    <reference>Martius, C. F. P. von, A. W. Eichler, and I. Urban, eds. 1840–1906. Flora Brasiliensis. 15 vols. in 40 parts, 130 fasc. Munich, Vienna, and Leipzig. [Volumes and parts numbered in systematic sequence, fascicles numbered independently in chronological sequence.] (Fl. Bras.)</reference>
    <reference>Mattfeld, J. 1922. Geographisch-genetische Untersuchungen über die Gattung Minuartia (L.) Hiern. Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg. Beih. 15.</reference>
    <reference>McCormick, J. F., J. R. Bozeman, and S. A. Spongberg. 1971. A taxonomic revision of granite outcrop species of Minuartia (Arenaria). Brittonia 23: 149–160.</reference>
    <reference>McDonald, C. B. 1980. A biosystematic study of the Polygonum hydropiperoides (Polygonaceae) complex. Amer. J. Bot. 67: 664–670.</reference>
    <reference>McNeill, J. 1962. Taxonomic studies in the Alsinoideae: I. Generic and infra-generic groups. Notes Roy. Bot. Gard. Edinburgh 24: 79–155.</reference>
    <reference>McNeill, J. 1978. Silene alba and S. dioica in North America and the generic delimitation of Lychnis, Melandrium and Silene (Caryophyllaceae). Canad. J. Bot. 56: 297–308.</reference>
    <reference>McNeill, J. 1980b. The delimitation of Arenaria (Caryophyllaceae) and related genera in North America, with 11 new combinations in Minuartia. Rhodora 82: 495–502.</reference>
    <reference>McNeill, J. and I. J. Bassett. 1974. Pollen morphology and the infrageneric classification of Minuartia (Caryophyllaceae). Canad. J. Bot. 52: 1225–1231.</reference>
    <reference>McNeill, J. and J. N. Findlay. 1972. Introduced perennial species of Stellaria in Quebec. Naturaliste Canad. 99: 59–60.</reference>
    <reference>Med. Repos. = Medical Repository.</reference>
    <reference>Meddel. Grønland = Meddelelser om Grønland, af Kommissionen for Ledelsen af de Geologiske og Geografiske Undersølgeser i Grønland.</reference>
    <reference>Meded. Bot. Mus. Herb. Rijks Univ. Utrecht = Mededeelingen van het Botanisch Museum en Herbarium van de Rijks Universiteit te Utrecht.</reference>
    <reference>Meerts, P., T. Baya, and C. Lefèbvre. 1998. Allozyme variation in the annual weed species complex Polygonum aviculare (Polygonaceae) in relation to ploidy level and colonizing ability. Pl. Syst. Evol. 211: 239–256.</reference>
    <reference>Meerts, P., J.-P. Briane, and C. Lefèbvre. 1990. A numerical taxonomic study of the Polygonum aviculare complex (Polygonaceae) in Belgium. Watsonia 5: 177–214.</reference>
    <reference>Meinke, R. J. and P. F. Zika. 1992. A new annual species of Minuartia (Caryophyllaceae) from Oregon and California. Madroño 39: 288–300.</reference>
    <reference>Meisner, C. F. 1826. Monographiae Generis Polygoni Prodromus. Geneva. (Monogr. Polyg.)</reference>
    <reference>Meisner, C. F. 1837–1843. Plantarum Vascularium Genera.... 2 parts in 14 fasc. Leipzig. [Parts (1: “Tab. Diagn.”; 2: “Commentarius”) issued together incrementally within fascicles and paged independently, fascicles paged consecutively for each part.] (Pl. Vasc. Gen.)</reference>
    <reference>Meisner, C. F. 1856. Rumex. In: A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, eds. 1823–1873. Prodromus Systematis Naturalis Regni Vegetabilis.... 17 vols. Paris etc. Vol. 14, pp. 41–74.</reference>
    <reference>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. Saint-Pétersbourg, Sér. 6, Sci. Math., Seconde Pt. Sci. Nat. = Mémoires de l’Académie Impériale des Sciences de Saint-Pétersbourg. Sixième Série. Sciences Mathématiques, Physiques et Naturelles. Seconde Partie: Sciences Naturelles.</reference>
    <reference>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg Divers Savans = Mémoires Présentés à l’Académie Impériale des Sciences de St.-Pétersbourg par Divers Savans et Lus dans ses Assemblées.</reference>
    <reference>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St. Pétersbourg Hist. Acad. = Mémoires de l’Académie Impériale des Sciences de St. Pétersbourg. Avec l’Histoire de l’Académie.</reference>
    <reference>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg, Sér. 6, Sci. Math. = Mémoires de l’Académie Impériale des Sciences de St.-Pétersbourg. Sixième Série. Sciences Mathématiques, Physiques et Naturelles.</reference>
    <reference>Mem. Amer. Acad. Arts = Memoirs of the American Academy of Arts and Science.</reference>
    <reference>Mem. Amer. Anthropol. Assoc. = Memoirs of the American Anthropological Association.</reference>
    <reference>Mem. New York Bot. Gard. = Memoirs of the New York Botanical Garden.</reference>
    <reference>Mem. Reale Accad. Sci. Torino = Memorie della Reale Accademia delle Scienze di Torino</reference>
    <reference>Mem. Torrey Bot. Club = Memoirs of the Torrey Botanical Club.</reference>
    <reference>Mem. Tour N. Mexico—See: F. A. Wislizenus 1848</reference>
    <reference>Memoranda Soc. Fauna Fl. Fenn. = Memoranda Societatis pro Fauna et Flora Fennica.</reference>
    <reference>Mentzelia = Mentzelia; Journal of the Northern Nevada Native Plant Society.</reference>
    <reference>Merriam-Webster 1988. Webster’s New Geographical Dictionary. Springfield, Mass.</reference>
    <reference>Mertens, T. R. and P. H. Raven. 1965. Taxonomy of Polygonum, section Polygonum (Avicularia) in North America. Madroño 18: 85–92.</reference>
    <reference>Meth. Pl.—See: J. A. Scopoli 1754</reference>
    <reference>Methodus—See: C. Moench 1794</reference>
    <reference>Meyer, C. A. von. 1831. Verzeichniss der Pflanzen...Reise im Caucasus und in den Provinzen am westlichen Ufer des Caspischen Meeres gefunden.... St. Petersburg. (Verz. Pfl. Casp. Meer.)</reference>
    <reference>Michaux, A. 1803. Flora Boreali-Americana.... 2 vols. Paris and Strasbourg. (Fl. Bor.-Amer.)</reference>
    <reference>Michigan Agric. Exp. Sta. Bull. = Michigan Agricultural Experiment Station. Bulletin.</reference>
    <reference>Michigan Bot. = Michigan Botanist.</reference>
    <reference>Middendorff, A. T. von. 1847–1867. Reise in den äussersten Norden und Osten Siberiens während der Jahre 1843 und 1844.... 4 vols. in parts and fasc. St. Petersburg. (Reise Siber.)</reference>
    <reference>Miller, P. 1754. The Gardeners Dictionary.... Abridged..., ed. 4. 3 vols. London. (Gard. Dict. Abr. ed. 4)</reference>
    <reference>Miller, P. 1768. The Gardeners Dictionary..., ed. 8. London. (Gard. Dict. ed. 8)</reference>
    <reference>Miquel, F. A. W. [1851–]1853–1855[–1857]. Plantae Junghuhnianae. Enumeratio Plantarum, Quas in Insulis Java et Sumatra, Detexit Fr. Junghuhn.... 5 parts. Leiden and Paris. [Parts paged consecutively.] (Pl. Jungh.)</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. 1968. Variation in the Polygonum amphibium complex and its taxonomic significance. Univ. Calif. Publ. Bot. 45: 1–65.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. 1971. Comparative leaf structure of aquatic Polygonum species. Amer. J. Bot. 58: 342–360.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. 1976. Submergence experiments on nine species of semi-aquatic Polygonum. Amer. J. Bot. 63: 1158–1165.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. 1978. Rumex maritimus L. versus R. persicarioides L. (Polygonaceae) in the Western Hemisphere. Brittonia 30: 293–296.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. 1986. A checklist of New York State plants. Bull. New York State Mus. Sci. Serv. 458.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. and J. K. Dean. 1978. Polygonaceae (buckwheat family) of New York State. Bull. New York State Mus. Sci. Serv. 431: 1–79.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. and G. C. Tucker. 1991. Sagina japonica (Sw.) Ohwi (Caryophyllaceae), an overlooked adventive in the northeastern United States. Rhodora 93: 192–194.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. and G. C. Tucker. 1997. Revised checklist of New York State plants. Bull. New York State Mus. Sci. Serv. 490.</reference>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. and L. J. Uttal. 1969. Natural hybridization in Virginia Silene (Caryophyllaceae). Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 99: 544–549.</reference>
    <reference>Mizushima, M. 1965. Critical studies on Japanese plants, II: The genus Pseudostellaria Pax in Japan. Bull. Bot. Surv. India 7: 62–72.</reference>
    <reference>Moench, C. 1794. Methodus Plantas Horti Botanici et Agri Marburgensis.... Marburg. (Methodus)</reference>
    <reference>Moerman, D. E. 1986. Medicinal Plants of Native America. 2 vols. Ann Arbor. [Univ. Michigan, Mus. Anthropol., Techn. Rep. 19.]</reference>
    <reference>Moerman, D. E. 1998. Native American Ethnobotany. Portland.</reference>
    <reference>Mohr, C. T. 1901. Plant life of Alabama. Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 6.</reference>
    <reference>Monogr. Amer. Sp. Polygonum—See: J. K. Small 1895</reference>
    <reference>Monogr. Polyg.—See: C. F. Meisner 1826</reference>
    <reference>Monogr. Rumex—See: F. Campderá 1819</reference>
    <reference>Monogr. Syst. Bot. Missouri Bot. Gard. = Monographs in Systematic Botany from the Missouri Botanical Garden.</reference>
    <reference>Mooney, H. A. and W. D. Billings. 1961. Comparative physiological ecology of arctic and alpine populations of Oxyria digyna. Ecol. Monogr. 31: 1–29.</reference>
    <reference>Mori, T. 1922. An Enumeration of Plants hitherto Known from Corea.... Seoul. (Enum. Pl. Corea)</reference>
    <reference>Morton, J. K. 1972. On the occurrence of Stellaria pallida in North America. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 99: 95–97.</reference>
    <reference>Morton, J. K. 1973. Spontaneous hybrids between Cerastium tomentosum Linn. and C. arvense Linn. Rhodora 74: 519–521.</reference>
    <reference>Morton, J. K. and R. K. Rabeler. 1989. Biosystematic studies on the Stellaria calycantha (Caryophyllaceae) complex. I. Cytology and cytogeography. Canad. J. Bot. 67: 121–127.</reference>
    <reference>Morton, J. K. and J. M. Venn. 1990. A Checklist of the Flora of Ontario: Vascular Plants. Waterloo.</reference>
    <reference>Moseley, R. K. and J. L. Reveal. 1995. The Taxonomy and Preliminary Conservation Status of Eriogonum shockleyi S. Wats. in Idaho. Boise. [U.S. Bur. Land Managem., Idaho, Techn. Bull. 96-4.]</reference>
    <reference>Mosyakin, S. L. and W. L. Wagner. 1998. Notes on two alien taxa of Rumex L. (Polygonaceae) naturalized in the Hawaiian Islands. Bishop Mus. Occas. Pap. 55: 39–44.</reference>
    <reference>Muhlenbergia = Muhlenbergia; a Journal of Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Mulligan, G. A. and C. Frankton. 1972. Chromosome races in Rumex arcticus (Polygonaceae). Canad. J. Bot. 50: 378–380.</reference>
    <reference>Mun, J. H. and C. W. Park. 1995. Flavonoid chemistry of Polygonum sect. Tovara (Polygonaceae): A systematic survey. Pl. Syst. Evol. 196: 153–159.</reference>
    <reference>Munz, P. A. 1935. A Manual of Southern California Botany.... San Francisco. (Man. S. Calif. Bot.)</reference>
    <reference>Munz, P. A. 1968. Supplement to A California Flora. Berkeley and Los Angeles. (Suppl. Calif. Fl.)</reference>
    <reference>Murphey, E. V. A. 1959. Indian Uses of Native Plants. Fort Bragg, Calif.</reference>
    <reference>Murray, E. 1982. Notae spermatophytae. Kalmia 12: 18–27.</reference>
    <reference>Murray, J. A. 1770. Prodromus Designationis Stirpium Gottingensium.... Göttingen. (Prodr. Stirp. Gott.)</reference>
    <reference>Napier, M., ed. 1830–1842. Encyclopedia Britannica..., ed. 7. 21 vols. Edinburgh. (Encycl. Brit. ed. 7)</reference>
    <reference>Narr. Journey Polar Sea—See: J. Franklin et al. 1823</reference>
    <reference>Nat. Arr. Brit. Pl.—See: S. F. Gray 1821</reference>
    <reference>Nat. Hist.—See: M. Houttuyn 1773–1783</reference>
    <reference>Nat. Pflanzenfam. ed. 2—See: H. G. A. Engler et al. 1924+</reference>
    <reference>Naturaliste Canad. = Naturaliste Canadien. Bulletin de Recherches, Observations et Découvertes se Rapportant à l’Histoire Naturelle du Canada.</reference>
    <reference>Nature = Nature; a Weekly Illustrated Journal of Science.</reference>
    <reference>Ned. Kruidk. Arch. = Nederlandsch Kruidkundig Archief; Verslagen en Mededelingen der Nederlandsche Botanische Vereeniging.</reference>
    <reference>Neel, M. C. and N. C. Ellstrand. 2003. Conservation of genetic diversity in the endemic endangered plant Eriogonum ovalifolium var. vineum (Polygonaceae). Conservation Genet. 4: 337–352.</reference>
    <reference>Neel, M. C., J. Ross-Ibarra, and N. C. Ellstrand. 2001. Implications of mating patterns for conservation of the endangered plant Eriogonum ovalifolium var. vineum (Polygonaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 88: 1214–1222.</reference>
    <reference>Nepokroeff, M. et al. 2001. Origin of the Hawaiian subfam. Alsinoideae and preliminary relationships in Caryophyllaceae inferred from matK and trnL C-F sequence data. In: Botanical Society of America. 2001. Botany 2001 Abstracts. Columbus. P. 130.</reference>
    <reference>Nepokroeff, M. et al. 2002. Relationships within Caryophyllaceae inferred from molecular sequence data. In: Botanical Society of America. 2002. Botany 2002 Abstracts. Columbus. P. 105.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. and V. M. Bates. 1984. Reevaluation of infraspecific taxonomy in Polygonella (Polygonaceae). Brittonia 36: 37–44.</reference>
    <reference>Nesom, G. L. and V. M. Bates. 1984b. A phylogenetic reconstruction of Polygonella. [Abstract.] A. S. B. Bull. 31: 74.</reference>
    <reference>Neues Mag. Aerzte = Neues Magazin für Aerzte.</reference>
    <reference>New, J. K. 1961. Biological flora of the British Isles. Spergula arvensis L. (S. sativa Boenn., S. vulgaris Boenn.). J. Ecol. 49: 205–215.</reference>
    <reference>New Phytol. = New Phytologist; a British Botanical Journal.</reference>
    <reference>New Zealand J. Bot. = New Zealand Journal of Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Nicholls, G. 2002. Alpine Plants of North America: An Encyclopedia of Mountain Flowers from the Rockies to Alaska. Portland.</reference>
    <reference>Nickrent, D. L. and D. Wiens. 1989. Genetic diversity in the rare California shrub Dedeckera eurekensis (Polygonaceae). Syst. Bot. 14: 245–253.</reference>
    <reference>Nilsson, Ö. 2001. Minuartia. In: B. Jonsell and T. Karlsson, eds. 2000+. Flora Nordica. 2+ vols. Stockholm. Vol. 2, pp. 108–113.</reference>
    <reference>Nomencl. Bot. ed. 2—See: E. G. Steudel 1840–1841</reference>
    <reference>Nordic J. Bot. = Nordic Journal of Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Not. Milit. Reconn.—See: W. H. Emory 1848</reference>
    <reference>Not. Nat. Civ. Lombardia—See: C. Cattaneo 1844</reference>
    <reference>Notes Roy. Bot. Gard. Edinburgh = Notes from the Royal Botanic Garden, Edinburgh.</reference>
    <reference>Nova Acta Phys.-Med. Acad. Caes. Leop.-Carol. Nat. Cur. = Nova Acta Physico-medica Academiae Caesareae Leopoldino-Carolinae Naturae Curiosorum Exhibentia Ephemerides, sive Observationes Historias et Experimenta....</reference>
    <reference>Novit. Fl. Suec. Mant.—See: E. M. Fries 1832–1845</reference>
    <reference>Novon = Novon; a Journal for Botanical Nomenclature.</reference>
    <reference>Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast. = Novosti Sistematiki Vysshikh Rastenii.</reference>
    <reference>Nowicke, J. W. and J. J. Skvarla. 1977. Pollen morphology and the relationship of the Plumbaginaceae, Polygonaceae, and Primulaceae to the order Centrospermae. Smithsonian Contr. Bot. 37: 1–64.</reference>
    <reference>Nuovo Giorn. Bot. Ital. = Nuovo Giornale Botanico Italiano.</reference>
    <reference>Nuttall, T. 1813. A Catalogue of New and Interesting Plants Collected in Upper Louisiana.... London. (Cat. Pl. Upper Louisiana)</reference>
    <reference>Nuttall, T. 1818. The Genera of North American Plants, and Catalogue of the Species, to the Year 1817.... 2 vols. Philadelphia. (Gen. N. Amer. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Nuytsia = Nuytsia; Bulletin of the Western Australian Herbarium.</reference>
    <reference>Nygren, A. 1951. Experimental studies in Scandinavian alpine plants. II. On the origin of the Greenlandic species Melandrium triflorum (R. Br.) J. Vahl. Hereditas (Lund) 37: 373–381.</reference>
    <reference>Nyman, C. F. 1878–1890. Conspectus Florae Europaeae.... 4 parts + 2 suppls. Örebro. [Parts 1–4 and suppl. 1 paged consecutively; suppl. 2 paged independently.] (Consp. Fl. Eur.)</reference>
    <reference>Nyt Mag. Naturvidensk. = Nyt Magazin for Naturvidenskaberne; Grundlagt af den Physiographiske Forening i Christiania.</reference>
    <reference>Oeder, G. C. et al., eds. [1761–]1764–1883. Icones Plantarum...Florae Danicae Nomine Inscriptum. 17 vols. in 51 fasc. Copenhagen. [Fascicles paged independently and numbered consecutively throughout volumes.] (Fl. Dan.)</reference>
    <reference>Oekon. Fl. Wetterau—See: P. G. Gaertner et al. 1799–1802</reference>
    <reference>Ohnishi, O. 1998. Search for the wild ancestor of buckwheat III. The wild ancestor of cultivated common buckwheat, and of Tartary buckwheat. Econ. Bot. 52: 123–133.</reference>
    <reference>Ohnishi, O. and Y. Matsuoka. 1996. Search for the wild ancestor of buckwheat II. Taxonomy of Fagopyrum (Polygonaceae) species based on morphology isozymes and cpDNA variability. Genes Genet. Systems 71: 383–390.</reference>
    <reference>Ohsako, T. and O. Ohnishi. 2000. Intra- and interspecific phylogeny of wild Fagopyrum (Polygonaceae) species based on nucleotide sequences of noncoding regions of chloroplast DNA. Amer. J. Bot. 87: 573–582.</reference>
    <reference>O’Kane, S. L., D. H. Wilken, and R. L. Hartman. 1988. Noteworthy collections: Colorado. Madroño 35: 72–74.</reference>
    <reference>Opiz, P. M. 1852. Seznam Rostlin Kveteny eské.... Prague. (Seznam)</reference>
    <reference>Opler, P. A. and A. B. Wright. 1999. A Field Guide to Western Butterflies, ed. 2. Boston.</reference>
    <reference>Orcutt, C. R. 1886. A botanical trip. W. Amer. Sci. 2: 53–58.</reference>
    <reference>Osmond, C. D., S. D. Smith, B. Gui-Ying, and T. D. Sharkey. 1987. Stem photosynthesis in a desert ephemeral, Eriogonum inflatum. Characterization of leaf and stem CO2 fixation and H2O vapor exchange under controlled conditions. Oecologia 72: 542–549.</reference>
    <reference>Oxelman, B., B. Ahlgren, and M. Thulin. 2002. Circumscription and phylogenetic relationships of Gymnocarpos (Caryophyllaceae–Paronychioideae). Edinburgh J. Bot. 59: 221–227.</reference>
    <reference>Oxelman, B. and M. Lidén. 1995. Generic boundaries in the tribe Sileneae (Caryophyllaceae) as inferred from nuclear rDNA sequences. Taxon 44: 525–542.</reference>
    <reference>Oxelman, B., M. Lidén, and D. Berglund. 1997. Chloroplast rps16 intron phylogeny of the tribe Sileneae (Caryophyllaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 206: 411–420.</reference>
    <reference>Oxelman, B., M. Lidén, R. K. Rabeler, and M. Popp. 2000. A revised generic classification of the tribe Sileneae (Caryophyllaceae). Nordic J. Bot. 20: 743–748.</reference>
    <reference>Pacif. Railr. Rep.—See: War Department 1855–1860</reference>
    <reference>Packer, J. G., ed. 1995+. Flora of the Russian Arctic.... 3+ vols. Edmonton. [Translation by G. C. D. Griffiths of: A. I. Tolmatchew, ed. 1960–1987. Flora Arctica SSSR.... 10 vols. Moscow and Leningrad.]</reference>
    <reference>Palacio = El Palacio.</reference>
    <reference>Palmer, E. J. and J. A. Steyermark. 1950. Notes on Geocarpon minimum Mackenzie. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 77: 268–273.</reference>
    <reference>Pap. Michigan Acad. Sci. = Papers of the Michigan Academy of Sciences, Arts and Letters.</reference>
    <reference>Pap. Peabody Mus. Amer. Archaeol. = Papers of the Peabody Museum of American Archaeology and Ethnology.</reference>
    <reference>Parfitt, B. D. and W. C. Hodgson. 1985. Drymaria viscosa (Caryophyllaceae): Correct author citation and range extension to the United States. Sida 11: 96–98.</reference>
    <reference>Park, C. W. 1986. Nomenclatural typifications in Polygonum section Echinocaulon (Polygonaceae). Brittonia 38: 394–406.</reference>
    <reference>Park, C. W. 1987. Flavonoid chemistry of Polygonum sect. Echinocaulon: A systematic survey. Syst. Bot. 12: 167–179.</reference>
    <reference>Park, C. W. 1988. Taxonomy of Polygonum section Echinocaulon (Polygonaceae). Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 47: 1–82.</reference>
    <reference>Parlatore, F. 1848–1896. Flora Italiana.... 10 vols. + index. Florence. (Fl. Ital.)</reference>
    <reference>Paterson, A. K. 2000. Range expansion of Polygonum caespitosum var. longisetum in the United States. Bartonia 60: 57–69.</reference>
    <reference>Patterson, D. T. et al. 1989. Composite List of Weeds. Champaign.</reference>
    <reference>Pax, F. A. and K. Hoffmann. 1934c. Caryophyllaceae. In: H. G. A. Engler et al., eds. 1924+. Die natürlichen Pflanzenfamilien..., ed. 2. 26+ vols. Leipzig and Berlin. Vol. 16c, pp. 275–364.</reference>
    <reference>Peck, M. E. 1941. A Manual of the Higher Plants of Oregon. Portland. (Man. Higher Pl. Oregon)</reference>
    <reference>Peck, M. E. 1961. A Manual of the Higher Plants of Oregon, ed. 2. Corvallis.</reference>
    <reference>Perez, C. J. et al. 1998. Seedbank characteristics of a Nebraska sandhills prairie. J. Range Managem. 51: 55–62.</reference>
    <reference>Persoon, C. H. 1805–1807. Synopsis Plantarum.... 2 vols. Paris and Tubingen. (Syn. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Pestova, I. O. 1998. Nomenklaturno-taksonomichne doslidzhennya Rumex arifolius complex (Polygonaceae). [Taxonomic and nomenclatural study of the Rumex arifolius complex (Polygonaceae).] Ukrayins’k. Bot. Zhurn. 55: 169–173.</reference>
    <reference>Petrovsky, V. V. 1971. Honckenya. In: A. I. Tolmatchew, ed. 1960–1987. Flora Arctica URSS. 10 vols. Moscow and Leningrad. Vol. 6, pp. 70–74.</reference>
    <reference>Petrovsky, V. V. 2000. Honckenya. In: J. G. Packer, ed. 1995+. Flora of the Russian Arctic.... 3+ vols. Edmonton. Vol. 3, pp. 270–273.</reference>
    <reference>Petrusson, L. and M. Thulin. 1996. Taxonomy and biogeography of Gymnocarpos. Edinburgh J. Bot. 53: 1–26.</reference>
    <reference>Physiogr. Sällsk. Tidskr. = Physiographiska Sällskapets Tidskrift.</reference>
    <reference>Phytologia = Phytologia; Designed to Expedite Botanical Publication.</reference>
    <reference>Phyton (Horn) = Phyton; Annales Rei Botanica.</reference>
    <reference>Pignatti, S. 1972. Limonium. In: T. G. Tutin et al., eds. 1964–1980. Flora Europaea. 5 vols. Cambridge. Vol. 3, pp. 38–50.</reference>
    <reference>Pinto da Silva, A. R. 1972. Armeria. In: T. G. Tutin et al., eds. 1964–1980. Flora Europaea. 5 vols. Cambridge. Vol. 3, pp. 30–38.</reference>
    <reference>Piper, C. V. 1906. Flora of the State of Washington. Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 11: 1–637.</reference>
    <reference>Piper, C. V. and R. K. Beattie. 1901. The Flora of the Palouse Region. Pullman. (Fl. Palouse Reg.)</reference>
    <reference>Piper, C. V. and R. K. Beattie. 1915. Flora of the Northwest Coast.... Lancaster, Pa. (Fl. N.W. Coast)</reference>
    <reference>Pl. Asiat. Rar.—See: N. Wallich [1829–]1830–1832</reference>
    <reference>Pl. Atticae—See: T. Heldreich [1851]</reference>
    <reference>Pl. Hartw.—See: G. Bentham 1839[–1857]</reference>
    <reference>Pl. Jungh.—See: F. A. W. Miquel [1851–]1853–1855[–1857]</reference>
    <reference>Pl. Spec. Biol. = Plant species Biology; an International Journal.</reference>
    <reference>Pl. Syst. Evol. = Plant Systematics and Evolution.</reference>
    <reference>Pl. Vasc. Gen.—See: C. F. Meisner 1837–1843</reference>
    <reference>Poiret, J. 1789. Voyage en Barbarie.... 2 vols. Paris. (Voy. Barbarie)</reference>
    <reference>Porsild, A. E. 1957. Illustrated flora of the Canadian Arctic Archipelago. Bull. Natl. Mus. Canada 146: 1–209.</reference>
    <reference>Porsild, A. E. 1963. Stellaria longipes Goldie and its allies in North America. Bull. Natl. Mus. Canada 186: 1–35.</reference>
    <reference>Porsild, A. E. and W. J. Cody. 1980. Vascular Plants of Continental Northwest Territories, Canada. Ottawa.</reference>
    <reference>Porter, T. C. 1892. Ballast-plants at South Bethlehem, Penn. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 19: 9–10.</reference>
    <reference>Post, T. E. von and O. Kuntze. 1903. Lexikon Generum Phanerogamarum.... Stuttgart. (Lex. Gen. Phan.)</reference>
    <reference>Pratt, G. F. and G. R. Ballmer. 1991. Three biotypes of Apodemia mormo (Riodinidae) in the Mojave Desert. J. Lepid. Soc. 45: 46–51.</reference>
    <reference>Précis Découv. Somiol.—See: C. S. Rafinesque 1814</reference>
    <reference>Presl, C. B. 1825–1835. Reliquiae Haenkeanae seu Descriptiones et Icones Plantarum, Quas in America Meridionali et Boreali, in Insulis Philippinis et Marianis Collegit Thaddeus Haenke.... 2 vols. in 7 parts. Prague. (Reliq. Haenk.)</reference>
    <reference>Presl, C. B. 1826. Flora Sicula, Exhibens Plantas Vasculosas in Sicilia.... Prague. (Fl. Sicul.)</reference>
    <reference>Presl, J. S. and C. B. Presl. 1819. Flora echica. Prague. (Fl.   ech.)</reference>
    <reference>Preslia = Preslia. Vestník (Casopis) Ceskoslovenské Botanické Spolecnosti.</reference>
    <reference>Press, J. R. 1988. Infraspecific variation in Rumex bucephalophorus L. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 97: 344–355.</reference>
    <reference>Pringle, J. S. 1976. Gypsophila scorzonerifolia (Caryophyl-laceae), a naturalized species in the Great Lakes region. Michigan Bot. 15: 215–219.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia = Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts = Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Biol. Soc. Wash. = Proceedings of the Biological Society of Washington.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Boston Soc. Nat. Hist. = Proceedings of the Boston Society of Natural History.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Calif. Acad. Sci. = Proceedings of the California Academy of Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Davenport Acad. Nat. Sci. = Proceedings of the Davenport Academy of Natural Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Indiana Acad. Sci. = Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Providence Franklin Soc. = Proceedings of the Providence Franklin Society.</reference>
    <reference>Proc. Utah Acad. Sci. = Proceedings of the Utah Academy of Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Prodr.—See: R. Brown 1810; A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle 1823–1873</reference>
    <reference>Prodr. Fl. Hispan.—See: H. M. Willkomm and J. M. C. Lange 1861–1880</reference>
    <reference>Prodr. Fl. Nepal.—See: D. Don 1825</reference>
    <reference>Prodr. Stirp. Gott.—See: J. A. Murray 1770</reference>
    <reference>Publ. Bot. (Ottawa) = Publications in Botany, National Museum of Natural Sciences, Canada.</reference>
    <reference>Publ. Field Mus. Nat. Hist., Bot. Ser. = Publications of the Field Museum of Natural History. Botanical Series.</reference>
    <reference>Pugsley, H. W. 1930. The duration of Herniaria glabra. J. Bot. 68: 214–218.</reference>
    <reference>Pursh, F. [1813] 1814. Flora Americae Septentrionalis; or, a Systematic Arrangement and Description of the Plants of North America. 2 vols. London. (Fl. Amer. Sept.)</reference>
    <reference>Putievsky, E., P. W. Weiss, and D. R. Marshall. 1980. Interspecific hybridization between Emex australis and E. spinosa. Austral. J. Bot. 28: 323–328.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1981. Gypsophila muralis: Is it naturalized in Michigan? Michigan Bot. 20: 21–26.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1985. Petrorhagia (Caryophyllaceae) in North America. Sida 11: 6–44.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1986. Revision of the Stellaria calycantha (Caryophyllaceae) Complex and Taxonomic Notes on the Genus. Ph.D. dissertation. Michigan State University.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1991. Moenchia erecta (Caryophyllaceae) in eastern North America. Castanea 56: 150–151.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1992. A new combination in Minuartia (Caryophyllaceae). Sida 15: 95–96.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1993. The occurrence of anther smut, Ustilago violacea s.l., on Stellaria borealis (Caryophyllaceae) in North America. Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 19: 165–169.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1996. Sagina japonica (Caryophyllaceae) in the Great Lakes region. Michigan Bot. 35: 43–44.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 2004. Caryophyllaceae (pink family). In: N. P. Smith et al., eds. 2004. Flowering Plants of the Neotropics. Princeton. Pp. 88–90.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. and A. W. Cusick. 1994. Comments on the introduced Caryophyllaceae of Ohio and nearby states. Michigan Bot. 33: 87–100.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. and R. E. Gereau. 1984. Eurasian introductions to the Michigan flora. I. Michigan Bot. 23: 39–47.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. and R. R. Old. 1992. Lepyrodiclis holosteoides (Caryophyllaceae), “new” to North America. Madroño 39: 240–242.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. and J. W. Thieret. 1988. Comments on the Caryophyllaceae of the southeastern United States. Sida 13: 149–156.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. and J. W. Thieret. 1997. Sagina (Caryophyllaceae) range extensions in Canada: S. japonica new to Newfoundland, S. procumbens new to the Northwest Territories. Canad. Field-Naturalist 111: 309–310.</reference>
    <reference>Rafinesque, C. S. 1810. Caratteri di Alcune Nuovi Generi.... Palermo. (Caratt. Nuov. Gen.)</reference>
    <reference>Rafinesque, C. S. 1814. Précis des Découvertes et Travaux Somiologiques.... Palermo. (Précis Découv. Somiol.)</reference>
    <reference>Rafinesque, C. S. 1817. Florula Ludoviciana; or, a Flora of the State of Louisiana. Translated, Revised, and Improved, from the French of C. C. Robin.... New York. (Fl. Ludov.)</reference>
    <reference>Randall, J. M. and J. Marinelli, eds. 1996. Invasive Plants: Weeds of the Global Garden. Brooklyn.</reference>
    <reference>Ray, V. F. 1933. The Sanpoil and Nesplem: Salishan peoples of northeastern Washington. Univ. Wash. Publ. Anthropol. 5. [Reprinted 1954, New Haven; 1980, New York.]</reference>
    <reference>Reagan, A. B. 1929. Plants used by the White Mountain Apache Indians of Arizona. Wisconsin Archaeologist 8: 143–161.</reference>
    <reference>Rechinger, K. H. 1937. The North American species of Rumex. (Vorarbeiten zu einer Monographie der Gattung Rumex 5.) Publ. Field Mus. Nat. Hist., Bot. Ser. 17: 1–150.</reference>
    <reference>Rechinger, K. H. 1939. Versuch einer natürlichen Gliedewrung des Formenkrieses von Rumex bucephalophorus L. Bot. Not. 1939: 485–504.</reference>
    <reference>Rechinger, K. H. 1949. Rumices Asiatici. (Vorarbeiten zu einer Monographie der Gattung Rumex 7.) Candollea 12: 9–152.</reference>
    <reference>Rechinger, K. H. 1954. Some new American species of Rumex. (Beitrage zur Kenntnis von Rumex 12.) Leafl. W. Bot. 7: 133–135.</reference>
    <reference>Rechinger, K. H. 1964. Rumex. In: T. G. Tutin et al., eds. 1964–1980. Flora Europaea. 5 vols. Cambridge. Vol. 1, pp. 82–89.</reference>
    <reference>Rechinger, K. H. 1984. Rumex (Polygonaceae) in Australia: A reconsideration. Nuytsia 5: 75–122.</reference>
    <reference>Rechinger, K. H. 1990. Rumex subgen. Rumex sect. Axillares (Polygonaceae) in South America. Pl. Syst. Evol. 172: 151–192.</reference>
    <reference>Reed, H. S. and I. Smoot. 1906. The mechanism of seed-dispersal in Polygonum virginianum. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 33: 377–386.</reference>
    <reference>Rees, A. [1802–]1819–1820. The Cyclopaedia; or, Universal Dictionary of Arts, Sciences, and Literature.... 39 vols. in 79 parts. London. [Pages unnumbered.] (Cycl.)</reference>
    <reference>Reichenbach, H. G. L. 1828. Conspectus Regni Vegetabilis.... Leipzig. (Consp. Regn. Veg.)</reference>
    <reference>Reichenbach, H. G. L. 1837. Handbuch des natürlichen Pflanzensystems.... Dresden and Leipzig. (Handb. Nat. Pfl.-Syst.)</reference>
    <reference>Reise Siber.—See: A. T. von Middendorff 1847–1867</reference>
    <reference>Reliq. Haenk.—See: C. B. Presl 1825–1835</reference>
    <reference>Rep. (Annual) Bur. Amer. Ethnol. = Annual Report of the Bureau of American Ethnology.</reference>
    <reference>Rep. (Annual) Michigan Acad. Sci. = Report (Annual) of the Michigan Academy of Science, (Arts, and Letters).</reference>
    <reference>Rep. (Annual) Missouri Bot. Gard. = Report (Annual) of the Missouri Botanical Garden.</reference>
    <reference>Rep. Colorado R.—See: J. C. Ives 1861</reference>
    <reference>Rep. Exped. Rocky Mts.—See: J. C. Frémont 1843–1845</reference>
    <reference>Rep. Exped. Zuni Colorado Rivers—See: L. Sitgreaves 1853</reference>
    <reference>Rep. Inst. Sci. Res. Manchoukuo = Report of the Institute of Scientific Research, Manchoukuo.</reference>
    <reference>Rep. U.S. Mex. Bound.—See: W. H. Emory 1857–1859</reference>
    <reference>Repert. Bot. Syst.—See: W. G. Walpers 1842–1847</reference>
    <reference>Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg. = Repertorium Specierum Novarum Regni Vegetabilis.</reference>
    <reference>Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg. Beih. = Repertorium specierum novarum regni vegetabilis. Beihefte.</reference>
    <reference>Res. J. Wyoming Agric. Exp. Sta. = Research Journal, Wyoming Agricultural Experiment Station.</reference>
    <reference>Res. Stud. State Coll. Wash. = Research Studies of the State College of Washington.</reference>
    <reference>Retzius, A. J. 1795. Florae Scandinaviae Prodromus..., ed. 2. Leipzig. (Fl. Scand. Prodr. ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Rev. Bot. Recueil Mens. = Revue Botanique; Recueil Mensuel Renfermant l’Analyse des Travaux Publiés en France et à l’Étranger sur la Botanique, et sur Ses Applications à l’Horticulture, l’Agriculture, la Médecine, etc.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1968b. Eriogonum (part). In: P. A. Munz. 1968. Supplement to A California Flora. Berkeley and Los Angeles. Pp. 33–72.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1970b. Eriogonum. In: D. S. Correll and M. C. Johnston. 1970. Manual of the Vascular Plants of Texas. Renner, Tex. Pp. 510–516.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1973. Eriogonum. In: C. L. Hitchcock and A. Cronquist. 1973. Flora of the Pacific Northwest: An Illustrated Manual. Seattle. Pp. 79–84.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1973b. Eriogonum (Polygonaceae) of Utah. Phytologia 25: 169–217.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1976. Eriogonum (Polygonaceae) of Arizona and New Mexico. Phytologia 34: 409–484.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1978. Distribution and phylogeny of the Eriogonoideae (Polygonaceae). Great Basin Naturalist Mem. 2: 169–190.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1980. Intermountain biogeography—a speculative appraisal. Mentzelia 4: 1–92.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1981b. Eriogonum divaricatum Hook. (Polygonaceae), an intermountain species in Argentina. Great Basin Naturalist 41: 143–146.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1985. An annotated key to Eriogonum (Polygonaceae) of Nevada. Great Basin Naturalist 45: 493–519.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1989. The eriogonoid flora of California (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae). Phytologia 66: 295–416.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1989b. Notes on selected genera related to Eriogonum (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae). Phytologia 66: 236–245.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 1989c. Remarks on the genus Pterostegia (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae). Phytologia 66: 228–235.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 2004. Proposal to conserve the name Gilmania Coville against Phyllogonum Coville (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae)—A case of mistaken homonymy. Taxon 53: 573.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. 2004b. Nomenclatural summary of Polygonaceae subfamily Eriogonoideae. Harvard Pap. Bot. 9: 143–230.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. and B. Ertter. 1977. Re-establishment of Stenogonum (Polygonaceae). Great Basin Naturalist 36: 272–280.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. and B. Ertter. 1980. The genus Nemacaulis Nutt. (Polygonaceae). Madroño 27: 101–109.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. and C. B. Hardham. 1989. Notes on selected genera related to Chorizanthe (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae). Phytologia 66: 199–220.</reference>
    <reference>Reveal, J. L. and C. B. Hardham. 1989b. A revision of the annual species of Chorizanthe (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae). Phytologia 66: 98–198.</reference>
    <reference>Revis. Gen. Pl.—See: O. Kuntze 1891–1898</reference>
    <reference>Revis. N. Amer. Silene—See: C. L. Hitchcock and B. Maguire 1947</reference>
    <reference>Reznicek, A. A. 1980. Halophytes along a Michigan roadside with comments on the occurrence of halophytes in Michigan. Michigan Bot. 19: 23–30.</reference>
    <reference>Rhodora = Rhodora; Journal of the New England Botanical Club.</reference>
    <reference>Riefner, R. E. 1982. Studies on the Maryland flora VIII: Range extensions of Polygonum perfoliatum L., with notes on introduction and dispersal in North America. Phytologia 50: 152–159.</reference>
    <reference>Rink, H. J. 1852–1857. Grønland Geografisk og Statistisk Beskrevet.... 2 vols. Copenhagen. [Vol. 1 in 2 parts, paged independently.] (Grønland)</reference>
    <reference>Roberts, R. H. 1977. Polygonum minus Huds. × P. persicaria L. in Anglesey. Watsonia 11: 255–256.</reference>
    <reference>Roberty, G. E. and S. Vautier. 1964. Les genres de Polygonacées. Boissiera 10: 7–128.</reference>
    <reference>Robinson, B. L. 1902. The New England polygonums of the section Avicularia. Rhodora 40: 65–73.</reference>
    <reference>Roché, C. T. 1991. Rupturewort (Herniaria cinerea DC.). Olympia etc.</reference>
    <reference>Roemer, J. J., J. A. Schultes, and J. H. Schultes. 1817[–1830]. Caroli a Linné...Systema Vegetabilium...Editione XV.... 7 vols. Stuttgart. (Syst. Veg.)</reference>
    <reference>Rogers, D. J. 1980. Lakota Names and Traditional Uses of Native Plants by Sicangu (Brulé) People in the Rosebud Area, South Dakota: A Study Based on Father Eugene Buechel’s Collection of Plants of Rosebud around 1920. St. Francis, S.Dak.</reference>
    <reference>Röhling, J. C., F. C. Mertens, and W. D. J. Koch. 1823–1839. Deutschlands Flora, ed. 3. 5 vols. Frankfurt am Main. (Deutschl. Fl. ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Rohrer, J. R. 1998. Noteworthy collection. Wisconsin. Gypsophila muralis L. (Caryophyllaceae). Cushion baby’s breath. Michigan Bot. 37: 113–114.</reference>
    <reference>Romero, J. B. 1954. The Botanical Lore of the California Indians. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Ronse Decraene, L.-P. and J. R. Akeroyd. 1988. Generic limits in Polygonum and related genera (Polygonaceae) on the basis of floral characters. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 98: 321–371.</reference>
    <reference>Ronse Decraene, L.-P., Hong S. P., and E. F. Smets. 2000. Systematic significance of fruit morphology and anatomy in tribes Persicarieae and Polygoneae (Polygonaceae). Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 134: 301–337.</reference>
    <reference>Ronse Decraene, L.-P., Hong S. P., and E. F. Smets. 2004. What is the taxonomic status of Polygonella? Evidence from floral morphology. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 91: 320–345.</reference>
    <reference>Ross, T. S. and S. Boyd. 1996b. Arenaria macradenia var. kuschei (Caryophyllaceae), re-collection of an obscure California taxon, with notes on known habitat and morphological variation. Crossosoma 22: 65–71.</reference>
    <reference>Rossbach, R. P. 1940. Spergularia in North and South America. Rhodora 42: 57–83, 105–143, 158–193, 203–213.</reference>
    <reference>Ruprecht, F. 1850. Ueber die Verbreitung der Pflanzen im nördlichen Ural. St. Petersburg. [Alt. title: Beiträge zur Pflanzenkunde des Russischen Reiches.... Siebente Lieferung.] (Verbr. Pfl. Ural)</reference>
    <reference>Rydberg, P. A. 1906. Flora of Colorado.... Fort Collins, Colo. (Fl. Colorado)</reference>
    <reference>Rydberg, P. A. 1917. Flora of the Rocky Mountains and Adjacent Plains. New York. (Fl. Rocky Mts.)</reference>
    <reference>Sargentia = Sargentia; Continuation of the Contributions from the Arnold Arboretum of Harvard University.</reference>
    <reference>Sarkar, N. M. 1958. Cytotaxonomic studies on Rumex sect. Axillares. Canad. J. Bot. 36: 947–996.</reference>
    <reference>Scarry, C. M., ed. 1993. Foraging and Farming in the Eastern Woodlands. Gainesville.</reference>
    <reference>Schaffner, J. H. 1932. Revised catalog of Ohio vascular plants.... Bull. Ohio Biol. Surv. 5(2): 89–215.</reference>
    <reference>Schenck, S. M. and E. W. Gifford. 1952. Karok ethnobotany. Anthropol. Rec. 13: 377–392.</reference>
    <reference>Schischkin, B. K. 1936. Cerastium. In: V. L. Komarov et al., eds. 1934–1964. Flora URSS.... 30 vols. Leningrad. Vol. 6, pp. 430–466.</reference>
    <reference>Schlising, R. A. and H. H. Iltis. 1961. Preliminary reports on the flora of Wisconsin, no. 46. Caryophyllaceae—pink family. Trans. Wisconsin Acad. Sci. 50: 89–139.</reference>
    <reference>Sci. Bull. Brigham Young Univ., Biol. Ser. = Science Bulletin, Brigham Young University. Biological Series.</reference>
    <reference>Sci. Stud. Montana Coll. Agric., Bot. = Science Studies, Montana College of Agriculture and Mechanic Arts. Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Scoggan, H. J. 1978–1979. The Flora of Canada. 4 parts. Ottawa. [Natl. Mus. Nat. Sci. Publ. Bot. 7.]</reference>
    <reference>Scopoli, J. A. 1754. Methodus Plantarum.... Vienna. (Meth. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Seznam—See: P. M. Opiz 1852</reference>
    <reference>Shields, O. and J. L. Reveal. 1988. Sequential evolution of Euphilotes (Lycaenidae: Scolitantidini) on their plant host Eriogonum (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae). Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 33: 51–93.</reference>
    <reference>Shildneck, P. and A. G. Jones. 1986. Cerastium dubium (Caryophyllaceae) new for the eastern half of North America (a comparison with sympatric Cerastium species, including cytological data). Castanea 51: 49–55.</reference>
    <reference>Shildneck, P., A. G. Jones, and V. Muhlenbach. 1981. Additions to the vouchered records of Illinois plants and a note on the occurrence of Rumex cristatus in North America. Phytologia 47: 265–290.</reference>
    <reference>Shinners, L. H. 1962c. Siphonychia transferred to Paronychia (Caryophyllaceae). Sida 1: 101–103.</reference>
    <reference>Shinners, L. H. 1965. Holosteum umbellatum (Caryophyllaceae) in the United States: Population explosion and fractionated suicide. Sida 2: 119–128.</reference>
    <reference>Shults, V. A. 1989. Rod Myl’nyanka (Saponaria L. s.l.) vo Flore SSSR. Riga.</reference>
    <reference>Shultz, L. M. 1998. A new species of Eriogonum (Polygonaceae: Eriogonoideae) from Utah and Nevada. Harvard Pap. Bot. 3: 49–52.</reference>
    <reference>Sida = Sida; Contributions to Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Sitgreaves, L. 1853. Report of an Expedition down the Zuni and Colorado Rivers.... Washington. [Botany by J. Torrey, pp. 153–178, plates 1–21.] (Rep. Exped. Zuni Colorado Rivers)</reference>
    <reference>Sivinski, R. C. and K. Lightfoot, eds. 1993. Southwestern Rare and Endangered Plants: Proceedings of the...Conference. Santa Fe.</reference>
    <reference>Sketch Bot. S. Carolina—See: S. Elliott [1816–]1821–1824</reference>
    <reference>Skr. Kiøbenhavnske Selsk. Laerd. Elsk. = Skrifter, Som Udi det Kiøbenhavnske Selskab af Saerdoms og Videnskabers Elskere ere Fremlagte og Oplaeste.</reference>
    <reference>Skr. Vidensk.-Selsk. Christiana, Math.-Naturvidensk. Kl. = Skrifter Udgivne af Videnskabs-Selskabet i Christiana. Mathematisk-Naturvidenskabelig Klasse.</reference>
    <reference>Small, J. K. 1895. A Monograph of the American Species of the Genus Polygonum. New York. [Mem. Dept. Bot. Columbia Coll. 1.] (Monogr. Amer. Sp. Polygonum)</reference>
    <reference>Small, J. K. 1903. Flora of the Southeastern United States.... New York. (Fl. S.E. U.S.)</reference>
    <reference>Small, J. K. 1933. Manual of the Southeastern Flora, Being Descriptions of the Seed Plants Growing Naturally in Florida, Alabama, Mississippi, Eastern Louisiana, Tennessee, North Carolina, South Carolina and Georgia. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Smissen, R. D., J. C. Clement, P. J. Garnock-Jones, and G. K. Chambers. 2002. Subfamilial relationships within Caryophyllaceae as inferred from 5' NDHF sequences. Amer. J. Bot. 89: 1336–1341.</reference>
    <reference>Smissen, R. D. and P. J. Garnock-Jones. 2002. Relationships, classification and evolution of Scleranthus (Caryophyllaceae) as inferred from analysis of morphological characters. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 140: 15–29.</reference>
    <reference>Smissen, R. D., P. J. Garnock-Jones, and G. K. Chambers. 2003. Phylogenetic analysis of ITS sequences suggests a Pliocene origin for the bipolar distribution of Scleranthus (Caryophyllaceae). Austral. Syst. Bot. 16: 301–315.</reference>
    <reference>Smith, B. W. 1968. Cytogeography and cytotaxonomic relationships of Rumex paucifolius. Amer. J. Bot. 55: 673–683.</reference>
    <reference>Smith, C. F. 1998. A Flora of the Santa Barbara Region, California, ed. 2. Santa Barbara.</reference>
    <reference>Smith, J. E. 1800–1804. Flora Britannica. 3 vols. London. [Vols. paged consecutively. Vols. 1 and 2, 1800; vol. 3, 1804.] (Fl. Brit.)</reference>
    <reference>Smith, J. F. and T. A. Bateman. 2002. Genetic differentiation of rare and common varieties of Eriogonum shockleyi (Polygonaceae) in Idaho using ISSR variability. W. N. Amer. Naturalist 62: 316–326.</reference>
    <reference>Smith, N. P. et al., eds. 2004. Flowering Plants of the Neotropics. Princeton.</reference>
    <reference>Smithsonian Contr. Bot. = Smithsonian Contributions to Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl. = Smithsonian Contributions to Knowledge.</reference>
    <reference>Snyder, D. B. 1987. Notes on some of New Jersey’s adventive flora. Bartonia 53: 17–23.</reference>
    <reference>SouthW. Naturalist = Southwestern Naturalist.</reference>
    <reference>Söyrinki, N. 1989. Fruit production and seedlings in Polygonum viviparum. Memoranda Soc. Fauna Fl. Fenn. 65: 13–15.</reference>
    <reference>Sp. Pl.—See: C. Linnaeus 1753; C. L. Willdenow et al. 1797–1830</reference>
    <reference>Sp. Pl. ed. 2—See: C. Linnaeus 1762–1763</reference>
    <reference>Spach, E. 1834–1848. Histoire Naturelle des Végétaux. Phanérogames.... 14 vols., atlas. Paris. (Hist. Nat. Vég.)</reference>
    <reference>Spellenberg, R., C. Leiva, and E. Lessa. 1988. An evaluation of Eriogonum densum (Polygonaceae). SouthW. Naturalist 33: 71–80.</reference>
    <reference>Spier, L. 1930. Klamath ethnography. Univ. Calif. Publ. Amer. Archaeol. Ethnol. 30.</reference>
    <reference>Sprengel, K. [1824–]1825–1828. Caroli Linnaei...Systema Vegetabilium. Editio Decima Sexta.... 5 vols. Göttingen. [Vol. 4 in 2 parts paged independently; vol. 5 by A. Sprengel.] (Syst. Veg.)</reference>
    <reference>St. John, H. 1915. Rumex persicarioides and its allies in North America. Rhodora 17: 73–83.</reference>
    <reference>St.-Hilaire, A., J. Cambessèdes, and A. H. L. de Jussieu. 1824[–1833]. Flora Brasiliae Meridionalis.... 3 vols. in 24 parts. Paris. [Volumes paged independently, parts and plates numbered consecutively.] (Fl. Bras. Merid.)</reference>
    <reference>Stafleu, F. A. and R. S. Cowan. 1976–1988. Taxonomic Literature: A Selective Guide to Botanical Publications and Collections with Dates, Commentaries and Types, ed. 2. 7 vols. Utrecht, Antwerp, The Hague, and Boston.</reference>
    <reference>Stafleu, F. A. and E. A. Mennega. 1992+. Taxonomic Literature. A Selective Guide to Botanical Publications and Collections with Dates, Commentaries and Types. Supplement. 6+ vols. Königstein.</reference>
    <reference>Stearn, W. T. 1980. Swartz’s contributions to West Indian botany. Taxon 29: 1–13.</reference>
    <reference>Steedman, E. V. 1930. Ethnobotany of the Thompson Indians of British Columbia, based on field notes by James A. Teit. Rep. (Annual) Bur. Amer. Ethnol. 45: 441–522. [Reprinted 1973, Seattle.]</reference>
    <reference>Steudel, E. G. 1840–1841. Nomenclator Botanicus Enumerans Ordine Alphabetico Nomina atque Synonyma tum Generica tum Specifica.... 2 vols. Stuttgart and Tübingen. (Nomencl. Bot. ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Steury, B. W. 2004. Noteworthy collections from the District of Columbia and Maryland. Castanea 69: 154–157.</reference>
    <reference>Stevenson, M. C. 1915. Ethnobotany of the Zuñi Indians. Rep. (Annual) Bur. Amer. Ethnol. 30: 35–102. [Reprinted 1993, New York.]</reference>
    <reference>Steward, A. N. 1930. The Polygoneae of eastern Asia. Contr. Gray Herb. 88: 1–129.</reference>
    <reference>Steward, J. H. 1933. Ethnography of the Owens Valley Paiute. Univ. Calif. Publ. Amer. Archaeol. Ethnol. 33: 233–350.</reference>
    <reference>Steyermark, J. A. 1941. A study of Arenaria patula. Rhodora 43: 325–333.</reference>
    <reference>Steyermark, J. A. 1963. Flora of Missouri. Ames.</reference>
    <reference>Steyermark, J. A., J. W. Voigt, and R. H. Mohlenbrock. 1959. Present biological status of Geocarpon minimum Mackenzie. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 86: 228–235.</reference>
    <reference>Stokes, S. G. 1936. The Genus Eriogonum, a Preliminary Study Based on Geographical Distribution. San Francisco. (Eriogonum)</reference>
    <reference>Stone, A. M. and C. T. Mason. 1979. A study of stem inflation in wild buckwheat, Eriogonum inflatum. Desert Pl. 1: 77–81.</reference>
    <reference>Sturm, J. et al. 1900–1907. J. Sturm’s Flora von Deutschland..., ed. 2. 15 vols. Stuttgart. (Deutschl. Fl. ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Styles, B. T. 1962. The taxonomy of Polygonum aviculare and its allies in Britain. Watsonia 5: 177–214.</reference>
    <reference>Sundaramoorthy, S. and D. N. Sen. 1988. Ecology of Indian arid zone weeds. XI. Polycarpaea corymbosa (Linn.) Lamk. Geobios (Jodhpur) 15: 235–237.</reference>
    <reference>Suom. Kasvio—See: H. I. A. Hiitonen [1933]</reference>
    <reference>Suppl. Calif. Fl.—See: P. A. Munz 1968</reference>
    <reference>Suppl. Fl. Maine-et-Loire—See: T. Bastard 1812</reference>
    <reference>Svensk Bot. Tidskr. = Svensk Botanisk Tidskrift Utgifven af Svenska Botaniska Föreningen.</reference>
    <reference>Svensson, L. 1988. Inbreeding, crossing and variation in stamen number in Scleranthus annuus (Caryophyl-laceae), a selfing annual. Evol. Trends Pl. 2: 31–37.</reference>
    <reference>Svensson, R. and M. Wigren. 1986. A changing flora—a matter of human concern. Acta Univ. Upsal., Symb. Bot. Upsal. 27: 241–251.</reference>
    <reference>Swink, F. and G. S. Wilhelm. 1994. Plants of the Chicago Region: An Annotated Checklist of the Vascular Flora..., ed. 4. Indianapolis.</reference>
    <reference>Sydowia = Sydowia; Annales Mycologici Editi in Notitiam Scientiae Mycologicae Universalis.</reference>
    <reference>Syn. Mitteleur. Fl.—See: P. F. A. Ascherson et al. 1896–1939</reference>
    <reference>Syn. Pl.—See: C. H. Persoon 1805–1807</reference>
    <reference>Syst. Bot. = Systematic Botany; Quarterly Journal of the American Society of Plant Taxonomists.</reference>
    <reference>Syst. Nat. ed. 10—See: C. Linnaeus 1758[–1759]</reference>
    <reference>Syst. Nat. ed. 12—See: C. Linnaeus 1766[–1768]</reference>
    <reference>Syst. Veg.—See: J. J. Roemer et al. 1817[–1830]; K. Sprengel [1824–]1825–1828</reference>
    <reference>Tabl. Encycl.—See: J. Lamarck and J. Poiret 1791–1823</reference>
    <reference>Takhtajan, A. L. 1997. Diversity and Classification of Flowering Plants. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Taxon = Taxon; Journal of the International Association for Plant Taxonomy.</reference>
    <reference>Taylor-Lehman, J. W. 1987. Variation in Polygonum pensylvanicum L. (Polygonaceae) with an Emphasis on Variety eglandulosum Myers. M.S. thesis. Ohio State University.</reference>
    <reference>Thieret, J. W. 1969c. Rumex obovatus and Rumex paraguayensis (Polygonaceae) in Louisiana: New to North America. Sida 3: 445–446.</reference>
    <reference>Thomas, S. M. and B. G. Murray. 1983. Chromosome studies in species and hybrids of Petrorhagia sect. Kohlrauschia (Caryophyllaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 141: 243–255.</reference>
    <reference>Thuillier, J. L. 1799. Flore des Environs de Paris..., ed. 2. Paris. (Fl. Env. Paris ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Timson, J. 1963. The taxonomy of Polygonum lapathifolium L., P. nodosum Pers., and P. tomentosum Schrank. Watsonia 5: 386–395.</reference>
    <reference>Timson, J. 1965. A study of hybridization in Polygonum section Persicaria. J. Linn. Soc., Bot. 59: 155–161.</reference>
    <reference>Tolmatchew, A. I., ed. 1960–1987. Flora Arctica URSS. 10 vols. Moscow and Leningrad. (Fl. Arct. URSS)</reference>
    <reference>Tolmatchew, A. I. 1966. Rumex. In: A. I. Tolmatchew, ed. 1960–1987. Flora Arctica URSS. 10 vols. Moscow and Leningrad. Vol. 5, pp. 143–161.</reference>
    <reference>Torrey, J. and A. Gray. 1838–1843. A Flora of North America.... 2 vols. in 7 parts. New York, London, and Paris. (Fl. N. Amer.)</reference>
    <reference>Torrey, J. and A. Gray. 1870. A revision of the Eriogoneae. Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts 8: 145–200.</reference>
    <reference>Torreya = Torreya; a Monthly Journal of Botanical Notes and News.</reference>
    <reference>Train, P., J. R. Henrichs, and W. A. Archer. 1941. Medicinal Uses of Plants by Indian Tribes of Nevada. Washington. [Contr. Fl. Nevada 33; reprinted 1982, Lawrence, Mass.]</reference>
    <reference>Trans. Amer. Philos. Soc. = Transactions of the American Philosophical Society Held at Philadelphia for Promoting Useful Knowledge.</reference>
    <reference>Trans. Illinois State Acad. Sci. = Transactions of the Illinois State Academy of Science.</reference>
    <reference>Trans. Linn. Soc. London = Transactions of the Linnean Society of London.</reference>
    <reference>Trans. Missouri Acad. Sci. = Transactions of the Missouri Academy of Science.</reference>
    <reference>Trans. Wisconsin Acad. Sci. = Transactions of the Wisconsin Academy of Sciences, Arts and Letters.</reference>
    <reference>Transylvania J. Med. Assoc. Sci. = The Transylvania Journal of Medicine and the Associate Sciences.</reference>
    <reference>Trelease, W. 1892. A revision of the American species of Rumex occurring north of Mexico. Rep. (Annual) Missouri Bot. Gard. 3: 74–98.</reference>
    <reference>Trudy Bot. Muz. = Trudy Botanicheskogo Muzeya.</reference>
    <reference>Trudy Imp. S.-Peterburgsk. Bot. Sada = Trudy Imperatorskago S.-Peterburgskago Botanicheskago Sada.</reference>
    <reference>Tsukui, T. and T. Sugawara. 1992. Dioecy in Honckenya peploides var. major (Caryophyllaceae). Bot. Mag. (Tokyo) 105: 615–624.</reference>
    <reference>Turesson, G. 1961. Habitat modifications in some widespread plant species. Bot. Not. 114: 435–452.</reference>
    <reference>Turkington, R., N. C. Kenkel, and G. C. Franko. 1980. The biology of Canadian weeds. 42. Stellaria media (L.) Vill. Canad. J. Pl. Sci. 60: 981–982.</reference>
    <reference>Turland, N. J. and M. Wyse Jackson. 1997. Proposals to reject the names Cerastium viscosum and C. vulgatum (Caryophyllaceae). Taxon 46: 775–778.</reference>
    <reference>Turner, B. L. 1983b. The Texas species of Paronychia (Caryophyllaceae). Phytologia 54: 9–23.</reference>
    <reference>Turner, B. L. 1995. Cerastium texanum does not occur in Texas. Phytologia 79: 356–363.</reference>
    <reference>Turner, N. J., R. Bouchard, and D. I. D. Kennedy. 1980. Ethnobotany of the Okanagan-Coleville Indians of British Columbia and Washington. Victoria.</reference>
    <reference>Tutin, T. G. et al., eds. 1964–1980. Flora Europaea. 5 vols. Cambridge.</reference>
    <reference>Tutin, T. G. et al., eds. 1993+. Flora Europaea, ed. 2. 1+ vol. Cambridge and New York.</reference>
    <reference>Tutin, T. G. and S. M. Walters. 1993. Dianthus. In: T. G. Tutin et al., eds. 1993+. Flora Europaea, ed. 2. 1+ vol. Cambridge and New York. Vol. 1, pp. 227–246.</reference>
    <reference>Tzvelev, N. N. 1987b. Zametki o Polygonaceae vo flore Dal’nego Vostoka. (Notulae de Polygonaceis in flora Orientis Extremi.) Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast. 24: 72–79.</reference>
    <reference>Tzvelev, N. N. 1989b. Rumex, Acetocella, Acetosa. In: S. S. Kharkevich, ed. 1985+. Plantae Vasculares Orientis Extremi Sovietici. 7+ vols. Leningrad. Vol. 4, pp. 29–53.</reference>
    <reference>Ugborogho, R. E. 1974. North American Cerastium arvense Linnaeus. IV. Phenotypic variation. Phyton (Horn) 32: 89–97.</reference>
    <reference>Ugborogho, R. E. 1977. North American Cerastium arvense Linnaeus: Taxonomy, reproductive system and evolution. Phyton (Horn) 35: 169–187.</reference>
    <reference>Ukrayins’k. Bot. Zhurn. = Ukrayins’kyi Botanichnyi Zhurnal.</reference>
    <reference>Univ. Calif. Publ. Amer. Archaeol. Ethnol. = University of California Publications in American Archaeology and Ethnology.</reference>
    <reference>Univ. Calif. Publ. Bot. = University of California Publications in Botany.</reference>
    <reference>Univ. Colorado Stud., Ser. Biol. = University of Colorado Studies. Series in Biology.</reference>
    <reference>Univ. Wash. Publ. Anthropol. = University of Washington Publications in Anthropology.</reference>
    <reference>University of Chicago Press 1993. The Chicago Manual of Style, ed. 14. Chicago.</reference>
    <reference>Utah Fl. ed. 3—See: S. L. Welsh et al. 2003</reference>
    <reference>Vasc. Pl. Pacif. N.W.—See: C. L. Hitchcock et al. 1955–1969</reference>
    <reference>Vasc. Pl. Wyoming—See: R. D. Dorn 1988</reference>
    <reference>Vasc. Pl. Wyoming ed. 3—See: R. D. Dorn 2001</reference>
    <reference>Veg. Syst.—See: J. Hill 1759–1775</reference>
    <reference>Ventenat, É. P. [1800–1803.] Description des Plantes Nouvelles et Peu Connues Cultivés dans le Jardin de J. M. Cels.... 10 parts. Paris. [Plates numbered consecutively.] (Descr. Pl. Nouv.)</reference>
    <reference>Verbr. Pfl. Ural—See: F. Ruprecht 1850</reference>
    <reference>Vers. Darstell. Alsin.—See: E. Fenzl 1833</reference>
    <reference>Verz. Pfl. Casp. Meer.—See: C. A. von Meyer 1831</reference>
    <reference>Vestal, P. A. 1940. Notes on a collection of plants from the Hopi Indian region of Arizona made by J. G. Owens in 1891. Bot. Mus. Leafl. 8: 153–168.</reference>
    <reference>Vestal, P. A. 1952. The ethnobotany of the Ramah Navaho. Pap. Peabody Mus. Amer. Archaeol. 40(4).</reference>
    <reference>Vestal, P. A. and R. E. Schultes. 1939. The Economic Botany of the Kiowa Indians. Cambridge, Mass.</reference>
    <reference>Villars, D. 1786–1789. Histoire des Plantes de Dauphiné. 3 vols. Grenoble, Lyon, and Paris. (Hist. Pl. Dauphiné)</reference>
    <reference>Virginia J. Sci. = Virginia Journal of Science.</reference>
    <reference>Voegelin, E. W. 1938. Tübatulabal Ethnography. Berkeley. [Anthropol. Rec. 2(1).]</reference>
    <reference>Vogel, A. 1997. Die Verbreitung, Vergesellschaftung und Populationsökologie von Corrigiola litoralis, Illecebrum verticillatum und Herniaria glabra (Illecebraceae). Berlin.</reference>
    <reference>Voy. Barbarie—See: J. Poiret 1789</reference>
    <reference>W. Amer. Sci. = West American Scientist.</reference>
    <reference>W. N. Amer. Naturalist = Western North American Naturalist.</reference>
    <reference>Wagner, W. L. and E. M. Harris. 2000. A unique Hawaiian Schiedea (Caryophyllaceae: Alsinoideae) with only five fertile stamens. Amer. J. Bot. 87: 153–160.</reference>
    <reference>Wagstaff, S. J. and R. J. Taylor. 1988. Genecology of Cerastium arvense and C. beeringianum (Caryophyllaceae) in northwest Washington. Madroño 35: 266–277.</reference>
    <reference>Wahlenberg, G. 1812. Flora Lapponica Exhibens Plantas Geographice et Botanice Consideratas.... Berlin. (Fl. Lapp.)</reference>
    <reference>Wallich, N. [1829–]1830–1832. Plantae Asiaticae Rariores.... 3 vols. in 12 parts. London, Paris, and Strasburgh. [Parts paged consecutively within volumes, parts and plates numbered consecutively throughout.] (Pl. Asiat. Rar.)</reference>
    <reference>Walpers, W. G. 1842–1847. Repertorium Botanices Systematicae.... 6 vols. Leipzig. (Repert. Bot. Syst.)</reference>
    <reference>Walter, T. 1788. Flora Caroliniana, Secundum Systema Vegetabilium Perillustris Linnaei Digesta.... London. (Fl. Carol.)</reference>
    <reference>War Department [U.S.]. 1855–1860. Reports of Explorations and Surveys, to Ascertain the Most Practicable and Economical Route for a Railroad from the Mississippi River to the Pacific Ocean. Made under the Direction of the Secretary of War, in 1853[–1856].... 12 vols. in 13. Washington. (Pacif. Railr. Rep.)</reference>
    <reference>Ward, D. B. 1977c. Keys to the flora of Florida. 2. Paronychia (Caryophyllaceae). Phytologia 35: 414–418.</reference>
    <reference>Ward, D. B. 2001. New combinations in the Florida flora. Novon 11: 360–365.</reference>
    <reference>Wasmann J. Biol. = Wasmann Journal of Biology.</reference>
    <reference>Watson, S. 1871. United States Geological Expolration [sic] of the Fortieth Parallel. Clarence King, Geologist-in-charge. [Vol. 5] Botany. By Sereno Watson.... Washington. [Botanical portion of larger work by C. King.] [Botany (Fortieth Parallel)]</reference>
    <reference>Watsonia = Watsonia; Journal of the Botanical Society of the British Isles.</reference>
    <reference>Weaver, R. E. 1970. The arenarias of the southeastern granitic flat-rocks. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 97: 40–52.</reference>
    <reference>Webb, D. A. and A. O. Chater. 1963. Polygonum oxyspermum subsp. raii (Bab.) D. A. Webb &amp; A. O. Chater, stat. nov. Feddes Repert. Spec. Nov. Regni Veg. 68: 187–189.</reference>
    <reference>Weber, S. A. and P. D. Seaman. 1985. Havasupai Habitat: A. F. Whiting’s Ethnography of a Traditional Indian Culture. Tucson.</reference>
    <reference>Weber, W. A. 1961. Stellaria irrigua Bunge in America. Univ. Colorado Stud., Ser. Biol. 7: 12–15.</reference>
    <reference>Weber, W. A. and R. L. Hartman. 1979. Pseudostellaria jamesiana, comb. nov., a North American representative of a Eurasian genus. Phytologia 44: 313–314.</reference>
    <reference>Weber, W. A., B. C. Johnston, and D. H. Wilken. 1979. Additions to the flora of Colorado–VI. Phytologia 41: 486–498.</reference>
    <reference>Weber, W. A. and R. C. Wittmann. 1992. Catalog of the Colorado Flora: A Biodiversity Baseline. Niwot, Colo.</reference>
    <reference>Weed Res. = Weed Research.</reference>
    <reference>Weed Sci. = Weed Science; Journal of the Weed Science Society of America.</reference>
    <reference>Welsh, S. L., N. D. Atwood, S. Goodrich, and L. C. Higgins, eds. 1987. A Utah flora. Great Basin Naturalist Mem. 9.</reference>
    <reference>Welsh, S. L., N. D. Atwood, S. Goodrich, and L. C. Higgins, eds. 1993. A Utah Flora, ed. 2. Provo.</reference>
    <reference>Welsh, S. L., N. D. Atwood, S. Goodrich, and L. C. Higgins. 2003. A Utah Flora, ed. 3. Provo. (Utah Fl. ed. 3)</reference>
    <reference>Whitehead, F. H. and R. P. Sinha. 1967. Taxonomy and taximetrics of Stellaria media (Linnaeus) Vill., S. neglecta Weihe and S. pallida (Dumort.) Piré. New Phytol. 66: 769–784.</reference>
    <reference>Wiens, D. et al. 1989. Developmental failure and loss of reproductive capacity in the rare palaeoendemic shrub Dedeckera eurekensis. Nature 338: 65–67.</reference>
    <reference>Wiens, D., L. Allphin, D. H. Mansfield, and G. Thackray. 2004. Developmental failure and loss of reproductive capacity as a factor in extinction: A nine-year study of Dedeckera eurekensis (Polygonaceae). Aliso 21: 55–63.</reference>
    <reference>Wiens, D., C. I. Davern, and C. L. Calvin. 1988. Exceptionally low seed set in Dedeckera eurekensis: Is there a genetic component of extinction? In: C. A. Hall Jr. and V. Doyle-Jones, eds. 1988. Plant Biology of Eastern California. Los Angeles. Pp. 19–29.</reference>
    <reference>Wiens, D., M. DeDecker, and C. D. Wiens. 1986. Observations on the pollination of Dedeckera eurekensis (Polygonaceae). Madroño 33: 302–305.</reference>
    <reference>Willdenow, C. L. 1809–1813[–1814]. Enumeratio Plantarum Horti Regii Botanici Berolinensis.... 2 parts + suppl. Berlin. [Parts paged consecutively.] (Enum. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Willdenow, C. L., C. F. Schwägrichen, and J. H. F. Link. 1797–1830. Caroli a Linné Species Plantarum.... Editio Quarta.... 6 vols. Berlin. [Vols. 1–5(1), 1797–1810, by Willdenow; vol. 5(2), 1830, by Schwägrichen; vol. 6, 1824–1825, by Link.] (Sp. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Williams, F. N. 1896. A revision of the genus Herniaria. Bull. Herb. Boissier 4: 556–570.</reference>
    <reference>Williams, F. N. 1896b. A revision of the genus Silene Linn. J. Linn. Soc., Bot. 32: 1–196.</reference>
    <reference>Willkomm, H. M. and J. M. C. Lange. 1861–1880. Prodromus Florae Hispanicae.... 3 vols. in 9 parts. Stuttgart. (Prodr. Fl. Hispan.)</reference>
    <reference>Wilson, K. L. 1990b. Some widespread species of Persicaria (Polygonaceae) and their allies. Kew Bull. 45: 621–636.</reference>
    <reference>Wilson, P. 1934. Tetragoniaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 21, pp. 267–277.</reference>
    <reference>Wislizenus, F. A. 1848. Memoir of a Tour to Northern Mexico, Connected with Col. Doniphan’s Expedition, in 1846 and 1847.... Washington. (Mem. Tour N. Mexico)</reference>
    <reference>Wofford, B. E. 1981. External seed morphology of Arenaria (Caryophyllaceae) of the southeastern United States. Syst. Bot. 6: 126–135.</reference>
    <reference>Wofford, B. E., D. H. Webb, and W. M. Dennis. 1977. State records and other recent noteworthy collections of Tennessee plants II. Castanea 42: 190–193.</reference>
    <reference>Wolf, N. M. 1776. Genera Plantarum.... [Danzig.] (Gen. Pl.)</reference>
    <reference>Wolf, S. J. and J. McNeill. 1986. Synopsis and achene morphology of Polygonum section Polygonum (Polygonaceae) in Canada. Rhodora 88: 457–479.</reference>
    <reference>Wolf, S. J., J. G. Packer, and K. E. Denford. 1979. The taxonomy of Minuartia rossii (Caryophyllaceae). Canad. J. Bot. 57: 1673–1686.</reference>
    <reference>Wood, A. 1847. A Class-book of Botany..., ed 2. Boston and Claremont, N.H. (Class-book Bot. ed. 2)</reference>
    <reference>Wood, A. 1861. A Class-book of Botany.... New York. [Class-book Bot. ed. s.n.(b)]</reference>
    <reference>Wrightia = Wrightia; a Botanical Journal.</reference>
    <reference>Wunderlin, R. P. 1981. Polygonella polygama (Polygonaceae) in Florida. Florida Sci. 44: 78–80.</reference>
    <reference>Wyatt, R. 1984. The evolution of self-pollination in granite outcrop species of Arenaria (Caryophyllaceae). I. Morphological correlates. Evolution 38: 804–816.</reference>
    <reference>Wyman, L. C. and S. K. Harris. 1951. The Ethnobotany of the Kayenta Navaho: An Analysis of the John and Louisa Wetherill Ethnobotanical Collection. Albuquerque.</reference>
    <reference>Yang, J. and J. W. Wang. 1991. A taxometric analysis of characters of Polygonum lapathifolium L. Acta Phytotax. Sin. 29: 258–263.</reference>
    <reference>Yasui, Y. and O. Ohnishi. 1998. Phylogenetic relationships among Fagopyrum species revealed by the nucleotide sequences of the ITS region of the nuclear rRNA gene. Genes Genet. Systems 73: 201–210.</reference>
    <reference>Yasui, Y. and O. Ohnishi. 1998b. Interspecific relationships in Fagopyrum (Polygonaceae) revealed by the nucleotide sequences of the rbcL and accD genes and their intergenic region. Amer. J. Bot. 85: 1134–1142.</reference>
    <reference>Yatskievych, G. and J. Turner. 1990. Catalogue of the flora of Missouri. Monogr. Syst. Bot. Missouri Bot. Gard. 37.</reference>
    <reference>Youngbae, S., S. Kim, and C. W. Park. 1997. A phylogenetic study of Polygonum sect. Tovara (Polygonaceae) based on ITS sequences of nuclear ribosomal DNA. J. Pl. Biol. 40: 47–52.</reference>
    <reference>Yurtseva, O. V., N. D. Yakolevleva, and T. I. Ivanova-Radkevich. 1999. Heterocarpy in Polygonum aviculare L. s. str. and related species (Polygonum, subsect. Polygonum). Byull. Moskovsk. Obshch. Isp. Prir., Otd. Biol. 104: 13–20.</reference>
    <reference>Zigmond, M. L. 1981. Kawaiisu Ethnobotany. Salt Lake City.</reference>
    <reference>Zika, P. F. and A. L. Jacobson. 2003. An overlooked hybrid Japanese knotweed (Polygonum cuspidatum × sachalinense; Polygonaceae) in North America. Rhodora 105: 143–152.</reference>
    <reference>Zoë = Zoë; a Biological Journal.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
