<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>7.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eremogone</genus_name><species_name>ferrisiae</species_name><species_authority>(Abrams) R. L. Hartman &amp; Rabeler</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sida</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>21: 754. 2004</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Ferris’s sandwort</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Arenaria</genus_name><species_name>macradenia</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><subspecies_name>ferrisiae</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>Abrams</subspecies_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in L. Abrams and R. S. Ferris, Ill. Fl. Pacific States </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 151. 1944</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Eremogone</genus_name><species_name>macradenia</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><variety_name>ferrisiae</variety_name><variety_authority>(Abrams) R. L. Hartman &amp; Rabeler</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants tufted, green, not glaucous, with woody base. Stems erect, (10–)20–40(–100) cm, glabrous to stipitate-glandular. Leaves: basal leaves sparse or absent; cauline leaves usually in 5–7 pairs, not significantly reduced; basal blades ascending, needlelike or narrowly linear, 2–6(–7) cm × 0.5–1 mm, ± rigid, herbaceous to subsucculent, apex blunt to spinose, usually glabrous, not glaucous. Inflorescences 10–30(–80)-flowered, diffuse cymes; branches spreading. Pedicels 15–55 mm, glabrous or stipitate-glandular. Flowers: sepals 1–3-veined, ovate to lanceolate or elliptic, 3–4.3 mm, to 5.5 mm in fruit, margins narrow to broad, apex acute to acuminate, glabrous to sparsely stipitate-glandular; petals white or yellowish, oblanceolate to spatulate, 6–9 mm, 1–1.5 times as long as sepals, apex entire or erose; nectaries as lateral and abaxial rounding of base of filaments opposite sepals, 0.3–0.4 mm. Capsules 6–7 mm, glabrous. Seeds reddish brown to blackish, suborbicular to pyriform or ovoid, 1.3–3.2 mm, tuberculate; tubercles low, rounded to conic.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>pine and oak woodlands</habitat><habitat>granitic alluvium on foothills and mountain slopes</habitat><elevation>1400–2900 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Utah.</us_distribution><discussion>We now believe that Eremogone macradenia (in the sense of R. L. Hartman 1993) should be split into two species, with E. macradenia var. ferrisiae (Abrams) R. L. Hartman &amp; Rabeler being elevated to species rank (Hartman and R. K. Rabeler 2004), as here. This became particularly obvious when comparing nectary morphology of E. macradenia (rectangular, two-lobed or truncate, 0.7–1.5 mm or narrowly longitudinally rectangular, truncate, densely minutely pubescent with erect to spreading hairs, 0.7–0.8 mm) with that of E. ferrisiae (rounded, 0.3–0.4 mm). Furthermore, the nectary types correlate well with sepal size and inflorescence type, as indicated in the key. This disposition agrees with the conclusions of M. F. Baad (1969).</discussion></treatment>
