<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>17.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>LEPYRODICLIS</genus_name><genus_authority>Fenzl</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in S. L. Endlicher, Gen. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>13: 966. 1840</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek lepyron , rind or husk, and diklis , double-folding, alluding to two-valved capsule]</etymology><author>Richard K. Rabeler</author><description>Herbs, annual. Taproots slender. Stems ascending to decumbent or sprawling, simple or branched, terete or angled. Leaves connate proximally, sessile; blade 1-veined, lanceolate or rarely elliptic, not succulent, apex acute. Inflorescences axillary and terminal, compound cymes; bracts paired, foliaceous, smaller. Pedicels reflexed in fruit. Flowers: perianth and androecium weakly perigynous; hypanthium minimal; sepals 5, distinct, green, lanceolate to elliptic or ovate, 4–5 mm, herbaceous, margins white, scarious, apex somewhat acute, not hooded; petals 5, white or pink, not clawed, blade apex entire or emarginate; nectaries at base of filaments opposite sepals; stamens 10, arising from nectariferous disc at ovary base; filaments distinct nearly to base; staminodes absent; styles 2, clavate, 3.5–4 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 2, subterminal, minutely roughened to papillate (50×). Capsules globose-ovoid, opening by 2 straight valves; carpophore absent. Seeds 1–2(–4), dark brown, reniform, laterally compressed, tuberculate, marginal wing absent, appendage absent. x = 17.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 3–4 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>c</global_distribution><global_distribution>sw Asia</global_distribution><global_distribution>introduced in Europe (Germany)</global_distribution><global_distribution>Asia (Japan).</global_distribution><references>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. and R. R. Old. 1992. Lepyrodiclis holosteoides (Caryophyllaceae), “new” to North America. Madroño 39: 240–242.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
