<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ronald L. Hartman,Richard K. Rabeler</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">SPERGULA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 440. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>ed. 5, 199. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus SPERGULA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin spargo , scatter or sow, alluding to discharge of seeds]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or winter annual. Taproots slender to ± stout, especially proximally. Stems spreading or ascending to erect, simple or branched, terete to somewhat angular. Leaves opposite but appearing whorled, as 8–15 per axillary cluster, 2 clusters per node, connate proximally by often-prominent ridge from which stipules arise, sessile; stipules 4 per node, white, ovate to triangular, margins entire but splitting variously with age, apex obtuse to acuminate; blade 1-veined, linear or filiform, sometimes succulent, apex blunt to apiculate. Inflorescences terminal, open to diffuse cymes; bracts paired, minute. Pedicels erect to ascending, spreading or usually reflexed and sometimes secund in fruit. Flowers usually bisexual, sometimes pistillate by stamen abortion; perianth and androecium briefly perigynous; hypanthium dish- or cup-shaped, not abruptly expanded distally; sepals distinct, silvery, elliptic to nearly ovate, 2.5–5 mm, herbaceous, margins scarious, apex acute to obtuse; petals 5, white, blade apex entire; nectaries at adaxial base of broader filaments opposite sepals; stamens 5 and opposite sepals, or 10 and arising from distally tapered rim of hypanthium; filaments distinct; styles 5, distinct, filiform, 0.4–0.6 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 5, linear along adaxial surface of styles, obscurely papillate (30×). Capsules ovoid, opening by 5 spreading to somewhat recurved valves; carpophore absent. Seeds 5–25, blackish, circular, subglobose or lenticular and laterally compressed, nearly smooth or finely papillate, membranous, entire marginal wing often present, appendage absent; embryo peripheral, annular to spirally curved. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia (esp. Mediterranean region).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia (Europe).</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name"> Spurrey</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">spargoute</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 5 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Spergula arvensis is the only species of the genus that has been introduced extensively outside of Eurasia.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually appearing terete, 1.5–3(–5) cm, margins often revolute, forming abaxial channel; seeds subglobose, sometimes with keel or wing ± 0.1 mm wide</description>
      <determination>1.  Spergula arvensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually flat, 0.3–1.5(–2) cm, usually not channeled abaxially; seeds lenticular, laterally compressed, wings 0.2–0.6 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed wings light brown to brownish black, 0.2–0.3 mm wide; stamens usually 10</description>
      <determination>2.  Spergula morisonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seed wings white or sometimes slightly tannish, 0.4–0.6 mm wide; stamens usually 5</description>
      <determination>3.  Spergula pentandra</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
