<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>18.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Cerastium</genus_name><species_name>maximum</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 439. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Great mouse-ear chickweed</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Dichodon</genus_name><species_name>maximum</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) Á. Löve &amp; D. Löve</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, subrhizomatous. Stems simple, or few together, erect or ascending, 20–70 cm, proximal internodes moderately pilose, becoming glandular distally; nonflowering, axillary branches usually present; small axillary tufts of leaves absent. Leaves sessile, not marcescent; blade narrowly lanceolate, with prominent midrib, 0.2–1 × 3–12 mm, apex acuminate, ± pubescent on both surfaces, short-ciliate. Inflorescences open or congested, usually 3–10-flowered cymes; bracts normally lanceolate, acuminate, herbaceous, pubescent. Pedicels erect, 2–25(–60) mm, usually ca. 2 times as long as sepals in fruit, glandular-pubescent. Flowers large, conspicuous, more than 2 cm diam.; sepals lanceolate, 8–11(–12) mm, outer sepal margins herbaceous, inner sepal margins narrow, membranous, apex acute, moderately to sparsely glandular-hairy; petals obovate, (15–)18–25 mm, at least 2 times as long as sepals, apex deeply 2-fid; stamens 10; styles 5. Capsules narrowly conic, straight, 15–22 mm, ca. 2 times as long as sepals; teeth 10, erect, short, becoming outwardly coiled. Seeds yellowish brown, round, 2–2.5 mm diam., finely rugose in concentric rings; testa not inflated. 2n = 38.</description><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>open woods</habitat><habitat>gravel bars</habitat><habitat>terraces by rivers</habitat><elevation>0–1200 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution><global_distribution>Asia.</global_distribution><discussion>This beautiful species is distinguished by its long, narrowly conic capsule with teeth that coil outward like a watch spring.</discussion></treatment>
