<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">cerastium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rafinesque" date="1814">nutans</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Précis Découv. Somiol.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36. 1814</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus cerastium;species nutans</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, slender, finely glandular-pubescent (often per-ennial and tomentose in var. obtectum), with slender taproot. Stems erect, simple or branched at or near base, sometimes with straggling, nonflowering basal shoots, 10–50 cm, softly pubes-cent, often with a few long, flex-uous, woolly hairs at proximal nodes, glandular and somewhat viscid distally; small axillary tufts of leaves usually absent. Leaves marcescent or not, sessile; blade oblanceolate to spatulate in proximal leaves, becoming lanceolate to linear-lanceolate in distal leaves, occasionally elliptic, 10–60 × 3–15 mm, apex acuminate to acute, softly pubescent and glandular, sometimes tomentose. Inflorescences rather open, 3–21(–40)-flowered cymes, ultimately widely branched; bracts herbaceous, lanceolate, glandular-pubescent. Pedicels ascending, sharply deflexed at apex in fruit, 5–20(–35) mm, usually 1–3 times as long as sepals in flower, elongating to 5 times as long as sepals in fruit, longer than capsules, glandular-pubescent and viscid. Flowers: sepals ovate-lanceolate, 4–6 mm, outer sepals herbaceous or with narrow margins, inner with margins ca. as wide as herbaceous center, apex broadly acute to obtuse, glandular-puberulent, hairs shorter than sepal tips; petals oblanceolate, sometimes absent, 3–6(–8) mm, shorter to 1.5 times longer than sepals, apex 2-fid; stamens 10; styles 5. Capsules cylindric, curved, (9–)10–12(–13) mm, 2–3 times as long as sepals; teeth 10, erect, margins convolute. Seeds golden brown, 0.5–0.8 mm diam., shallowly tuberculate; testa not inflated. 2n = 34, 36.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora): North America, Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>19</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Nodding mouse-ear chickweed</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">céraiste penché</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not marcescent, long, woolly pubescence confined to proximal nodes</description>
      <determination>19a. Cerastium nutans var. nutans</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves tending to be marcescent, leaves and stem with long, woolly pubescence</description>
      <determination>19b. Cerastium nutans var. obtectum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
