<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>23.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Cerastium</genus_name><species_name>terrae-novae</species_name><species_authority>Fernald &amp; Wiegand</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>22: 176. 1921</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Newfoundland mouse-ear chickweed</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Cerastium</genus_name><species_name>beeringianum</species_name><species_authority>Chamisso &amp; Schlechtendal</species_authority><subspecies_name>terrae-novae</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Fernald &amp; Wiegand) Hultén</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, tufted, rhizom-atous. Stems loosely ascending to suberect, branched, very leafy, 10–15 cm, pubescence short, dense, glandular; small axillary tufts of leaves usually absent. Leaves tending to be marcescent, sessile but spatulate proximally; blade elliptic-oblong, 5–14 × 1.5–3.5 mm, apex obtuse, densely glandular-hirsute. Inflorescences lax, 1–3-flowered cymes; bracts ovate-lanceolate, margins very narrow, scarious, glandular-pubescent. Pedicels mostly erect, slender, 10–25 mm, 1–4 times as long as sepals, densely glandular-pubescent. Flowers: sepals ovate-oblong, 5.5–6.5 mm, elongating to 6–7 mm in fruit, margins broad, apex obtuse, glandular-pubescent; petals narrowly oblanceolate, 7–10 mm, 1.5–2 times as long as sepals, apex 2-fid; stamens 10; styles 5. Capsules ovate-cylindric, ca. straight, short, broad, 9–13 mm, ca. 2 times as long as sepals; teeth 10, erect or partially spreading, margins convolute. Seeds brown, 1.3–1.7 mm diam., with prominent papillae around margins and rows of small, transverse ridges on sides; testa inflated, loose (rubs off when rolled between finger and thumb). 2n = 108.</description><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>serpentine gravel</habitat><habitat>sands</habitat><habitat>rocky tablelands</habitat><elevation>20–700 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.).</ca_distribution><discussion>Cerastium terrae-novae is the only member of the European C. nigrescens group of species to occur in North America. The group is distinguished by large seeds with loose testae. Cerastium terrae-novae is distinguished by its narrowly elliptic leaves, usually purple-suffused stems and sepals, broad, straight capsule, short pubescence, and poorly developed inflorescence that often is reduced to a single flower.</discussion></treatment>
