<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard K. Rabeler,Ronald L. Hartman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Fenzl" date="unknown">Alsinoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Ehrhart" date="unknown">MOENCHIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Neues Mag. Aerzte</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 203. 1783</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Caryophyllaceae;subfamily Alsinoideae;genus MOENCHIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Conrad Moench, 1744–1805, professor at Marburg, Germany]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual. Taproots slender. Stems ascending to erect, simple or sometimes branched proximally, terete. Leaves: cauline leaves connate proximally, sessile or sometimes petiolate (basal leaves); blade 1-veined, linear to linear-oblanceolate, not succulent, apex acute. Inflorescences terminal, 1–3-flowered, spreading cymes or flowers solitary; bracts paired, foliaceous, those of axillary flowers with scarious margins. Pedicels erect. Flowers: perianth and androecium hypogynous; sepals 4, distinct, green, lanceolate, 3.8–7 mm, herbaceous, margins white or silvery, scarious, apex acute; petals 4 or rarely absent, white, claw absent, blade apex entire; nectaries at base of filaments opposite sepals; stamens 4, inserted at base of ovary; filaments distinct nearly to base; staminodes absent; styles 4, filiform, 0.7–1 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 4, linear along adaxial surface of styles, minutely papillate (50×). Capsules cylindric, opening by 8 revolute teeth, shorter than or equaling sepals; carpophore absent. Seeds 35–55, brown, reniform with deep abaxial groove, laterally compressed, papillate, marginal wing absent, appendage absent. x = 19.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe (Mediterranean region)</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced in Africa (Republic of South Africa)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>19.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Upright chickweed</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ketzner, D. M. 1996. Crepis pulchra (Asteraceae) and Moenchia erecta (Caryophyllaceae) in Illinois. Trans. Illinois State Acad. Sci. 89: 21–23.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1991. Moenchia erecta (Caryophyllaceae) in eastern North America. Castanea 56: 150–151.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
