<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>21.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>MYOSOTON</genus_name><genus_authority>Moench</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Methodus,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>225. 1794</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek myos , mouse, and otos , ear, alluding to leaves]</etymology><common_name>Giant or water chickweed</common_name><common_name>stellaire aquatique</common_name><author>Richard K. Rabeler</author><description>Herbs, perennial. Taproots slender, rhizomes slender. Stems decumbent to ascending, simple or branched, terete to angular. Leaves sessile leaves clasping proximally, petiolate (proximal leaves) or sessile (most cauline leaves); blade 1-veined, ovate to broadly elliptic, not succulent, apex acute. Inflorescences axillary or terminal, open cymes; bracts paired, foliaceous, smaller. Pedicels ascending to erect, reflexed in fruit. Flowers bisexual, occasionally pistillate or reduced and sterile; perianth and androecium weakly perigynous; hypanthium minimal; sepals 5, distinct, green, ovate, 4–6(–9) mm, herbaceous, margins green or white, herbaceous or scarious, apex acute, not hooded; petals 5, white, claw absent, blade apex deeply 2-fid; nectaries at base of filaments opposite sepals; stamens 10, occasionally fewer, arising from nectariferous disc at ovary base; filaments distinct; staminodes sometimes present, linear; styles 5(–6), distinct, filiform, 0.7–1.8 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 5(–6), linear along adaxial surface of styles, papillate (30×). Capsules ovoid to globose-ovoid, opening by 5(–6), slightly recurved, briefly 2-fid valves; carpophore absent. Seeds 50–100, brown-blackish, reniform, laterally compressed, papillate, marginal wing absent, appendage absent. x = 14.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution>temperate Asia.</global_distribution><discussion>The combination of 5(–6) styles and a capsule opening by the same number of briefly 2-fid valves characterizes Myosoton and is not known in Stellaria. Most chromosome counts of M. aquaticum are 2n = 28, a very rare number in Stellaria.</discussion></treatment>
