<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">stellaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bunge" date="1835">irrigua</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St.-Pétersbourg Divers Savans</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 548. 1835</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus stellaria;species irrigua</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Alsine</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene ex Rydberg" date="unknown">polygonoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Alsine;species polygonoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, forming mats or low cushions, with elongate rhizomes. Stems ascending to spreading, striate, branched, 4-sided, 2–10 cm, glabrous, inter-nodes usually shorter than leaves. Leaves sessile; blade with promi-nent midrib, elliptic or lanceolate to oblanceolate, 0.1–1 cm × 0.5–4 mm, fleshy, base cuneate to spatulate, margins transparent, entire, narrow, apex acute, glabrous, rarely with few cilia near base, with sessile, often purple glands impressed on abaxial surface; proximal leaves marcescent. Inflorescences with flowers solitary in distal leaf axils, often ± concealed among leaves; bracts, when present, paired near base of pedicel, with midrib, ovate-lanceolate, ca. 1 mm, scarious. Pedicels erect, becoming curved and deflexed distally, 3–15 mm, glabrous. Flowers ca. 6 mm diam.; sepals 5, purple tinged, outer prominently 3-veined, carinate, inner with midrib only, lanceolate, 3–4 mm, margins narrow, membranous, apex acute, glabrous; petals 5, ca. 2 mm, shorter than sepals, blade apex deeply 2-fid, lobes narrowly elliptic; stamens 5, inserted in prominent nectary disc; styles 3, outwardly ascending, curved, 0.75 mm. Capsules green, becoming straw colored, ovoid-obtuse, ca. 3 mm, ± equaling and enclosed in sepals, opening with 6 teeth. Seeds pale brown, reniform, 1–1.2 mm diam., not glossy, sides smooth to shallowly rugose, margins thickened with shallow, parallel, longitudinal ridges.</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="phenology">aug</description>
  <description type="habitat">mountain rills and screes</description>
  <description type="elevation">2500–4000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Colo.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia (Siberia: Altai Mountains).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering summer. Mountain rills and screes; 2500-4000 m; Colo.; Asia (Siberia: Altai Mountains).</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering summer.</phenology>
      <habitat>Mountain rills and screes;</habitat>
      <elevation>2500-4000 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Colo.; Asia (Siberia: Altai Mountains).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>15.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Altai chickweed or starwort</other_name>
  <discussion>Stellaria irrigua has a remarkable and perhaps uniquely disjunct distribution. It is known to occur only in Colorado and the Altai Mountains of Siberia. This raises the possibility that the two populations may not be conspecific, which requires further study.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Weber, W. A. 1961. Stellaria irrigua Bunge in America. Univ. Colorado Stud., Ser. Biol. 7: 12–15.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
