<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>18.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Minuartia</genus_name><species_name>macrocarpa</species_name><species_authority>(Pursh) Ostenfeld</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Meddel. Grønland</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>37: 226. 1920</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Long-pod stitchwort</common_name><common_name>large-fruited sandwort</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Arenaria</genus_name><species_name>macrocarpa</species_name><species_authority>Pursh</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 318. 1813</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Alsinopsis</genus_name><species_name>macrocarpa</species_name><species_authority>(Pursh) A. Heller</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Wierzbickia</genus_name><species_name>macrocarpa</species_name><species_authority>(Pursh) Reichenbach</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, mat-forming. Taproots stout, woody. Stems erect to ascending, green, 3–10 cm, glabrous or sometimes stip-itate-glandular, internodes of flowering stems 1–5 times as long as leaves. Leaves tightly overlapping (vegetative), variably spaced (cauline), usually connate proximally, with tight, scarious to herbaceous sheath 1–1.5 mm; blade straight to outwardly curved, green, flat, 3-veined, often prominently so abaxially, linear to oblong or narrowly lanceolate, 4–14 × 0.5–2 mm, flexuous, margins thickened, ± coriaceous, ciliate, often densely so, apex green, rounded, navicular, shiny, glabrous or essentially so throughout or abaxially, sometimes pubescent adaxially, hairs resembling cilia; axillary leaves present among vegetative leaves. Inflorescences solitary flowers, terminal; bracts linear, herbaceous. Pedicels 0.4–1 cm, usually densely stipitate-glandular. Flowers: hypanthium cup-shaped; sepals prominently 3-veined proximally, lanceolate to oblong (herbaceous portion often purple, lanceolate to oblong), 4.5–6 mm, to 9 mm in fruit, apex often purple, rounded, hooded, stipitate-glandular; petals broadly obovate, 1.2–1.6 times as long as sepals, apex blunt or rounded, entire. Capsules narrowly ellipsoid, 10–18 mm, longer than sepals. Seeds red-brown to brown, orbiculate with radicle prominent and notch filled with papillae, somewhat compressed, 1–1.1 mm (excluding papillae), rounded-tuberculate, ringed with longitudinal, cylindrical, tan papillae 0.5–0.8 mm. 2n = 44 (Russia), 46, 48 (Russia).</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>rocky, montane ridges</habitat><habitat>sandy slopes</habitat><habitat>well-drained alpine tundra and heathlands</habitat><elevation>0–2200 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution><global_distribution>Asia (Japan).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Asia (Russian Far East).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Asia (Siberia).</global_distribution><discussion>An amphi-Beringian species, Minaurtia macrocarpa is easily distinguished by having the largest capsules of any North American Minuartia.</discussion></treatment>
