<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>19.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Minuartia</genus_name><species_name>marcescens</species_name><species_authority>(Fernald) House</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Amer. Midl. Naturalist</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>7: 132. 1921</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Serpentine stitchwort or sandwort</common_name><common_name>minuartie de la serpentine</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Arenaria</genus_name><species_name>marcescens</species_name><species_authority>Fernald</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Rhodora </publication_title><place_in_publication>21: 15. 1919</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Arenaria</genus_name><species_name>laricifolia</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><variety_name>marcescens</variety_name><variety_authority>(Fernald) B. Boivin</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, mat-forming or more commonly straggly. Taproots stout, woody. Stems as-cending, green, 4–6 cm, glabrous proximally, stipitate-glandular distally, internodes of flowering stems 6–8 times as long as leaves. Leaves tightly overlapping (vegetative), variably spaced (cauline), usually connate proximally, with tight, scarious to herbaceous sheath 0.5–1.5 mm; blade straight to outwardly curved, green, 3-angled, prominently 1-veined abaxially, subulate, 4–8 × 0.3–0.8 mm, flexuous, margins not thickened, herbaceous, smooth, apex green, rounded to truncate, sometimes apiculate, shiny, glabrous; axillary leaves present among vegetative leaves. Inflorescences solitary flowers, terminal; bracts lance-subulate, herbaceous. Pedicels 0.5–1.5 cm, usually densely stipitate-glandular. Flowers: hypanthium cup-shaped; sepals 3-veined, ovate to broadly lanceolate (herbaceous portion oblong to narrowly ovate), 3–4 mm, not enlarging in fruit proximally, apex often purple, rounded, hooded or not, stipitate-glandular; petals white or rarely lilac, spatulate to spatulate-obovate, 1.5–2 times as long as sepals, apex rounded, entire. Capsules narrowly ellipsoid, 6–10 mm, longer than sepals. Seeds brown, suborbiculate with radicle prolonged into beak, somewhat compressed, 0.9–1.2 mm, smooth.</description><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>ultramafic ledges and barrens</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>200–1000 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution><ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Vt.</us_distribution><discussion>Marcescent leaves are a characteristic feature of this species.</discussion></treatment>
