<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Warren L. Wagner</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Ehrhart" date="1783">HONCKENYA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Neues Mag. Aerzte</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 206. 1783</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus HONCKENYA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Gerhard August Honckeny, 1724–1805, German botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">Adenarium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Adenarium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Desvaux" date="unknown">Ammonalia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ammonalia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Fries" date="unknown">Halianthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Halianthus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, forming large mats or clumps by leafy rhizomes; rhizomes fleshy, often with prominent nodal buds and small membranous leaves. Taproots slender. Stems prostrate to decumbent, flowering stems ascending or weakly erect, simple or branched, terete or weakly 4-angled. Leaves not basally connate, sessile; blade 1-veined or obscurely so, usually elliptic to ovate, less commonly lanceolate to oblanceolate, obovate, or broadly elliptic, succulent, apex acute to acuminate or apiculate. Inflorescences terminal, open, leafy, 1–6-flowered cymes or axillary and flowers solitary; bracts paired, foliaceous. Pedicels erect. Flowers functionally unisexual or, occasionally, staminate plants also with some bisexual; perianth and androecium subperigynous; hypanthium minimal; sepals 5(–6), distinct, green, narrowly ovate to elliptic, 3.5–7 mm, herbaceous, margins pale, scarious, apex obtuse or acute to apiculate, not hooded; petals absent or 5(–6), white, base clawed, blade apex emarginate; nectaries at base of filaments opposite sepals enlarged on both sides of filament, slightly reduced in pistillate flowers; stamens 10, fertile in staminate flowers, fewer or abortive in pistillate flowers, arising from rim of very brief hypanthium disc; filaments distinct; staminodes absent; styles (2–)3–5(–6), filiform, 1–2 mm, shorter and erect in staminate flowers, glabrous proximally; stigmas (2–)3–5(–6), linear along adaxial surface of styles, minutely papillate (30×). Capsules globose, inflated, opening by 3 spreading valves; carpophore absent. Seeds 3–15, reddish brown to dark reddish or yellowish brown, narrowly to broadly obovate, laterally compressed, smooth to minutely papillate, marginal wing absent, appendage absent. x = 15.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate and arctic North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Eurasia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: temperate and arctic North America, n Eurasia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>temperate and arctic North America, n Eurasia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>26.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Seaside sandwort</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sea purslane</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>The resemblance in habit between Honckenya and Wilhelmsia previously presumed to represent convergence has proven to indicate a close relationship based on recent molecular studies (M. Nepokroeff et al., unpubl.).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
