<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sagina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Fenzl" date="1833">nodosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Vers. Darstell. Alsin.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18. 1833</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus sagina;species nodosa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Spergula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">nodosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 440. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Spergula;species nodosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, tufted, pubescent or glabrous. Stems ascending to loosely spreading or prostrate, simple or with few to many lateral branches bearing only tiny, succulent, subulate leaves, not filiform. Leaves: axillary fascicles of subulate, fleshy leaves among distal cauline leaves, giving knotted appearance; basal ascending, forming tuft, not in rosettes, blade linear, ca. 15–30 mm, herbaceous, apex apiculate to mucronate, glabrous or glandular; cauline conspicuously connate basally, cuplike, proximal with blade linear to subulate, apex apiculate to mucronate, glabrous or glandular-pubescent, axillary fascicles of leaves absent; distal with blade subulate, 1–1.5 mm, fleshy, apex mucronate, glabrous. Pedicels filiform, base glabrous or glandular-pubescent. Flowers terminal and axillary, 5-merous or 4- and 5-merous; calyx base glabrous or glandular-pubescent; sepals elliptic, 2–3 mm, hyaline margins rarely purplish, apex frequently purplish, obtuse to rounded, remaining appressed after capsule dehiscence; petals elliptic to orbiculate, 3–4.5 mm, ca. 2 times sepal length; stamens 8 or 10. Capsules 3–4 mm, longer than sepals, dehiscing to base. Seeds dark brown, ovoid to reniform, laterally compressed, 0.5 mm, smooth or distinctly pebbled, abaxial groove present or absent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Europe.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Knotted pearlwort</other_name>
  <discussion>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glandular-pubescent; pedicels distally glandular-pubescent; bases of calyces glandular-pubescent; basal leaf blades often glandular-pubescent (especially on margins and midrib) or glabrous</description>
      <determination>1a. Sagina nodosa subsp. nodosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or occasionally weakly pubescent at nodes; pedicels distally glabrous or occasionally weakly glandular-pubescent; bases of calyces glabrous or weakly glandular-pubescent; basal leaf blades glabrous</description>
      <determination>1b. Sagina nodosa subsp. borealis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
