<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sagina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Swartz) C. Presl" date="1826">subulata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Sicul.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>158. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus sagina;species subulata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Spergula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Swartz" date="unknown">subulata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Kongl. Vetensk. Acad. Nya Handl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 45, plate 1, fig. 3a–c. 1789</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Spergula;species subulata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, cespitose, frequently forming dense mats or tufted, glandular-pubescent or glabrous. Stems ascending or decumbent, few-branched, not filiform, densely glandular-pubescent, or less frequently glabrous; horizontal stems becoming slightly woody with extensive mat formation. Leaves: axillary fascicles absent; basal forming tufts, blade linear, curled inward, 3–12 mm, not fleshy, apex long-aristate, aristae equaling or exceeding leaf width, densely glandular-pubescent, or with glandular hairs restricted to margins, and then often minutely glandular-ciliate, rarely glabrous; cauline connate basally, forming conspicuous cup, blade linear-subulate, 3–10 mm, scarious. Pedicels filiform, densely to weakly glandular-pubescent. Flowers axillary or terminal, usually solitary, 5-merous, rarely 4- and 5-merous; calyx bases glandular-pubescent; sepals elliptic, 1.5–2 mm, hyaline margins white, apex obtuse to rounded, glandular-pubescent, remaining appressed following capsule dehiscence; petals elliptic, 1.5–2 mm, shorter than or equaling sepals; stamens (8 or) 10. Capsules 2–3(–3.5) mm, slightly longer than sepals, dehiscing to base. Seeds brown, obliquely triangular with abaxial groove, 0.4(–0.5) mm, smooth.</description>
  <description type="habitat">wet, gravelly sands of stream margins</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Baja California Sur)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering mid-late summer. Wet, gravelly sands of stream margins; 0-1800 m; introduced; Oreg.; Mexico (Baja California Sur); Europe.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering mid-late summer.</phenology>
      <habitat>Wet, gravelly sands of stream margins;</habitat>
      <elevation>0-1800 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>introduced; Oreg.; Mexico (Baja California Sur); Europe.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Scottish moss</other_name>
  <discussion>Three specimens from the alpine zone of Steens Mountain, Harney County, are referable to Sagina subulata. Introduction of the species into that remote area is without explanation.</discussion>
  <discussion>A strongly mat-forming cultivar of Sagina subulata is sometimes grown as a ground cover; plants flower profusely, but no subsequent capsule development typically occurs. The cultivar differs from the native European mat-forming plants by being glabrous except for the minutely glandular-ciliate leaf margins. Occasional waifs have been collected in the San Francisco area of California.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
