<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sagina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Swartz) Ohwi" date="1937">japonica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Jap. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 438. 1937</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus sagina;species japonica</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Spergula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Swartz" date="unknown">japonica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ges. Naturf. Freude Berlin Neue Schriften</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 164, plate 1, fig. 2. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Spergula;species japonica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, glandular-pubescent. Stems ascending to spreading, much-branched, usually filiform, frequently glandular-pubescent distally. Leaves: axillary fascicles rarely present; basal frequently in tuft of ascending leaves, rosette rarely present, blade linear, 4–10 mm, succulent, apex apiculate, glabrous; cauline leaves conspicuously connate basally, forming shallow, scarious cup, blade linear, fleshy, apex apiculate, glabrous or rarely pubescent; proximal leaf blades 9–20 mm, becoming shorter distally, 4–7 mm. Pedicels slender, distal portion densely glandular-pubescent, becoming less densely glandular-pubescent proximally, proximal 1/4 usually glabrous. Flowers axillary, 5-merous; calyx glandular-pubescent basally; sepals elliptic to orbiculate, 2–2.5 mm, hyaline margins whitish, apex obtuse to rounded, glandular-pubescent, remaining appressed following capsule dehiscence; petals ovate to orbiculate, 1–2 mm, shorter than sepals; stamens 5 or 10. Capsules 2.5–3 mm, exceeding sepals, dehiscing ca. 1/4 length. Seeds dark brown, reniform to nearly globose, plump, abaxial groove absent, 0.4–0.5 mm, densely tuberculate or strongly pebbled (e North America).</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering early-late summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Dryish sites, waste places;</description>
  <description type="elevation">200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; B.C., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), Ont., Que.; Conn., Ill., Mass., N.H., N.Y., Ohio, Oreg., Pa., R.I., Vt.; e Asia; introduced in Mexico (Veracruz).</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sagine du Japon</other_name>
  <discussion>Sagina japonica was recently introduced in widely scattered locations in northeastern North America, and can be found especially in gravelly roadsides, walkways, and driveways. The plants tend to be much less robust and without distinctly succulent leaves.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Mitchell, R. S. and G. C. Tucker. 1991. Sagina japonica (Sw.) Ohwi (Caryophyllaceae), an overlooked adventive in the northeastern United States. Rhodora 93: 192–194.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. 1996. Sagina japonica (Caryophyllaceae) in the Great Lakes region. Michigan Bot. 35: 43–44.</reference>
    <reference>Rabeler, R. K. and J. W. Thieret. 1997. Sagina (Caryophyllaceae) range extensions in Canada: S. japonica new to Newfoundland, S. procumbens new to the Northwest Territories. Canad. Field-Naturalist 111: 309–310.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
