<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">gypsophila</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Seringe in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle" date="1824">scorzonerifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 352. 1824</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus gypsophila;species scorzonerifolia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial. Stems ± erect, simple or few-branched proximal to inflorescence, 5–20 dm, proximally glabrous, distally glandular-puberulent. Leaves basal and cauline, bases clasping; blade oblong-lanceolate to nar-rowly ovate, larger leaves 2–15 cm × 7–22(–35) mm, glaucous, apex obtuse to acute. Pedicels 1–12 mm, glandular-puberulent. Flowers: calyx 2.5–4 mm, lobes glandular-puberulent, apex obtuse; petals white with pink tinge to light purplish pink (drying darker), 4–6 mm. Capsules globose. Seed coats coarsely tuberculate. 2n = 68 (Europe, introduced population).</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer-fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Beaches, roadsides, railroad grades, quarries, and other open, calcareous, sandy or rocky, disturbed sites;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-1700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Alta., B.C., Ont.; Calif., Colo., Conn., Ill., Ind., Mich., Nev., N.Mex., N.Y., Ohio, Utah, Wis., Wyo.; Europe (se; introduced elsewhere in Europe).</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Glandular baby’s-breath</other_name>
  <discussion>There is a historic record of Gypsophila scorzonerifolia from Massachusetts collected in 1921.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some Ohio specimens of Gypsophila scorzonerifolia have calyces rather sparsely glandular or appearing to lack glands at maturity, but all of the young flowers have obviously glandular calyces.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Pringle, J. S. 1976. Gypsophila scorzonerifolia (Caryophyllaceae), a naturalized species in the Great Lakes region. Michigan Bot. 15: 215–219.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
