<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>31.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>VACCARIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Wolf</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. Pl.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3. 1776</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Latin vacca , cow, and -aria , pertaining to, alluding to alleged value for fodder]</etymology><author>John W. Thieret</author><author>Richard K. Rabeler</author><description>Herbs, annual. Taproots stout. Stems simple proximally, branched distally, terete. Leaves opposite, somewhat clasping or connate proximally into sheath, petiolate (basal) or sessile (cauline); blade 1-veined, lanceolate to oblong- or ovate-lanceolate, apex acute to obtuse. Inflorescences terminal, lax to erect, open, often flat-topped cymes; bracts paired, foliaceous; involucel bracteoles absent. Pedicels erect. Flowers: sepals connate proximally into tube, 9–17 cm, tube whitish green, 5-veined, cylindric to ovoid, 5-angled or winged, especially in fruit, commissures between sepals absent; lobes green, 1-veined, obovate to broadly triangular, shorter than tube, margins green or reddish, scarious, apex acute or acuminate; petals 5, pink to purplish, clawed, auricles absent, coronal appendages absent, blade apex entire or sometimes briefly 2-fid; nectaries at filament bases; stamens 10, adnate to petals; filaments distinct; staminodes absent; ovary 1-locular or sometimes 2-locular proximally; styles 2(–3), filiform, 10–12 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 2(–3), linear along adaxial surface of styles, papillate (30×). Capsules oblong to subglobose, exocarp opening by 4(–6) slightly spreading teeth, endocarp opening irregularly; carpophore present. Seeds ca. 10, black, subglobose, laterally compressed, papillose, marginal wing absent, appendage absent; embryo peripheral, curved. x = 15.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1 or 4 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>Eurasia</global_distribution><global_distribution>introduced in South America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Africa (Republic of South Africa)</global_distribution><global_distribution>Australia.</global_distribution></treatment>
