<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>32.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>SAPONARIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 408. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5, 191. 1754</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[from Latin saponis , soap, and - aria , pertaining to, alluding to sap]</etymology><common_name>Soapwort</common_name><common_name>saponaire</common_name><author>John W. Thieret</author><author>Richard K. Rabeler</author><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Spanizium</genus_name><genus_authority>Grisebach</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, [annual, biennial, or] perennial. Rhizomes stout or slender. Stems erect to spreading, simple or branched, terete. Leaves connate proximally, petiolate or sessile; blade 3(–5)-veined, spatulate to elliptic or ovate, apex acute or rounded. Inflorescences terminal, dense to open, lax cymes; bracts paired, foliaceous; involucel bracteoles absent. Pedicels erect. Flowers: sepals connate proximally into tube, greenish, reddish, or purple, 7–25 mm, tube 15–25-veined, oblong-cylindric, terete, commissures between sepals absent; lobes green, reddish, or purple, 3–5-veined, triangular-attenuate, shorter than tube, margins white, scarious, apex acute or acuminate; petals 5 (doubled in some cultivars), pink to white, clawed, auricles absent, with 2 coronal scales, blade apex entire or emarginate; nectaries at filament bases; stamens 10, adnate with petals to carpophore; filaments briefly connate proximally; staminodes absent (present in some cultivars); ovary 1-locular; styles 2(–3), filiform, 12–15 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 2(–3), linear along adaxial surface of styles, papillate (30×). Capsules cylindric to ovoid, opening by 4(–6) ascending or recurving teeth; carpophore present. Seeds 15–75, dark brown, reniform, laterally compressed, papillose, marginal wing absent, appendage absent; embryo peripheral, curved. x = 7.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 40 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution>c</global_distribution><global_distribution>w Asia</global_distribution><global_distribution>Africa (Mediterranean region)</global_distribution><global_distribution>S. officinalis widely naturalized elsewhere.</global_distribution><discussion>Saponaria pumilio (Linnaeus) Fenzl ex A. Braun [= Silene pumilio (Linnaeus) Wulfen], a species of the Alps and the Carpathians, was collected once from a ledge on Mount Washington, New Hampshire, in 1964; the collector, S. K. Harris (1965), suggested that it may have been an intentional planting. A cespitose plant, it differs from the two species below also in its one-flowered, rather than several-flowered, stems.</discussion><references>
    <reference>Shults, V. A. 1989. Rod Myl’nyanka (Saponaria L. s.l.) vo Flore SSSR. Riga.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems erect, 30–90 cm; calyx 15–25 mm, glabrous or rarely with scattered trichomes; capsules ca. 15–20 mm</statement>
      <determination>1. Saponaria officinalis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems trailing, procumbent, or ascending, 5–25 cm; calyx 7–12 mm, glandular-pubescent; capsule 6–8 mm</statement>
      <determination>2. Saponaria ocymoides</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
