<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">saponaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">officinalis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 408. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus saponaria;species officinalis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, colonial. Stems erect, simple or branched distally, 30–90 cm. Leaves: petiole often absent or winged, 0.1–1.5 cm; blade strongly 3(–5)-veined, elliptic to oblanceolate or ovate, 3–11(–15) × 1.5–4.5 cm. Cymes dense to open. Pedicels 1–5 mm. Flowers sometimes double; calyx green or reddish, often cleft, 15–25 mm, glabrous or rarely with scattered trichomes; petals pink to white, often drying to dull purple, blade 8–15 mm. Capsules ca. 15–20 mm. Seeds 1.6–2 mm wide. 2n = 28.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring-fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Waste places, streamsides, fields, roadsides;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-2600 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask.; Ala., Ariz., Ark., Calif., Colo., Conn., Del., D.C., Fla., Ga., Idaho, Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Miss., Mo., Mont., Nebr., Nev., N.H., N.J., N.Mex., N.Y., N.C., N.Dak., Ohio, Okla., Oreg., Pa., R.I., S.C., S.Dak., Tenn., Tex., Utah, Vt., Va., Wash., W.Va., Wis., Wyo.; Eurasia; introduced in Mexico, South America, Asia (India), Africa (Egypt), Australia.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Bouncing-bet</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">saponaire officinale</other_name>
  <discussion>Saponaria officinalis, long cultivated for its showy flowers, is a widely naturalized, sometimes troublesome weed. It may persist for years about abandoned home sites. “Double”-flowered horticultural forms, which may lack functional stamens, also occur in the wild, where locally they may be as common as, or even more common than, “single”-flowered forms.</discussion>
  <discussion>In former times, the leaves of this species were gathered and either soaked or boiled in water, the resulting liquid being used for washing as a liquid soap. Because of its saponin content, the species can be poisonous upon ingestion, in much the same manner as Agrostemma githago.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
