<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">silene</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene" date="1904">aperta</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Leafl. Bot. Observ. Crit.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 75. 1904</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus silene;species aperta</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, cespitose, puberulent throughout; caudex woody, branched, with clusters of leaves. Stems several, erect, not much-branched, slender, 15–60 cm, flowering above middle. Leaves: cauline in 2–4 pairs, gradually reduced distally, blade linear with broadened base, 1–8 cm × 1–2 mm, apex acute; basal leaves tending to wither by flowering time, blade with midrib present, linear-oblanceolate, 5–12 cm × 1–4 mm, apex acute. Inflorescences few-flowered, bracteate, narrow, flowers terminal and axillary; bracts linear, 2–10 mm. Pedicels ascending, straight, slender, very short in bud but equaling or exceeding flower at anthesis. Flowers: calyx 10-veined, campanulate, lobed to middle or below, 6–10 mm; lobes 6, recurved, 1–3-veined, lanceolate to linear-lanceolate, margins membranous, ciliate, apex acute; petals white to pale greenish, lobed, clawed, 12–20 mm including claw, ca. 2 times length of calyx; lobes 4, small, 1.5–2 mm, claw woolly towards base, appendages absent; stamens equaling petals; filaments pubescent at base; styles 3, shorter than to equaling stamens. Capsules ovoid, exceeding calyx, dehiscing with 6 spreading teeth; carpophore 1–2 mm. Seeds brown, broadly reniform, less than 1.75 mm, margins coarsely tuberculate to papillate, with concentric rings of tubercles on both faces. 2n = 48.</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="phenology">aug</description>
  <description type="phenology">sep</description>
  <description type="phenology">fall</description>
  <description type="habitat">open, grassy areas in fir and pine forests</description>
  <description type="elevation">1800–3000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering Jun-Sep. Open, grassy areas in fir and pine forests; 1800-3000 m; Calif.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering Jun-Sep.</phenology>
      <habitat>Open, grassy areas in fir and pine forests;</habitat>
      <elevation>1800-3000 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Calif.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Naked catchfly</other_name>
  <discussion>A deeply lobed calyx and grasslike leaves give Silene aperta a very distinct appearance. The species is found only in Tulare County.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
