<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>11.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>coniflora</species_name><species_authority>Nees ex de Candolle</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 371. 1824</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Multinerved catchfly</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>multinervia</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants annual; taproot slender. Stems erect, simple or branched, 20–65 cm, glandular-pubescent. Leaves: proximal forming rosette, blade oblanceolate, spatulate, 3–8(–12) cm × 5–13(–25) mm, apex ± obtuse, sparingly pubescent and glandular; cauline reduced distally, blade lanceolate, 1–7 cm × 2–15 mm, apex ± acute, sparingly pubescent and glandular. Inflorescences dichasiate, open, bracteate; bracts leaflike, to 15 mm. Pedicels ascending, 1–3(–5) cm, densely glandular-pubescent, viscid. Flowers: calyx prominently 20–25-veined, ovate-conic, 8–12 mm, margins dentate, coarsely pubescent, glandular, lobes erect, narrowly lanceolate, 2–3 mm, margins membranous ca. 1/4 length of calyx; corolla inconspicuous, cream, purple tinged adaxially, dull orange abaxially, equaling or slightly longer than calyx, limb ovate, 1–3 mm, apex notched, appendages absent, auricles round, small; stamens shorter than corolla; stigmas 3, shorter than corolla. Capsules tightly enclosed in calyx, ovoid, with narrow opening, opening by 6 triangular teeth ca. 1 mm; carpophore ca. 1 mm. Seeds dark brown to black, rotund, 0.6–1 mm broad, papillate. 2n = 20 (Asia).</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>open places</habitat><habitat>oak parklands</habitat><habitat>especially after burning</habitat><elevation>0–2000 m;</elevation><introduced>introduced;</introduced><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Baja California)</global_distribution><global_distribution>Asia.</global_distribution><discussion>Silene coniflora apparently was introduced into North America in the early days of European exploration and settlement of the Pacific coast. It occurs as a native species from the eastern shores of the Mediterranean to Pakistan and Afghanistan. The report by C. V. Piper (1906) of its occurrence in Washington is based on a specimen of S. conica. I have been unable to confirm the statement by M. E. Peck (1961) that S. multinervia is “sparingly introduced” along the coast of Oregon.</discussion></treatment>
