<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">silene</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ehrhart" date="1792">dichotoma</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="unknown" date="unknown">dichotoma</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus silene;species dichotoma;subspecies dichotoma</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, robust; taproot slender. Stems erect, branched distally, usually reddish, (20–)50–100 cm, coarsely hispid. Leaves 2 per node; proximal petiolate, blade lanceolate-spatulate, 3–10 cm × 6–30 mm (including petiole), base tapering into petiole as long as lamina; cauline sessile or nearly so, smaller distally, blade lanceolate-cuneate, 1.5–5 cm × 3–15 mm, apex acute, hispid on both surfaces. Inflorescences with many ascending, elongate branches, many-flowered, open, setose, glandular or not but not viscid; flowers 1 per node; bracts ranging from resembling leaves to narrowly lanceolate, 5–10 mm, apex caudate-acuminate. Flowers subsessile; calyx prominently 10-veined, not inflated, setose, lobed, tubular in flower, ovoid and (7–)10–15 × 2.5–4 mm in fruit, veins parallel, with pale commissures; lobes 5, spreading to recurved, narrowly lanceolate, 2–3 mm, apex acuminate; petals white, rarely pink, clawed, claw equaling calyx, limb obovate but deeply 2-lobed, 5–9 mm, apex truncate, appendages 0.2 mm; stamens exceeding petals, reduced to staminodes in some flowers; filaments white; styles 3, white, ca. 2 times calyx. Capsules enclosed in calyx, ellipsoid, opening by 6 spreading, lanceolate teeth; carpophore stout, 1.5–4 mm, glabrous. Seeds grayish brown to black, broadly reniform with concave faces, ca. 1 mm diam., rugose. 2n = 24.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cultivated land, roadsides, burnt clearings in forests, disturbed prairies;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-2200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; B.C., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), Ont., Que., Sask.; Calif., Colo., Conn., Ga., Idaho, Ill., Ind., Iowa, Ky., Maine, Mass., Mich., Minn., Mo., Mont., Nebr., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Oreg., Pa., Tenn., Tex., Vt., Va., Wash., W.Va., Wis., Wyo.; Europe.</description>
  <number>15a.</number>
  <discussion>Subspecies dichotoma is an occasional adventive weed.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
