<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>18.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>drummondii</species_name><species_authority>Hooker</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 89. 1830</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Drummond’s catchfly</common_name><common_name>forked catchfly</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Gastrolychnis</genus_name><species_name>drummondii</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker) Á. Löve &amp; D. Löve</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lychnis</genus_name><species_name>drummondii</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker) S. Watson</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Melandrium</genus_name><species_name>drummondii</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker) Porsild</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Wahlbergella</genus_name><species_name>drummondii</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker) Rydberg</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial; taproot stout; caudex branched, somewhat fleshy. Stems erect, simple or several from base, retrorsely puberulent proximally, densely so and viscid distally, with stipitate glands. Leaves: blade with stiff, appressed pubescence on both surfaces; basal petiolate, blade lanceolate to elliptic or oblanceolate, (1.5–)3–10 cm × 4–12 mm (including petiole); cauline in 2–5 pairs, blade linear to linear-lanceolate, 3–9 cm × 2–7 mm. Inflorescences 1–20-flowered, bracteate, strongly viscid-glandular or less densely pubescent, longer hairs sometimes purple-septate; bracts narrowly lanceolate, thick, 3–15 mm, herbaceous, apex acuminate. Pedicels stiffly erect, 0.1–5 cm, varying in length within same inflorescence. Flowers: calyx 10-veined, broadly tubular to narrowly ellipsoid, not inflated, 12–18 × 4–8 mm in fruit, 2–3 times as long as broad, membranous between veins, margins dentate with 5 triangular, 1.2–2 mm lobes erect in flower and spreading in fruit, apex acuminate, veins green; petals off-white to dusky pink or dingy reddish purple, clawed, equaling or to 11/2 times calyx, claw broadened distally, limb not differentiated from claw, narrower than claw, 1–3 mm; stamens included in calyx; styles (4–)5, included in calyx. Capsules 12–15 mm, equaling calyx (rarely to 11/2 times calyx), opening by (4–)5 spreading teeth. Seeds dark brown, not winged, reniform to angular, 0.7–1 mm diam., margins finely papillate; papillae triangular, slender, longer than broad.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>c</global_distribution><global_distribution>w North America.</global_distribution><discussion>Subspecies drummondii is characteristically a prairie taxon, while subsp. striata is associated with the Rocky Mountains. However, the two taxa frequently appear to intergrade; e.g., in the Cypress Hills of southern Alberta and Saskatchewan, and in the southern Rockies. Variety kruckebergii appears to be a luxuriant form with a more elongate capsule and calyx. Silene invisa, a Californian species, is similar to S. drummondii, some plants of which, from Nevada and Arizona, tend to be intermediate (see note under S. invisa).</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Petals equaling calyx; fruiting calyces 12–15 × 4–6 mm, 2 1 / 4 –3 times as long as broad; seeds ca. 0.7 mm diam.; inflorescences typically (1–)3–10(–20)-flowered</statement>
      <determination>18a. Silene drummondii subsp. drummondii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Petals 1 1 / 4 –1 1 / 2 times calyx and clearly exserted from it; fruiting calyces 13–18 × 6–8 mm, ca. 2 times as long as broad; seeds ca. 1 mm diam.; inflorescences typically 1–4(–8)-flowered</statement>
      <determination>18b. Silene drummondii subsp. striata</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
