<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Caryophylloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Silene</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Nuttall" date="unknown">hookeri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Torrey and A. Gray, Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 193. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Caryophyllaceae;subfamily Caryophylloideae;genus Silene;species hookeri;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial; caudex much-branched, thick and woody. Stems solitary or numerous, decumbent and rooting at base, becoming erect, 5–14(–25) cm, with gray, soft, curly to retrorsely crispate pubescence, rarely glandular. Leaves: blade spatulate or narrowly lanceolate to oblanceolate, some-times broadly so, 4–7(–10) cm × 8–12(–20) mm, reduced toward base, apex acute, pubescent on both surfaces, especially on midrib; subterranean bractlike, papery. Inflorescences reduced to single, terminal flower or open, (1–)3–5(–9)-flowered cyme, bracteate; bracts leaflike, reduced distally to ca. 1 cm. Pedicels ascending, straight, 1–6 cm, with a short canescence. Flowers: calyx 10-veined, broadly tubular in flower, 12–25  5–8 mm, turbinate in fruit and swelling in middle to ca. 10 mm broad, canescent, rarely sparsely pubescent or glandular; lobes lanceolate, 4–7 mm, with narrow, membranous margins, apex acute; corolla coral pink or white, clawed, claw equaling calyx; limb 4-lobed, usually deeply so, rarely 2-lobed with smaller lateral teeth, lobes 7–22 mm, appendages 2, linear, 1.5–3.5 mm (absent in subsp. bolanderi); stamens slightly longer than corolla claw; stigmas 3, slightly longer than corolla claw. Capsules ovoid to oblong, equaling calyx, dehiscing by 6 teeth; carpophore 2–5 mm. Seeds dark brown to black, reniform, ca. 2 mm broad, with concentric rings of small papillae.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <number>23.</number>
  <discussion>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corolla lobes either 4 of unequal size or 2 with lateral teeth, lobes lanceolate to broadly oblong, 5–10 mm, corolla coral pink or white, appendages 2, 1.5–3.5 mm, linear</description>
      <determination>23a. Silene hookeri subsp. hookeri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corolla lobes 4, equal, linear, 15–25 mm, corolla white with greenish center, appendages absent</description>
      <determination>23b. Silene hookeri subsp. bolanderi</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
