<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>25.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>involucrata</species_name><species_authority>(Chamisso &amp; Schlechtendal) Bocquet</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Candollea</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>22: 22. 1967</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Arctic campion</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Lychnis</genus_name><species_name>apetala</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><variety_name>involucrata</variety_name><variety_authority>Chamisso &amp; Schlechtendal</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Linnaea </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 43. 1826</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lychnis</genus_name><species_name>gillettii</species_name><species_authority>B. Boivin</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, sometimes with dense tufts of basal rosettes of leaves, subglabrous to pubescent and glandular; taproot slender or stout. Flowering stems several, erect, simple or branched, 10–45 cm, usually with 2–5 pairs of leaves. Leaves mainly basal, petiolate; blade narrowly oblanceolate, ± spatulate, 20–60 × 3–5(–10) mm (including petiole), glabrous to pubescent, especially on margins and abaxial veins, pubescence spreading, short, stiff, mainly eglandular. Inflorescences 1–3-flowered, open, bracteate, pubescent, usually densely so, hairs long, flexuous, purple-septate, mostly glandular; bracts narrowly lanceolate, 4–10 mm, usually pubescent. Pedicels usually several times longer than calyx. Flowers pedicellate, rarely sessile, erect, 8–16 mm diam.; calyx prominently 10-veined, not inflated or thin, campanulate or ovate, 8–20 mm, pubescent, especially on veins, rarely almost glabrous, hairs long and short purple-septate, ± glandular, veins heavily suffused with purple (rarely green), sinuses between veins pale, cream colored; petals white, often pink or purple tinged, claw equaling calyx, limb not differentiated from claw, emarginate to obovate, often 2-lobed, ca. 1/2 as long as calyx; stamens included in calyx, spreading horizontally; styles 5, included in calyx. Capsules equaling calyx, opening by 5 teeth, tardily splitting into 10. Seeds brown, winged, ± reniform to angular, 1–1.5 mm diam.; wing to 1/2 seed diam.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>Greenland</global_distribution><global_distribution>nw Canada</global_distribution><global_distribution>Alaska</global_distribution><global_distribution>arctic Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution>e Asia (Russian Far East).</global_distribution><global_distribution>e Asia (Siberia).</global_distribution><discussion>Silene involucrata is a very variable circumpolar and arctic-alpine species complex. Many of the variants have been treated as species by earlier workers. Here, a single species with two subspecies is recognized.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Calyx campanulate to ovoid, 10–20 mm in fruit; flowering stems sturdy, usually less than 20 cm, internodes equaling or shorter than leaves</statement>
      <determination>25a. Silene involucrata subsp. involucrata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Calyx campanulate, 8–10(–12) mm in fruit; flowering stems slender, usually over 30 cm, internodes longer than leaves</statement>
      <determination>25b. Silene involucrata subsp. tenella</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
