<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John W. Thieret,Richard K. Rabeler</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Lamarck" date="unknown">POLYCARPAEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Hist. Nat.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 3, 5, plate 25. 1792</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus POLYCARPAEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">   [Greek poly- , numerous, and karpos , fruit, alluding to the numerous capsules]  </other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs [small shrubs], annual [perennial]. Taproots slender to stout. Stems erect, branched, terete. Leaves opposite, sometimes appearing whorled, not connate, short-petiolate (basal leaves) or sessile (cauline leaves); stipules 2 per node, white, lanceolate, margins entire, apex hairlike; blade 1-veined, oblong-ovate to suborbiculate (basal leaves), subulate to linear (cauline leaves), not succulent, apex acute or hairlike. Inflorescences terminal, compact to loose cymes; bracts paired, scarious. Pedicels erect or spreading. Flowers: perianth and androecium perigynous; hypanthium cup-shaped, not abruptly expanded distally; sepals distinct, silvery with brown midrib, ovate to lanceolate, not keeled, 2.2–3.1 mm, scarious, margins scarious, apex acute; petals 5, pink, blade apex irregularly toothed or entire; nectaries between filament bases; stamens 5; filaments distinct; style 1, filiform, minute, less than 0.1 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 3, subcapitate, smooth to obscurely papillate (50×). Capsules ellipsoid, opening by 3 recurved valves; carpophore present. Seeds 5–8, tan, translucent, pyriform, not compressed, rugulose, marginal wing absent, appendage absent. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Florida</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropics and subtropics</description>
  <description type="distribution">chiefly Old World.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species ca. 50 (1 in the flora): introduced; Florida, tropics and subtropics, chiefly Old World.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species ca. 50 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; Florida, tropics and subtropics, chiefly Old World.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">Polycarpea</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name"> </other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bakker, K. 1957. Revision of the genus Polycarpaea (Caryoph.) in Malaysia. Acta Bot. Neerl. 6: 48–53.</reference>
    <reference>Gagnepain, F. 1908. Contribution à la connaissance du genre Polycarpaea Lamk. J. Bot. (Morot), sér. 2, 1: 275–280.</reference>
    <reference>Lakela, O. 1962. Occurrence of species of Polycarpaea Lam. (Caryophyllaceae) in North America. Rhodora 64: 179–182.</reference>
    <reference>Lakela, O. 1963. Annotation of North American Polycarpaea. Rhodora 65: 35–44.</reference>
    <reference>Sundaramoorthy, S. and D. N. Sen. 1988. Ecology of Indian arid zone weeds. XI. Polycarpaea corymbosa (Linn.) Lamk. Geobios (Jodhpur) 15: 235–237.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
