<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>45.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>polypetala</species_name><species_authority>(Walter) Fernald &amp; B. G. Schubert</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>50: 198. 1948</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Fringed campion</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Cucubalus</genus_name><species_name>polypetalus</species_name><species_authority>Walter</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. Carol., </publication_title><place_in_publication>141. 1788</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>baldwinii</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>fimbriata</species_name><species_authority>Baldwin ex Elliott</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, rhizomatous; taproot stout; caudex branched, woody. Stems decumbent to ascending, scarcely branched, weak, leafy, with several basal, procumbent, nonflowering shoots, 10–40 cm, softly pilose. Leaves 2 per node, blade 2–9 cm × 10–25 mm; proximal petiolate, petiole ciliate, blade broadly oblanceolate; distal sessile, blade obovate to elliptic or lanceolate, spatulate, margins ciliate, apex acute or obtuse, apiculate, glabrous to sparsely pilose. Inflorescences terminal, cymose, usually 3-flowered, open, bracteate; bracts foliaceous. Pedicels shorter than calyx, pilose, with colorless, large, stipitate glands. Flowers: calyx prominently 10-veined, funnelform, umbilicate in fruit, constricted around carpophore, 20–28 × 5–9 mm, broadening distally, papery, thinly pilose, veins parallel, green, with pale commissures, lobes lanceolate, 4–7 mm, apex acute; corolla showy, pink or white, large, clawed, claw equaling calyx, limb fan-shaped, 15–25 mm, laciniate into many narrow segments, appendages absent; stamens equaling calyx; stigmas 3(–4), equaling calyx. Capsules ovoid, included in calyx, opening by 6 (or 8) teeth; carpophore 7–10 mm. Seeds dark reddish brown, broadly reniform, ca. 1 mm, rugose on sides, margins papillate. 2n = 48.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><habitat>rich calcareous loam in deciduous forests and on wooded bluffs</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>0–100 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution><discussion>There is an old collection (Mohr 4000, MO) labelled “Alabama” without date. I have no other records of the occurrence of Silene polypetala in that state.</discussion></treatment>
