<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Caryophylloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Silene</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Desfontaines" date="unknown">pseudatocion</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Atlant.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 353. 1798</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Caryophyllaceae;subfamily Caryophylloideae;genus Silene;species pseudatocion;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual; taproot slender. Stems straggling to erect, much-branched, elongate, 20–70 cm, sparsely retrorse-puberulent. Leaves 2 per node, sessile with spatulate, broad, ciliate base, blade oblanceolate, 1.3–5 cm × 4–15 mm, apex acuminate, glabrous or sparsely setose. Inflorescences cymose, open, compound, pedunculate; bracts leaflike, lanceolate, 3–15 mm, apex acuminate; peduncle ascending, elongate, viscid stipitate-glandular. Pedicels ascending, elongate, viscid stipitate-glandular. Flowers: calyx prominently 10-veined, clavate, with long, slender tube surrounding carpophore, 17–20 × 4–6 mm, veins parallel, green or purple with purple stipitate glands, with pale commissures, lobes lanceolate, 2–3 mm, margins ciliate, apex acute; corolla bright pink, clawed, claw slightly longer than calyx, limb obovate, unlobed, ca. 1 cm, appendages 2, oblong, 2 mm, entire; stamens included in tip of calyx tube; styles 3, exserted. Capsules ovoid, slightly longer than calyx, opening by 6 recurved teeth; carpophore 9–10 mm, pubescent. Seeds dull and very dark brown, almost globose, inrolled like a clenched fist, 1–1.3 mm, sides with radiating wrinkles, finely tuberculate abaxially. 2n = 24 (Balearic Islands).</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">mar</description>
  <description type="phenology">apr</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="habitat">neglected gardens</description>
  <description type="habitat">roadsides</description>
  <description type="habitat">waste places</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe (Balearic Islands)</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa.</description>
  <number>46.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">pseudo-atocion</other_name>
  <discussion>Silene pseudatocion is occasionally grown in gardens and rarely occurs as a weed in California. It is similar to another garden escape, S. pendula, but it differs in having a calyx tube with a very long, slender base and unlobed petals.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
