<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John W. Thieret,Richard K. Rabeler</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Loefling in C. Linnaeus" date="unknown">POLYCARPON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Nat. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10, 2: 859 (as Polycarpa), 881, 1360. 1759</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus POLYCARPON</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek polys , many, and karpos , fruit, alluding to numerous capsules]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual. Taproots slender. Stems prostrate to erect, branched, terete to finely ridged. Leaves opposite or in whorls of 4, not connate, petiolate; stipules 2 per node, silvery, lanceolate to triangular-ovate, margins entire or irregularly cut, apex acuminate to aristate; blade 1-veined, spatulate or oblanceolate to ovate or elliptic, not succulent, apex obtuse, sometimes mucronate. Inflorescences terminal or axillary, dense or lax cymes; bracts paired or absent. Pedicels erect. Flowers: perianth and androecium perigynous; hypanthium minute, cup-shaped, not abruptly expanded distally; sepals distinct, green, lanceolate to elliptic or ovate, often keeled, 1–2.5 mm, herbaceous, margins white, scarious, apex acute, ± hooded, ± awned; petals often fugacious, 5, white, blade apex emarginate; nectaries between filament bases; stamens 3–5; filaments shortly connate distally around ovary; style 1, obscurely 3-branched, filiform, 0.1–0.3 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 3, linear along adaxial surface of style branches, papillate (30×). Capsules ovoid to spherical, opening by 3 incurved or twisting valves; carpophore present. Seeds ca. 8–15, whitish, ovoid to lenticular or triangular, laterally compressed to angular, papillate or granular, marginal wing absent, appendage absent. x = [7], 8, 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America, South America, Europe (including Mediterranean region), Asia, Africa; Polycarpon tetraphyllum introduced widely, including e North America, Australia.</description>
  <number>5.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name"> Manyseed</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 9 or 15 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>C. Mohr’s (1901) report of Polycarpon alsinifolium (Bivona-Bernardi) de Candolle from Alabama was based on misidentification of P. tetraphyllum subsp. tetraphyllum.</discussion>
  <discussion>The shape of the sepal apex in Polycarpon is varied, with the herbaceous central portion sometimes prolonged beyond the scarious margins into a brief, narrow hood or awn, suggesting an aristate apex.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Howell, J. T. 1941. Notes on Polycarpon. Leafl. W. Bot. 3: 80.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals 1.5–2.5 mm, keeled; stipules 1.8–2.8 mm; leaves in whorls of 4 or opposite</description>
      <determination>1.  Polycarpon tetraphyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals 1–1.5 mm, flat or sometimes barely keeled; stipules 0.4–1.2 mm; leaves opposite, not whorled</description>
      <determination>2.  Polycarpon depressum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
