<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>50.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>rotundifolia</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 288. 1818</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Round-leaved catchfly</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Melandrium</genus_name><species_name>rotundifolium</species_name><species_authority>(Nuttall) Rohrbach</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial; taproot stout, fleshy; caudex branched. Stems several, straggling to erect, freely branched, 2–7 cm, pilose and glandular, sparsely so proximally. Leaves: basal leaves withered at time of flowering, distal sessile, proximal petiolate, largest on mid to distal stem; blade subrotund to broadly ovate-lanceolate, 3–10 cm × 20–70 mm, base cuneate into petiole, apex short-acuminate, sparsely short-pilose. Inflorescences cymose, open, few-flowered, leafy, bracteate; bracts resembling distal leaves. Pedicels 1–3(–4) cm, viscid, with long septate-glandular hairs. Flowers: calyx indistinctly veined, tubular, broadened distally, constricted towards base around carpophore, ± umbilicate, 20–25 × 5–8 mm, herbaceous, glandular-pilose, lobes triangular, 3–4 mm, margins narrow, membranous, ciliate; corolla scarlet, clawed, claw equaling calyx, limb deeply 2-lobed, 10–15 mm, lobes lanceolate, sometimes with 2 smaller lateral teeth, ciliate, appendages saccate, 1–1.5 mm, with clear area abaxially; stamens shortly exserted; styles 3, shortly exserted. Capsules narrowly ellipsoid, not distending calyx, included within it, opening by 6 teeth; carpophore 6–8 mm. Seeds gray, broadly reniform, plump, ca. 1 mm, shallowly papillate. 2n = 48.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>woodlands</habitat><habitat>partially shaded cliffs and bluffs</habitat><elevation>200–600 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ky.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ohio</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tenn.</us_distribution><us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution><discussion>Silene rotundifolia is clearly related to S. laciniata but is a well-marked species of the deciduous forest region.</discussion></treatment>
