<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">silene</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="C. V. Morton &amp; J. W. Thompson" date="1933">seelyi</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Torreya</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>33: 70. 1933</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus silene;species seelyi</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Anotites</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(C. V. Morton &amp; J. W. Thompson) W. A. Weber" date="unknown">seelyi</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Anotites;species seelyi;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; taproot slender; caudex with much-branched crown, finely pubescent throughout with mainly glandular hairs. Stems numerous, decumbent to ascending, branched, tufted, leafy, slender, 5–30 cm. Leaves 2 per node, sessile or nearly so, blade reticulate-veined, lanceolate to ovate-lanceolate, thin, 0.8–2 cm × 3–8 mm, broadest proximally, base rounded, apex acute. Inflorescences cymose, open, compound, leafy, single flowers borne terminally and in axils of distal leaves; bracteoles, when present, 2. Pedicels straight, slender, 1/2–3 times longer than calyx. Flowers: calyx green, obscurely 10-veined, narrowly campanulate, in fruit 6–9 × 3–4 mm, herbaceous, pubescent, veins without conspicuous pale commissures; lobes triangular, 2–3 mm; corolla dark red, sometimes white, clawed, claw slightly longer than calyx, limb deeply 2-lobed, 2–3 mm, appendages 2, very small; stamens exserted; styles 3, exserted. Capsules ellipsoid, included in calyx, opening by 6 teeth; carpophore ca. 1.5 mm. Seeds brown, not winged, broadly reniform, flattened, ca. 0.8 mm, reticulate. 2n = 24.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Crevices and ledges on granite and basalt cliffs;</description>
  <description type="elevation">800-1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wash.</description>
  <number>54.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Seely’s catchfly or silene</other_name>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Silene seelyi is confined to the Wenatchee Mountains. It closely related to S. menziesii, but is distinguished by its usually dark red flowers and broadly lanceolate leaves.</discussion>
  <discussion>Silene seelyi is in the Center for Plant Conservation’s National Collection of Endangered Plants.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
