<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">silene</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Persoon" date="1805">sibirica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 497. 1805</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus silene;species sibirica</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cucubalus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">sibiricus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Nat. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10, 2: 1031. 1759</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cucubalus;species sibiricus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, producing several decumbent, short, woody, underground shoots bearing perennating buds and terminated by erect flowering shoots; taproot stout, woody; caudex crown branched. Stems simple but with short axillary leafy shoots, leafy, 40–60 cm, glossy, ± glabrous, with 10–20 nodes proximal to inflorescence. Leaves: basal withered at time of flowering; cauline whorled, appearing fasciculate (more than 4) at each node, connate at base, reduced distally, tapered at both ends, blade linear to very narrowly elliptic-lanceolate, 0.5–8 cm × 1–12 mm, base broadened, margins scabrous, apex acute, subglabrous to minutely puberulent on both surfaces. Inflorescences thyrsate, verticillate, open, with many short, ascending branches bearing large numbers of small, unisexual flowers, bracteate; bracts connate basally, triangular, 2–10 mm, margins finely ciliate, apex acuminate. Pedicels ascending, straight, fasciculate, wiry, ± equaling calyx, glabrous or sparsely and minutely puberulent. Flowers mostly unisexual; calyx pale green, indistinctly 10-veined, elliptic, constricted near base, umbilicate, ca. 5 × 2 mm, lobes with thickened midrib, ovate-obtuse, 0.2 mm, margins crenate, membranous; corolla greenish white, clawed, claw and limb not differentiated, narrowly oblong, unlobed, less than 2 times length of calyx, appendages absent; stamens exserted, longer than corolla; styles 3, exserted, longer than corolla. Capsules green, ovoid-conic, longer than calyx, opening by 6 teeth; carpophore shorter than 1 mm. Seeds brown, winged, reniform, ca. 1 mm, faces with shallow radiating ridges.</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="phenology">aug</description>
  <description type="habitat">arable land</description>
  <description type="habitat">pastures</description>
  <description type="habitat">roadsides</description>
  <description type="habitat">sand dunes</description>
  <description type="elevation">300–500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Sask.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe (Ukraine)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia (Mongolia).</description>
  <number>56.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Siberian catchfly</other_name>
  <discussion>Silene sibirica is a very distinct species with masses of small flowers on stiffly erect stems, and narrow, fascicled leaves. It was abundant and persisted for a number of years in the 1950s near Duck Lake and Bladworth in central Saskatchewan.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
