<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>58.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Silene</genus_name><species_name>spaldingii</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>10: 344. 1875</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Spalding’s catchfly or campion</common_name><description>Plants perennial, viscid; taproot stout; caudex branched, woody, producing several to many shoots. Stems erect, branched, leafy, 20–60 cm, villose-tomentose, viscid-glandular. Leaves 2 per node, connate proximally, sessile, largest in mid stem; blade lanceolate, 3–7 cm × 5–15 mm, apex acute, glandular-tomentose throughout. Inflorescences open, leafy cymes, bracteate, viscid and glandular-tomentose, branches ascending, mostly floriferous, flowers terminal and at distal nodes; bracts leaflike, 5–30 mm. Pedicels shorter than calyx. Flowers: calyx obscurely 10-veined, tubular-campanulate, 10–15 × 4–5 mm in flower, becoming clavate and 15–20 × 6–8 mm in fruit, narrowed toward base around carpophore, herbaceous, viscid-pubescent, veins more distinct at base, without conspicuous pale commissures, lobes narrowly lanceolate, 3–6 mm, margins very narrow, membranous, apex blunt; corolla greenish white, clawed, claw equaling calyx, widened distally, limb emarginate, 2 × 4 mm, appendages 4(–6), ca. 0.5 mm; stamens equaling petals; styles 3, equaling petals. Capsules ellipsoid, slightly longer than calyx, opening by 6 teeth; carpophore 1.5–2.5 mm. Seeds yellowish brown, winged, reniform, ca. 2 mm, rugose; wing broad, wrinkled. 2n = 48.</description><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>mixed prairie and ponderosa pine forests in swales and on dry hillsides</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>800–1100 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution></treatment>
