<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Caryophylloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Silene</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Jessen" date="unknown">viscaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="unknown" date="unknown">viscaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Caryophyllaceae;subfamily Caryophylloideae;genus Silene;species viscaria;subspecies viscaria;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; taproot stout, branched; caudex compact, multicapitate. Stems erect, simple proximal to inflorescence, 30–90 cm, glabrous, viscid, especially at nodes. Leaves: basal numer-ous, tufted, petiolate, blade ob-lanceolate to linear-oblanceo-late, 4–15 cm × 2–10 mm (in-cluding petiole), apex acute, glabrous, ciliate at base; cauline in 2–4 pairs, connate proximally, sessile. reduced distally, blade linear-lanceolate, 2–10 cm × 2–8 mm, apex acute, glabrous, ciliate at base. Inflorescences paniculate, consisting of short, interrupted cymes, narrow, bracteate, bracteolate; cyme 3–10-flowered, proximal ones pedunculate; peduncle to 3 cm; bracts leaflike, to 3 cm; bracteoles broadly lanceolate, 3–10 mm, margins membranous, apex acuminate. Pedicels shorter than calyx, glabrous but viscid. Flowers 14–22 mm diam.; calyx purple, obscurely veined, narrowly campanulate in flower, 6–10 × 3–4 mm, clavate in fruit, 10–15 × ca. 5 mm, papery, puberulent, lobes ovate, ca. 1.5 cm, margins narrow, membranous, apex obtuse; corolla purple or dark pink (rarely white), ca. 11/2–2 times calyx, clawed, claw equaling calyx, limb spreading, obovate, entire or slightly notched, 5–9 mm, appendages 2, oblong, 3 mm; stamens shortly exserted; stigmas 5, shortly exserted. Capsules ovoid, equaling calyx, opening by 5 teeth; carpophore 3–5 mm. Seeds dark brown, reniform, 0.3–0.5 mm, finely tuberculate. 2n = 24 (Europe).</description>
  <description type="phenology">early summer</description>
  <description type="habitat">roadsides</description>
  <description type="habitat">waste ground</description>
  <description type="habitat">fields</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Conn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Maine</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mass.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.H.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ohio</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe.</description>
  <number>67a.</number>
  <discussion>Subspecies viscaria is an attractive garden plant similar to S. suecica but somewhat larger and sturdier with viscid pedicels. It occasionally escapes but does not persist.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
