<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ronald L. Hartman,Richard K. Rabeler</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">caryophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">LOEFLINGIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 35. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ge. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 22. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family caryophyllaceae;genus LOEFLINGIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For P. Loefling, 1729–1756, Swedish botanist and explorer]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual. Taproots slender. Stems prostrate to erect, usually dichotomously branched at or near base, terete. Leaves opposite, basal leaves absent, axillary leaf clusters often present, weakly connate, sessile; stipules 2 per node, ± white to silvery, bristlelike, margins entire, apex acuminate; blade 1-veined or obscurely so, subulate to oblong, not succulent, apex blunt to spine-tipped. Inflorescences axillary, 1(–2)-flowered; bracts absent. Pedicels: flowers sessile. Flowers: perianth and androecium hypogynous; sepals ± distinct, green, linear to lanceolate, 1.8–6.5 mm, herbaceous, margins silvery, often scarious, apex acute to spinose; petals absent or rudimentary; nectaries not apparent; stamens 3–5, arising from base of ovary; filaments distinct; styles 3, distinct, filiform, shorter than 0.1 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 3, linear along adaxial surface of styles, papillate (30×). Capsules lanceoloid to ovoid, opening by 3 slightly recurved valves; carpophore absent. Seeds 25–35, tan with reddish brown band on curved edge, tear-shaped, plump, minutely papillate on broadly grooved edge, marginal wing absent, appendage absent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Europe (w Mediterranean region), sw Asia, Africa (w Mediterranean region, Sahara).</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name"> </other_name>
  <discussion>Species 7 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Barneby, R. C. and E. C. Twisselmann. 1970. Notes on Loeflingia (Caryophyllaceae). Madroño 20: 398–408.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
