<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="J. T. Howell" date="1944">ripleyi</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Leafl. W. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 5. 1944</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;species ripleyi</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, sprawling to decum-bent, occasionally scapose, 0.5–2.5(–4) × 0.5–5(–7) dm, grayish-tomentose. Stems decumbent to slightly spreading or erect, often with persistent leaf bases, up to 1/4 height of plant; caudex stems absent or compact; aerial flowering stems spreading to erect, slender, solid, not fistulose, 0.05–2.5(–3.5) dm, tomentose. Leaves cauline, 1 per node or fasciculate; petiole 0.05–0.15 cm, villous; blade narrowly oblanceolate, 0.2–0.6 × 0.05–0.1 cm, densely white-tomentose abaxially, thinly floccose to villous adaxially, margins revolute. Inflorescences cymose-umbellate or capitate and reduced to single involucre; branches usually dichotomous, sometimes with secondaries suppressed, occasionally absent, tomentose; bracts absent. Peduncles erect, 0.1–1.5 cm, thinly floccose. Involucres 1 per node, campanulate, 3–3.5 × 3–3.5 mm, thinly floccose or villous to subglabrous; teeth 3–5, erect, 0.7–1 mm. Flowers 3.5–4.5 mm; perianth white, glabrous; tepals connate proximal 1/5, dimorphic, those of outer whorl nearly orbiculate, 3–3.5 mm wide, those of inner whorl broadly obovate, 2–2.5 mm wide; stamens long-exserted, 4–5 mm; filaments villous to densely pilose proximally. Achenes light brown, 2–2.5 mm, glabrous.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Mar-Jun.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy clay flats and slopes on edge of sandstone outcrops, oak-juniper woodlands;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1000-1900 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <number>11.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Ripley’s wild buckwheat</other_name>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Eriogonum ripleyi is known only from two areas in Arizona, one near Frazier’s Well in Coconino County and a second in the Verdi Valley area of southeastern Yavapai and extreme northwestern Maricopa counties. The species is worthy of cultivation. Ripley’s wild buckwheat is considered a “sensitive” species in Arizona.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
