<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>11.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><species_name>ripleyi</species_name><species_authority>J. T. Howell</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Leafl. W. Bot.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4: 5. 1944</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Ripley’s wild buckwheat</common_name><description>Subshrubs, sprawling to decum-bent, occasionally scapose, 0.5–2.5(–4) × 0.5–5(–7) dm, grayish-tomentose. Stems decumbent to slightly spreading or erect, often with persistent leaf bases, up to 1/4 height of plant; caudex stems absent or compact; aerial flowering stems spreading to erect, slender, solid, not fistulose, 0.05–2.5(–3.5) dm, tomentose. Leaves cauline, 1 per node or fasciculate; petiole 0.05–0.15 cm, villous; blade narrowly oblanceolate, 0.2–0.6 × 0.05–0.1 cm, densely white-tomentose abaxially, thinly floccose to villous adaxially, margins revolute. Inflorescences cymose-umbellate or capitate and reduced to single involucre; branches usually dichotomous, sometimes with secondaries suppressed, occasionally absent, tomentose; bracts absent. Peduncles erect, 0.1–1.5 cm, thinly floccose. Involucres 1 per node, campanulate, 3–3.5 × 3–3.5 mm, thinly floccose or villous to subglabrous; teeth 3–5, erect, 0.7–1 mm. Flowers 3.5–4.5 mm; perianth white, glabrous; tepals connate proximal 1/5, dimorphic, those of outer whorl nearly orbiculate, 3–3.5 mm wide, those of inner whorl broadly obovate, 2–2.5 mm wide; stamens long-exserted, 4–5 mm; filaments villous to densely pilose proximally. Achenes light brown, 2–2.5 mm, glabrous.</description><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>sandy clay flats and slopes on edge of sandstone outcrops</habitat><habitat>oak-juniper woodlands</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>1000–1900 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution><discussion>Eriogonum ripleyi is known only from two areas in Arizona, one near Frazier’s Well in Coconino County and a second in the Verdi Valley area of southeastern Yavapai and extreme northwestern Maricopa counties. The species is worthy of cultivation. Ripley’s wild buckwheat is considered a “sensitive” species in Arizona.</discussion></treatment>
