<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bentham" date="1836">fasciculatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="unknown" date="unknown">fasciculatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;species fasciculatum;variety fasciculatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">fasciculatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="(Gandoger) S. Stokes" date="unknown">aspalathoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eriogonum;species fasciculatum;subspecies aspalathoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or subshrubs, spreading and often decumbent, 1–5 × 5–30 dm, mostly glabrous. grayish. Aerial flowering stems glabrous, usually grayish or reddish. Leaf blades blade linear to linear-oblanceolate, 0.6–1(–1.2) × 0.05–0.2(–0.4) cm, thinly white-tomentose abaxially, glabrous and green adaxially, margins tightly revolute. Inflorescences usually capitate, occasionally cymose; branches mostly glabrous. Involucres narrowly turbinate, 3–4 × 1.5–2 mm, glabrous or nearly so. Perianths glabrous or with only a few hairs proximally. 2n = 40.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering year-round.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy mesa tops and slopes in coast scrub and chaparral communities;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.; Mexico (Baja California).</description>
  <number>80c.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Coastal California buckwheat</other_name>
  <discussion>Variety fasciculatum is the tetraploid coastal expression of the species, consisting mainly of low, spreading plants of the coastal bluffs and mesas near the ocean and on the offshore islands. It occurs along the immediate coast from San Luis Obispo County southward, but is found inland in Los Angeles, Orange, and San Diego counties, where plants typically are larger and more shrub-like. The tetraploid var. fasciculatum and the octoploid var. foliolosum are not always distinct morphologically. Variety fasciculatum hybridizes with E. molle Greene on Cedros Island in Mexico. The decumbent coastal expressions are occasionally cultivated as cover plants in rock gardens.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
