<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1b.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><genus_authority>Michaux</genus_authority><subgenus_name>Micrantha</subgenus_name><subgenus_authority>(Bentham) Reveal</subgenus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in J. E. Gunckel, Curr. Topics Pl. Sci.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>237. 1969</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><section_name>Micrantha</section_name><section_authority>Bentham</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London </publication_title><place_in_publication>17: 413. 1836</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, biennial or annual, polygamodioecious, floccose to tomentose; taproot somewhat woody. Stems erect, without persistent leaf bases, pubescent; caudex stems absent; aerial flowering stems erect, slender to stout, solid, not disarticulating in ringlike segments proximally, arising directly from the root. Leaves persistent or marcescent, in basal rosettes or fasciculate and scattered along stems, 1 per node; blade usually tomentose. Inflorescences terminal, cymose, compact to open; branches dichotomous, round, smooth, tomentose to floccose; bracts 3, connate basally, scalelike. Peduncles absent or erect, slender. Involucres 1 per node, not appressed to inflorescence branches, turbinate to campanulate; teeth 5–6, erect, apex acute. Flowers not attenuate at base, without stipelike base; perianth white to cream, rose, or reddish brown, glabrous abaxially, densely pubescent and minutely glandular adaxially; tepals connate proximally 1/4–1/3 their length, dimorphic; stamens included or slightly exserted; filaments pilose proximally. Achenes brown, not winged, 3-gonous, glabrous. Seeds: embryo curved.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>c North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>including n Mexico.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Outer tepals obovate, 0.9–1.5 mm wide; involucres 2.5–4 mm, tomentose to floccose abaxially, glabrous adaxially; plants grayish</statement>
      <determination>102. Eriogonum annuum</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Outer tepals oblong-cordate, 1.5–2 mm wide; involucres 2–2.5 mm, usually tomentose on both surfaces; plants reddish</statement>
      <determination>103. Eriogonum multiflorum</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
