<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;subgenus Eriogonum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, erect, polycarpic perennials, tomentose or glabrous; taproot woody. Stems erect, tomentose to floccose or glabrous; caudex stems absent; aerial flowering stems erect, slender to stout, solid, not hollow, fistulose, or disarticulating in ringlike segments proximally, arising directly from the root. Leaves usually persistent, basal or cauline, 1 per node or fasciculate; blade tomentose abaxially. Inflorescences terminal, cymose, open; branches mostly dichotomous, not disarticulating into ringlike segments, round and smooth or finely striated or grooved, tomentose; bracts 3(–5), connate basally, scalelike or leaflike. Peduncles absent or erect and stout. Involucres 1 per node, not appressed to the inflorescence branches, turbinate to campanulate; teeth 5, erect, apex acute. Flowers attenuate at base, with stipelike base 0.5–7 mm; perianth cream to light tan or yellow, densely pubescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially; tepals connate proximally 1/4–1/3 their length, monomorphic or dimorphic; stamens exserted; filaments glabrous or densely pilose. Achenes brown, not winged, 3-gonous, glabrous or pubescent. Seeds: embryo straight.</description>
  <description type="distribution">United States.</description>
  <number>1d.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals monomorphic; perianths densely white- or silvery-tomentose abaxially; filaments glabrous; Arkansas, Kansas, New Mexico, Oklahoma, and Texas e to Alabama, Florida, Kentucky, and Tennessee</description>
      <determination>105. Eriogonum longifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals dimorphic; perianths densely tannish- to rusty-lanate abaxially; filaments pilose; se Alabama, Florida, Georgia, and South Carolina</description>
      <determination>106. Eriogonum tomentosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
