<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey" date="1827">umbellatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Lyceum Nat. Hist. New York</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 241. 1827</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;species umbellatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, subshrubs, or shrubs, cespitose, matted or spreading, sometimes erect, often polygamo-dioecious, (0.2–)1–12(–20) × (0.5–)1–12(–20) dm, glabrous or tomentose. Stems: caudex spread-ing; aerial flowering stems spread-ing to erect or nearly so, slender, solid, not fistulose, arising at nodes of caudex branches and at distal nodes of short, nonflowering aerial branches, (0.1–)0.5–3(–4) dm, without a whorl of bracts at midlength. Leaves in loose to compact basal rosettes; petiole 0.1–3(–4) cm, mostly tomentose to floccose or glabrous; blade oblong-ovate or oblanceolate to elliptic to oval, 0.3–3(–4) × 0.1–2.5 cm, densely lanate to tomentose or floccose abaxially, tomentose to floccose or glabrous adaxially, occasionally glabrous on both surfaces, margins entire, plane or rarely wavy. Inflorescences umbellate or compound-umbellate, rarely subcapitate or capitate, 3–25 × 2–18 cm; branches tomentose to floccose or glabrous, rarely with whorl of bracts ca. midlength; bracts 3–several, semileaflike at proximal node, 0.3–2.5 × 0.2–1.8 cm, usually scalelike distally, 1–5 × 0.5–3 mm. Involucres 1 per node, turbinate to campanulate, 1–6 × (1–)1.5–10 mm, tomentose to thinly floccose or glabrous; teeth 6–12, lobelike, reflexed, 1–4(–6) mm. Flowers 2–10(–12) mm, including (0.7–)1.3–2 mm stipelike base; perianth various shades of white, yellow, or red, glabrous; tepals monomorphic, usually spatulate to obovate; stamens exserted, 2–8 mm; filaments pilose proximally. Achenes light brown to brown, 2–7 mm, glabrous except for sparsely pubescent beak.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <number>107.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sulphur flower</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 41 (41 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Eriogonum umbellatum is a widespread and exceedingly variable species rivaling Astragalus lentiginosus Douglas ex Hooker in complexity. Only the variety majus is sometimes recognized at the species rank (as E. subalpinum).</discussion>
  <discussion>In the following key and descriptions, reference is made to “glabrous” leaf surfaces. This is a function of both age and power of observation. High-power magnification may show some exceedingly fine hairs that are not readily observable to the naked eye. Furthermore, new leaves that ultimately will be “glabrous” will have some fine-tomentose pubescence that becomes less obvious (or even wholly inconspicuous) as the blade expands and matures. Here, the term “glabrous” is used to refer to leaves that are not obviously hairy and are typically bright green on both surfaces when the plant is at full anthesis.</discussion>
  <discussion>There are several reported uses of sulphur flower in the enthobotany literature, mostly without an indication of the variety. J. B. Romero (1954) indicated that in California, where most of the variants are found, an infusion of the flowers is used for ptomaine poisoning, and M. L. Zigmond (1981) stated that the Kawaiisu used mashed flowers as a salve for gonorrheal sores. E. V. A. Murphey (1959), who worked with P. Train et al. (1941), reported that in Nevada members of the species (most likely var. nevadense) were used in the treatment of colds and stomachaches; J. H. Steward (1933) reported the same uses among the Owens Valley Piute in California. Train and his group noted that poultices of leaves and sometimes roots were used for lameness or rheumatism. In Oregon, leaves of var. ellipticum were used in a poultice to soothe pain, especially that resulting from burns (F. V. Coville 1897; L. Spier 1930). Most of the reports associated with the Navajo or Diné people probably relate to the use of var. subaridum. L. C. Wyman and S. K. Harris (1951) found the species used as a disinfectant or an emetic. The Cheyenne people employed a mixture of powdered stems and flowers to halt lengthy menses (G. B. Grinnell 1923; J. A. Hart 1981). According to A. Johnston (1987), the Blackfoot made a tea from boiled leaves.</discussion>
  <discussion>The cythera metalmark butterfly (Apodemia mormo cythera) is found in association with a few varieties of sulphur flower (G. F. Pratt and G. R. Ballmer 1991). More commonly seen with the species are the Rocky Mountain dotted-blue (Euphilotes ancilla) and lupine blue (Plebeius lupini).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences compound-umbellate, or with at least some branches seemingly with whorl of bracts about midlength.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence branches with a whorl of bracts at midlength (see also E. umbellatum var. polyanthum ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths bright yellow; flowers 7–10 mm; Sierra Nevada, c California107nn. Eriogonum umbellatum var. torreyanum</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths cream or whitish; flowers 4–7 mm; Warner Mountains, se Oregon and ne California107oo. Eriogonum umbellatum var. glaberrimum</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence branches without a whorl of bracts at midlength, bracts restricted to base of inflorescence or involucres.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers 7–10(–12) mm; shrubs 5–15(–20) × 5–20 dm; inflorescences branched 2–4 times; Humboldt and Trinity counties, California107kk. Eriogonum umbellatum var. speciosum</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers 3–8 mm; matted herbs or subshrubs, or, if shrubby, inflorescences branched 4 or more times, or not of Humboldt and Trinity counties, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths cream, whitish, or pale yellow to greenish yellow, becoming reddish brown to rose or pink.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths yellow, becoming reddish brown to rose or pink, with large reddish spot on each midrib; plants spreading to somewhat prostrate mats; se California, s Nevada107gg. Eriogonum umbellatum var. versicolor (in part)</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths cream, whitish, or pale yellow to greenish yellow, without large reddish spot on midrib; plants subshrubs or shrubs; nc Arizona, se California, s Nevada, s Utah107hh. Eriogonum umbellatum var. juniporinum</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths bright yellow, not becoming reddish brown to rose or pink.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades thinly floccose, glabrous, or densely lanate to tomentose on both surfaces at anthesis (see also E. umbellatum var. munzii , s California).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades densely lanate on both surfaces; wc California107bb. Eriogonum umbellatum var. bahiiforme</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades lanate to tomentose abaxially, tomentose to densely floccose adaxially, sometimes thinly floccose or glabrous on both surfaces; nw or ec California, Intermountain West, or Pacific Northwest.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades lanate to tomentose abaxially, thinly tomentose to floccose and greenish adaxially; nw California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 0.3–0.7 cm wide; involucral lobes 1–3 mm; plants of serpentine soils; Glenn, Lake, Mendocino, Sonoma, Tehama, and Trinity counties, California107cc. Eriogonum umbellatum var. smallianum (in part)</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades (0.5–)0.8–1.8(–2) cm wide; involucral lobes (3–)4–6 mm; plants of nonserpentine soils; Siskiyou County,California107ii. Eriogonum umbellatum var. lautum (in part)</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually thinly floccose or glabrous on both surfaces; not of nw California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades thinly floccose on both surfaces, or glabrous and green adaxially (rarely glabrous on both surfaces in s Utah, or tomentose abaxially in se Utah); e and s California to sw Colorado and ne Arizona107dd. Eriogonum umbellatum var. subaridum</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades glabrous on both surfaces; e Idaho, ne Oregon, se Washington, and ec California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Herbs; leaf blades broadly elliptic, 1–1.5 cm wide; e Idaho, ne Oregon, and se Washington</description>
      <determination>107x. Eriogonum umbellatum var. devestivum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Subshrubs or shrubs; leaf blades oblanceolate to narrowly elliptic, 0.3–1 cm wide; s Mono, Inyo, and ne Tulare counties, California107ee. Eriogonum umbellatum var. chlorothamnus</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades thinly to densely tomentose or lanate abaxially, less so to floccose, nearly glabrous, or glabrous adaxially (rarely both surfaces tomentose in E. umbellatum var. munzii , s California).</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants densely branched, shrubs; w foothills, Sierra Nevada, n California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades white-tomentose abaxially; inflorescences branched 1–2(–3) times, branches thinly floccose or glabrous, central branch sometimes seemingly with a whorl of bracts ca. midlength; Butte, Plumas, and Sierra counties107jj. Eriogonum umbellatum var. polyanthum</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades rusty-lanate to tomentose abaxially; inflorescences branched 3–4 time, branches tomentose to floccose, central branch without a whorl of bracts ca. midlength; Butte County107ll. Eriogonum umbellatum var. ahartii</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants usually matted herbs or more openly and sparsely branched subshrubs or shrubs; mountains, Sierra Nevada, c and n California, wc Nevada, or Siskiyou and Trinity mountains, nw California (but not on the western foothills), sw Oregon, n Arizona, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, or Washington.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowering stems mostly sparsely floccose or glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades oblong-ovate to elliptic or oval, 1–1.5(–2) cm wide; plants compact mats; n Arizona107mm. Eriogonum umbellatum var. cognatum</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually narrowly elliptic, 0.3–1(–1.3) cm wide; plants subshrubs or spreading mats; California, Nevada, Oregon.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins plane; flowering stems without a single leaflike bract ca. midlength; Sierra Nevada, e California, wc Nevada</description>
      <determination>107y. Eriogonum umbellatum var. furcosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins often finely wavy; flowering stems often with a single leaflike bract ca. midlength; Siskiyou and Trinity mountains, nw California, sw Oregon</description>
      <determination>107z. Eriogonum umbellatum var. argus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowering stems usually tomentose or floccose, rarely nearly glabrous at maturity.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually broadly elliptic to oval.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades gray abaxially; c Colorado</description>
      <determination>107v. Eriogonum umbellatum var. ramulosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades white abaxially; n California107ii. Eriogonum umbellatum var. lautum (in part)</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 1–1.5 cm wide, usually glabrous adaxially; Idaho, w Montana, Oregon, and e Washington</description>
      <determination>107w. Eriogonum umbellatum var. ellipticum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 0.3–1 cm wide, usually floccose adaxially; California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 0.3–0.7 cm wide; nw California107cc. Eriogonum umbellatum var. smallianum (in part)</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 0.5–1 cm wide; s California107ff. Eriogonum umbellatum var. munzii</description>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences umbellate, not compound-umbellate or with any branches seemingly with whorl of bracts about midlength.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths usually whitish or cream to red, occasionally yellow.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades densely lanate on both surfaces; perianths lemon yellow to yellowish red; San Gabriel and San Bernardino mountains, e Los Angeles and w San Bernardino counties, California</description>
      <determination>107t. Eriogonum umbellatum var. minus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades tomentose to floccose or glabrous adaxially, sometimes glabrous on both surfaces at full anthesis; perianths not lemon yellow or yellowish red; not of e Los Angeles or w San Bernardino counties, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades glabrous on both surfaces; s Idaho and sw Montana to w Wyoming, ne Nevada, and n Utah</description>
      <determination>107r. Eriogonum umbellatum var. desereticum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades densely floccose to to-mentose or lanate at least abaxially at full anthesis; widespread.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades densely lanate abaxially, glabrous and olive green to bright green adaxially; plants compact mats; perianths cream; Rocky Mountains to Cascade Range</description>
      <determination>107u. Eriogonum umbellatum var. majus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades densely floccose to tomentose abaxially, less so or glabrous and green adaxially; plants spreading mats, rarely compact; perianths pale yellow to cream or whitish, rarely greenish white or yellow, becoming reddish brown to rose or pink, with large reddish spots on each midrib; Rocky Mountains to Sierra Nevada.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths pale yellow to cream or whitish, rarely greenish white; leaf blades usually greenish adaxially; se Oregon and e California to w Montana, s Idaho, w Wyoming, c Nevada, and n Utah</description>
      <determination>107q. Eriogonum umbellatum var. dichrocephalum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths yellow, becoming reddish brown to rose or pink, with large reddish spot on each midrib; leaf blades usually reddish adaxially; se California, s Nevada107gg. Eriogonum umbellatum var. versicolor (in part)</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths bright yellow (pale yellow in some individuals of var. vernum in Nevada).</description>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Umbels with branches usually longer than 2.5 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades glabrous on both surfaces at full anthesis, occasionally with some individual blades thinly floccose abaxially</description>
      <determination>107d. Eriogonum umbellatum var. aureum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades at least thinly tomentose or lanate abaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades thinly tomentose to thinly floccose on both surfaces, or glabrous adaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants matted herbs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades broadly elliptic to ovate, (0.8–)2–3(–3.5) × (0.7–)1–2(–2.5) cm; s Idaho, ne Nevada, wc Wyoming</description>
      <determination>107c. Eriogonumumbellatum var. stragulum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades narrowly elliptic, 0.7–2.5 × 0.3–1 cm; nw Arizona</description>
      <determination>107s. Eriogonumumbellatum var. mohavense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants subshrubs or shrubs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers 4–7 mm; Cali-fornia, n Nevada, se Oregon</description>
      <determination>107n. Eriogonum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers (5–)6–10 mm; n Nye County, Nevada</description>
      <determination>107o. Eriogonumumbellatum var. vernum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades densely white-lanate or tomentose abaxially, less so to floccose or glabrous adaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Subshrubs 3–5 dm; non-serpentine soils; n California and sc Oregon</description>
      <determination>107k. Eriogonumumbellatum var. dumosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Herbs (0.7–)1–4.5(–5) dm; Rocky Mountains or, if in California and Oregon, often on serpentine soils.</description>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants usually compact mats; nonserpentine soils; Rocky Mountains, sw Montana and e Idaho to Colorado, s and w Wyo-ming, and n Utah</description>
      <determination>107a. Eriogonumumbellatum var.umbellatum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants spreading to prostrate mats; often on serpentine soils; n California and sw Oregon.</description>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowering stems 1–2.5(–4) dm; leaf blades 0.5–2(–3.5) cm; flowers 6–8(–9) mm; 400–1700(–2100) m</description>
      <determination>107l. Eriogonumumbellatum var. goodmanii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowering stems 0.5–1.5 dm; leaf blades 0.5–1(–1.5) cm; flowers 3–6 mm; 1700–2800 m</description>
      <determination>107m. Eriogonumumbellatum var. humistratum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Umbels with branches usually shorter than 2.5 cm (immature specimens should be keyed through the opposing couplet as well).</description>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants prostrate, mostly in montane to subalpine or alpine communities.</description>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades glabrous on both surfaces at full anthesis</description>
      <determination>107e. Eriogonum umbellatum var. porteri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades tomentose at least abaxially at full anthesis.</description>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades narrowly elliptic, 0.3–0.6(–1) × 0.2–0.4(–0.6) cm, tomentose abaxially, slightly less so and greenish adaxially; s Sierra Nevada and White Mountains, Mono, Inyo, and Tulare counties, California</description>
      <determination>107p. Eriogonumumbellatum var. covillei</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades broadly elliptic, 0.5–1.5(–2.5) × 0.5–1.2(–1.5) cm, tomentose or glabrous and olive green adaxially; n Cascade Range, Benton, Clackamas, Hood River, and Wasco counties, Oregon, and Kittitas and Yakima counties, Washington</description>
      <determination>107h. Eriogonum umbellatum var. haussknechtii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants erect to slightly spreading, not prostrate, usually not in subalpine or alpine communities.</description>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades glabrous on both surfaces, sometimes with marginal hairs at full anthesis.</description>
      <next_statement_id>40.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades without marginal hairs; se Oregon, Idaho, and Nevada to w Montana, Wyoming, Colorado, and Utah</description>
      <determination>107d. Eriogonum umbellatum var. aureum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades with marginal hairs; Cascade Range, Washington</description>
      <determination>107f. Eriogonum umbellatum var. hypoleium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades lanate to tomentose or floccose at least abaxially at full anthesis.</description>
      <next_statement_id>41.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades thinly tomentose abaxially, less so to floccose or glabrous and green adaxially; Sierra Nevada and Great Basin ranges</description>
      <determination>107n. Eriogonum umbellatum var. nevadense (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades densely lanate to tomentose abaxially; widespread, generally not in Great Basin ranges.</description>
      <next_statement_id>42.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mature leaf blades lanate to tomentose on both surfaces; Yellowstone National Park, Wyoming</description>
      <determination>107b. Eriogonum umbellatum var. cladophorum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mature leaf blades densely lanate or tomentose abaxially, less so to floccose or glabrous and greenish adaxially; w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>43.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Larger leaf blades usually 0.3–1.5(–2) cm, usually elliptic to oblong; plants subshrubs or herbs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>44.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually elliptic; non-serpentine soils; ne California, se Oregon, sw Idaho, n Nevada</description>
      <determination>107j. Eriogonum umbellatum var. modocense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic to oblong; serpentine outcrops; nw California107aa. Eriogonum umbellatum var. nelsoniorum</description>
      <next_statement_id>43.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Larger leaf blades 1–3(–3.5) cm, elliptic to ovate; plants subshrubs, or compact or spreading mats.</description>
      <next_statement_id>45.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants subshrubs; n Cascade Range, Washington.</description>
      <determination>107g. Eriogonum umbellatum var. sandbergii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants compact or spreading mats; Rocky Mountains, Sierra Nevada, Transverse, and Argus ranges, California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Utah, and Wyoming.</description>
      <next_statement_id>46.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic to ovate, densely white-lanate abax-ially; Rocky Mountains, sw Montana and e Idaho to s Colorado, w and s Wyoming, and s Utah</description>
      <determination>107a. Eriogonumumbellatum var.umbellatum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic, densely grayish-lanate abaxially; s Sierra Nevada, Transverse Ranges, and Argus Range, California</description>
      <determination>107i. Eriogonumumbellatum var. canifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
