<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey" date="1827">umbellatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Reveal" date="1976">desereticum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Great Basin Naturalist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>35: 365. 1976</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;species umbellatum;variety desereticum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, spreading mats, 1–3.5(–4) × 3–6 dm. Aerial flowering stems erect, 1–3 dm, thinly floccose or glabrous, without one or more leaflike bracts ca. midlength. Leaves in loose rosettes; blade usually elliptic, 1–2(–2.5) × 0.5–1.5(–2) cm, glabrous on both surfaces at full anthesis, margins plane. Inflorescences umbellate; branches 2–4.5(–5.5) cm, glabrous, without a whorl of bracts ca. midlength; involucral tubes 2–3 mm, lobes 1–2.5 mm. Flowers 4–8 mm; perianth pale yellow to cream.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jun-Sep.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy to gravelly slopes and ridges, mixed grassland and sagebrush communities, oak, aspen, and montane to subalpine conifer woodlands;</description>
  <description type="elevation">(1500-)1900-3300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Idaho, Mont., Nev., Utah, Wyo.</description>
  <number>107r.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Deseret sulphur flower</other_name>
  <discussion>Variety desereticum is widely scattered in southern Idaho (Bear Lake, Blaine, Custer, and Owyhee counties), southwestern Montana (Park County), and southwestern Wyoming (Carbon, Teton, and Uinta counties) south into northeastern Nevada (Elko County) and northern Utah (Box Elder, Carbon, Daggett, Duchesne, Emery, Juab, Millard, Piute, Rich, Salt Lake, Sanpete, Summit, Tooele, Utah, and Wasatch counties). It is common only in Utah and southeastern Idaho. Variety desereticum is related to var. dichrocephalum, but the two rarely occur together. Late in the season, high-elevation plants can have attractive, bright red leaves. Such plants approach var. porteri in aspect, especially in the Jarbidge, Ruby, and East Humboldt mountains of Nevada. The Deseret sulphur flower is worthy of cultivation.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
