<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3a.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Drymaria</genus_name><species_name>effusa</species_name><species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority><variety_name>effusa</variety_name></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants annual, herbaceous, minutely glandular-puberulent or glabrate, not glaucous. Stems mostly erect, usually unbranched at base, 0.8–25 cm. Leaves sometimes appearing whorled proximally, opposite distally; stipules ± deciduous, simple, subulate, 0.5–1.2 mm; petiole absent or nearly so; blade orbiculate or spatulate (basal leaves) or linear to oblong (cauline leaves), 0.5–2.5 cm × 0.2–1.2 mm, base briefly obtuse or attenuate, apex rounded to apiculate. Inflorescences terminal, congested or open, 7–50+-flowered cymes. Pedicels shorter to longer than subtending bracts at maturity. Flowers: sepals with 3 prominent veins arcing outward at midsection and confluent apically, broadly ovate to elliptic (herbaceous portion narrowly elliptic to ovate), 1.5–2.3 mm, unequal, outer 2 shorter (± 0.5 mm) than inner, apex acute or obtuse (herbaceous portion acute to acuminate), hood oblique to apex, on outer 2 or all 5 sepals formed in part by scarious margins, glabrous or glandular; petals 2-fid for ca. 1/2+ their length, 1.5–4 mm, 11/4–11/2 times as long as sepals, lobes 1-veined, vein unbranched, linear, trunk absent, base gradually tapered, apex rounded. Seeds brown, snail-shell- to teardrop-shaped, 0.6–0.7 mm; tubercles minute, rounded.</description><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><phenology>nov</phenology><habitat>rocky or gravelly flats or slopes</habitat><habitat>disturbed areas in pine or oak woodland</habitat><elevation>1400–1900 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution><global_distribution>n Mexico (Sinaloa).</global_distribution><global_distribution>n Mexico (Sonora).</global_distribution></treatment>
