<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>114b.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><species_name>ursinum</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><variety_name>ursinum</variety_name></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Bear Valley wild buckwheat</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><species_name>ovatum</species_name><species_authority>Greene</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 0.5–4 × 3–6 dm. Aerial flowering stems 0.4–4 dm, thinly tomentose to glabrate. Leaves: petiole 0.1–0.5(–0.8) cm; blade ovate, 0.8–1.4(–2.5) × 0.5–1.2(–2) cm, densely white- or rufous-tomentose abaxially, thinly tomentose or glabrous and greenish adaxially. Inflorescences thinly tomentose to glabrate; proximal bracts 3–8, lanceolate, 0.5–1.5(–2) × 0.3–1 cm, distal bracts scalelike, not midway along branch, 1–5 mm. Involucres turbinate, 3.5–4.5(–5) × 2.5–4 mm. Flowers 4–6 mm at anthesis, 5–6 mm in fruit; perianth pale yellow, rarely yellow, not suffused with blush of color. Achenes 3–3.5 mm.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><habitat>sandy to gravelly, mostly volcanic flats and slopes</habitat><habitat>oak and montane conifer woodlands</habitat><elevation>(500–)900–2500(–2800) m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Variety ursinum is rather common in the northern Sierra Nevada (Lassen, Nevada, Placer, Plumas, Shasta, and Sierra counties), with a series of disjunct populations on the Trinity-Tehama-Shasta county lines. A low-elevation population (Hutchinson et al. 2693, JEPS) is known from near Pulga along the Feather River in Butte County.</discussion><discussion>Bear Valley wild buckwheat forms large, colorful mats on the forest floor, with rather compact but compound umbels of pale yellow flowers. The plants do well in the garden. A specimen (T. J. Howell s.n., NY) supposedly gathered somewhere in Oregon is discounted as to location.</discussion></treatment>
