<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas ex Bentham" date="1836">sphaerocephalum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 407. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;species sphaerocephalum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, spreading to erect, infrequently polygamodioecious, 0.5–4 × 3–5(–6) dm, floccose or glabrous. Stems: caudex spread-ing; aerial flowering stems erect, slender, solid, not fistulose, arising at nodes of caudex branches and at distal nodes of short, non-flowering aerial branches, (0.3–)0.5–1 dm, thinly floccose or glabrous, with a whorl of 4–8 leaflike bracts ca. midlength or proximally, linear-oblanceolate to oblanceolate, 1–2 × 0.1–0.4 cm. Leaves in loose to congested basal rosettes; petiole 0.05–0.3 cm, floccose or glabrous; blade linear-oblanceolate, narrowly oblanceolate, or narrowly spatulate, 1–3(–4) × (0.1–)0.3–0.6(–1) cm, lanate or tomentose to floccose or glabrous, margins entire, plane or revolute. Inflorescences capitate, compound-umbellate, or umbellate, 1–2 cm wide or 1–5 × 1–5 cm; branches thinly floccose or glabrous; bracts absent immediately below involucre. Involucres 1 per node, turbinate-campanulate to campanulate, 3–4 × 2.5–4.5 mm; teeth 6–10, lobelike, slightly reflexed, 1.5–3(–5) mm. Flowers (5–)6–9 mm, including 1–2 mm stipelike base; perianth pale to bright yellow or cream to ochroleucous, villous abaxially; tepals monomorphic, obovate to oblong-ovate; stamens exserted, 4–6 mm; filaments pilose proximally. Achenes light brown, 3–4 mm, glabrous except for sparsely pubescent beak.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora): w United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>120.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The Piute of Nevada have used a decoction of the root of Eriogonum sphaerocephalum (either var. sphaerocephalum or var. halimoides) to treat colds and diarrhea (P. Train et al. 1941).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths bright yellow; inflorescences umbellate or compound-umbellate; ne California, sw Idaho, n and wc Nevada, e Oregon, and e Washington</description>
      <determination>120a. Eriogonum sphaerocephalum var. sphaerocephalum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths pale yellow to cream or ochroleucous; inflorescences umbellate, compound-umbellate, or capitate; ne California, sw or wc Idaho, c Oregon, and c Washington.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually thinly floccose or glabrous on both surfaces; inflorescences umbellate or compound-umbellate; sw Idaho</description>
      <determination>120b. Eriogonum sphaerocephalum var. fasciculifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades tomentose on both surfaces, or floccose adaxially; inflorescence capitate or umbellate; ne California to nw Nevada, c Oregon to wc Idaho, and c Washington.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually narrowly oblanceolate to narrowly spatulate, margins plane; ne California to nw Nevada, c Oregon to wc Idaho, and c Washington</description>
      <determination>120c. Eriogonum sphaerocephalum var. halimioides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades linear-oblanceolate, margins usually revolute; nc Oregon, sc Washington</description>
      <determination>120d. Eriogonum sphaerocephalum var. sublineare</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
