<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey in L. Sitgreaves" date="1853">alatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in L. Sitgreaves, Rep. Exped. Zuni Colorado Rivers,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>168, plate 8. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;species alatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pterogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Torrey) H. Gross" date="unknown">alatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pterogonum;species alatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, monocarpic, 5–20(–25) dm, strigose or glabrous; taproot often chambered. Stems: caudex absent; aerial flowering stems usually 1, not fistulose, 2–13 dm, strigose or glabrous. Leaves basal and sometimes cauline; basal petiolate, petiole 2–6 cm, stigose to woolly or glabrous, blade linear-lanceolate or lanceolate to oblanceolate to spatulate, (3–)5–20 × 0.3–2 cm, strigose, becoming glabrous and green on both surfaces except for margins and midvein; cauline sessile, blade linear-oblanceolate to lanceolate, 1–9 × 0.3–0.8(–1) cm, similar to basal blade. Inflorescences 2–10 dm; branches strigose or glabrous; bracts semileaflike proximally, linear to linear-lanceolate, 2–9 × 1–3 mm, scalelike distally, triangular, 0.8–5 × 0.5–2 mm. Peduncles erect, straight or curving upward, 0.5–3.5 cm, strigose or glabrous. Involucres turbinate to campanulate, 2–4(–4.5) × 2–4(–4.5) mm, strigose or glabrous; teeth 1–1.8 mm. Flowers 1.5–2.5 mm in anthesis, 3–6 mm in fruit; perianth yellow to yellowish green, rarely maroon in anthesis, often reddish or maroon in fruit, glabrous; tepals lanceolate; stamens 1.5–3 mm; filaments glabrous. Achenes yellowish green to reddish brown, 5–9 mm, glabrous, 3-winged entire length, beakless.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">including Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora): w North America, including Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w North America, including Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>146.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The mature reddish roots of Eriogonum alatum can be distinctively chambered. The Navajo (Diné) people consider the species to be a “life medicine” (L. C. Wyman and S. K. Harris 1951), using a mixture of shredded roots and water primarily to treat internal ailments. The species is used also as a ceremonial medicine (P. A. Vestal 1952). The Zuni use it as an emetic for stomachaches (S. Camazine and R. A. Bye 1980).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowering stems and inflorescence branches usually strigose; peduncles strigose or nearly so; involucres strigose, rarely glabrous; plants 5–13(–17) dm; n Arizona, Colorado, w Kansas, sw Nebraska, New Mexico, w Texas, e Utah, se Wyoming</description>
      <determination>146a. Eriogonum alatum var. alatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowering stems and inflorescence branches glabrous or nearly so; peduncles glabrous, occasionally slightly strigose; involucres glabrous; plants 10–20(–25) dm; ne New Mexico, w Oklahoma, n Texas</description>
      <determination>146b. Eriogonum alatum var. glabriusculum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
