<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>190.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><species_name>pharnaceoides</species_name><species_authority>Torrey</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in L. Sitgreaves, Rep. Exped. Zuni Colorado Rivers,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>167, plate 11. 1853</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, erect or spreading, annual, 1–5 dm, villous, greenish, yellowish green, or reddish. Stems: caudex absent; aerial flowering stems erect or nearly so, solid, not fistulose, 0.1–0.8 dm, villous. Leaves basal and cauline; basal: petiole 0.1–0.5(–1) cm, blade linear-lanceolate to linear-oblanceolate, 1–4 × 0.1–0.4 cm, white-lanate abaxially, villous and greenish to yellowish green adaxially, margins plane or revolute; cauline sessile, blade linear, 0.5–2.5 × 0.05–0.3 cm, tomentose abaxially, thinly villous or glabrous and greenish adaxially. Inflorescences cymose, open, 5–45 × 3–40 cm; branches villous; bracts 3–8, semileaflike, 5–15 × 0.3–1.5(–2) mm. Peduncles erect or nearly so, straight, slender, (1–)2–5(–7) cm, sparsely villous or glabrous. Involucres campanulate, 1–2 × 2–3 mm, villous; teeth 5, mostly erect to spreading, 1–3 mm. Flowers 1–3 mm; perianth white to rose or yellow, sometimes becoming reddish, glabrous; tepals dimorphic, those of outer whorl oblong-ovate, 2-saccate-dilated proximally, those of inner whorl linear-oblong; stamens mostly included, 1–1.5 mm; filaments mostly pilose proximally. Achenes brown to blackish, lenticular, 1.8–2 mm, glabrous.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>including n Mexico.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perianths white to rose; n and e Arizona, w New Mexico, Mexico</statement>
      <determination>190a. Eriogonum pharnaceoides var. pharnaceoides</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perianths yellow; nw Arizona, se Nevada, sw Utah</statement>
      <determination>190b. Eriogonum pharnaceoides var. cervinum</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
