<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(S. Watson) Greene" date="1891">Oregonium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Francisc.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>146. 1891</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus eriogonum;subgenus Oregonium</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="S. Watson" date="unknown">Oregonium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 262. 1877</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eriogonum;section Oregonium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, spreading to erect or prostrate, rarely decumbent annuals, glabrous or floccose to tomentose or lanate, sometimes sericeous puberulent, or short-pilose; taproot not woody. Stems prostrate, ascending or erect, without persistent leaf bases, lanate, tomentose, floccose, or glabrous, sometimes sericeous, puberulent, or short-pilose; caudex absent; aerial flowering stems prostrate to ascending or erect, slender to stout, solid, not fistulose, not disarticulating in ringlike segments proximally, arising directly from root. Leaves persistent or marcescent, basal, cauline, or basal and cauline, 1 per node not fasciculate; blade tomentose to floccose or glabrous, sometimes sericeous, puberulent, or short-pilose, not glandular. Inflorescences cymose, open or diffuse; bracts 3, connate basally, scalelike. Peduncles usually absent, when present restricted to proximal nodes, erect, straight, slender. Involucres 1 per node, usually appressed to the inflorescence branches, cylindric to turbinate or rarely campanulate; teeth 5, rarely 6–8, erect or rarely spreading, rarely lobelike, spreading to somewhat reflexed and dividing involucral tube nearly to base. Flowers abruptly narrowing to acute base on slender pedicel, without stipelike base; perianth cream, white to pink or rose, yellow, or red, rarely ochroleucous, usually glabrous or glandular, sometimes hispid, hispidulous, pubescent, or hirtellous abaxially, occasionally papillose, mostly glabrous adaxially; tepals connate proximally 1/4–1/2 their length, monomorphic or dimorphic; stamens included or exserted; filaments glabrous or pilose proximally. Achenes light to dark brown or rarely nearly black, not winged, lenticular to more often 3-gonous, glabrous. Seeds: embryo curved.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America including n Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">mainly California.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 28 (26 in the flora): w North America including n Mexico, mainly California.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 28 (26 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w North America including n Mexico, mainly California.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>1h.</number>
  <discussion>Species 28 (26 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The species of Eriogonum subg. Oregonium not treated here are E. foliosum S. Watson and E. hastatum Wiggins; they occur in northern Mexico.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres terminal at tips of short branchlets proximally, not appressed to branches; peduncles sometimes present.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers 0.7–1.5 mm; perianth yellow or cream; arid regions of e and se California, wc Nevada.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths yellow; flowers 0.7–1 mm; inflorescences diffuse, spreading; Mojave Desert, se Kern, ne Los Angeles, and nw San Bernardino counties, California</description>
      <determination>199. Eriogonum mohavense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths cream; flowers 1–1.5 mm; inflorescences narrow; Great Basin, s Mono and n Inyo counties, California, w Mineral and Esmeralda counties, Nevada</description>
      <determination>200. Eriogonum ampullaceum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers 1–2.5(–3) mm; perianth yellow or white to pink, rose, or red; Coast Ranges and w Sierra Nevada, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous; involucres sessile or, if short-pedunculate, plants from western foothills of Sierra Nevada, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaf blades oblong-ovate, reniform, or rounded to cordate; involucres 3–4 mm, 5-toothed; n California from San Mateo, Santa Clara, and Mariposa counties n to sw and sc Oregon</description>
      <determination>208. Eriogonum luteolum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaf blades suborbiculate or round to reniform; involucres 2–4 mm, 5–8-toothed; wc California from Santa Clara and Stanislaus counties s to Santa Barbara and Ventura counties.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 2–2.5 mm; 5-toothed; flowers 2–2.5(–3) mm, perianth minutely puberulent, white to rose or yellow in fruit; Santa Clara and Stanislaus counties s to w Kern and nw Ventura counties, California</description>
      <determination>206. Eriogonum covilleanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 3–4 mm; 6–8-toothed; flowers 1–2 mm, perianth glabrous, white to rose in fruit; c Monterey and w San Benito counties, California</description>
      <determination>207. Eriogonum nortonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems tomentose or, if glabrous, involucres pedunculate at proximal nodes and plants from Coast Ranges of California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres glabrous; e Monterey, w San Benito, and s Santa Clara (extirpated) counties, California</description>
      <determination>205. Eriogonum argillosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres tomentose; Contra Costa, Fresno, Kern, Merced, Monterey, San Benito, San Luis Obispo, and Solano counties, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves strictly basal, blade suborbiculate; styles 0.1–0.3 mm; sw Fresno County, California.</description>
      <determination>201. Eriogonum eastwoodianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal and subbasal, or basal and cauline, suborbiculate or narrowly oblong to ovate; styles 0.2–1 mm; Contra Costa, Fresno, Kern, Merced, Monterey, San Benito, San Luis Obispo, and Solano counties, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 2.5–3.5(–4) mm; styles 0.2–0.3 mm; e Contra Costa and s Solano counties, California (extinct)</description>
      <determination>204. Eriogonum truncatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres (1.5–)1.8–2.5 mm; styles 0.2–1 mm; Fresno, Kern, Merced Monterey, San Benito, and San Luis Obispo counties, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths not pustulose; achene beaks granular; involucres 2–2.5 mm; leaves basal and subbasal, rarely cauline; nw Kern, se Monterey, and ne San Luis Obispo counties, California</description>
      <determination>202. Eriogonum temblorense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths pustulose; achene beaks papillose; involucres (1.5–)1.8–2 mm; leaves basal and often cauline; w Fresno, sw Merced, and se San Benito counties, California</description>
      <determination>203. Eriogonum vestitum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres not terminal at tips of short branchlets proximally, usually appressed to branches; peduncles absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades puberulent to short-pilose or sericeous; flowering stems and inflorescence branches puberulent to short-pilose or sericeous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals oblong-lanceolate to oblong-ovate; plants puberulent to short-pilose; n Arizona, nw and sw Colorado, nw New Mexico, e and wc Utah, sw Wyoming</description>
      <determination>223. Eriogonum divaricatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals fan-shaped and hooded; plants sericeous; nw Arizona, se Nevada, sc Utah</description>
      <determination>224. Eriogonum darrovii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades tomentose at least abaxially; flowering stems and inflorescence branches glabrous or tomentose to floccose or lanate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths densely pubescent, white to rose; nw California</description>
      <determination>222. Eriogonum dasyanthemum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths glabrous or sparsely glandular, not densely hairy, white, creamy white, yellow, rose, or red; widespread.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres (1.8–)2–5(–7) mm; outer tepals not fan-shaped.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades oblong-obovate to oblanceolate or oblong; flowering stems and inflorescence branches lanate to tomentose or floccose or, if glabrous, plants not of central Sierra Nevada.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres (3.5–)4–5 mm, cylindric; outer tepals narrowly obovate to oblong; achenes 1.8–2(–2.2) mm; California and sw Oregon</description>
      <determination>212. Eriogonum roseum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres (1.8–)2–3 mm, turbinate; outer tepals lanceolate to oblong or oblong-obovate; achenes 1–2 mm; California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence branches straight; basal leaf blades oblanceolate to oblong, (0.8–)1–4(–6) cm, petiole not winged; involucres (1.8–)2–3 mm; flowers 1.5–3 mm; perianth white to pink or yellow; California</description>
      <determination>213. Eriogonum gracile</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence branches upwardly curved; basal leaf blades oblanceolate or elliptic to ovate or nearly rounded, 1–2 cm, petiole occasionally winged; involucres 2.5–3 mm; flowers 1.5–2 mm, perianth white to rose; sw California</description>
      <determination>214. Eriogonum cithariforme</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades round-ovate to rounded, reniform, or nearly so or, if not, inflorescence branches glabrous and plants of Sierra Nevada; flowering stems and inflorescence branches glabrous or tomentose to floccose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence branches floccose, especially proximally; leaves basal; perianths white to rose or pale yellow; nw California, w Idaho, n Nevada, c and e Oregon, se Washington</description>
      <determination>209. Eriogonum vimineum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence branches glabrous or occasionally tomentose, or if floccose then leaves basal and cauline; stems usually 1; perianths white to pink, red, or yellow; California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres (3.5–)4–5(–7) mm; plants 4–10 dm; s California</description>
      <determination>211. Eriogonum molestum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 2–4 mm; plants 1–5 dm; California n to Oregon, e to Arizona and Utah.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal and cauline, involucres 3–3.5 mm, and flowers 1.5–2 mm on floccose inflorescence branches or, if leaves strictly basal and stems glabrous, involucres 2–3.5 mm and plants of foothills and mid-elevation of central Sierra Nevada; perianths white to rose; n California</description>
      <determination>208. Eriogonum luteolum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal; involucres 3–4 mm; flowers 1.5–2 mm; perianth white to pink or red, rarely yellow; flowering stems glabrous; w Arizona, s California, s Nevada, s Utah</description>
      <determination>210. Eriogonum davidsonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres 1–1.5 mm or, if 2 mm, outer tepals fan-shaped or slightly hastate proximally and plants primarily of Great Basin and warm desert regions.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or, if tomentose, then flowers glandular and plants of eastern slope of Sierra Nevada and Great Basin; outer tepals oblong to oblong-obovate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths yellow or pale yellowish, rarely whitish; flowers 0.6–0.8(–1) mm;e California, w Nevada, sc Oregon</description>
      <determination>217. Eriogonum brachyanthum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths white to rose; flowers 1–2 mm; e and s California, sc Idaho, Nevada, e Oregon, sw Utah, e Washington.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers 1.5–2 mm; perianths usually minutely glandular, rarely glabrous; flowering stems and inflorescence branches glabrous or tomentose; e and s California, sc Idaho, Nevada, e Oregon, sw Utah, e Washington</description>
      <determination>215. Eriogonum baileyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers 1–1.5 mm; perianths glabrous; flowering stems and inflorescence branches glabrous; sw California</description>
      <determination>216. Eriogonum elegans</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems tomentose to floccose; outer tepals narrowly to broadly fan-shaped or slightly hastate proximally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals slightly hastate proximally in fruit; flowers 0.8–1.2 mm; involucres campanulate, 1–2 mm; montane habitats; c Riverside, w San Bernardino, and nc San Diego counties, California (presumed extinct)</description>
      <determination>218. Eriogonum evanidum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals fan-shaped; flowers 1–3.5 mm; involucres 1–2.5 mm; desert habitats; not of c Riverside, w San Bernardino, and nc San Diego counties, California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves cauline; leaf blades narrowly oblanceolate to broadly elliptic; plants narrowly erect, (0.5–)1–6 dm; perianths white, becoming pink or red; c and s Arizona, se California (presumed extirpated), w and s New Mexico, w Texas, s Utah</description>
      <determination>221. Eriogonum polycladon</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves basal; leaf blades suborbiculate or rounded to cordate; plants usually spreading, 0.5–1.5(–3) dm; perianths white to pink or pale yellow to yellow, rarely creamy white, becoming pink or red; widespread.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths pale yellow or yellow, rarely creamy white, becoming red; outer tepals broadly fan-shaped; inflorescences diffuse, branches inwardly curved distally; achenes 1–1.3 mm; nw Arizona, e California, sw Idaho, Nevada, se Oregon, sw Utah</description>
      <determination>219. Eriogonum nidularium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths white to pink or pale yellowish, outer tepals narrowly fan-shaped; inflorescences open, branches not inwardly curved distally; achenes 1.5–1.8 mm; Arizona, e California, nw and sw Colorado, sw Idaho, Nevada, w New Mexico, Utah</description>
      <determination>220. Eriogonum palmerianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
