<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>208.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><species_name>luteolum</species_name><species_authority>Greene</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3: 200. 1897</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><species_name>vimineum</species_name><species_authority>Douglas ex Bentham</species_authority><variety_name>luteolum</variety_name><variety_authority>(Greene) S. Stokes</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, erect or prostrate to spreading, 0.5–6 dm, glabrous or occasionally tomentose, greenish to reddish. Stems: aerial flowering stems prostrate to erect, 0.2–2 dm, glabrous or occasionally tomen-tose. Leaves basal or basal and cauline; basal: petiole 1–8 cm, floccose, blade oblong-ovate, reniform, or rounded to cordate, 0.5–5 × 0.5–3.5 cm, densely white-tomentose abaxially, floccose or glabrous and reddish or greenish adaxially; cauline: petiole 0.5–3 cm, floccose, blade cordate to reniform or orbiculate, 0.5–3 × 0.5–3 cm, similar to basal blade. Inflorescences cymose, occasionally distally uniparous due to suppression of secondary branches, open, 2–50 × 3–40 cm; branches glabrous or occasionally tomentose; bracts 1–3(–4) × 1–2 mm. Peduncles absent or erect, straight, slender, 0.1–0.5 cm, glabrous. Involucres terminal at tips of slender branchlets proximally or appressed to branches, cylindric or occasionally turbinate, 2–4 × 1.5–2.5 mm, glabrous or rarely floccose; teeth 5, erect, 0.3–0.5 mm. Flowers 1–2.5 mm; perianth white to rose or yellow, glabrous; tepals monomorphic, obovate; stamens included, 1–1.5 mm; filaments glabrous. Achenes light brown, 3-gonous, 1–2 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w North America.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants prostrate to spreading, 0.5–3 dm; involucres 3–4 mm, often terminal on elongated branchlets; leaves basal and cauline; serpentine soil; w Alameda and s Marin counties, California</statement>
      <determination>208d. Eriogonum luteolum var. caninum</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants erect, 2–6 dm; involucres 2–3.5 mm, appressed to inflorescence branches; leaves basal, sometimes also cauline; serpentine or granitic soils; San Mateo, Santa Clara, and Mariposa counties, California, n to sw and sc Oregon.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres 2–3 mm; flowers 2–2.5 mm; granitic soils; Sierra Nevada, Alpine and Tuolumne counties, California</statement>
      <determination>208c. Eriogonum luteolum var. saltuarium</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres 3–3.5 mm; flowers 1–2 mm; serpentine soils; Coast Ranges and lower foothills of Sierra Nevada, San Mateo, Santa Clara, and Mariposa counties, California, n to sw and sc Oregon.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Flowers 1.8–2 mm; Coast Ranges, w California from San Mateo and Santa Clara counties n to sw and sc Oregon</statement>
      <determination>208a. Eriogonum luteolum var. luteolum</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Flowers 1–1.5(–1.8) mm; e California from Mariposa County to Plumas County</statement>
      <determination>208b. Eriogonum luteolum var. pedunculatum</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
