<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>218.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eriogonum</genus_name><species_name>evanidum</species_name><species_authority>Reveal</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>86: 132. 2004</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Vanishing wild buckwheat</common_name><description>Herbs, erect, 1–2 dm, tomentose to floccose, grayish. Stems: aerial flowering stems erect, 0.3–0.6 dm, tomentose to floccose. Leaves basal; petiole 0.5–1.5 cm, tomentose; blade broadly ovate to orbiculate or reniform, 0.7–1.2 × 0.7–1.2 cm, densely white-tomentose abaxially, floccose and greenish adaxially. Inflorescences narrowly cymose, infrequently distally uniparous due to suppression of secondary branches, open, 5–15 × 5–10 cm; branches tomentose to floccose; bracts 0.5–2 × 0.5–1 mm. Peduncles absent. Involucres somewhat appressed to branches, campanulate, 1–2 × 1–2 mm, glabrous; teeth 5, spreading, 0.4–0.8 mm. Flowers 0.8–1.2 mm; perianth ochroleucous, glabrous; tepals dimorphic, those of outer whorl ovate, slightly hastate proximally in fruit, those of inner whorl lanceolate to elliptic; stamens included, 0.4–0.6 mm; filaments glabrous. Achenes dark brown, 3-gonous, 1.3–1.5 mm.</description><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><habitat>sandy to gravelly flats and slopes</habitat><habitat>sagebrush communities</habitat><habitat>oak and montane conifer woodlands</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>1100–2100 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Baja California).</global_distribution><discussion>Eriogonum evanidum is presumed extinct. The last known collections were made in Bear Valley in the San Bernardino Mountains, San Bernardino County, in 1931 (Templeton 1588, BRY, KANS, NY); Hemet Valley in the San Jacinto Mountains, Riverside County (Ziegler s.n., 10 Oct 1967, GH, RSA, UC, UTC); and the Pine Valley area, San Diego County, in 1938. It is related to two sprawling annual Mexican species with mostly elliptic basal leaf blades: E. foliosum S. Watson, with weakly hastate cauline leaves, and E. hastatum Wiggins, with strongly hastate cauline leaves.</discussion></treatment>
