<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Eriogonoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eriogonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker" date="unknown">divaricatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hooker’s J. Bot. Kew Gard. Misc.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 265. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Polygonaceae;subfamily Eriogonoideae;genus Eriogonum;species divaricatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>223.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Divergent wild buckwheat</other_name>
  <discussion>Eriogonum divaricatum basically is a species of the Colorado Plateau of southwestern Wyoming (Sublette, Sweetwater, and Uinta counties), eastern Utah (Carbon, Emery, Garfield, Grand, Kane, San Juan, Sevier, and Wayne counties), western Colorado (Mesa and Montezuma counties), northern Arizona (Apache, Coconino, and Navajo counties), and northwestern New Mexico (McKinley and San Juan counties), where it is infrequent to common but only rarely abundant. There are several disjunct populations well removed from that core area; the species occurs in Beaver and Millard counties of west-central Utah, and in Clayhole Valley, Mohave County, Arizona. In New Mexico, it was found around San Ysidro, Sandoval County, in 1926. The most extreme disjunctions were two populations found in Argentina during the growing season of 1899–1900. Those plants were named Eriogonum ameghinoi Spegazzini, which ultimately became the only species of the genus Sanmartinia M. Buchinger. Probably introduced there by migrating birds, the species did not persist in South America (J. L. Reveal 1981b).</discussion>
  <discussion>The divergent wild buckwheat was used ceremonially by the Navajo (Diné) people in one of their snake dances, and portions of the plant were smoked in the treatment of snakebite (A. Clifford, pers. comm.; L. C. Wyman and S. K. Harris 1951).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
