<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>James L. Reveal</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Small" date="1898">ACANTHOSCYPHUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>25: 53. 1898</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polygonaceae;genus ACANTHOSCYPHUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek acantha , thorn, and scyphos , cup, alluding to awn on involucre]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="unknown">Oxytheca</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Small) Ertter" date="unknown">Acanthoscyphus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Oxytheca;section Acanthoscyphus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual; taproot slender. Stems arising directly from the root, erect to somewhat spreading, solid, not fistulose or disarticulating into ringlike segments, glabrous, partially glandular. Leaves usually persistent through anthesis, basal, rosulate; petiole indistinct; blade broadly obovate or spatulate to oblong or oblanceolate, margins ciliate-denticulate. Inflorescences terminal, cymose; branches dichotomous, not brittle or disarticulating into segments, round, glabrous except for glandular nodes and proximal 1/2 of internode; bracts 2–3, connate basally, scalelike, triangular to lanceolate or subulate, awned at proximal nodes, glabrous or sparsely glandular. Peduncles erect to deflexed. Involucres 1 per node, not ribbed, tubular, turbinate; teeth 4(–5) or 7–30(–36), 1/2 to completely connate, awn-tipped, glandular distally adaxially. Flowers 3–10(–20) per involucre at any single time during full anthesis; perianth white to rose, occasionally greenish white to cream, broadly campanulate when open, narrowly urceolate when closed, hirsute to strigose and sparsely glandular abaxially; tepals 6, connate 1/4–1/3 their length, monomorphic, entire or rarely irregularly divided apically; stamens 9; filaments basally adnate, glabrous or sparsely pubescent basally; anthers red to maroon, oblong to oval. Achenes usually included, dark brown to deep maroon, not winged, globose-lenticular, glabrous. Seeds: embryo curved. x = 20.</description>
  <description type="distribution">s California.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: s California.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>s California.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>7.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Flowery puncturebract</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Acanthoscyphus is allied to Eriogonum subg. Ganysma, specifically to E. parishii, E. apiculatum, and their close relatives. It is distinguished from Eriogonum by its awned involucres.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ertter, B. 1980. A revision of the genus Oxytheca (Polygonaceae). Brittonia 32: 70–102.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
