<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>6.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Chorizanthe</genus_name><species_name>pungens</species_name><species_authority>Bentham</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>17: 419, plate 19, fig. 2. 1836</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants prostrate to ascending or erect, 0.5–2(–2.5) × 0.5–10 dm, grayish-villous. Leaves basal; petiole (0.5–)1–3(–4) cm; blade oblanceolate, (0.5–)1–5(–7) × (0.3–)0.4–0.7(–1) cm, villous. Inflorescences rather dense with secondary branches suppressed, grayish; bracts 2, similar to leaf blades at proximal nodes only reduced, short-petiolate, becoming linear and aciculate at distal nodes, acerose, 0.5–7 cm × 2–7 mm, awns 0.5–1.2 mm. Involucres 1, grayish, cylindric, often ventricose basally, 2–2.5(–3) mm, with distinct, white to pink or purple, scarious margins extending nearly full length of awn, corrugate, villous abaxially; teeth spreading, equal, 0.5–1.5 mm; awns uncinate with longer ones 2–3 mm and alternating with shorter (1–1.5 mm) ones. Flowers exserted; perianth bicolored with floral tube white and tepals white to rose, cylindric, 2–3.5 mm, pubescent abaxially; tepals connate less than 1/4 their length, monomorphic, obovate to oblong, acute to truncate and erose apically; stamens 9, slightly exserted; filaments distinct, 2–3 mm, glabrous; anthers cream to rose, ovate, 0.3–0.4 mm. Achenes dark brown, globose-lenticular, 2–2.5 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>California.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Margins of involucres white (rarely pinkish), scarious; plants prostrate to slightly ascending; coastal areas and adjacent inland valleys</statement>
      <determination>6a. Chorizanthe pungens var. pungens</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Margins of involucres dark pinkish to purple, scarious; plants slightly ascending to erect; coastal mountains</statement>
      <determination>6b. Chorizanthe pungens var. hartwegiana</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
