<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>9.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Chorizanthe</genus_name><species_name>robusta</species_name><species_authority>Parry</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Proc. Davenport Acad. Nat. Sci.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5: 176. 1889</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants erect to spreading or decumbent, 0.5–3 × 0.1–6 dm, villous. Leaves basal or nearly so; petiole 1–4(–7) cm; blade oblance-olate, 1.5–5 × 0.2–0.7(–1) cm, villous. Inflorescences with secondary branches not sup-pressed except in terminal clusters of involucres, green to reddish; bracts 2, similar to proximal leaf blades only reduced, short-petiolate, becoming linear and aciculate at distal nodes, acerose, 1–5 cm × 2–5(–7) mm, awns absent. Involucres 1, greenish, cylindric, not ventricose, 2.5–4 mm, with white to pinkish, thin scarious margins restricted to basal portion of teeth, not corrugate, thinly pubescent abaxially; teeth spreading, equal, 0.3–0.8(–1) mm; awns uncinate with longer ones 0.7–1.3 mm and anterior one mostly 1–1.3 mm, these alternating with shorter (0.3–0.7 mm) ones. Flowers slightly exserted; perianth bicolored with floral tube white and tepals white to rose, cylindric, 2.5–4 mm, pubescent abaxially; tepals connate 1/4 their length, monomorphic, oblanceolate to narrowly oblong, usually truncate to rounded and erose or denticulate apically, occasionally distinctly cuspidate; stamens 9, included; filaments distinct, 2–3.5 mm, glabrous; anthers pink to red or maroon, oblong, 0.6–0.8 mm. Achenes light brown, globose-lenticular, 3.5–4 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>wc California.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Margins of involucres white; plants spreading or decumbent; sandy to gravelly places; Alameda and San Mateo counties s in mountains and near coast to n Monterey County</statement>
      <determination>9a. Chorizanthe robusta var. robusta</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Margins of involucres rose-pink; plants erect; annual grasslands near Scotts Valley, Santa Cruz Mountains, Santa Cruz County</statement>
      <determination>9a. Chorizanthe robusta var. hartwegii</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
