<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>17.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Chorizanthe</genus_name><species_name>rectispina</species_name><species_authority>Goodman</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>21: 72. 1934</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Prickly spineflower</common_name><description>Plants spreading to decumbent, 0.3–0.8(–1) × 0.5–4(–5) dm, appressed-pubescent. Leaves basal; petiole 0.5–2 cm; blade oblanceolate to spatulate, 0.5–1.5(–2) × 0.2–0.6 cm, thinly pubescent. Inflorescences with involucres in small, open clusters 0.5–1.5 cm diam., greenish to grayish; bracts 2, without whorl of sessile bracts about midstem, usually leaflike, oblanceolate to elliptic, 0.5–1.5 cm × 1.5–5 mm, gradually reduced and becoming scalelike at distal nodes, linear, aciculate, acerose, 0.3–0.8 cm × 1–2 mm, awns straight, 0.5–1.5 mm. Involucres 3–10+, grayish to reddish, urceolate, slightly ventricose basally, 2–2.5(–3) mm, slightly corrugate, without scarious or membranous margins, densely pubescent; teeth spreading, unequal, 1–2 mm; awns straight or uncinate, unequal, with longer anterior one straight, mostly 1.5–2.5 mm, others uncinate, 0.3–0.6 mm. Flowers exserted; perianth bicolored with floral tube yellow and tepals yellow or white, cylindric, 3.5–4 mm, sparsely pubescent; tepals connate 1/2 their length, dimorphic, obovate, those of outer whorl white, obovate to nearly orbiculate, 3–4 times longer than those of inner whorl, , truncate to slightly 2-lobed apically, those of inner lobes erect, yellow, broadly obovate, truncate and erose apically; stamens 9, included; filaments distinct, 1–1.5 mm, glabrous; anthers yellow to golden, oblong, 0.5–0.6 mm. Achenes brown, globose-lenticular, 3–3.5 mm. 2n = (36), 40, (44).</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>sandy to gravelly flats and slopes</habitat><habitat>mixed grassland communities</habitat><habitat>pine-oak woodlands</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>200–600 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Chorizanthe rectispina is infrequent and localized in the Coast Ranges of west-central California.</discussion></treatment>
