<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>13.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>CORRIGIOLA</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 271. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5, 132. 1754</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Latin corrigia , shoelace, perhaps alluding to the slender stems]</etymology><common_name>Strapwort</common_name><author>John W. Thieret</author><author>Richard K. Rabeler</author><description>Herbs, annual or biennial [perennial]. Taproots slender. Stems decumbent to ascending, branched, terete. Leaves alternate or rarely subopposite, sometimes forming basal rosette, not connate, petiolate or sessile; stipules 2 per node, white, ovate, margins mostly entire, apex acuminate; petiole minute (subopposite leaves); blade 1-veined, narrowly oblanceolate to spatulate, not succulent, apex obtuse. Inflorescences terminal or axillary, dense cymes; bracts paired, smaller, scarious. Pedicels erect. Flowers: perianth and androecium slightly perigynous; hypanthium cup-shaped, not abruptly expanded distally; sepals 5, distinct, green or reddish brown, 1–1.5 mm, herbaceous, margins white-scarious, apex blunt, not hooded, not awned; nectaries not apparent; stamens 5; filaments distinct; staminodes 5, arising from hypanthium rim, ovate to oblong; styles 3, distinct, capitate, 0.1–0.2 mm, glabrous proximally; stigmas 3, capitate, obscurely papillate (at 50×). Utricles at least partly enclosed by persistent calyx/hypanthium, obscurely 3-gonous, indehiscent. Seeds white with tan band, reniform or subglobose, not compressed, finely papillose, marginal wing absent, appendage absent; embryo peripheral, curved. x = 8, 9.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 10 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>South America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Eurasia</global_distribution><global_distribution>Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution>introduced elsewhere.</global_distribution><references>
    <reference>Coker, P. D. 1962. Corrigiola litoralis L. J. Ecol. 50: 833–840.</reference>
    <reference>Gilbert, M. G. 1987. The taxonomic position of the genera Telephium and Corrigiola. Taxon 36: 47–49.</reference>
    <reference>Vogel, A. 1997. Die Verbreitung, Vergesellschaftung und Populationsökologie von Corrigiola litoralis, Illecebrum verticillatum und Herniaria glabra (Illecebraceae). Berlin.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
