<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>26.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Chorizanthe</genus_name><species_name>wheeleri</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>12: 272. 1877</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Wheeler’s spineflower</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Chorizanthe</genus_name><species_name>insularis</species_name><species_authority>R. Hoffmann</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants erect to spreading, 0.5–2(–2.5) × 1–2 dm, thinly pubescent. Leaves basal; petiole 0.5–3 cm; blade elliptic to oblong, 0.5–2 × 0.2–0.6 cm, thinly pubescent adaxially, tomentose abaxially. Inflorescences mostly flat-topped, openly branched, greenish to reddish; bracts persistent, 2, usually leaflike at proximal nodes and similar to leaf blades, short-petiolate, oblong, 0.5–1.2 cm × 2–4 mm, sessile, reduced and scalelike at distal nodes, linear, acicular, often acerose, 0.1–0.5 cm × 0.5–1 mm, awns straight, 0.5–1 mm. Involucres in dense terminal clusters with 1 at node of dichotomies, reddish, cylindric, not ventricose, 2–2.5 mm, corrugate, without scarious or membranous margins, thinly pubescent with stoutish, recurved hairs; teeth spreading, unequal, 0.3–0.8(–1) mm, with 3 longer ones more erect than 3 shorter and less-prominent ones; awns uncinate, 0.3–0.5 mm. Flowers exserted; perianth white or rose or red with white lobes, cylindric, 2.5–3 mm, glabrous except for few scattered hairs ca. midlength along midrib abaxially; tepals connate 1/2 their length, monomorphic to slightly dimorphic, oblong, rounded apically, those of outer whorl usually slightly broader and longer than those of inner whorl; stamens 6, included; filaments distinct, 1.5–2 mm, glabrous; anthers pink to red, oblong, 0.3–0.4 mm. Achenes brown, lenticular, 2.5–3 mm.</description><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>gravelly to rocky slopes</habitat><habitat>coastal scrub communities</habitat><elevation>0–400(–600) m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Chorizanthe wheeleri is a rare insular endemic known only from Santa Cruz and Santa Rosa islands.</discussion></treatment>
