<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>13.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>MUCRONEA</genus_name><genus_authority>Bentham</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>17: 405, 419, plate 20. 1836</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Latin mucronis , sharp point, alluding to awns of bracts and involucres]</etymology><common_name>California spineflower</common_name><author>James L. Reveal</author><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Chorizanthe</genus_name><genus_authority>R. Brown ex Bentham</genus_authority><section_name>Mucronea</section_name><section_authority>(Bentham) A. Gray</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, annual; taproot slender. Stems arising directly from the root, erect to spreading, solid, not fistulose or disarticulating into ringlike segments, sparsely glandular-pubescent. Leaves usually quickly deciduous, basal, rosulate; petiole absent; blade spatulate to obovate, margins entire. Inflorescences terminal, cymose, uniparous due to suppression of secondaries; branches dichotomous, not brittle or disarticulating into segments, round, sparsely glandular-pubescent; bracts 3(–5), positioned to side of node or perfoliate and completely but unequally surrounding node, connate nearly completely, triangular to ovate or oblong, awned, sparsely glandular-pubescent. Peduncles absent. Involucres 1–3 per node, tubular, cylindric, (2–)3–4-angled, slightly ventricose on the angles in some; teeth (2–)3–4, awn-tipped. Flowers 1(–2) per involucre; perianth white to pink, campanulate when open, cylindric when closed, pubescent abaxially; tepals 6, connate ca. 1/3 their length, monomorphic, entire or erose to fimbriate apically; stamens 6–9; filaments free, glabrous; anthers pink to red, oblong. Achenes mostly included, brown to black, not winged, globose-lenticular, glabrous. Seeds: embryo straight. x = 19.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>California.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence bracts positioned to side of node, involucres 1–3 per node, 2.5–5(–7) mm,bracts (2–)3(–4), awns (0.5–)1–2.5 (3) mm; flowers 1–2; tepals entire apically</statement>
      <determination>1. Mucronea californica</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence bracts perfoliate; involucres 1 per node, 3–5(–6) mm, bracts 4, awns (0.3–)0.5–1.2 mm; flowers 1; tepals entire to fimbriate apically</statement>
      <determination>2. Mucronea perfoliata</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
