<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>James L. Reveal</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Polygonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Eriogonoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="J. Rémy" date="unknown">LASTARRIAEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in C. Gay, Fl. Chil.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 289. 1851 or 1852</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Polygonaceae;subfamily Eriogonoideae;genus LASTARRIAEA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For José Victorino Lastarria Santander, 1817–1888, lawyer and founder of the Liberal
        Party in Chile]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual; taproot slender. Stems arising directly from the root, prostrate to
        ascending, solid, not fistulose or disarticulating into ringlike segments, thinly pubescent.
        Leaves quickly deciduous, basal, rosulate; petiole present; blade linear, margins entire,
        hirsute. Peduncles absent. Inflorescences terminal, cymose, often uniparous due to
        suppression of secondaries; branches dichotomous, brittle and disarticulating into segments,
        round, thinly pubescent; bracts 2, opposite, connate proximally, lanceolate to narrowly
        ovate, mucronate or awned, thinly pubescent. Involucral bracts obvious, in 1 whorl of 3,
        linear to broadly lanceolate, awn-tipped. Flowers 1 per involucral cluster; perianth light
        green to greenish white, cylindric, thinly pubescent abaxially; tepals 5, connate 1/2–3/4
        their length, slightly dimorphic, coriaceous, acute and awn-tipped apically; stamens 3;
        filaments basally adnate, glabrous; anthers cream to white, oval. Achenes mostly included,
        brownish, not winged, lenticular to slightly 3-gonous, glabrous. Seeds: embryo straight. x =
        20.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America (including Mexico)</description>
  <description type="distribution">s South America.</description>
  <number>18.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Spineflower</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The awn-tipped, coriaceous tepals easily distinguish Lastarriaea from other genera
        of the Eriogonoideae. The mostly prostrate habit with brittle stems and inflorescence
        branches is seen elsewhere in Chorizanthe, most notably C. brevicornu and in the Baja
        California, Mexico, endemic C. interposita (the only species of sect. Clastoscapa), and
        because of these features early authors assigned the North and South American species of
        Lastarriaea to Chorizanthe. The names L. chilensis J. Rémy and C. lastarriaea Parry have
        been misapplied to the California species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
