<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>9</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Abies</genus_name><species_name>lowiana</species_name><species_authority>(Gordon) A. Murray bis</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Proc. Roy. Hort. Soc. London</publication_title><place_in_publication>3: 317. 1863</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Sierra white fir</common_name><common_name> California white fir</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Picea</genus_name><species_name>lowiana</species_name><species_authority>Gordon</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Pinetum Suppl., </publication_title><place_in_publication>53. 1862</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Abies</genus_name><species_name>concolor</species_name><species_authority>(Gordon &amp; Glendinning) Hildebrand</species_authority><variety_name>lowiana</variety_name><variety_authority>(Gordon) Lemmon</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Trees  to 60m; trunk to 1.9m diam.; crown somewhat spirelike.  Bark  gray, thin, smooth, with age thickening and breaking into deep longitudinal furrows ("corky"), which may reveal inner yellow-caramel periderm.  Branches  diverging from trunk at right angles, or slightly drooping; twigs mostly opposite, yellow-green, pubescent or glabrous.  Buds  exposed, tan, globose, resinous, moderately large, apex rounded; basal scales short, broad, equilaterally triangular, sparsely pubescent, not resinous, margins entire, apex sharp-pointed.  Leaves  2--6cm × 2--3mm, mostly 2-ranked, flexible, proximal portion ± straight; cross section flat, grooved adaxially; odor pungent, pinelike; abaxial surface glaucous or not, with 5--8 stomatal rows on each side of midrib; adaxial surface light green, not glaucous, with ca. (5--)7(--9) stomatal rows at midleaf, these fewer toward leaf apex; apex weakly notched; resin canals small, near margins and abaxial epidermal layer.  Seed cones  cylindric, 8--9 × 4--4.5cm, olive-green, turning to yellowish brown, then darker brown, sessile, apex round; scales ca. 2.5--3 × 2.8--3.8cm, pubescent; bracts included. Seeds 8--12 × 3mm, body dull brown; wing about twice as long as body, brown with rosy tinge; cotyledons 5--9.</description><habitat>Mixed coniferous forests</habitat><elevation> 900--2300m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Nev.</us_distribution></treatment>
