<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Abies</genus_name><species_name>bracteata</species_name><species_authority>(D. Don) Poiteau</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Rev. Hort.</publication_title><place_in_publication>sér. 2, 4: 7. l845 - Bristlecon. fir</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>bracteata</species_name><species_authority>D. Don</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London </publication_title><place_in_publication>17: 443. 1836</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Abies</genus_name><species_name>venusta</species_name><species_authority>(Douglas) K. Koch</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Trees  to 25 m; trunk to 1 m diam.; crown spirelike, narrow.  Bark  red-brown, thin, smooth, with age slightly fissured and broken into appressed scales.  Branches  diverging from trunk at right angles, the lower often drooping in age; twigs becoming purplish green or brown, glabrous, glaucous when young.  Buds  exposed, brown, ovate to fusiform, extremely large, not resinous, apex pointed; basal scales short, broad, equilaterally triangular, glabrous, not resinous, margins entire, apex sharp-pointed.  Leaves  2.5--6cm × 3mm, 2-ranked to spiraled, stiff; cross section flat, with raised vein abaxially, grooveless to faintly grooved adaxially; odor pungent; abaxial surface with 8--10 stomatal rows on each side of midrib; adaxial surface dark green, lacking stomates; apex sharply pointed; resin canals small, near margins and abaxial epidermal layer.  Pollen cones  at pollination yellow to yellow-green.  Seed cones  ovoid, 7--10 × 4--5cm, pale purplish brown, borne on stout peduncles, apex round; scales ca. 1.5--2 × 2--2.5cm, glabrous; bracts exserted, not reflexed.  Seeds  10 × 5mm, body deep red-brown; wing about as long as body, deep red-brown; cotyledons ca. 7.</description><discussion>Abies bracteata grows in the Santa Lucia Mountains along the coast of California.</discussion><habitat>Dry, coastal coniferous forests</habitat><conservation> of conservation concern</conservation><elevation> 600--900m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution></treatment>
