<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Actinostachys</genus_name><species_name>pennula</species_name><species_authority>(Swartz) Hooker</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gen. Fil.</publication_title><place_in_publication>plate 111A. 1842</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Ray spiked fern</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Schizaea</genus_name><species_name>pennula</species_name><species_authority>Swartz</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Syn. Fil., </publication_title><place_in_publication>150, 379. 1806</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Actinostachys</genus_name><species_name>germanii</species_name><species_authority>Fée</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Schizaea</genus_name><species_name>germanii</species_name><species_authority>(Fée) Prantl</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants  extremely variable in size, 5--50 cm, those in leaf mold (only form known in flora) usually small, those in open sunny areas much larger.  Leaves  1--60; rays 1--12, 4--40 mm; petioles 0.5--2 cm. 2 n  = 168 (Trinidad).</description><discussion>Small individuals of Actinostachys pennula have sometimes been called A . germanii , but plants conforming to A . germanii are merely at the end of a morphological series; they are probably juvenile. Each juvenile has a large bulbous gametophyte remaining attached (a so-called "tuber") that is sometimes mistaken for the stem. Not only is the persistent gametophyte mistaken for a stem, but in the large forms of typical A . pennula the stem is not a solitary structure. Instead it resembles a compact, intergrown bush, made up of numerous tiny, narrow stems, usually less than 1 mm diam., that proliferate from old leaf bases---a type of cauline organization apparently unknown in any other living fern but possibly found in the fossil genus Tempskya . Measurements for plants in the North American flora are all in the lower parts of the range for the species. Actinostachys pennula is among North America's most unusual ferns, a highly treasured species, sought by field botanists who must, however, respect its rarity.</discussion></treatment>
