<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>22</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>adiantum-nigrum</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 1081. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Black spleenwort</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>andrewsii</species_name><species_authority>A. Nelson</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>chihuahuense</species_name><species_authority>J. G. Baker</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>dubiosum</species_name><species_authority>Davenport</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Roots  not proliferous.  Stems  ascending or short-creeping, infrequently branched; scales dark brown to blackish throughout, narrowly deltate, 2--4(--5) × 0.2--0.5 mm, margins entire or shallowly denticulate to serrulate.  Leaves  monomorphic.  Petiole  dark reddish brown proximally, often fading to green distally, lustrous, 2--20 cm, 2/3--2 times length of blade; indument of black filiform scales and minute hairs.  Blade  deltate, 2--3-pinnate, 2.5--10 × 2--6.5 cm, thick, hairs dark, scattered, minute; base truncate; apex acute to acuminate, not rooting.  Rachis  greenish throughout or sometimes reddish brown proximally, lustrous, sparsely pubescent.  Pinnae  in 4--10 pairs, deltate to lanceolate; most proximal (largest) pinnae 1.5--4 × 1--2.5 cm; base obliquely obtuse; segment margins coarsely incised; apex acute.  Veins  free, evident.  Sori  1--numerous pairs per pinna [1--6 pairs per segment], on both basiscopic and acroscopic sides.  Spores  64 per sporangium. 2 n  = 144.</description><discussion>Asplenium adiantum-nigrum is principally a Eurasian species and occurs extremely rarely in North America (see M. G. Shivas 1969 and M. D. Windham 1983 for a discussion of the conspecificity of Western Hemisphere and Eastern Hemisphere material). It is an allotetraploid derived from hybridization of two European taxa, A . cuneifolium Viviani and A . onopteris Linnaeus (M. G. Shivas 1969). Hybrids involving A . adiantum-nigrum and other Asplenium species occur in Europe but are unknown in North America.</discussion><habitat>Cliffs</habitat><elevation> 1675--2300 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Colo.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Utah</us_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia</global_distribution><global_distribution> Africa.</global_distribution></treatment>
