<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Asplenium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. R. Scott" date="unknown">ebenoides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Monthly &amp; Hort. Advertiser</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 267. 1865</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Asplenium;species ebenoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Asplenosorus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(R. R. Scott) Wherry" date="unknown">ebenoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Asplenosorus;species ebenoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Scott's spleenwort</other_name>
  <discussion>The above description applies to the sterile hybrid Asplenium platyneuron × rhizophyllum and its allopolyploid derivative. The allotetraploid form is known only from Hale County, Alabama, where it occurs with A . platyneuron (but not with A . rhizophyllum ) on conglomerate boulders (K. S. Walter et al. 1982). The sterile diploid form of A . ebenoides occurs at elevations of 70 to 500 m within the region where the ranges of the parental species overlap, always occurring with both parents on limestone, sandstone, or other rock strata. A hybrid between the allopolyploid and A . platyneuron [ A . × boydstoniae (K. S. Walter) J. W. Short] was discovered at Havana Glen. An unnamed hybrid between the sterile diploid (presumably via unreduced spores) and A . rhizophyllum is known from West Virginia and Missouri (K. S. Walter et al. 1982).</discussion>
  <discussion>This fern has been pivotal in the study of fern hybridization. Called the "most famous hybrid fern," it was one of the first crosses to be synthesized deliberately in culture (M. Slosson 1902) and the first to be converted from the sterile diploid state to the fertile tetraploid state experimentally (W. H. Wagner Jr. and R. S. Whitmire 1957).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
