<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>24</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>bradleyi</species_name><species_authority>D. C. Eaton</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title><place_in_publication>4: 11. 1873</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Bradley's spleenwort</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>stotleri</species_name><species_authority>Wherry</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Roots  not proliferous.  Stems  short-creeping to ascending, occasionally branched; scales dark reddish to brown throughout, narrowly deltate, (2--)3--5 × 0.2--0.4 mm, margins entire or shallowly dentate.  Leaves  monomorphic.  Petiole  reddish or purplish brown throughout, lustrous, 1--10(--13) cm, 1/3--3/4 length of blade; indument of brown, narrowly lanceolate scales at base, grading into hairs.  Blade  narrowly oblong to lanceolate, pinnate-pinnatifid to 2-pinnate, 2--17(--20) × 1--6 cm, thin to moderately thick, sparsely pubescent; base truncate or obtuse; apex acute, not rooting.  Rachis  reddish or purplish brown proximally, fading to green in distal 1/3--2/3, lustrous, sparsely pubescent.  Pinnae  in (3--)5--15(--25) pairs, ovate, obovate to lanceolate or deltate-lanceolate; medial pinnae 6--40 × 3--10 mm; base truncate to obliquely obtuse; margins dentate to denticulate; apex acute or rounded.  Veins  free, barely evident.  Sori  3 to numerous pairs per pinna, on both basiscopic and acroscopic sides.  Spores  64 per sporangium. 2 n  = 144.</description><discussion>Asplenium bradleyi is a morphologically variable species, the allotetraploid derivative of A . montanum × platyneuron (W. H. Wagner Jr. 1954; D. M. Smith and D. A. Levin 1963; C. R. Werth et al. 1985). The sterile diploid form of A . bradleyi has been collected twice in nature (W. H. Wagner Jr. et al. 1973; A. M. Evans 1988), and isozyme studies indicate that the allotetraploid has had a polytopic origin (C. R. Werth et al. 1985b). Occurring rarely to locally in the Appalachian region, A . bradleyi overlaps with both progenitor taxa, but it is fairly frequent in the Ozark and Ouachita region where A . montanum is absent. Sterile hybrids with A . pinnatifidum ( A . × gravesii ), A . montanum ( A . × wherryi D. M. Smith et al.), and A . platyneuron are known from nature.</discussion><habitat>Acidic rocks, usually on steep ledges</habitat><elevation> 0--1000 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ark.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ill.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ky.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mo.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.J.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Y.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ohio</us_distribution><us_distribution> Okla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Pa.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tenn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution> W.Va.</us_distribution></treatment>
