<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>dalhousiae</species_name><species_authority>Hooker</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Icon. Pl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>plate 105. 1837</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Countess Dalhousie's spleenwort</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Ceterach</genus_name><species_name>dalhousiae</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker) C. Christensen</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Ceterachopsis</genus_name><species_name>dalhousiae</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker) Ching</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Roots  not proliferous.  Stems  erect, unbranched; scales black with brown margins, lanceolate, 2--5 × 0.6--1 mm, sparsely denticulate.  Leaves  monomorphic.  Petiole  dark to light brown throughout, dull, to 1 cm, 1/10--1/15 length of blade, indument of scales throughout.  Blade  narrowly elliptic to narrowly lanceolate, pinnatifid, 4--15 × 1.5--6 cm, thick, sparsely puberulent to glabrescent; base gradually tapered; apex obtuse, not rooting.  Rachis  light brown to tan, dull-scaly; scales brown, lanceolate.  Veins  free, obscure.  Sori  3--7 pairs per pinna, on both basiscopic and acroscopic sides of lobes.  Spores  64 per sporangium. 2 n  = 72.</description><discussion>In the flora, Asplenium dalhousiae is found only in the Mule, Huachuca, and Baboquivari mountains of southern Arizona. The pattern of disjunction in the worldwide range of this species is highly unusual.</discussion><discussion>Asplenium dalhousiae is sometimes placed in the genus Ceterach on the basis of its thick, pinnatifid leaves. Most pteridologists, however, restrict Ceterach to species with densely scaly, pinnatifid leaves. Asplenium dalhousiae is placed in Ceterachopsis by pteridologists who believe it merits its own genus.</discussion><habitat>Moist, rocky ravines, terrestrial among and at bases of rocks</habitat><elevation> 1300--2000 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><global_distribution> n Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> Asia in the Himalayas.</global_distribution></treatment>
