<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>7</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Asplenium</genus_name><species_name>septentrionale</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) Hoffmann</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Deutschl. Fl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 12. 1796</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Forked spleenwort</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Acrostichum</genus_name><species_name>septentrionale</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 1068. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Roots  not proliferous.  Stems  erect, much branched to produce dense many-stemmed tufts or mats bearing numerous crowded leaves; scales dark reddish brown to black throughout, narrowly deltate, 2--4 × 0.3--0.6 mm, margins entire.  Leaves  monomorphic.  Petiole  dark reddish brown proximally, fading to green distally, 2--13 cm, 2--5 times length of blade; indument absent.  Blade  linear, simple or more often 1-pinnate, 0.5--4 × 0.1--0.4 cm, occasionally wider when pinnae strongly diverge, leathery, glabrous; base acute; apex acute, not rooting at tip.  Rachis  green, lustrous, glabrous.  Pinnae  of pinnate leaves 2(--4), strongly ascending to give forked appearance, linear, (5--)10--30 × 0.75--3 mm; base acute; margins remotely lacerate; apex acute.  Veins  free, obscure.  Sori  usually 2+ per pinna, parallel to margins.  Spores  64 per sporangium. 2 n  = 144.</description><discussion>In North America Asplenium septentrionale is principally a western species with isolated disjunct populations in Monroe and Hardy counties, West Virginia. Because of its close resemblance to a tuft of grass, it is easily overlooked, and discoveries of additional localities are to be expected. In Europe A . septentrionale is known to hybridize with several species, but in North America only the hybrid with A . trichomanes ( A . × alternifolium Wulfen) is known.</discussion><habitat>Cliffs of various substrates</habitat><elevation> 700--2900 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Colo.</us_distribution><us_distribution> D.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Okla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Utah</us_distribution><us_distribution> W.Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wyo.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico in Baja California</global_distribution><global_distribution> Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution> Asia.</global_distribution></treatment>
