<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Athyrium</genus_name><species_name>filix-femina</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) Roth ex Mertens</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Arch. Bot. (Leipzig)</publication_title><place_in_publication>2(1): 106. 1799</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Lady fern</common_name><common_name> athyrie fougère-femelle</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>filix-femina</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 1090. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  short-creeping or ascending.  Petiole  straw-colored distally, 7--60 cm, base dark red-brown or black, swollen, with 2 rows of teeth; scales light to dark brown, linear- to ovate-lanceolate, 7--20 × 1--5 mm.  Blade  elliptic, lanceolate to oblanceolate, 2-pinnate to 2-pinnate-pinnatifid, 18--30 × 5--50 cm, herbaceous but with cartilaginous margin, narrowed to base, apex acuminate.  Pinnae  sessile to short-stalked, linear-oblong to lanceolate, apex acuminate.  Pinnules  pinnatifid, segments oblong-linear to narrowly deltate, margins serrate.  Rachis , costae, and costules glabrous or with glands or hairs.  Veins  pinnate.  Sori  straight, hooked at distal end, or horseshoe-shaped; indusia dentate or ciliate.</description><discussion>Athyrium filix-femina is circumboreal, and this or closely related species extend into Mexico, Central America, and South America. The delimitation and infraspecific classification of A . filix-femina need detailed study.</discussion><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties ca. 5 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution> Asia.</global_distribution><key><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Petiole scales more than 1 cm; blades ca. 2 times length of petioles, elliptic to oblanceolate.</statement><next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Petiole scales 1 cm or less; blades 1-1.5 times length of petioles, elliptic to lanceolate.</statement><next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Pinnules narrowly deltate or oblong-lanceolate, nearly equilateral at base; indusia long-ciliate; spores yellow.</statement><determination>2a var. cyclosorum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Pinnules linear-oblong or linear-lanceolate, inequilateral at base; indusia dentate or long-ciliate; spores brown.</statement><determination>2b var. californicum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3</statement_id><statement>Petiole scales brown to dark brown; blades elliptic, narrowed to base, broadest near or just below middle; pinnae sessile or short-stalked; pinnules linear to oblong; indusia not glandular; spores yellow.</statement><determination>2c var. angustum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3</statement_id><statement>Petiole scales light brown to brown; blades ovate-lanceolate to lanceolate, slightly narrowed to base, broadest just above base; pinnae usually stalked; pinnules oblong-lanceolate to narrowly deltate; indusia glandular or not; spores dark brown.</statement><determination>2d var. asplenioides</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
