<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Blechnum</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 1077. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5, 485, 1754</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Deer ferns</common_name><etymology>[Greek blechnon, an ancient name for ferns in general]</etymology><description>Plants  terrestrial or rarely on rock.  Stems  creeping to ascending or erect, slender to stout, sometimes climbing [rarely subarborescent]; scales brown or black.  Leaves  monomorphic or variously dimorphic, cespitose to scattered.  Blades  pinnatifid to 1-pinnate, rarely simple or 2-pinnate.  Rachis  and costae glabrous, scaly, or hairy abaxially.  Veins  free, often forked.  Sori  borne on vascular commissures parallel to costae, 1 per side, normally uninterrupted, linear, continuous along length of costa.  Spores  with perine smooth to variously winged or rugose.  x  = 28, 29, 31, 32, 34, 36.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 220 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> mostly tropical</global_distribution><global_distribution> especially Southern Hemisphere.</global_distribution><author>Clifton E. Nauman</author><key><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Leaves strongly dimorphic, fertile leaves notably more erect, longer, and with narrower pinnae than sterile leaves; sterile blades tapering at base.</statement><determination>1 Blechnum spicant</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Leaves ± monomorphic, fertile leaves only slightly longer and somewhat contracted relative to sterile leaves; sterile blades ± truncate at base.</statement><next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Blades 1-pinnate proximally and pinnatifid distally or pinnatifid nearly throughout, usually less than 50 cm; pinna margins ± entire.</statement><determination>2a var. minor</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Blades 1-pinnate throughout, usually more than 50 cm; pinna margins ± evenly serrulate.</statement><determination>3 Blechnum serrulatum</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
