<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Ceratopteris</genus_name><species_name>thalictroides</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) Brongniart</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bull. Sci. Soc. Philom. Paris</publication_title><place_in_publication>sér. 3, 8: 186. 1821</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Acrostichum</genus_name><species_name>thalictroides</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 1070. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants  usually rooted in soil.  Sterile leaves  lanceolate to lance-ovate to ovate to deltate or cordate.  Petiole of sterile leaf  1--31 cm, not inflated.  Blade of sterile leaf  1--3-pinnate, 2--41 × 2--20 cm; segments lobed or incised, elliptic to lanceolate to ovate or deltate, to 12.5 cm; proximal pinnae ± alternate.  Fertile leaves  lanceolate to ovate to deltate or cordate, 2--117 × 2--48 cm.  Petiole of fertile leaf  1--46 cm.  Blade of fertile leaf  3--4-pinnate proximally, 2-pinnate distally; terminal segments linear.  Sporangia  usually crowded between segment midvein and revolute margin, with 13--71 indurate annulus cells.  Spores  32 per sporangium, 96--124 µm diam. 2 n  = 154, 156.</description><discussion>Ceratopteris thalictroides is common in Florida but rare elsewhere. It is tetraploid ( n = 77, 78), the two cytotypes reproductively isolated. It can be distinguished from the diploid C . richardii on the basis of spore number per sporangium. The single population in southern California may have been a recent introduction and apparently has not persisted. Several populations are of hybrid origin, with reduced spore viability and irregular meiotic pairing. These include some in southern Florida and Texas.</discussion><habitat>Aquatic to semiaquatic in swamps, bogs, canals, ponds, lakes, ditches, marshes</habitat><elevation> 0--200 m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> La.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> worldwide in tropical areas except Africa.</global_distribution></treatment>
