<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Ceratopteris</genus_name><species_name>richardii</species_name><species_authority>Brongniart</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Dict. Class. Hist. Nat.</publication_title><place_in_publication>3: 351. 1823</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Ceratopteris</genus_name><species_name>deltoidea</species_name><species_authority>Benedict</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants  floating or rooted.  Sterile leaves  lanceolate to deltate to ovate.  Petiole of sterile leaf  1--11 cm, not inflated; small leaves lobed to pinnate, segments or pinnae with entire to somewhat incised margins, larger leaves 2-pinnate-pinnatifid with deeply incised pinnae.  Blade of sterile leaf  3--16 × 2.5--17 cm, pinnae deltate to ovate; proximal pinnae usually alternate.  Fertile leaves  lanceolate to deltate to ovate to 19 × 12 cm.  Petiole of fertile leaf  6--9 cm.  Blade of fertile leaf  2--3-pinnate; terminal segments narrow.  Sporangia  scattered to densely crowded between midvein and revolute margin, with 20--40 or more indurate annulus cells.  Spores  16 per sporangium, 107--150 µm diam. 2 n  = 78.</description><discussion>According to L. G. Hickok (1977), Ceratopteris richardii is diploid. Morphologically, specimens from the United States are difficult to distinguish from tetraploid C . thalictroides . The primary characteristic distinguishing C . richardii is its 16-spored sporangia. Herbarium specimens with 16-spored sporangia from the West Indies and Latin America have variable morphology ranging from that of C . pteridoides to that of C . thalictroides (R. M. Lloyd 1974, fig. 6). Some specimens have both 16- and 32-spored sporangia. This suggests multiple origins for C . richardii . Because reproductive isolation is incomplete among the diploid taxa, and highly fertile F 2 segregates of various morphologic types occur, further work is needed to determine the nature, origin, and distinctness of C . richardii .</discussion><habitat>Aquatic to semiaquatic</habitat><habitat> lakes and ponds</habitat><elevation> 0 m</elevation><us_distribution> La.</us_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America in Guatemala</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Africa.</global_distribution></treatment>
