<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>20</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Cheilanthes</genus_name><species_name>bonariensis</species_name><species_authority>(Willdenow) Proctor</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bull. Inst. Jamaica, Sci. Ser.</publication_title><place_in_publication>5(1): 15. 1953</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Bonaire lip fern</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Acrostichum</genus_name><species_name>bonariense</species_name><species_authority>Willdenow</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>5: 114. 1810</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Notholaena</genus_name><species_name>aurea</species_name><species_authority>(Poiret) Desvaux</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  short-creeping to compact, usually 4--8 mm diam.; scales bicolored, with broad, well-defined, dark, central stripe and narrow, light brown margins, narrowly lanceolate, slightly contorted, strongly appressed, persistent.  Leaves  clustered, 10--60 cm; vernation noncircinate.  Petiole  dark brown, rounded adaxially.  Blade  linear, pinnate-pinnatifid throughout, 1--4 cm wide; rachis rounded adaxially, lacking scales, with dense monomorphic pubescence.  Pinnae  articulate at swollen, hirsute nodes, basal pair slightly smaller than adjacent pair, ± equilateral, appearing hirsute adaxially.  Costae  absent.  Ultimate segments  elongate-deltate to ovate, not especially beadlike, the largest 1--7 mm, abaxially densely tomentose, adaxially hirsute.  False indusia  marginal, weakly differentiated, 0.05--0.25 mm wide.  Sori  ± continuous around segment margins.  Sporangia  containing 32 spores.  n  = 2 n  = 90, apogamous.</description><discussion>Cheilanthes bonariensis has been assigned to Notholaena in past treatments. It is distantly related (at best) to the species here included in Notholaena , however, and we concur with R. M. Tryon and A. F. Tryon (1982) that it should be transferred to Cheilanthes . Chromosomal studies (G. J. Gastony and M. D. Windham 1989) suggest that C . bonariensis is an apogamous triploid that arose through autopolyploidy. Further investigation is necessary to determine whether 64-spored, sexually reproducing populations of C . bonariensis are still extant.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Rocky slopes and ledges</habitat><habitat> found on a variety of substrates though rarely observed on limestone</habitat><elevation> 1200--2400 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America.</global_distribution></treatment>
