<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Cryptogramma</genus_name><species_name>cascadensis</species_name><species_authority>E. R. Alverson</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title><place_in_publication>79: 95. 1989</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Cascade parsley fern</common_name><description>Stems  decumbent to erect, much branched from base, stout, 4--8 mm diam. (including hardened, persistent leaf bases); scales often bicolored, dense, broadly lanceolate to linear, to 6 × 2 mm.  Leaves  strongly tufted, deciduous; sterile leaves spreading, 3--20 cm; fertile leaves erect, 5--25 cm; petioles, costae, and costules glabrous.  Petiole  green to straw-colored, dark brown only on proximal 1/8 or less, ca. 1 mm wide when dry, collapsing and strongly furrowed; scales bicolored or ± concolored, becoming sparse distally.  Blade  deltate to ovate-lanceolate, all 2--3-pinnate, herbaceous, thin and translucent when dried, hydathodes superficial.  Segments  of sterile leaves oblong to fan-shaped, bases cuneate, distal 1/2--1/3 of each segment regularly dentate and often more deeply incised every 2d and 4th tooth; segments of fertile leaves ascending to erect, strongly differentiated from those of sterile leaves, linear, 3--12 × 1--2 mm; fertile segments revolute, covering sporangia.  Sporangia  in sori that coalesce at maturity. 2 n  = 60.</description><discussion>Populations of Cryptogramma cascadensis were previously identified as C . acrostichoides .</discussion><phenology>New growth produced in spring, spores maturing in late summer and autumn, leaves dying in autumn</phenology><habitat> Talus slopes and cliff crevices, often on igneous rocks, typically in relatively mesic subalpine habitats</habitat><elevation> 900--3500 m</elevation><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mont.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution></treatment>
