<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>15</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Ctenitis</genus_name><genus_authority>(C. Christensen) C. Christensen</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Verdoorn et al.,Man. Pteridol.</publication_title><place_in_publication>543. 1938</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Comb fern</common_name><etymology>[Greek kteis, comb]</etymology><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Dryopteris</genus_name><genus_authority>Adanson</genus_authority><subgenus_name>Ctenitis</subgenus_name><subgenus_authority>C. Christensen</subgenus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in L. K. Rosenvinge, Biol. Arb. Tilegn. Eug. Warming, </publication_title><place_in_publication>79. 1911</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants  generally terrestrial.  Stems  erect to obliquely ascending, stolons absent.  Leaves  monomorphic, evergreen or dying back in winter.  Petiole  2/3 to equaling length of blade, base not swollen; vascular bundles more than 3, arranged in an arc, ± round in cross section.  Blade  lanceolate to deltate, 1--4-pinnate-pinnatifid, gradually reduced distally to confluent, pinnatifid apex, herbaceous.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, segment margins nearly entire to crenulate, ciliate; proximal pinnae not reduced, sometimes basal pair much the longest, sessile to petiolulate, equilateral or inequilateral with basiscopic side more developed (pinnules noticeably longer); costae adaxially rounded or flat, not grooved; indument of linear to lanceolate scales and often multicellular glandular hairs abaxially, of multicellular reddish hairs adaxially.  Veins  free, simple or forked.  Sori  in 1 row between midrib and margin, round; indusia round-reniform, attached at narrow sinus, sometimes small or seemingly absent, persistent or caducous.  Spores  brownish, usually spiny, sometimes prominently cristate, rarely finely reticulate.  x  = 41.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 100 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> nearly worldwide in the tropics.</global_distribution><author>Robbin C. Moran</author><key><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Blades ovate-lanceolate, 2-4-pinnate-pinnatifid; basal pinnae inequilateral, elongate basiscopically.</statement><determination>1 Ctenitis sloanei</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Blades oblong or narrowly lanceolate, 1-pinnate-pinnatifid; basal pinnae equilateral.</statement><determination>2 Ctenitis submarginalis</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
