<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Dennstaedtia</genus_name><genus_authority>Bernhardi</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title><place_in_publication>1800(2): 124. 1802 [Named after A. W. Dennstaedt,. 1776</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name /><etymology>[Named after A. W. Dennstaedt, 1826, German botanist]</etymology><description>Plants  terrestrial, often forming colonies.  Stems  subterranean, long- to short-creeping; hairs dark reddish brown, jointed.  Leaves  clustered or scattered, erect to arching, ovate to lanceolate to deltate, 0.4--3 m.  Petiole  glabrous to pubescent, usually without prickles, often with stem buds near base; vascular bundles 1--2, arranged in U- or O-shape in cross section.  Blade  2--4-pinnate; rachis without prickles; nectaries absent.  Segments  pinnately divided, ultimate segments ovate to lanceolate, margins dentate or lobed.  Veins  free, pinnately branched.  Sori  marginal at vein tips, distinct, round or cylindric; indusia formed by fusion of true indusium and minute blade tooth to form circular or slightly 2-valvate cup.  Spores  tetrahedral-globose, trilete (rarely monolete), tuberculate or ridged.  x  = 34, 46, 47.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 70 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> worldwide</global_distribution><global_distribution> mostly tropical.</global_distribution><author>Clifton E. Nauman </author><author> A. Murray Evans</author><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Tryon, R. M. 1960. A review of the genus  Dennstaedtia  in America. Contr. Gray Herb. 187: 23--52.</reference></references><key><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Blades yellow-green or pale green, mostly 2-pinnate-pinnatifid, leaves usually less than 1 m.</statement><determination>1 Dennstaedtia punctilobula</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Blades dark green, 3-pinnate, leaves 1–2(–3) m.</statement><next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Basal segments of pinnules alternate; blades dull; indusia globose; Texas.</statement><determination>2 Dennstaedtia globulifera</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Basal segments of pinnules opposite; blades lustrous; indusia tubular or cylindric; Florida.</statement><determination>3 Dennstaedtia bipinnata</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
