<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><family_name>Gleicheniaceae</family_name><family_authority>C. Presl</family_authority></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Forking Fern Family</common_name><description>Plants  coarse, terrestrial.  Stems  long-creeping, forked, stele protostelic (a solid rod of vascular tissue with phloem surrounding xylem), covered with scales or hairs.  Leaves  monomorphic, large, scrambling or trailing, 1--many times forked.  Petiole  not articulate to stem, with pair of opposite pinnae and arrested bud at apex, or rachis continuing and producing 2 or more pairs of opposite pinnae.  Pinnae  1--several times forked, with arrested bud at each fork; indument of simple, branched, or stellate hairs [scales].  Veins  free, 1--4-forked.  Sori  round, indusia absent.  Sporangia  2--many on slightly elevated receptacle, sessile to subsessile; annulus complete, transverse, medial, longitudinally dehiscent; spores 120--800 per sporangium.  Spores  all alike, whitish to yellowish, bilateral to globose, monolete or trilete, generally smooth without elaborately ornamented surface.  Gametophyte  borne aboveground, green, obcordate to elongate.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Genera 4, species ca. 140 (1 genus, 1 species in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> nearly worldwide in tropical to subtropical regions.</global_distribution><author>Clifton E. Nauman</author><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Holttum, R. E. 1957. Morphology, growth habit, and classification in the family Gleicheniaceae. Phytomorphology 7: 168--184.</reference><reference> Maxon, W. R. 1909. Gleicheniaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905--1972. North American Flora. New York. Vol. 16, pp. 53--63.</reference><reference> Underwood, L. M. 1907. American ferns --- VIII. A preliminary review of the North American Gleicheniaceae. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 34: 243--262.</reference></references></treatment>
