<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Nephrolepis</genus_name><species_name>biserrata</species_name><species_authority>(Swartz) Schott</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gen. Fil.</publication_title><place_in_publication>plate 3. 1834</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Giant sword fern</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Aspidium</genus_name><species_name>biserratum</species_name><species_authority>Swartz</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader) </publication_title><place_in_publication>1800(2): 32. 1801</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stem scales loosely appressed to spreading, concolored or bicolored with pale margins. Tubers absent.  Leaves  2--22 × 0.3--3.5 dm.  Petiole  0.2--5.4 dm, sparsely to moderately scaly; scales spreading, reddish to light brown throughout (rarely with pale margins).  Blade  sparsely to densely scaly, glabrous or pubescent, hairs mostly on veins and abaxial, pale to light brown, 0.2--0.7 mm. Rachis 1.8--17 dm, points of pinna attachment 7.5--35 mm apart; scales moderately spaced, pale brown throughout. Central pinnae narrowly deltate to narrowly elliptic-lanceolate, 2.5--23 × 0.5--2 cm, base cuneate, truncate to auriculate-cordate acroscopically, rounded basiscopically, acroscopic lobe small and oblong or absent, margins biserrate to serrulate, apex attenuate; costae adaxially glabrous or densely hairy, hairs erect, pale, 0.3 mm.  Indusia  circular to horseshoe-shaped, peltate or attached at narrow sinus, 0.8--1.1 mm wide. 2 n  = 82.</description><discussion>Some forms of Nephrolepis biserrata closely resemble N . multiflora in pinna shape and indument but lack the distinctively transparent-margined (i.e., bicolored) and persistent petiole scales of the latter species. Nephrolepis multiflora also has more appressed and darker-colored stem scales.</discussion><habitat>Terrestrial or less commonly epiphytic in forested, relatively wet habitats, e.g., swamps, but occasionally thickets, roadsides, or clearings</habitat><elevation> 0 m</elevation><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution> se Asia.</global_distribution></treatment>
