<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>5</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Nephrolepis</genus_name><species_name>exaltata</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) Schott</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gen. Fil.</publication_title><place_in_publication>plate 3. 1834</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Sword fern</common_name><common_name> wild Boston fern</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>exaltatum</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Syst. Nat. ed. </publication_title><place_in_publication>10, 2: 1326. 1759</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stem scales spreading, concolored. Tubers absent.  Leaves  4--15 × 0.5--1.2 dm.  Petiole  0.2--4 dm, sparsely to moderately scaly; scales spreading, pale brown to reddish brown, concolored.  Blade  glabrous, sparsely to moderately scaly abaxially near costae and adaxially. Rachis 2.4--16.3 dm, points of pinna attachment 7.3--21 mm apart; scales moderately spaced, pale to dark brown, essentially concolored or margin indistinctly paler; hairs absent. Central pinnae deltate-oblong, slightly to distinctly falcate, 2.3--7.4 × 0.6--1.8 cm, base truncate to truncate-auriculate or auriculate, occasionally overlapping rachis, acroscopic lobe deltate to acute, margins serrulate, apex acute to deltate; costae adaxially glabrous.  Indusia  reniform to horseshoe-shaped, attached at narrow or broad sinus, 1--1.7 mm wide.</description><discussion>Nephrolepis exaltata is occasionally found farther north in the flora, but only as an escape from cultivation. Nephrolepis exaltata is usually confused with N . cordifolia when sterile; the latter species can be distinguished by its distinctly bicolored, adaxial rachis scales. These bicolored scales will distinguish N . cordifolia from all of the other species, even in the absence of other key features.</discussion><habitat>Terrestrial or epiphytic in forested to open habitats, most often as an epiphyte</habitat><elevation> 0 m</elevation><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Pacific Islands in scattered locations.</global_distribution></treatment>
