<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>5</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Notholaena</genus_name><species_name>lemmonii</species_name><species_authority>D. C. Eaton</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title><place_in_publication>7: 63. 1880</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Cheilanthes</genus_name><species_name>lemmonii</species_name><species_authority>(D. C. Eaton) Domin</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Chrysochosma</genus_name><species_name>lemmonii</species_name><species_authority>(D. C. Eaton) Pichi-Sermolli</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stem scales  weakly bicolored, margins brown, narrow, poorly defined, thin, sparsely ciliate-denticulate.  Leaves  7--30 cm.  Petiole  black to dark brown, much shorter than blade, grooved or flattened adaxially, bearing scattered glands and a few scales near base.  Blade  linear-lanceolate, 2-pinnate-pinnatifid, 3--6 times longer than wide, abaxially with conspicuous white or pale yellow farina, scales absent, adaxially glabrous at maturity; basal pinnae usually slightly smaller than adjacent pair, ± equilateral, proximal basiscopic pinnules not greatly enlarged.  Ultimate segments  sessile, broadly adnate to costae; segment margins slightly recurved, rarely concealing sporangia.  Sporangia  containing 64 spores. 2 n  = 60.</description><discussion>According to E. Wollenweber (1984), Notholaena lemmonii shows remarkable infraspecific variability in the chemical composition of the farina. R. M. Tryon (1956) recognized two varieties of N . lemmonii . The type collection of the species came from southern Arizona, and all specimens from the flora area are N . lemmonii var. lemmonii . The disjunct N . lemmonii var. australis , known only from the Mexican states of Puebla and Oaxaca, probably represents a distinct species.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Rocky slopes and cliffs, usually on granitic or volcanic substrates</habitat><elevation> 1000--1500 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><global_distribution> w Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
