<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Notholaena</genus_name><species_name>neglecta</species_name><species_authority>Maxon</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title><place_in_publication>17: 602. 1916</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Cheilanthes</genus_name><species_name>neglecta</species_name><species_authority>(Maxon) Mickel</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Chrysochosma</genus_name><species_name>neglecta</species_name><species_authority>(Maxon) Pichi-Sermolli</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stem scales  strongly bicolored, margins brown, broad and well defined, thin, ciliate-denticulate.  Leaves  4--15 cm.  Petiole  black, equal to or somewhat longer than blade, rounded adaxially, bearing scattered glands and a few scales near base.  Blade  narrowly deltate-pentagonal, 3--4-pinnate, 1--2 times longer than wide, abaxially with conspicuous pale yellow farina, scales absent, adaxially glabrous to sparsely glandular; basal pinnae much larger than adjacent pair, strongly inequilateral, proximal basiscopic pinnules greatly enlarged.  Ultimate segments  sessile to subsessile, narrowly adnate to costae or free; segment margins strongly revolute, often concealing sporangia.  Sporangia  containing 32 spores.  n  = 2 n  = 90, apogamous.</description><discussion>Notholaena neglecta is closely related to N . californica and may have been involved in the origin of polyploids within that complex. Populations occurring in the flora are composed of apogamous triploids, but a sexually reproducing diploid cytotype has been found in Nuevo León, Mexico (M. D. Windham, unpublished data).</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Rocky slopes and cliffs, apparently confined to limestone</habitat><elevation> 300--1900 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
