<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Notholaena</genus_name><species_name>nealleyi</species_name><species_authority>Seaton ex J. M. Coulter</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 61. 1890</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Cheilanthes</genus_name><species_name>nealleyi</species_name><species_authority>(Seaton ex J. M. Coulter) Domin</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Chrysochosma</genus_name><species_name>schaffneri</species_name><species_authority>(E. Fournier) L. Underwood ex Davenport</species_authority><variety_name>nealleyi</variety_name><variety_authority>(Seaton ex J. M. Coulter) Pichi-Sermolli</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Notholaena</genus_name><species_name>schaffneri</species_name><species_authority>(E. Fournier)</species_authority><variety_name>nealleyi</variety_name><variety_authority>(Seaton ex J. M. Coulter) Weatherby</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stem scales  mostly bicolored, margins black, broad and poorly defined, thick, ciliate-denticulate.  Leaves  5--15 cm.  Petiole  black to dark brown, much shorter than blade, rounded adaxially, sparsely glandular farinose, bearing needlelike, multicelled hairs and ciliate scales.  Blade  lanceolate, 2-pinnate-pinnatifid, 3--6 times longer than wide, abaxially with conspicuous whitish farina and shiny, dark brown, needlelike hairs scattered along rachises and costae, adaxially distinctly glandular; basal pinnae equal to or slightly smaller than adjacent pair, ± equilateral, proximal basiscopic pinnules not greatly enlarged.  Ultimate segments  sessile to subsessile, narrowly adnate to costae; segment margins slightly recurved, rarely concealing sporangia.  Sporangia  containing 64 spores.</description><discussion>Notholaena nealleyi often has been treated as a variety of the Mexican species N . schaffneri (Fournier) L. Underwood ex Davenport, but recent studies (Windham, unpublished data) suggest that it may represent an allotetraploid hybrid between diploid N . schaffneri and another, as yet unidentified, species. Results of these studies, combined with morphologic differences and geographic isolation, favor the recognition of N . nealleyi as a distinct species.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Calcareous cliffs and ledges, usually on limestone</habitat><elevation> 200--1700 m</elevation><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
