<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>7</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>brachyptera</species_name><species_authority>(T. Moore) Baker</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Hooker &amp; Baker,Syn. Fil. ed. 2</publication_title><place_in_publication>477. 1874</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Platyloma</genus_name><species_name>brachyptera</species_name><species_authority>T. Moore</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gard. Chron., </publication_title><place_in_publication>141. 1873</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales bicolored, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, centers dark brown to black, thick, margins brown, thin, dentate.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered on stem, 8--40 cm; croziers sparsely villous.  Petiole  dark brown, lustrous, flattened or slightly grooved adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  linear-oblong, 2-pinnate proximally, 1--4 cm wide; rachis brown throughout, straight, shallowly grooved adaxially, usually glabrous.  Pinnae  strongly ascending, not decurrent on rachis, usually with 5--11 ultimate segments; costae straight, 5--20 mm, usually shorter than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  linear, 5--20 mm, leathery, glabrous; margins on fertile segments strongly revolute, covering more than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders greenish, crenate; apex mucronate.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  short-stalked, containing 64 spores, intermixed with abundant farina-producing glands.</description><discussion>The distinctive Pellaea brachyptera reportedly hybridizes with P . mucronata (A. F. Tryon 1957; D. B. Lellinger 1985); the hybrids are morphologically intermediate plants with malformed spores.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Cliffs and rocky slopes, usually on igneous substrates, occasionally on serpentine</habitat><elevation> 900--2700 m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution></treatment>
