<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>14</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>lyngholmii</species_name><species_authority>Windham</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb.</publication_title><place_in_publication>19: 40. 1993</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales uniformly brown or tan, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, thin, margins entire to denticulate.  Leaves  somewhat dimorphic, sterile leaves shorter and less divided than fertile leaves, clustered on stem, 10--30 cm; croziers villous.  Petiole  dark brown to reddish purple, lustrous, rounded adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  elongate-deltate to ovate, 2-pinnate proximally, 5--15 cm wide; rachis brown or reddish purple throughout, straight, often slightly flattened adaxially, sparsely villous with long, divergent hairs.  Pinnae  perpendicular to rachis or slightly ascending, not decurrent on rachis, usually with 7--15 ultimate segments; costae straight, 25--80 mm, usually longer than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  oblong-lanceolate, 7--25 mm, leathery, sparsely villous abaxially near midrib; margins usually recurved on fertile segments, covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, crenulate; apex slightly mucronate.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  long-stalked, containing 32 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands.</description><discussion>Pellaea lyngholmii is an apogamous tetraploid that arose through hybridization between P . atropurpurea and P . truncata (M. D. Windham 1993). It is most often confused with P . atropurpurea , from which P . lyngholmii differs in having sparsely villous rachises, smaller and more numerous ultimate segments, and spores usually more than 62 µm in diameter.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Rocky slopes and ledges, usually on sandstone</habitat><elevation> 1200--1800 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution></treatment>
