<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>ovata</species_name><species_authority>(Desvaux) Weatherby</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. Gray Herb.</publication_title><place_in_publication>114: 34. 1936 Pteris ovata  Desvaux, Mém. Soc. Lin. 1827</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Pellaea flexuosa (Kaulfuss ex Schlechtendal &amp; Chamisso) Link</common_name><description>Stems  creeping, horizontal, slender, 2--5 mm diam.; scales mostly bicolored, lanceolate, largest scales 0.3--0.8 mm wide, centers black, thick, margins brown, thin, erose-dentate.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered or scattered along stem, 15--100 cm; croziers pubescent, bearing a few scales.  Petiole  straw-colored, tan, or gray, not lustrous, rounded or slightly flattened adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  elongate-deltate, usually 3-pinnate proximally, 5--25 cm wide; rachis tan throughout, strongly flexuous, rounded or flattened adaxially, usually glabrous.  Pinnae  retrorse, projecting downward toward base of leaf, not decurrent on rachis, with 5--40 ultimate segments; costae strongly flexuous, 25--120 mm, longer than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  lanceolate-deltate, 5--20 mm, leathery, glabrous or sparsely pubescent; margins recurved on fertile segments, covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, entire; apex obtuse to truncate.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  short-stalked, containing 64 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands. 2 n  = 58.</description><discussion>Populations of Pellaea ovata in the flora are composed of sexual diploids; an apogamous triploid cytotype predominates south of the United States. I have not seen herbarium specimens to substantiate reports of P . ovata from New Mexico (D. B. Lellinger 1985).</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Rocky slopes and ledges, leaves often supported by associated vegetation, on a variety of substrates including granite and limestone</habitat><elevation> 300--1700 m</elevation><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies in Hispaniola</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America.</global_distribution></treatment>
