<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>wrightiana</species_name><species_authority>Hooker</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Fil.</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 142. 1858</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>ternifolia</species_name><species_authority>(Cavanilles) Link</species_authority><variety_name>wrightiana</variety_name><variety_authority>(Hooker) A. F. Tryon</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 5--10 mm diam.; scales bicolored, linear-subulate, 0.1--0.3 mm wide, centers black, thick, margins brown, thin, erose-dentate.  Leaves  monomorphic, clustered on stem, 6--40 cm; croziers sparsely villous.  Petiole  dark brown, lustrous, flattened or slightly grooved adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  linear-oblong, 2-pinnate proximally, 1.5--5 cm wide; rachis brown throughout, straight, shallowly grooved adaxially, usually glabrous.  Pinnae  perpendicular to rachis or slightly ascending, not decurrent on rachis, usually with 3--9 ultimate segments; costae straight, 2--20 mm, usually shorter than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  narrowly oblong, 5--20 mm, leathery, glabrous; margins recurved on fertile segments, usually covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, crenulate; apex mucronate.  Veins  of ultimate segments obscure.  Sporangia  long-stalked, containing 64 spores, intermixed with sparse farina-producing glands. 2 n  = 116.</description><discussion>W. H. Wagner Jr. (1965) suggested that Pellaea wrightiana was a fertile allotetraploid hybrid between P . truncata (as P . longimucronata ) and P . ternifolia . This hypothesis has been confirmed by isozyme analyses (M. D. Windham 1988). Pellaea wrightiana is therefore treated as a distinct species rather than a variety of P . ternifolia . This tetraploid species hybridizes with P . truncata and P . ternifolia subsp. arizonica to produce sterile triploids and tetraploids with intermediate morphology and malformed spores. Pellaea wrightiana has also hybridized with P . atropurpurea to form a rare apogamous pentaploid known only from western Oklahoma.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Cliffs and rocky slopes, on a variety of acidic to mildly basic substrates</habitat><elevation> 300--2900 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Colo.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Okla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Utah</us_distribution><global_distribution> n Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
