<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>cordifolia</species_name><species_authority>(Sessé &amp; Mociño) A. R. Smith</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Amer. Fern J.</publication_title><place_in_publication>70: 26. 1980</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Adiantum</genus_name><species_name>cordifolium</species_name><species_authority>Sessé &amp; Mociño</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Naturaleza (Mexico City), ser. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2, 1(App.): 182. 1890</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>cardiomorpha</species_name><species_authority>Weatherby</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pellaea</genus_name><species_name>sagittata</species_name><species_authority>(Cavanilles) Link</species_authority><variety_name>cordata</variety_name><variety_authority>(Cavanilles) A. F. Tryon</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  compact, ascending, stout, 6--10 mm diam.; scales uniformly orange-brown and thin, lanceolate to ovate, largest scales 0.3--1 mm wide, margins dentate.  Leaves  somewhat dimorphic, sterile leaves shorter than fertile leaves, clustered on stem, 15--50 cm; croziers not conspicuously pubescent, densely scaly.  Petiole  straw-colored, tan, or gray, not lustrous, rounded or slightly flattened adaxially, without prominent articulation lines.  Blade  ovate-deltate, 2-pinnate proximally, 5--20 cm wide; rachis tan throughout, straight to slightly flexuous, rounded or flattened adaxially, glabrous.  Pinnae  perpendicular to rachis or slightly ascending, not decurrent on rachis, usually with 3--15 ultimate segments; costae straight to slightly flexuous, 25--100 mm, longer than ultimate segments.  Ultimate segments  round-cordate to deltate-cordate, 5--15 mm, herbaceous to leathery, glabrous or puberulent; margins recurved on fertile segments, covering less than 1/2 abaxial surface, borders whitish, crenulate; apex rounded or retuse.  Veins  of ultimate segments usually evident.  Sporangia  short-stalked, containing 64 spores, not intermixed with farina-producing glands. 2 n  = 58.</description><discussion>The diploid Pellaea cordifolia has often been treated as a variety of the Central American and South American apogamous triploid, P . sagittata . The two taxa are distinguished by a number of qualitative morphologic features (A. R. Smith 1980), and it seems unlikely that they represent cytotypes of a single species. A. F. Tryon (1957) suggested that P . sagittata may have originated through hybridization between P . ovata and P . cordifolia (as P . sagittata var. cordata ).</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Rocky slopes and ledges, usually on volcanic substrates</habitat><elevation> 1000--2500 m</elevation><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
