<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Phegopteris</genus_name><genus_authority>(C. Presl) Fée</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Mém. Foug.</publication_title><place_in_publication>5: 242. 1852</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Beech fern</common_name><etymology>[Greek phegos, beech, and pteris, fern]</etymology><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><section_name>Phegopteris</section_name><section_authority>C. Presl</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Tent. Pterid., </publication_title><place_in_publication>179. 1836</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Thelypteris</genus_name><genus_authority>Schmidel</genus_authority><subgenus_name>Phegopteris</subgenus_name><subgenus_authority>(C. Presl) Ching</subgenus_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  long-creeping, 1--4 mm diam.  Blades  2--3-pinnatifid in proximal part, broadest at base, apex gradually reduced; pinnae deeply lobed, mostly strongly adnate, connected by wing along rachis, wing sometimes forming lobe between pinnae and served by vein arising from rachis; costae not grooved adaxially; buds absent; veins free, simple or often forked, distal veins of segment reaching margin or nearly so; indument abaxially of unbranched, unicellular hairs, rachises and costae also with spreading, ovate-lanceolate scales.  Sori  round to oblong, supramedial to inframarginal, lacking indusia; sporangial capsule often bearing stalked glands or hairs.  x  = 30.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> north temperate and boreal</global_distribution><global_distribution> 1 in temperate e Asia.</global_distribution><author>Alan R. Smith</author><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Holttum, R. E. 1969. Studies in the family Thelypteridaceae. The genera  Phegopteris ,  Pseudophegopteris , and  Macrothelypteris . Blumea 17: 5--32.</reference></references><key><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Proximal pair of pinnae (7–)10–20 cm, connected to those next above by wing along rachis; scales on costae abaxially whitish to light tan, narrowly lanceolate, mostly 3–5 cells wide at base; hairs of costae abaxially mostly less than 0.25 mm, a few sometimes to 0.5 mm; segments of larger pinnae deeply lobed; veins always forked to pinnate.</statement><determination>1 Phegopteris hexagonoptera</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Proximal pair of pinnae 3–10(–15) cm, sessile or slightly adnate to rachis; scales on costae abaxially tan to often shiny brown, ovate-lanceolate, usually 6–12 or more cells wide at base; hairs of costae abaxially mostly more than 0.3 mm with many ca. 0.5 mm; segments of pinna entire or crenate, rarely shallowly lobed; veins in segments of middle pinnae mostly simple.</statement><determination>2 Phegopteris connectilis</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
