<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>34</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>virginiana</species_name><species_authority>Miller</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gard. Dict., ed. 8</publication_title><place_in_publication>Pinus no. 9. 1768</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Virginia pine</common_name><description>Trees  to 18m; trunk to 0.5m diam., straight or contorted to erect or leaning; crown irregularly rounded or flattened.  Bark  gray-brown with irregular, scaly-plated ridges, on upper sections of trunk reddish, scaly.  Branches  spreading-ascending to spreading-descending; twigs slender, red- or purple-tinged, often glaucous, aging red-brown to gray, rough.  Buds  ovoid to cylindric, red-brown, 0.6--1cm, resinous or not resinous; scale margins white-fringed.  Leaves  2 per fascicle, spreading or ascending, persisting 3--4 years, 2--8cm × 1--1.5mm, strongly twisted, deep to pale yellow-green, all surfaces with inconspicuous stomatal lines, margins serrulate, apex narrowly acute; sheath 0.4--1cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid-cylindric, 10--20mm, red-brown or yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter, persisting to 5 years, symmetric, lance-ovoid or lanceoloid before opening, ovoid when open, 3-- 7(--8)cm, dull red-brown, nearly sessile or on stalks to 1cm, scales rigid, with strong purple-red or purple-brown border on adaxial surface distally; apophyses slightly thickened, slightly elongate; umbo central, low-pyramidal, with slender, stiff prickle.  Seeds  compressed-obovoid, oblique apically; body 4--7mm, pale brown, mottled darker; wing narrow, to 20mm. 2 n =24.</description><discussion>Pinus virginiana is weedy and fire successional and often forms large stands. It is mostly too small and too profusely branched to be valued except as pulpwood.</discussion><habitat>Dry uplands, sterile sandy or shaly barrens, old fields, and lower mountains</habitat><elevation> 0--900m</elevation><us_distribution> Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Del.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ind.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ky.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Miss.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.J.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Y.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ohio</us_distribution><us_distribution> Pa.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tenn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution> W.Va.</us_distribution></treatment>
