<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>29</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>sabiniana</species_name><species_authority>Douglas ex D. Don</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Lambert,Descr. Pinus [ed. 3]</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: unnumbered page between 144 and 145, plate 80. 1832</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Digger pine</common_name><common_name> gray pine</common_name><description>Trees  to 25m; trunk to 1.2m diam., straight to crooked, often forked; crown conic to raggedly lobed, sparse.  Bark  dark brown to near black, irregularly and deeply furrowed, ridges irregularly rectangular or blocky, scaly, often breaking away, bases of furrows and underbark orangish.  Branches  often ascending; cone-bearing branchlets stout, twigs comparatively slender, both pale purple-brown and glaucous, aging gray, rough.  Buds  ovoid, red-brown, ca. 1cm, resinous; scale margins white-fringed.  Leaves  mostly 3 per fascicle, drooping, persisting 3--4 years, 15--32cm × 1.5mm, slightly twisted, dull blue-green, all surfaces with pale, narrow stomatal lines, margins serrulate, apex short-acuminate; sheath to 2.4cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid, 10--15mm, yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds soon thereafter, persisting to 7 years, pendent, massive, heavy, nearly symmetric, ovoid before opening, broadly to narrowly ovoid or ovoid-cylindric when open, 15--25cm, dull brown, resinous, stalks to 5cm; apophyses elongate, curved, continuous with umbos to form long, upcurved claws to 2cm.  Seeds  narrowly obovoid; body ca. 20mm, dark brown; wing broad, short, ca. 10mm. 2n = 24.</description><discussion>Seeds of Pinus sabiniana were an important food source for many Indian groups in California, sometimes collectively referred to as "Digger Indians." Because the name "Digger" has been used as a derogatory ethnic term, many people prefer to avoid using the vernacular name Digger pine.</discussion><habitat>Dry foothills on the west slope of the Sierra Nevada, and in the coast ranges, nearly ringing the Central Valley of California</habitat><elevation> 30--1900m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Griffin, J.R. 1964. Cone morphology in  Pinus sabiniana . J. Arnold Arbor. 45: 260--273.</reference></references></treatment>
