<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>28</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>engelmannii</species_name><species_authority>Carrière</species_authority><place_of_publication><place_in_publication>3: 227. 1854</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Apache pine</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>macrophylla</species_name><species_authority>Engelmann</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Wislizenus </publication_title><place_in_publication>1848,</place_in_publication><other_info>not Lindley 1839</other_info></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>apacheca</species_name><species_authority>Lemmon</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>latifolia</species_name><species_authority>Sargent</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Trees  to 35m; trunk to 0.6m diam., straight; crown irregularly rounded, rather thin.  Bark  dark brown, at maturity deeply furrowed, ridges becoming yellowish, of narrow, elongate, scaly plates.  Branches  straight to ascending; twigs stout (1--2cm thick), pale gray-brown, aging darker brown, rough.  Buds  ovoid-conic, to 2cm, resinous; scale margins pale fringed.  Leaves  3(--5) per fascicle, spreading-ascending, often drooping, forming a brush at twig tips, persisting 2 years, (20--)25--45cm × 2mm, dull green, all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins coarsely serrulate, apex conic-subulate; sheath 3--4cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  cylindric, ca. 25mm, yellow to yellow-brown.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years and shedding seeds soon thereafter, not persistent, terminal, sometimes curved, often asymmetric, lance-ovoid before opening, ovoid when open, 11--14cm, light dull brown, nearly sessile or short-stalked; apophyses rhombic, somewhat to quite elongate, strongly raised toward outer cone base, sometimes curved, strongly cross-keeled, narrowed to thick, curved, broadly triangular-based umbo, this often producing outcurved claw.  Seeds  obovoid; body ca. 8--9mm, dark brown; wing to 20mm. 2 n =24.</description><discussion>In general appearance Pinus engelmannii much resembles P . palustris with its short-persistent, long leaves (but in this species drooping) and in its tendency to form a grass stage. It has a deep taproot as do P . palustris and P . ponderosa .</discussion><habitat>High and dry mountain ranges, valleys, and plateaus</habitat><elevation> 1500--2500m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
