<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>9</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>quadrifolia</species_name><species_authority>Parlatore ex Sudworth</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>U.S.D.A. Div. Forest. Bull.</publication_title><place_in_publication>14: 17. 1897</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Parry pinyon</common_name><common_name> piñón</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>cembroides</species_name><species_authority>Zuccarini</species_authority><variety_name>parryana</variety_name><variety_authority>Voss</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>juarezensis</species_name><species_authority>Lanner</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>parryana</species_name><species_authority>Engelmann</species_authority><place_of_publication><place_in_publication>1862,</place_in_publication><other_info>not Gordon 1858</other_info></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Trees  to 10m; trunk to 0.5m diam., straight, much branched; crown dense, becoming rounded.  Bark  red-brown, irregularly furrowed and cross-checked to irregularly rectangular, plates scaly.  Branches  spreading to ascending, persistent to trunk base; twigs slender, pale orange-brown, puberulent-glandular, aging brown to gray-brown.  Buds  ovoid, light red-brown, ca. 0.4--0.5cm, slightly resinous.  Leaves  (3--)4(--5) per fascicle, persisting 3--4 years, (2--)3--6cm × (1--)1.2--1.7mm, curved, connivent, stiff, green to blue-green, margins entire to minutely scaly-denticulate, finely serrulate, apex subulate, adaxial surfaces mostly strongly whitened with stomatal bands, abaxial surface not so but 2 subepidermal resin bands evident; sheath 0.5--0.6cm, scales soon recurved, forming rosette, shed early.  Pollen cones  ovoid, ca. 10mm, yellowish.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, shedding seeds and falling soon thereafter, spreading, symmetric, ovoid before opening, broadly ovoid to depressed-globose when open, (3--)4--8(--10)cm, pale yellow-brown, sessile to short-stalked, apophyses thickened, strongly raised, diamond-shaped, transversely keeled, umbo subcentral, low-pyramidal or sunken, blunt.  Seeds  obovoid, body ca. 15mm, brown, wingless.</description><discussion>Pinus quadrifolia is the rarest pinyon in the flora. It hybridizes naturally with P . monophylla .</discussion><habitat>Dry rocky sites</habitat><elevation> 1200--1800m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico in Baja California.</global_distribution></treatment>
