<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>23</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pinus</genus_name><species_name>pungens</species_name><species_authority>Lambert</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Ann. Bot. (London)</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 198. 1805</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Table mountain pine</common_name><common_name> mountain pine</common_name><description>Trees  to 12m; trunk to 0.6m diam., straight to crooked, erect to leaning, poorly self-pruning; crown irregularly rounded or flattened.  Bark  red- to gray-brown, irregularly checked into scaly plates.  Branches  horizontally spreading; twigs slender, orange- to yellow-brown, aging darker brown, rough.  Buds  ovoid to cylindric, red-brown, 0.6--0.9cm, resinous.  Leaves  2(--3) per fascicle, spreading or ascending, persisting 3 years, 3--6(--8)cm × 1--1.5mm, twisted, deep yellow-green, all surfaces with fine stomatal lines, margins harshly serrulate, apex acute to short-acuminate; sheath 0.5--1cm, base persistent.  Pollen cones  ellipsoid, ca. 15mm, yellow.  Seed cones  maturing in 2 years, variably serotinous, mostly whorled, downcurved, asymmetric, ovoid before opening, broadly ovoid when open, (4--)6--10cm, gray- to pale red-brown, nearly sessile or on stalks to 1cm; apophyses thickened, diamond-shaped, strongly keeled, elongate, mammillate at cone base abaxially; umbo central, a stout, curved, sharp claw.  Seeds  deltoid-obovoid, oblique; body ca. 6mm, deep purple-brown to black; wing 10--20(--30)mm. 2 n =24.</description><discussion>Pinus pungens is a scrub pine and is too small and knotty to be much utilized except for pulpwood and firewood. Its common name refers to a general type of landform, not to a specific, named mountain.</discussion><habitat>Dry, mostly sandy or shaly uplands</habitat><habitat> Appalachians and associated Piedmont</habitat><elevation> 500--1350m</elevation><us_distribution> Del.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.J.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Pa.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tenn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution> W.Va.</us_distribution></treatment>
