<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Pleopeltis</genus_name><species_name>riograndensis</species_name><species_authority>(T. Wendt) E. G. Andrews &amp; Windham</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Windham,Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb.</publication_title><place_in_publication>19: 46. 1993</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Rio Grande scaly polypody</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>thyssanolepis</species_name><species_authority>A. Braun ex Klotzsch</species_authority><variety_name>riograndense</variety_name><variety_authority>T. Wendt</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Amer. Fern J. </publication_title><place_in_publication>70: 6. 1980</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  short-creeping, sparingly branched, 2--3 mm diam.; scales subulate to lanceolate-acuminate, centrally clathrate with cell luminae large and clear, surfaces glabrous, margins lacerate-ciliate.  Leaves  to 20 cm, strongly hygroscopic.  Petiole  grooved, otherwise round in cross section, sparsely scaly; scales rarely overlapping, margins denticulate to ciliate.  Blade  triangular-oblong to ovate, deeply pinnatifid, to 5 cm wide, moderately scaly abaxially, glabrous adaxially; scales concolored to obscurely bicolored, usually dark reddish brown throughout, broadly ovate-lanceolate, clathrate, more than 0.5 mm wide, margins fringed-ciliate.  Venation  mostly free with occasional areoles, never more than 1 included veinlet in fertile areoles.  Sori  round, discrete, surficial to shallowly embossed, soral scales attached at periphery of receptacle.  Spores  smooth with scattered spheric deposits on surface, 60--74 µm. 2 n  = 148.</description><discussion>In the past Pleopeltis riograndensis has been treated as a variety of P . thyssanolepis , but it differs from the latter species in that the petiole and leaf are only sparsely scaly rather than densely so, the blade scales are mostly ovate or ovate-lanceolate rather than nearly spheric, the venation is mostly free rather than mostly areolate, and the basal segments of the blade are alternate rather than opposite to nearly opposite.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Growing on rocky slopes and ledges, and in crevices, usually in moist, shaded canyons</habitat><elevation> 1500--2500 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Texas</us_distribution><global_distribution> n Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
