<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>triseriale</species_name><species_authority>Swartz</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title><place_in_publication>1800(2): 26. 1801</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Goniophlebium</genus_name><species_name>triseriale</species_name><species_authority>(Swartz) Pichi-Sermolli</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>brasiliense</species_name><species_authority>Poiret</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  not whitish pruinose, slender to stout, 5--15 mm diam., taste unknown; scales brown, ovate-acuminate, symmetric, somewhat to strongly clathrate, margins somewhat lighter, entire.  Leaves  to 90 cm.  Petiole  slender to stout, to 7 mm diam.  Blade  broadly ovate, 1-pinnate at base, widest at or near base, to 60 cm wide, papery to almost leathery; rachis glabrous abaxially and adaxially.  Segments  (pinnae) linear to oblong, apex acuminate; proximal segments stalked to nearly sessile, distal ones slightly narrowed but broadly adnate at base, less than 35 mm wide; margins entire or slightly wavy; apex acute; midrib glabrous adaxially.  Venation  anastomosing with a regular series of 2--5 rows of areoles on both sides of costae.  Sori  in 1--3 parallel rows on both sides of costa, 0.5--3 mm diam., circular when immature.  Sporangiasters  absent.  Spores  less than 58 µm, verrucose, with surface projections less than 3 µm. 2 n  = 148.</description><discussion>Commonly found in montane tropical rainforests, the epiphytic Polypodium triseriale is quite distinct from and probably only distantly related to other North American members of Polypodium . It seems likely that spores are occasionally blown into southern Florida, probably from the West Indies, and plants develop as naturalized populations.</discussion><habitat>Epiphytic</habitat><elevation> 0 m</elevation><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution> s Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America to s Brazil</global_distribution><global_distribution> Bolivia.</global_distribution></treatment>
