<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>californicum</species_name><species_authority>Kaulfuss</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Enum. Filic.</publication_title><place_in_publication>102. 1824</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>California polypody</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>californicum</species_name><variety_name>kaulfussii</variety_name><variety_authority>D. C. Eaton</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>vulgare</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><subspecies_name>californicum</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Kaulfuss) Hultén</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Polypodium</genus_name><species_name>vulgare</species_name><variety_name>kaulfussii</variety_name><variety_authority>(D. C. Eaton) Fernald</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  dull or inconspicuously glaucous, moderately stout, to 10 mm diam., acrid or bland-tasting; scales uniformly brown or slightly darker near point of attachment, lanceolate-ovate, symmetric, margins entire to erose.  Leaves  to 70 cm.  Petiole  usually slender, to 3 mm diam.  Blade  deltate to lanceolate-ovate, pinnatifid, usually widest near base, to 20 cm wide, leathery to herbaceous; rachis sparsely scaly to glabrescent abaxially, puberulent adaxially; scales deltate to ovate, usually more than 10 cells wide.  Segments  linear-lanceolate to oblong, usually less than 15 mm wide; margins serrate; apex widely obtuse to rarely attenuate; midrib puberulent adaxially.  Venation  weakly to conspicuously anastomosing, most segments containing several areoles, often forming 1 row.  Sori  midway between margin and midrib or slightly closer to midrib, usually less than 3 mm diam., oval when immature.  Sporangiasters  absent.  Spores  less than 58 µm, verrucose, with surface projections to 3 µm. 2 n  = 74.</description><discussion>R. M. Lloyd and F. A. Lang (1964) recognized two cytotypes within Polypodium californicum . The tetraploid has proved to be an allopolyploid involving P . californicum and P . glycyrrhiza and is treated here as a separate species, P . calirhiza , following S. A. Whitmore and A. R. Smith (1991). Polypodium californicum can be confused with P . calirhiza , but it usually can be distinguished by blade shape, venation, spore size, and geographic distribution. D. S. Barrington et al. (1986) reported that spores of northern populations of P . californicum can be as large as those of P . calirhiza , but the former species has veins forming more areoles per segment than does the latter.</discussion><phenology>Sporulating early winter--spring</phenology><habitat> Cliffs and soil on rocky slopes</habitat><habitat> on a variety of substrates but usually igneous</habitat><habitat> 0--1500 m.</habitat><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><habitat> Mexico in Baja California.</habitat></treatment>
