<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>7a</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Polystichum</genus_name><species_name>imbricans</species_name><subspecies_name>imbricans</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(D. C. Eaton) D. H. Wagner</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Polystichum</genus_name><species_name>munitum</species_name><species_authority>(Kaulfuss) C. Presl</species_authority><subspecies_name>nudatum</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(D. C. Eaton) Ewan</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  decumbent to ascending.  Leaves  stiffly erect, 2.5--5 dm.  Pinnae  lanceolate-oblong, less than 5 times longer than wide, twisted out of plane of blade (adaxial surfaces facing upward like Venetian blinds), base usually cupped, apex cuspidate.  Indusia  entire.</description><discussion>Polystichum imbricans subsp. imbricans grows in the Coast Ranges and the Sierra-Cascade axis. It is isolated in the Wallowa Mountains of eastern Oregon.</discussion><discussion>Sun forms of Polystichum munitum are often mistaken for P . imbricans ; characteristics of the distal petiolar scales and indusial margins are more reliable than gross morphologic features for distinguishing them. Polystichum imbricans has narrow distal petiolar scales that fall off early; P . munitum has wide distal petiolar scales (the largest more than 1 mm wide) that are persistent. Polystichum imbricans hybridizes readily with P . munitum , the hybrids usually being sterile but in some places forming hybrid swarms because of partial fertility of the hybrids (D. H. Wagner 1979). The hybrids with P . californicum are discussed under that species.</discussion><habitat>Rooted at base of boulders or in cliff crevices in drier sites of mesic montane forests</habitat><elevation> 0--2500 m</elevation><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution></treatment>
