<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>30</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Selaginella</genus_name><species_name>pilifera</species_name><species_authority>A. Braun</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Index Seminum (Berlin)</publication_title><place_in_publication>20. 1857</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Resurrection plant</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Selaginella</genus_name><species_name>pilifera</species_name><species_authority>A. Braun</species_authority><variety_name>pringlei</variety_name><variety_authority>(Baker) C. V. Morton</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants  terrestrial or on rock, forming rosettes.  Main (central) stem  spirally compact, branched, branches 2--3-forked, prostrate, flat when moist, almost flat when dry, not articulate, glabrous.  Rhizophores  borne on underside of stems, restricted to base of rosette, 4--5 mm diam.  Leaves  thick and stiff.  Lateral leaves  overlapping, ascending, green, elliptic to elliptic-ovate, (2--)3--3.5 X 0.8--1 mm; base cordate, with 2 ciliate lobes or auricles; margins transparent, acroscopic margins short-ciliate at base, dentate toward apex; basiscopic margins entire to scattered dentate; apex bristle 1/3--1/2 length of leaf blade.  Median leaves  peltate, oblique-lanceolate, 2--3 X 0.7--1 mm; base rounded to truncate, pubescent; margins green to slightly transparent, inner margins dentate, outer margins entire or slightly dentate; apex bristle 1/3 length of leaf blade.  Strobili  solitary, 5--10 mm; sporophylls monomorphic, lanceolate-ovate, slightly keeled, keel not dentate, base pubescent, margins transparent to greenish, short-ciliate to denticulate, apex long-bristled. 2 n  = 20.</description><discussion>Selaginella lepidophylla Mettenius is a misapplied name.</discussion><discussion>The long-bristled leaf apex of Selaginella pilifera is unique among New World xerophytic members of subg. Stachygynandrum series Circinatae Spring. The closest relative of S . pilifera is S . gypsophila A. R. Smith &amp; T. Reeves, which is from Nuevo León, Mexico, and differs by having obtuse leaf apices. Further studies are needed to determine whether S . gypsophila represents a well-differentiated species or an environmental variant of S . pilifera .</discussion><habitat>Dry rocky soil, rock crevices, limestone rock, and cliff faces</habitat><conservation> of conservation concern</conservation><elevation> 1500--2500 m</elevation><global_distribution> N. Mex.</global_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> n Mexico.</global_distribution></treatment>
