<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>20</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Selaginella</genus_name><species_name>oregana</species_name><species_authority>D. C. Eaton</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in S. Watson,Bot. California</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 350. 1880</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Oregon spike-moss</common_name><description>Plants  usually epiphytic, less often terrestrial, forming festoonlike mats.  Stems  radially symmetric, long-pendent, not readily fragmenting, irregularly forked, without budlike arrested branches, tips straight; main stem indeterminate, lateral branches determinate, ascending, 1-forked.  Rhizophores  borne on upperside of stems, restricted to base of pendent stems, or borne throughout on terrestrial stems, 0.13--0.2 mm diam.  Leaves  monomorphic, in alternate pseudowhorls of 4 (on main stem) and 3 (on lateral branches and secondary branches), loosely appressed, ascending, green, narrowly triangular-lanceolate to linear-lanceolate, 2--3.35 X 0.4--0.6 mm; abaxial ridges prominent, often flanked by two bands of cells (several rows wide) with whitish papillae (only in  S .  oregana , better seen on dry leaves); base cuneate and strongly decurrent on main stems and lateral branches or rounded and slightly decurrent to adnate on secondary branches, glabrous (seldom pubescent); margins entire or with very short cilia or denticulate, cilia few, transparent, scattered, ascending to slightly spreading, dentiform toward apex, 0.02--0.04 mm; apex slightly keeled, long-attenuate, short-bristled; bristle (hard to distinguish from apex) transparent or greenish transparent to yellowish or brownish (in old leaves), smooth, sometimes breaking off, (0.07--)0.17--0.4 mm.  Strobili  often paired, 1--6 cm; sporophylls lanceolate to narrowly ovate-lanceolate, abaxial ridges prominent, base glabrous, margins short-ciliate to denticulate (at middle), entire toward both base and apex, apex keeled to plane, short-bristled or merely long-attenuate.</description><discussion>Selaginella oregana , one of the most distinct species in the flora, is easily distinguished by its usually long, epiphytic-pendent stems, slightly loose strobili, and curled branches (in dry specimens). In the flora, S . oregana is most closely related to S . underwoodii . It is sometimes confused with S . wallacei (see discussion), and it shares some characteristics with the Mexican species, S . extensa L. Underwood. In S . oregana , very often where a branch fork occurs, one of the branches is arrested (R. M. Tryon 1955). The strobili of S . oregana are among the longest in the flora, and they often show several novel features. Very often the apex of a strobilus undergoes a period of vegetative growth, thus becoming a vegetative shoot, and after an interval the apex reverts to the fertile condition, forming a strobilus again. In other cases, the strobilus forks, giving rise to two new strobili.</discussion><habitat>Pendent on trunks and branches of mossy trees ( Acer macrophyllum  Pursh,  Populus trichocarpa  Torrey &amp; A. Gray ex Hooker, and  Alnus rubra  Bongard) or on deep-shaded and moist rocky banks</habitat><conservation> of conservation concern</conservation><elevation> 0--200 m</elevation><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution></treatment>
