<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Woodwardia</genus_name><species_name>fimbriata</species_name><species_authority>Smith</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Rees,Cycl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>38(76). 1818</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Giant chain fern</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Woodwardia</genus_name><species_name>chamissoi</species_name><species_authority>Brackenridge</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Woodwardia</genus_name><species_name>paradoxa</species_name><species_authority>C. H. Wright</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems  forming a stout caudex covered with petiole bases, suberect; scales light brown, many, lanceolate-attenuate.  Leaves  monomorphic, evergreen, numerous in vaselike cluster, 40-170 cm.  Petiole  straw-colored, sometimes reddish at base; base thickened, with densely set orange scales.  Blade  pale green, elliptic-lanceolate, 25-100 cm, scaly-glandular upon emergence but soon glabrate.  Pinnae  not articulate to rachis, in 8-24 pairs, narrowly deltate to lanceolate, pinnatifid; proximal to middle pinnae 12-42 × 2.5-8 cm.  Veins  anastomosing to form single row of areoles, then free to margin.  Sori  short and broad, mostly curved and confined to costular areoles, deeply sunken into blades.  Indusia  cartilaginous and vaulted; cells thickened, retaining configuration after dehiscence of sporangia. 2 n  = 68.</description><discussion>Woodwardia fimbriata is confined primarily to the California floristic province; it is disjunct and local elsewhere.</discussion><habitat>Redwood forests, mixed conifer forests, and mixed conifer-hardwood forests, always where moisture is present, such as stream banks or springs</habitat><elevation> 0-1000 m</elevation><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico in n Baja California.</global_distribution></treatment>
