<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Kenton L. Chambers</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="1806">cichorieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rydberg" date="1906">PRENANTHELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>33: 160. 1906</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe cichorieae;genus PRENANTHELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Prenanthes and Latin - ella , diminutive, alluding to original assignment of type species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 5–30 cm; taprooted. Stems 1–5+, erect (leafy proximally, often flexuous distally), branched near base bases or distally, glandular-puberulent to glabrescent. Leaves basal or proximally cauline; sessile or petiolate; blades spatulate to oblanceolate, often runcinate, margins irregularly dentate to lobed, teeth often spinulose (faces glabrous). Heads (10–150+, on flexuous, bracteate, intricately-branched axes) in paniculiform arrays. Peduncles not inflated, minutely bracteate. Calyculi of 2–3, minute, deltate, unequal bractlets. Involucres ovoid, cylindric at flowering, 2–3 mm diam. Phyllaries 3–5 in 1 series, linear-lanceolate, equal, herbaceous, margins hyaline, apices acute. Receptacles flat, smooth (with scars), glabrous, epaleate. Florets 3–4; corollas pink or white (slightly surpassing phyllaries at flowering). Cypselae pale brown, columnar, tapering slightly proximally, not beaked, 5-ribbed and grooved, minutely rugulose, glabrous; pappi tardily falling, of 80+, basally connate, white, unequal, stiff, smooth bristles. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States, nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>73.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>The single species of Prenanthella was usually assigned to Lygodesmia in treatments prior to A. S. Tomb’s (1972b) reassessment. Its base chromosome number of x = 7 was taken as evidence of a possible relationship with Malacothrix, Calycoseris, and Anisocoma, also x = 7 (Tomb 1974). Recent molecular phylogenetic studies (J. Lee et al. 2003) place Prenanthella in a clade with Pleiacanthus, Stephanomeria, and Rafinesquia, all with x = 8. This group, together with Munzothamnus, constitutes the subtribe Stephanomeriinae of Lee and B. G. Baldwin (2004).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Tomb, A. S. 1972b. Re-establishment of the genus Prenanthella Rydb. (Compositae: Cichorieae). Brittonia 24: 223–228.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
