<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert L. Carr,Gerald D. Carr</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Bentham &amp; Hooker f." date="1873">madiinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="1841">OSMADENIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Amer. Philos. Soc., n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 391. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe madiinae;genus OSMADENIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek osma , odor, and aden , gland, alluding to strong-scented, glandular herbage]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 5–40 cm (self-incompatible; herbage strongly scented). Stems erect (branched, branchlets relatively many, commonly spreading, threadlike, densely glandular, scabrous to shaggy-hairy). Leaves mostly cauline; alternate; sessile; blades linear, margins entire, faces hispidulous and glandular (proximally ± ciliate or shaggy-hairy). Heads radiate, in loose, cymiform arrays. Peduncular bracts with tack-glands 0 (strigillose, strongly glandular, margins often proximally pectinate, ciliate). Involucres ovoid, 2–4 mm diam. Phyllaries falling, 3–5 in 1 series (each partly enveloping a ray cypsela, apices acute to attenuate). Receptacles flat, glabrous, paleate (paleae persistent, in 1 series between rays and discs, connate, forming cups, distinct apices acute, often apiculate). Ray florets 3–5, pistillate, fertile; corollas wholly or mostly white (laminae 3-lobed, lobes sometimes each with prominent medial red blotch, overall often fading reddish, sinuses ± equaling laminae). Disc florets 3–10, bisexual, fertile; corollas usually wholly white, sometimes lobes each with prominent medial red blotch or reddish overall, tubes shorter than throats, lobes 5, deltate (anthers ± dark purple; styles glabrous proximal to branches). Cypselae (rays) ± obcompressed (± 3-angled, abaxial sides usually broadly 2-faced, angles between those faces usually 90+°, adaxial sides nearly flat), apices beaked, beaks off center, faces rugose, glabrous; or (discs) narrowly clavate, appressed-hairy; pappi (rays) 0, or (discs) of 4–5 lance-attenuate to aristate scales alternating with 4–5 shorter, ± fimbriate scales. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">California, nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>336.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Carr, G. D. 1977. A cytological conspectus of the genus Calycadenia (Asteraceae): An example of contrasting modes of evolution. Amer. J. Bot. 64: 694–703.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
