<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="H. Robinson" date="1978">Clappiinae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>41: 39. 1978</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe Clappiinae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs or shrubs, 5–40 cm (often succulent or fleshy). Leaves mostly cauline; opposite (proximal) or distally or mostly alternate; sessile; blades mostly linear to filiform (terete or subterete), margins entire, faces glabrous. Heads radiate, borne singly. Calyculi 0. Involucres hemispheric or obconic. Phyllaries persistent, 12–16 in 2–4+ series (distinct, obovate or ovate to lanceolate or linear, unequal, striate with resinous nerves in Clappia). Receptacles convex, usually epaleate (paleae rarely scattered, subulate scales; receptacles sometimes with setiform or subulate enations). Ray florets 2–11 or 10–15, pistillate, fertile; corollas yellowish or yellow. Disc florets 20–100+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellowish or yellow, tubes shorter than to longer than funnelform throats, lobes 5, deltate to narrowly lance-ovate; anther thecae pale; stigmatic papillae in 2 lines. Cypselae clavate to columnar (10–12-ribbed, sparsely hairy); pappi persistent, either of 12–25 subulate scales in 1 series, or of ca. 50 bristles or setiform scales in 3–4 series.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States, Mexico.</description>
  <number>187m.16.</number>
  <discussion>Genera 2, species 3 (2 genera, 3 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Traditionally, Clappia has been included in Helenieae and Pseudoclappia in Senecioneae. H. Robinson (1981) suggested that the two genera are related to Varilla (Varillinae).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray florets 10–15; pappi of 12–25 subulate scales in 1 series</description>
      <determination>328. Clappia , p. 251</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ray florets 2–4; pappi of ca. 50 bristles or setiform scales in 3–4 series</description>
      <determination>329. Pseudoclappia , p. 252</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
