<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">heliantheae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Rydberg in N. L. Britton et al." date="1914">chaenactidinae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cassini" date="1817">FLORESTINA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Sci. Soc. Philom. Paris</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1817: 11. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe heliantheae;subtribe chaenactidinae;genus FLORESTINA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[No etymology given; possibly from Latin floreus , of flowers, and tina , a wine vessel; perhaps alluding to sometimes purplish involucres]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals [perennials], 10–60 cm. Stems erect, branched (mostly distally). Leaves cauline; opposite (proximal) or alternate (mostly); mostly petiolate; blades (3- or 5-nerved) simple (proximal and distal) or (mid-cauline) 3- or 5-lobed or -foliolate; blades or leaflets broadly to narrowly oblong to ovate, ultimate margins entire, faces sparsely to moderately scabrous (hairs white, antrorse, 0.3–0.7 mm), usually gland-dotted as well. Heads discoid, in ± corymbiform to paniculiform arrays. Involucres obconic to subhemispheric, 3–6+ mm diam. Phyllaries falling, 4–14 in 1–2 series (obovate to oblanceolate, subequal, thin-herbaceous, margins scarious, sometimes purplish). Receptacles concave to convex, knobby or smooth (sometimes minutely setose or hairy), epaleate. Ray florets 0. Disc florets 10–30+, bisexual, fertile; corollas whitish, sparsely glandular-hairy, tubes longer than funnelform throats, lobes 5, lance-linear (often unequal). Cypselae obpyramidal, 4-angled, faces sometimes ribbed, sparsely hairy (hairs curled); pappi persistent, of 8–12 (distinct) spatulate to lanceolate [suborbiculate], medially thickened, laterally scarious scales in 1 series (some, all, or the alternate aristate). x = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Texas, Mexico, Central America.</description>
  <number>373.</number>
  <discussion>Species 8 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Florestinas are closely related to, perhaps congeneric with, palafoxias.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Turner, B. L. 1963. Taxonomy of Florestina (Helenieae, Compositae). Brittonia 15: 27–46.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
