<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David J. Keil</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">eupatorieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Mociño ex de Candolle in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle" date="1838">CARMINATIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 267. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe eupatorieae;genus CARMINATIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Bassiani Carminati, eighteenth-century Italian author of book on hygiene, therapeutics, and materia medica]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 10–100+ cm. Stems erect (round to 4-angled or -ribbed), unbranched or sparingly branched (from proximal nodes, puberulent and/or villous to pilose, often in lines, sometimes glabrate). Leaves mostly cauline; usually opposite (proximal often withering before flowering, distal sometimes alternate); petiolate; blades (proximal) 3–5-nerved, triangular to broadly ovate (bases obtuse to cordate), margins subentire to dentate, faces glabrous or sparsely villous (at least along veins and on margins), not gland-dotted. Heads discoid, in spiciform or narrow, ± paniculiform arrays (subtended by lanceolate to linear, scalelike bracts). Involucres cylindric, [2–]3–4+ mm diam. Phyllaries persistent (spreading in age), (12–)17–22+ in 3–4+ series, 3-nerved, lance-deltate or lanceolate to linear, unequal (apices acute to acuminate). Receptacles flat, epaleate. Florets 8–12; corollas greenish white to cream-colored, (bases slightly enlarged, tubes and throats not markedly differentiated externally) throats cylindric to filiform, lobes 5, triangular-ovate (very short); styles: bases not enlarged, glabrous, branches ± filiform (appendages linear or weakly clavate). Cypselae ± prismatic (usually 5-angled) or subcylindric, usually 5-ribbed, minutely puberulent; pappi usually readily falling, of 8–13 plumose bristles or setiform scales in 1 series (basally coherent or weakly connate, falling together or in groups). x = 10.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States, Mexico, Central America (Guatemala).</description>
  <number>409.</number>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Turner, B. L. 1988b. Taxonomy of Carminatia (Asteraceae, Eupatorieae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 160: 169–179.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
