<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">coccineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="1940">Rotundifoliae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Cult. Trees ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 363. 1940</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section coccineae;series Rotundifoliae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Eggleston" date="unknown">Rotundifoliae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in B. L. Robinson and M. L. Fernald, Manual ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7, 467. 1908 (as Rotundifolia)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64f.15.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, sometimes trees, (15–)20–60(–70) dm, often multi-stemmed. Stems: trunk bark buff to darker, fibrous, checked into longitudinal plates, freshly exposed bark orange-brown; &lt;branches spreading; twigs ± straight&gt;, new growth &lt;green to reddish&gt;, pubescent or glabrous, 1-year old usually golden green to tan, sometimes deep reddish brown or gray-brown, older graying; thorns on twigs usually numerous, usually ± recurved, sometimes straight, 1-year old usually shiny, dark brown or blackish, older graying, ± stout to ± slender, 2.5–5(–7) cm. Leaves: petiole length 28–60% blade, &lt;winged&gt;, glabrous or pubescent, distally variably sessile-glandular; blade &lt;mid to dark green or blue-green&gt;, matte, usually ± rhombic, sometimes ovate, elliptic-oblong, or suborbiculate, 2–6(–9.5) cm, thin to chartaceous, sometimes subcoriaceous, base cuneate to rounded, truncate, or broadly ovate, lobes 0, or 1–5(or 6) per side, sinuses shallow to deep, lobe apex subacute to obtuse, sometimes acuminate, margins serrate, sometimes crenate, &lt;teeth gland-tipped&gt;, venation craspedodromous, veins (3–)5 or 6(–8) per side, apex acuminate to obtuse, abaxial surface usually glabrous young, sometimes persistently hairy, adaxial usually scabrous, glabrescent, sometimes persistently scabrous or glabrate. Inflorescences (1–)4–15(–20)-flowered, convex panicles; branches densely pubescent, sometimes glabrous; bracteoles caducous, &lt;usually numerous&gt;, linear or narrowly elliptic, usually membranous, sometimes subherbaceous, margins sessile-glandular, sometimes stipitate-glandular &lt;larger bracteoles&gt;. Flowers (8–)12–20 mm diam.; hypanthium &lt;obconic&gt;, densely pubescent, sometimes glabrous; sepals narrowly triangular, 1/2–2/3 petal length, margins entire or slightly glandular-serrate, &lt;apex usually obtuse, sometimes acute, abaxially pubescent or glabrous&gt;; stamens (5–)10 or (18–)20, anthers ivory, sometimes pink; styles 2–4(or 5). Pomes usually bright to deep red or yellowish, sometimes orangish or burgundy, usually ± suborbicular, sometimes ellipsoid or oblong, (7–)8–12(–14) mm diam., glabrous or pubescent; flesh mealy; sepals &lt;sessile except in C. margarettae&gt;, remnants erect-patent to reflexed, &lt;non-accrescent&gt;; pyrenes 2–4(or 5), &lt;sides plane, sometimes shallowly concave in 101. C. ursopedensis, dorsally grooved&gt;.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 8 (8 in the flora): North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 8 (8 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 8 (8 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Rotundifoliae ranges from southern interior British Columbia to Newfoundland, south to Oregon, Colorado, the northern Great Plains, the Midwest, the southern Great Lakes, New England, and mid latitude Appalachians. East of the Rocky Mountains, ser. Rotundifoliae is the most northerly series of Crataegus and only ser. Macracanthae has as great an east-west range. The most wide-ranging species are C. chrysocarpa, ranging from nearly the Pacific to the Atlantic, C. margarettae, midwestern, and C. dodgei, common mainly from the Great Lakes to New England.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of ser. Rotundifoliae are relatively small shrubs that are almost never treelike; their inflorescences are quite copiously glandular-bracteolate, at least when young. Putative hybrids with series other than ser. Macracanthae are rare.</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Rotundifoliae comprises two main groups plus the somewhat atypical Crataegus ursopedensis. The first group comprises the C. chrysocarpa complex, the second, C. margarettae and C. dodgei. Members of the C. chrysocarpa complex have relatively small, more or less ovate to rhombic-ovate, acute-tipped, sharply lobed leaves with glandular petioles and gland-tipped teeth. They also tend to have bracteoles with sessile glands and stouter thorns than members of the second group. The group occurs mostly in northern intermontane, Great Plains, and deciduous forest-conifer transition zone. It is also more xeromorphic, the plants typically being shrubs of dryish areas in the west and often on thin or rocky soils in the east. They usually have pubescent inflorescences and red mature pomes. Members of the second group, around C. margarettae and C. dodgei, are less glandular and often have more or less obtuse-tipped leaves, finer and often fewer thorns, larger, glabrous inflorescences, basal bracteoles that are often prominently stipitate-glandular, and a strong tendency to bear yellowish pomes. This group is more southerly.</discussion>
  <discussion>Members of the chrysocarpoid group of ser. Rotundifoliae can be difficult to distinguish from members of ser. Intricatae. Nearly all members of ser. Intricatae have a somewhat elevated calyx in fruit; their distribution is almost entirely south of Crataegus chrysocarpa in eastern North America, and they often have stipitate-glandular bracteoles. Crataegus submollis (ser. Molles), apart from being larger in all its parts and having more persistent bracteoles, is also sometimes difficult to differentiate from C. chrysocarpa and might key out under ser. Rotundifoliae, as might also C. flabellata (ser. Tenuifoliae). The inter-relationships of the taxa mentioned require deeper investigation; consequently, the key to species includes C. padifolia (ser. Intricatae) and C. submollis (ser. Molles) in the fourth and thirteenth couplets, respectively. The interserial hybrid C. ×sicca keys out in part in the fifth and fifteenth couplets, and C. laurentiana keys out in the eighth couplet.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
