<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">coccineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="2007">Apricae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. Res. Inst. Texas</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 173. 2007</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section coccineae;series Apricae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64f.19.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 20–70(–120) dm, often with main trunk dominant. Stems: trunk bark seldom recorded, black, dark gray, or brownish, ± rimose; &lt;branches spreading rather than pendent; twigs slightly flexuous (± straight in 124. C. frugiferens)&gt;, new growth glabrous or pubescent, 1-year old reddish to dark or very dark brown, rarely tan to chestnut, older gray or gray-brown, sometimes dark purple-brown; thorns on twigs usually few, straight to slightly recurved, 1–2-years old brown, purple-brown, deep chestnut brown to shiny, dark brown, black, or dark gray-brown, slender or ± fine, 1.5–4 cm. Leaves: petiole length 15–50% blade, glabrous or pubescent, usually sessile-glandular (sometimes stipitate-glandular in C. frugiferens); blade &lt;light to mid green&gt;, broadly ovate or rhombic-elliptic to obtrullate or obovate or ± orbiculate, 1.5–5 cm, thin to coriaceous, base ± cuneate, lobes 0 or 1–3 per side, sinuses shallow (sometimes apiculi) or obscure, more rarely moderately deep, lobe apex obtuse to acute, margins finely glandular-crenate to glandular-serrate, venation craspedodromous, veins 3–5 (5–7 in C. frugiferens) per side, apex acute to obtuse, abaxial surface glabrous, rarely pilose young, veins sparsely hairy, adaxial usually hairy young, glabrescent, sometimes glabrous. Inflorescences (1 or)2–6(or 7)-flowered, panicles, sometimes highly reduced, larger convex; branches glabrous or ± pubescent; bracteoles caducous (persistent in C. ignava), linear to narrowly oblong, &lt;small&gt;, membranous (to herbaceous in C. ignava), margins sessile-glandular, sometimes stipitate-glandular. Flowers 13–25 mm diam.; hypanthium glabrous or ± pubescent; sepals narrowly triangular, much shorter than petals, margins glandular-serrate; stamens 10 or 20 (12–15), anthers pink to purple, sometimes ivory or cream; styles (2 or)3–5. Pomes orange-red to red, sometimes green-mottled, suborbicular to orbicular, sometimes pyriform or broadly ellipsoid, 8–15(–18) mm diam., glabrous or sparsely hairy; flesh ± mealy; sepals &lt;sessile&gt;, usually reflexed, sometimes recurved or spreading, &lt;non-accrescent&gt;; pyrenes (2 or)3–5.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 12 (12 in the flora): se United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 12 (12 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>se United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 12 (12 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Apricae is essentially southern Appalachian and adjacent piedmont in distribution, with some extension into the coastal plain in northern Florida and South Carolina.</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Apricae is one of the two series to emerge from the ashes of ser. Flavae (Loudon) Rehder and results from the loss of the latter’s type species to ser. Intricatae. The species included here belong to groups Euflavae (minus C. flava), Ignavae, Segnes, Sororiae, and Visendae of Beadle. Series Apricae differs from the other Flavae-descendent series, Lacrimatae, in fruiting later (thus not a 'summer haw'), by lacking a conspicuously weeping habit, in the bracteoles generally being stipitate-glandular (compared to sessile-glandular), and in many taxa having anthocyanic anthers (unknown in ser. Lacrimatae except in sporadic individuals).</discussion>
  <discussion>In spite of the generally unambiguous nature of ser. Apricae, many species are neither particularly common nor well-marked, which makes the taxonomy difficult. It is possible that many of the taxa in this series arose by hybridization, perhaps with a ser. Lacrimatae parent when they would have flexuous twigs. Crataegus ignava and C. frugiferens are the most distinct species. Interesting, yet rare, forms include some not seen recently such as unnamed members of a rich Crataegus flora collected by Curtiss from the Augusta, Georgia, sandhills and C. calva Beadle from Alabama. Little is known about breeding systems and chromosome numbers, there being only one triploid count (N. Talent and T. A. Dickinson 2005), that from a cultivated specimen of uncertain identity.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Phipps, J. B. and K. A. Dvorsky. 2007. Review of Crataegus series Apricae, ser. nov., and C. flava (Rosaceae). J. Bot. Res. Inst. Texas 1: 171–202.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
