<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Crataegus ×atrorubens Ashe" date="unknown">xatrorubens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>16: 78. 1900</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>as species E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;species xatrorubens</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>154.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 40–60 dm. Stems: twigs: new growth not recorded, 1-year old bright red-brown, older grayish; thorns on twigs not recorded. Leaves: petiole slender, length 30–50% blade, adaxial sulcus pubescent; blade ovate, (3–)4–7 cm, base rounded to very broadly cuneate, lobes 3 or 4 per side, sinuses very shallow to ± deep, max LII 5–20%, lobe apex acute, margins serrulate, venation camptodromous, veins 4 or 5(or 6) per side, apex acute, abaxial surface with axillary hair tufts extending ± on basal part of leaf, adaxial sparsely appressed-hairy young, glabrescent. Inflorescences 6–14-flowered; branches sparsely pubescent; bracteoles usually persistent, linear-spatulate, margins glandular, sometimes caducous, linear, membranous, margins eglandular. Flowers 15–18 mm diam.; hypanthium densely canescent; sepals narrow, margins glandular-serrate; stamens 20, anther color not recorded; styles 4 or 5. Pomes dark red, orbicular, 9–11 mm diam., glabrous; sepals erose or ± reflexed; pyrenes 4 or 5, dorsally grooved, sides plane.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Apr; fruiting Sep–Oct.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Riverine flats;</description>
  <description type="elevation">200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mo.</description>
  <discussion>Crataegus ×atrorubens is probably a hybrid of C. viridis × C. mollis, originating near St. Louis. The C. viridis parentage is apparent in the axillary tufts of hairs on the abaxial leaf surfaces and in the occasional presence of eglandular bracteoles; the C. mollis parentage is apparent in leaf size and shape. This handsome tree is much favored by arboreta; a quite different C. crus-galli hybrid is often misidentified as it.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
