<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">rosoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="unknown">roseae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">rosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">rosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Rosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily rosoideae;tribe roseae;genus rosa;subgenus rosa;section Rosa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Rosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cinnamomeae</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7b.7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or subshrubs, forming dense, clumped thickets, colonies, or hedge clusters, miniatures forming small, low-clustered, or open habits; usually rhizomatous. Stems erect, flexuous, spreading, ascending, sprawling, or procumbent, 1–50 dm; distal &lt;and fertile&gt; branches glabrous, rarely puberulent to tomentose, eglandular; prickles infrastipular, single or paired (rarely to 3 in R. californica, to 4 in R. gymnocarpa), erect, curved, hooked, declined, introrse, appressed, thin, terete, deltate, subulate, stout, sparse, internodal similar, smaller, sometimes mixed with aciculi, rarely absent. Leaves deciduous, (2–)4–11(–17) cm, leathery to membranous; stipules persistent, adnate to petiole, &lt;auricles usually flared or erect&gt;, margins entire or serrate, sometimes serrulate, undulate, or sinuate, usually glandular; leaflets (3–)5–9(–11), terminal: petiolule 1–15(–20) mm, blade elliptic, lanceolate, obovate, or ovate, sometimes cordate, ovoid, oblong, or orbiculate, (4–)10–40(–63) × (3–)5–40 mm, &lt;rugose in R. rugosa)&gt;, abaxial surfaces &lt;sometimes glaucous&gt;, glabrous or pubescent, eglandular, sessile-, or stipitate-glandular, adaxial dull or lustrous, &lt;glabrous, rarely pubescent, eglandular&gt;. Inflorescences corymbs, panicles, sometimes solitary, 1–30(–50)-flowered. Pedicels erect or recurved, sometimes curved or reflexed as hips mature, slender or stout, 2–20(–35) mm, glabrous or pubescent, eglandular or usually stipitate-, rarely sessile- or setose-glandular; bracts persistent, 1–3, margins entire or serrate, sometimes undulate. Flowers 1–9 cm diam.; hypanthium globose to depressed-globose, ovoid, or ovoid-urceolate, sometimes cupulate, oblong, or hemispheric, glabrous or sparsely hairy, eglandular, stipitate-, or setose-glandular; sepals persistent or deciduous, erect, spreading, or reflexed, rarely ascending, lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, 5–30(–40) × 1.5–6 mm, margins entire or pinnatifid, abaxial surfaces glabrous, rarely pubescent, sessile-, stipitate-, or setose-glandular, sometimes eglandular; petals single or double, pink to rose or purplish pink, rarely white or crimson; carpels (3–)20–40(–65), styles free &lt;exsert (0.5–)1–2.5(–4) mm&gt;, pilose, stylar orifice 1–3 mm diam., hypanthial disc flat, 2–5(–10) mm diam. Hips scarlet or red to orange-red, rarely purplish, brownish, or crimson or blue-purple, globose to depressed-globose, ovoid, obovoid, or ellipsoid, rarely pyriform, urceolate, elongate, or oblong, 6–18(–24) × 5–15(–25) mm, glabrous, sometime setose, eglandular or stipitate-, rarely setose-, glandular; sepals persistent or deciduous, erect, reflexed, or spreading. Achenes basal or basiparietal.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced in Pacific Islands (New Zealand)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (19 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Molecular phylogenetic and multivariate analyses of Rosa (S. Joly et al. 2006; Joly and A. Bruneau 2006, 2007; Bruneau et al. 2007) determined that certain eastern diploid species form a clade distinct from more western diploids; that R. arkansana is derived from the R. blanda–R. woodsii group; that R. carolina is likely of hybrid origin from one of the latter groups and R. palustris; that R. virginiana is derived either from R. nitida, R. palustris, or a hybrid between the two; and that the three polyploid species, R. arkansana, R. carolina, and R. virginiana, evolved multiple times.</discussion>
  <discussion>Rosa ×dulcissima Lunell (R. blanda × R. woodsii) (W. H. Lewis 1962) occurs in Manitoba, southeastern Saskatchewan, Minnesota, North Dakota, South Dakota, and Wisconsin. In its Manitoba epicenter, B. Ziola and J. R. Dugle (1970) recognized numbers of the hybrid in excess of either parent. However, the validity of the hybrid has been questioned, as has the distinctiveness of R. woodsii from R. blanda (S. Joly and A. Bruneau 2007). The two species and their hybrid are retained here based on morphological and ecogeographic distinctions.</discussion>
  <discussion>Rosa collaris Rydberg (2n = 14, diploid) (D. Zlesak and W. H. Lewis, unpubl.) probably represents the hybrid between R. gymnocarpa and R. woodsii subsp. ultramontana. Plants annotated with this name differ from the former in having more persistent sepals and/or hairy leaflets with eglandular teeth, and from the latter in having solitary flowers, small hips, or other features more characteristic of R. gymnocarpa.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Joly, S. and A. Bruneau. 2007. Delimiting species boundaries in Rosa sect. Cinnamomeae (Rosaceae) in eastern North America. Syst. Bot. 32: 819–836.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
