<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Luc Brouillet</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">rosoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Sweet" date="unknown">Potentilleae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Brit. Fl. Gard.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: sub plate 124. 1825</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily rosoideae;tribe Potentilleae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, rarely annual or biennial, shrubs, or subshrubs; unarmed. Leaves alternate, rarely opposite, pinnately (palmately) compound (simple in Alchemilla, Aphanes, and Chamaerhodos); stipules persistent (absent in Chamaerhodos), adnate to petiole; venation pinnate or palmate. Flowers: perianth and androecium perigynous; epicalyx bractlets present, sometimes absent; hypanthium usually patelliform, cupulate, or campanulate, sometimes turbinate, saucer-shaped, flat-bottomed, or subglobose to ellipsoid or ovoid; torus flat to conic or turbinate, enlarged (absent or reduced in Alchemilla, Aphanes, and Chamaerhodos); carpels 1–260, styles basal or lateral to subterminal, distinct; ovules 1(or 2), basal. Fruits aggregated achenes (achenes in Alchemilla and Aphanes); &lt;torus sometimes fleshy&gt;; styles deciduous or persistent, not elongate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Bermuda</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Atlantic Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Genera 14–22, species ca. 860 (14 genera, 189 species, including 1 hybrid, in the flora area): North America, Mexico, West Indies, Bermuda, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Pacific Islands, Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Genera 14–22, species ca. 860 (14 genera, 189 species, including 1 hybrid, in the flora area)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, West Indies, Bermuda, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Pacific Islands, Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <other_name type="past_name">Potentillae</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 14–22, species ca. 860 (14 genera, 189 species, including 1 hybrid, in the flora area):</discussion>
  <discussion>The base chromosome number for Potentilleae is mostly x = 7 (8 in Alchemilla and Aphanes; 14 in Comarum).</discussion>
  <discussion>Variation in the number of genera recognized in Potentilleae is due to differences in generic delimitation between D. Potter et al. (2007) and the authors of Potentilla and segregates here (see 9. Ivesia and 8. Potentilla for discussion). In the former, Duchesnea, Horkelia, Horkeliella, and Ivesia are included within Potentilla. Likewise, Aphanes is included within Alchemilla by Potter et al. while it is kept distinct here.</discussion>
  <discussion>Potentilla and its segregates and Fragaria are host to Phragmidium rusts, but not the other genera of the tribe.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Keck, D. D. 1938[1939]. Revision of Horkelia and Ivesia. Lloydia 1: 75–142.</reference>
    <reference>Rydberg, P. A. 1898. A Monograph of the North American Potentilleae. New York. [Mem. Dept. Bot. Columbia Coll. 2.] Soják, J. 2008. Notes on Potentilla XXI. A new division of the tribe Potentilleae (Rosaceae) and notes on generic delimitations. Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 127: 349–358.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
