<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Barbara Ertter</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">rosoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Sweet" date="unknown">potentilleae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">potentilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Rydberg) A. Nelson in J. M. Coulter and A. Nelson" date="1909">Multijugae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. M. Coulter and A. Nelson, New Man. Bot. Rocky Mt.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>255. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily rosoideae;tribe potentilleae;genus potentilla;section Multijugae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potentilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="unranked" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">Multijugae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>23: 432. 1896</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potentilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Rydberg) O. Stevens" date="unknown">Candicantes</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8n.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, rosetted to ± matted, not stoloniferous; taproots often fleshy-thickened; vestiture primarily of straight hairs, not differentiated into long and short, crisped hairs often on stems and inflorescence, cottony hairs only in P. breweri, glands usually absent or sparse, rarely common, rarely ± red. Stems usually prostrate to decumbent, sometimes ascending (especially in supporting vegetation), not flagelliform, not rooting at nodes, lateral to persistent basal rosettes, (0.3–)0.5–5(–7) dm, lengths 1–3(–5) times basal leaves. Leaves: basal rarely ± 2-ranked; cauline (0–)1–3(–4); primary leaves pinnate (with distal leaflets distinct or confluent), (1.5–)2–20(–32) cm; petiole: long hairs soft to stiff, sometimes absent, spreading to ± appressed, glands usually absent or sparse; leaflets 7–21(–41), on distal (1/4–)1/3 to whole leaf axis, overlapping or not, oblanceolate to obovate, oblong, cuneate, flabellate, or elliptic, margins flat, distal (1/4–)1/2 to whole length evenly or unevenly incised ± 1/2 to completely to midvein, rarely entire, teeth (0–)1–5(–7) per side, surfaces ± similar, green to whitish, sometimes glaucous, long hairs, if present, soft to stiff, cottony hairs usually absent, sometimes sparse to dense (P. breweri). Inflorescences (1–)2–15(–25)-flowered, usually ± cymose, sometimes racemiform when prostrate, ± compact (P. arizonica) to very open. Pedicels recurved or straight in fruit, (0.5–)1–4(–6) cm, proximal often not much longer than distal. Flowers 5-merous; hypanthium 2–6 mm diam.; petals yellow, narrowly to broadly obcordate, (3.5–)4–10(–12) mm, equal to or longer than sepals, apex usually ± retuse; stamens (15–)20; styles subapical, filiform, often papillate-swollen in proximal 1/5 or less, (1.5–)2–3.5 mm. Achenes smooth to faintly rugose (± rugose in P. basaltica).</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">c Mexico.</description>
  <discussion>Species 11 (10 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Section Multijugae is used here for most North American species with fully pinnate leaves that have similar vestiture abaxially and adaxially, leaflets often so deeply divided and overlapping as to make the leaves nearly cylindric rather than planar, terminal leaflets often irregularly lobed and confluent with distalmost lateral leaflets, and relatively long styles somewhat glandular-papillate at the base. This circumscription includes the Mexican species Potentilla candicans Humboldt &amp; Bonpland ex Nestler, which P. A. Rydberg (1898, 1908d) placed in its own group Candicantes.</discussion>
  <discussion>This provisional circumscription of sect. Multijugae encompasses at least three species clusters. One cluster (species 40–45), largely coinciding with the original concept of group Multijugae Rydberg, tends to have fleshy-thickened taproots, prostrate stems that are usually no more than twice as long as the leaves, very open racemiform inflorescences with recurved pedicels, and carunculate achenes. This species cluster has evidently radiated in seasonally wet meadows in western North America, resulting in several highly localized endemics, two of which (P. multijuga, P. uliginosa) are presumed extinct (B. Ertter 1993; B. C. Johnston and Ertter 2010).</discussion>
  <discussion>The second cluster consists of Potentilla breweri and P. versicolor, montane species with taproots that are not fleshy-thickened, stems usually more than twice as long as leaves, pedicels scarcely recurved in fruit, and no caruncle on the achenes. These differences from the previous species cluster are offset by the intermediacy of P. ovina.</discussion>
  <discussion>Potentilla arizonica differs from both species clusters in its relatively congested and flat-topped inflorescences and anthers that are as long as or longer than the filaments. The species resembles the first species cluster in its fleshy-thickened taproots, but differs in that the stems are more likely to be decumbent to ascending, pedicels remain relatively straight in fruit, and achenes are not carunculate.</discussion>
  <discussion>Since Potentilla drummondii (sect. Graciles), and P. macounii and P. morefieldii (sect. Concinnae) are sometimes identified as members of sect. Multijugae, they are included herein and key out in the third, tenth, and eleventh couplets, respectively.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
