<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Luc Brouillet</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Rosoideae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Botany,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>107. 1832</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily Rosoideae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, shrubs, or subshrubs. Leaves alternate, rarely opposite, pinnately compound, sometimes simple or palmately compound; stipules present, rarely absent. Flowers: torus usually enlarged, sometimes small or absent; carpels 1–260(–450), distinct, free, styles distinct, rarely connate (Roseae); ovules 1(or 2), collateral (Rubeae) or superposed (Fallugia, Filipendula). Fruits achenes or aggregated achenes &lt;sometimes with fleshy, urn-shaped hypanthium or enlarged torus&gt;, sometimes aggregated drupelets; styles persistent or deciduous, not elongate (elongate &lt;but not plumose&gt; in Geum). x = 7(8).</description>
  <description type="habitat">tribes 6 genera 28–35 species ca. 1600 (6 tribes 26 genera 302 species including 1 hybrid in the flora): north america mexico west indies bermuda central america south america eurasia africa atlantic islands indian ocean islands pacific islands australia</description>
  <description type="habitat">genera 28–35</description>
  <description type="habitat">species ca. 1600 (6 tribes</description>
  <description type="habitat">26 genera</description>
  <description type="habitat">302 species</description>
  <description type="habitat">including 1 hybrid</description>
  <description type="habitat">in the flora): North America</description>
  <description type="habitat">Mexico</description>
  <description type="habitat">West Indies</description>
  <description type="habitat">Bermuda</description>
  <description type="habitat">Central America</description>
  <description type="habitat">South America</description>
  <description type="habitat">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="habitat">Africa</description>
  <description type="habitat">Atlantic Islands</description>
  <description type="habitat">Indian Ocean Islands</description>
  <description type="habitat">Pacific Islands</description>
  <description type="habitat">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Tribes 6, genera 28–35, species ca. 1600 (6 tribes, 26 genera, 302 species, including 1 hybrid, in the flora): North America, Mexico, West Indies, Bermuda, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Indian Ocean Islands, Pacific Islands, Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Tribes 6, genera 28–35, species ca. 1600 (6 tribes, 26 genera, 302 species, including 1 hybrid, in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, West Indies, Bermuda, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Indian Ocean Islands, Pacific Islands, Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <other_name type="past_name">Roseae</other_name>
  <discussion>Variation in the number of genera in subfam. Rosoideae is due to differences in generic delimitation between D. Potter et al. (2007) and the authors of some Potentilleae genera. Cyanogenic glycosides and sorbitol are absent in the subfamily.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Eriksson, T. et al. 1998. Phylogenetic analysis of Potentilla using DNA sequences of nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacers (ITS), and implications for the classification of Rosoideae (Rosaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 211: 155–179.</reference>
    <reference>Eriksson, T. et al. 2003. The phylogeny of Rosoideae (Rosaceae) based on sequences of the internal transcribed spacers (ITS) of nuclear ribosomal DNA and the trnL/F region of chloroplast DNA. Int. J. Pl. Sci. 164: 197–211.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
