<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Reidar Elven,Barbara Ertter</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">rosoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Sweet" date="unknown">potentilleae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">potentilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Rydberg) A. Nelson in J. M. Coulter and A. Nelson" date="1909">Rubricaules</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. M. Coulter and A. Nelson, New Man. Bot. Rocky Mt.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>255. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily rosoideae;tribe potentilleae;genus potentilla;section Rubricaules</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potentilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="unranked" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">Rubricaules</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Monogr. N. Amer. Potentilleae,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>30. 1898</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potentilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hookerianae Soják" date="unknown">ser.</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8t.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, tufted to ± matted, not stoloniferous; taproots not fleshy-thickened; vestiture of long, short, crisped, and/or cottony hairs, glands sparse to abundant, sometimes red. Stems decumbent to erect, not flagelliform, not rooting at nodes, lateral to persistent basal rosettes, (0.2–)0.5–3(–4) dm, lengths (1–)1.5–4(–6) times basal leaves. Leaves: basal not in ranks; cauline 0–3; primary leaves usually palmate to subpalmate, sometimes some (rarely all) ternate, 1–10 cm; petiole: long hairs soft to stiff, ± appressed to spreading, glands sparse to abundant, sometimes absent; leaflets 3–5(–7) (usually more than 3 on at least some leaves), usually at tip, sometimes to distal 1/6(–1/4) of leaf axis, usually ± overlapping, oblanceolate to obovate, oblong, or elliptic, margins slightly to strongly revolute, distal 2/3 to whole length evenly incised 1/2–3/4+ to midvein, teeth 2–8 per side, surfaces ± to strongly dissimilar, abaxial usually grayish white to white, sometimes gray, cottony (or cottony-crisped) hairs abundant to dense, adaxial green to gray, not glaucous, long hairs soft to stiff. Inflorescences 1–12(–20)-flowered, ± cymose, congested to open, sometimes solitary flowers. Pedicels ± straight in fruit, 0.2–2(–5) cm, proximal often much longer than distal. Flowers 5-merous; hypanthium 2.5–6 mm diam.; petals pale yellow or yellow, usually ± obcordate, (2–)3–7 mm, equal to or distinctly longer than sepals, apex usually ± retuse; stamens ca. 20; styles subapical, ± columnar to tapered, papillate-swollen in proximal 1/5–1/2, rarely to nearly whole length, 0.7–1.2(–1.5 in P. paucijuga) mm. Achenes smooth to faintly rugose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Eurasia.</description>
  <discussion>Species 35–40 (8 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Section Rubricaules is used here for independently propagating species that have at least some palmate to subpalmate basal leaves and styles less than 1.5 mm that are thickened and glandular-papillate basally. Such species purportedly originated as intersectional hybrids between ternate sect. Niveae and pinnate to subpalmate sect. Pensylvanicae (J. Soják 1986). The North American representatives of the section essentially coincide with Potentilla rubricaulis in the broadest sense. Although some early annotations and treatments by the authors (for example, R. Elven and S. G. Aiken 2007) reflect an inclusive P. rubricaulis, the current treatment recognizes several reasonably distinct species, based on characters and geographic ranges as presented here. These are only the best-defined elements, with further investigation needed to resolve poorly understood variants and transition zones, especially in western Canada. One additional segregated element, P. saximontana, is placed here in sect. Subjugae. Minor elements reported from North America but not otherwise addressed in the current treatment include P. borealis Soják, P. insularis Soják, P. murrayi Jurtzev, P. petrovskyi Soják, and P. psychrophila Soják.</discussion>
  <discussion>The name Potentilla nivea var. pentaphylla Turczaninow (mistakenly attributed to Lehmann) and its replacement name P. quinquefolia Rydberg, although commonly used as a synonym of P. rubricaulis, do not apply to North American plants (B. Ertter et al. 2013). Independent of the name itself, references to P. quinquefolia from Oregon (C. L. Hitchcock and A. Cronquist 1961b) are based on specimens of P. gracilis var. owyheensis; the voucher for P. quinquefolia in Washington has been reidentified as P. argentea.</discussion>
  <discussion>Potentilla nivea var. subquinata Lange [= P. subquinata (Lange) Rydberg, P. nivea subsp. subquinata (Lange) Hultén] is another name often used for members of this group. As discussed under sect. Niveae, however, the lectotype is here interpreted as the casual hybrid of P. arenosa and P. nivea. Plants of otherwise trifoliolate species in sect. Niveae will sometimes produce supernumerary leaflets; such plants might key to sect. Rubricaules and should be evaluated in a population context.</discussion>
  <discussion>Further discussion and synonymy of all these species, and the section in general, are provided elsewhere (B. Ertter et al. 2013).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
