<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">rosoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Sweet" date="unknown">potentilleae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Chamisso &amp; Schlechtendal" date="unknown">horkelia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lindley" date="1837">fusca</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Edwards’s Bot. Reg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>23: plate 1997. 1837</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Dusky , pinewoods , or tawny horkelia EF</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily rosoideae;tribe potentilleae;genus horkelia;species fusca</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potentilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene" date="unknown">douglasii</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>15.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Basal leaves (3–)4–20(–40) × (1–)1.5–4(–7) cm; leaflets narrowly cuneate to obovate to flabellate, 5–30(–35) × 2–20(–30) mm, 1/3 as wide to wider than long, divided into linear or oblanceolate to obovate teeth or lobes, sparsely to ± densely short-villous or hirsute, sometimes glabrate. Cauline leaves 1–5(or 6). Flowers 5–12 mm diam.; epicalyx bractlets 1–3 mm, 1/2 length of to nearly equal to sepals; hypanthium 1–3 × 2–4 mm, 1/2 to nearly as deep as wide; sepals spreading to ± reflexed, narrowly to broadly lanceolate, (1.7–)2–4(–4.5) mm; petals 2–6(–6.5) mm; filaments 0.2–1.5 × (0.2–)0.4–0.6(–1) mm, anthers 0.4–0.6 mm; styles 0.9–1.5 mm. Achenes brown.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <discussion>Varieties 7 (7 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Horkelia fusca represents the primary radiation of the genus beyond the California Floristic Province. Within California, H. fusca occurs in the Sierra Nevada and mountains of northern California, and it is the only representative of the genus extending beyond California and Oregon into Washington, Idaho, Nevada [with the possible exception of H. tridentata (10e. sect. Tridentatae) in Washoe County], and, questionably, Wyoming.</discussion>
  <discussion>As here circumscribed, Horkelia fusca is the most diverse, most widely distributed species in the genus, with significant additional work needed to fully elucidate its variation patterns. The treatment presented here differs from that of D. D. Keck (1938) and B. Ertter (1993d) in using the rank variety instead of subspecies, circumscribing var. capitata more narrowly, and transferring the application of var. pseudocapitata from what is here called var. brownii to the bulk of what had been subsp. capitata (Lindley) D. D. Keck (B. Ertter and J. L. Reveal 2007).</discussion>
  <discussion>There are two types of basal leaves in plants of Horkelia fusca. The ephemeral early-season leaves have leaflets that tend to be broadly cuneate-obovate, shallowly toothed, densely glandular but otherwise sparsely hairy, and deeply veined. The leaf features described below are drawn from the more persistent, mid season leaves that predominate at peak flowering and differ more strongly among varieties.</discussion>
  <discussion>Petals of first-formed flowers are often larger than average; end-of-season petals can be smaller than average.</discussion>
  <discussion>Although Montana is sometimes included in the range of Horkelia fusca, such references are based only on potential occurrence (W. E. Booth and J. C. Wright 1959).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
