<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Günter Staudt†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">rosoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Sweet" date="unknown">potentilleae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">FRAGARIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 494. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Strawberry , fraisier</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 218. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily rosoideae;tribe potentilleae;genus FRAGARIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin fraga , fragrance, and aria , possession, alluding to sweet-smelling strawberry fruit]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>13.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, acaulescent, 0.2–2.8 dm; short-rhizomatous, stoloniferous. Stems 1–10 (crowns), procumbent, &lt;sympodially branched, stolons not leafy, rooting and producing shoots at every 2d node&gt;, glabrate to densely spreading-hairy or appressed-ascending hairy. Leaves deciduous, basal, alternate, ternate; stipules persistent, basally adnate to petiole, lanceolate, margins entire; petiole present; blade shallowly deltate to widely ovate or widely depressed ovate, 1–6 cm, thin to thick, sometimes leathery, leaflets 3, usually ovate to obovate, sometimes rhombic to roundish, margins flat, serrate to crenate, venation pinnate, abaxial surface sericeous (at least along veins), adaxial mostly glabrate. Inflorescences axillary &lt;from leaf rosette&gt;, 1–10-flowered, cymes, glabrate to densely spreading-hairy or appressed-ascending-hairy; bracts usually present; bracteoles present, caducous. Pedicels present. Flowers bisexual or unisexual (plants synoecious, gynodioecious, dioecious, or trioecious), 12–29.8 mm diam.; epicalyx bractlets 5; hypanthium saucer-shaped, 9.5–27.8 mm diam., hairy; sepals 5, spreading, broadly lanceolate; petals 5[–9], usually white, rarely pink, orbiculate to ovate or obovate, &lt;base clawed&gt;; &lt;sterile staminodia in pistillate flowers&gt;; stamens 15 in 3 whorls, shorter than petals, &lt;anther thecae 2&gt;; torus globose to conic; carpels 30–150, glabrous, styles basal; ovule 1. Fruits accessory; aggregated achenes, 30 (or less)–150, &lt;borne on enlarged torus, superficial or embedded in torus flesh&gt;, ovate or ± ovoid, 1–2 mm, glabrous; &lt;torus usually red, wine red, or carmine, rarely white, globose or subglobose to oblong, conic, or oblate, 9–24(–37) mm, fleshy, apex sometimes pointed&gt;; hypanthium persistent; sepals persistent, spreading, reflexed, or clasping tori; styles deciduous. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, South America, Eurasia, Pacific Islands (Hawaii); introduced nearly worldwide.</description>
  <discussion>Species 24 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The marginal teeth on terminal leaflets vary in size and number depending on length of the terminal leaflet in the species of Fragaria. The following ratios are used in the keys and descriptions: relative size of teeth (length in mm of terminal leaflet to number of teeth per side) and relative number of teeth (number of teeth per side to length in mm of terminal leaflet). The length to width ratio of leaflets is also given.</discussion>
  <discussion>Fragaria belongs to subtribe Fragariinae (D. Potter et al. 2007), which is generally characterized by stamens with a single horseshoe-shaped theca (T. Eriksson et al. 2003), and includes, in the flora area, Alchemilla, Aphanes, Chamaerhodos, Comarum, Dasiphora, Drymocallis, Sibbaldia, and Sibbaldiopsis.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Staudt, G. 1999. Systematics and geographic distribution of the American strawberry species. Taxonomic studies in the genus Fragaria (Rosaceae: Potentilleae). Univ. Calif. Publ. Bot. 81.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
