<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Fernando &amp; Quinn" date="unknown">picramniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz" date="unknown">PICRAMNIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Prodr.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 27. 1788</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Bitter bush</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family picramniaceae;genus PICRAMNIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek picro , bitter]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, rarely subshrubs, (2–)15–80(–220) dm. Leaves imparipinnate [paripinnate (with 1 of distal pair of leaflets oriented terminally)]; leaflets [1–]5–11[–33], alternate or subopposite, ovate to elliptic, 14–300 × 8–160 mm, base of terminal usually symmetric, of lateral ones usually oblique. Inflorescences terminal or axillary, rarely cauliflorous, [racemes or simple] compound thyrses. Flowers: sepals 5; petals 5; staminate flowers: anthers usually with enlarged connective, thecae parallel; pistils reduced to cylindric or lobed pistillodia or tufts of hairs; pistillate flowers: stamens reduced to staminodia or 0; pistils 2- or 3-carpellate, all carpels potentially fertile. Fruits berries; sepals persistent. Seeds 1–3.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Florida</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 43 (1 in the flora): Florida, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 43 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>Florida, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 43 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Picramnia is a neotropical genus, extending from Florida (Miami-Dade County) and Mexico to subtropical South America (northern Argentina and southern Brazil); members of the genus are found primarily in moist and semideciduous forests.</discussion>
  <discussion>Shrubs or trees, 15–40 dm. Stems: young puberulent. Leaves imparipinnate; petiole ± puberulent; larger leaves 8–14 cm, sparsely puberulent; petiolules 1.5–3 mm, wrinkled, ± puberulent; leaflets 5–11, ovate to narrowly elliptic, larger 6–12.5 × 1.8–5 cm, apex usually acute to acuminate, usually shiny adaxially, secondary and tertiary veins salient on both surfaces, glabrous except along midveins adaxially and at base near petiolule. Thyrses 6–20 cm. Pedicels: staminate 0.5–0.7 mm; pistillate 1–2 mm. Staminate flowers: sepals lanceolate, 1–1.2 mm, puberulent; petals lanceolate to narrowly oblong, 1.5–1.6 mm, glabrous; intrastaminal discs circular; stamens 5, filaments 2.2–2.8 mm, anthers dorsifixed; pistils vestigial. Pistillate flowers: sepals triangular, 1 mm, puberulent; petals narrowly oblong, 1.3–1.6 mm, glabrous; stamens 0; pistils ovoid, 1–1.5 mm, glabrous, stigmas 2, slightly divergent. Berries becoming black, spheric to ellipsoid, 6–9 mm diam., glabrous; pedicels 7–10 mm.</discussion>
  <discussion>Flowering and fruiting year-round. Hammocks, pine woodlands, on limestone; 0–20 m; Fla.; West Indies (Bahamas, Cuba); Central America; n South America (Venezuela).</discussion>
  <discussion>In the flora area, Picramnia pentandra is known from Miami-Dade County.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Picramnia pentandra Swartz, Fl. Ind. Occid. 1: 220. 1797 * Florida bitterbush F</description>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <references>
    <reference>Thomas, W. W. 1988. A conspectus of Mexican and Central American Picramnia (Simaroubaceae). Brittonia 40: 89–105.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
