<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Luc Brouillet</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Botany,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>107. 1832</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily Amygdaloideae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, sometimes subshrubs or herbs. Leaves alternate, sometimes opposite, simple, sometimes pinnately compound; stipules present or absent. Flowers: torus absent or minute; carpels 1–5(–8), distinct or +/- connate (Maleae), free or +/- adnate to hypanthium (many Maleae), styles distinct or +/- connate (some Maleae); ovules (1 or)2(–5+), collateral, clustered, or biseriate. Fruits follicles aggregated or not, capsules, drupes aggregated or not, aggregated drupelets, pomes, or aggregated nutlets, rarely achenes or aggregated achenes; styles persistent or deciduous, not elongate (elongate in Gillenieae). x = 8, 9, 15, 17.</description>
  <description type="habitat">tribes 9 genera 55 species ca. 1300 (9 tribes 38 genera 361 species including 20 hybrids in the flora): north america mexico central america south america europe asia africa atlantic islands (madeira) pacific islands (hawaii) australia</description>
  <description type="habitat">genera 55</description>
  <description type="habitat">species ca. 1300 (9 tribes</description>
  <description type="habitat">38 genera</description>
  <description type="habitat">361 species</description>
  <description type="habitat">including 20 hybrids</description>
  <description type="habitat">in the flora): North America</description>
  <description type="habitat">Mexico</description>
  <description type="habitat">Central America</description>
  <description type="habitat">South America</description>
  <description type="habitat">Europe</description>
  <description type="habitat">Asia</description>
  <description type="habitat">Africa</description>
  <description type="habitat">Atlantic Islands (Madeira)</description>
  <description type="habitat">Pacific Islands (Hawaii)</description>
  <description type="habitat">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Tribes 9, genera 55, species ca. 1300 (9 tribes, 38 genera, 361 species, including 20 hybrids, in the flora): North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands (Madeira), Pacific Islands (Hawaii), Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Tribes 9, genera 55, species ca. 1300 (9 tribes, 38 genera, 361 species, including 20 hybrids, in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands (Madeira), Pacific Islands (Hawaii), Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <other_name type="past_name">Amygdaleae</other_name>
  <discussion>Cyanogenic glycosides are usually present in Amygdaloideae; sorbitol is present.</discussion>
  <discussion>The name Amygdaloideae Arnott (1832) has priority over Spiraeoideae Arnott (1832), used by D. Potter et al. (2007), because Amygdalaceae (1820) is an earlier conserved name.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Campbell, C. S. et al. 1995. Phylogenetic relationships in Maloideae (Rosaceae): Evidence from sequences of the internal transcribed spacers of nuclear ribosomal DNA and its congruence with morphology. Amer. J. Bot. 82: 903–918.</reference>
    <reference>Campbell, C. S., C. W. Greene, and T. A. Dickinson. 1991. Reproductive biology in subfam. Maloideae (Rosaceae). Syst. Bot. 16: 333–349.</reference>
    <reference>Evans, R. C. and C. S. Campbell. 2002. The origin of the apple subfamily (Rosaceae: Maloideae) is clarified by DNA sequence data from duplicated GBSSI genes. Amer. J. Bot. 89: 1478–1484.</reference>
    <reference>Evans, R. C. and T. A. Dickinson. 1999. Floral ontogeny and morphology in subfamily Amygdaloideae T. &amp; G. (Rosaceae). Int. J. Pl. Sci. 160: 955–979.</reference>
    <reference>Evans, R. C. and T. A. Dickinson. 1999b. Floral ontogeny and morphology in subfamily Spiraeoideae Endl. (Rosaceae). Int. J. Pl. Sci. 160: 981–1012.</reference>
    <reference>Iketani, H. and H. Ohashi. 1991. Anatomical structure of fruits and evolution of the tribe Sorbeae in the subfamily Maloideae (Rosaceae). J. Jap. Bot. 66: 319–351.</reference>
    <reference>Lee, S. and J. Wen. 2001. A phylogenetic analysis of Prunus and the Amygdaloideae (Rosaceae) using ITS sequences of nuclear ribosomal DNA. Amer. J. Bot. 88: 150–160.</reference>
    <reference>Phipps, J. B. et al. 1990. A checklist of the subfamily Maloideae (Rosaceae). Canad. J. Bot. 68: 2209–2269.</reference>
    <reference>Phipps, J. B. et al. 1991b. Origins and evolution of subfam. Maloideae (Rosaceae). Syst. Bot. 16: 303–332.</reference>
    <reference>Robertson, K. R. et al. 1991. A synopsis of genera in Maloideae (Rosaceae). Syst. Bot. 16: 376–394.</reference>
    <reference>Robertson, K. R., J. B. Phipps, and J. R. Rohrer. 1992. Summary of leaves in the genera of Maloideae (Rosaceae). Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 79: 81–94.</reference>
    <reference>Rohrer, J. R., K. R. Robertson, and J. B. Phipps. 1991. Variation in structure among fruits of Maloideae (Rosaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 78: 1617–1635.</reference>
    <reference>Rohrer, J. R., K. R. Robertson, and J. B. Phipps. 1994. Floral morphology of Maloideae (Rosaceae) and its systematic relevance. Amer. J. Bot. 81: 574–581.</reference>
    <reference>Sterling, C. 1966. Comparative morphology of the carpel in the Rosaceae. VIII. Spiraeoideae: Holodisceae, Neillieae, Spiraeeae, Ulmarieae. Amer. J. Bot. 53: 521–530.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
