<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Brouillet" date="2008">lyonothamneae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">LYONOTHAMNUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20: 291. 1885 * Catalina or island ironwood [For William Scrugham Lyon, 1851 – 1916</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>botanist, nurseryman, plant collector in California and Philippines, and Greek thamnos , bush or shrub] CE</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe lyonothamneae;genus LYONOTHAMNUS</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>31.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants clonal, 50–100(–150) dm, herbage usually glabrous, glabrate, or tomentulose (glabrescent). Stems 1+; bark brown or gray; short shoots absent. Leaves tardily falling, cauline; stipules absent or lance-linear, margins entire; petiole present; blade simple (sometimes lobed), palmate, or pinnate, simple blades or leaflets elliptic, lance-linear, lanceolate, or oblong, 6–18 cm, leathery, leaflets 3–7, usually pinnately lobed, margins ± revolute, entire, crenulate, or serrate. Inflorescences terminal, 50–800+-flowered, compound corymbs or panicles; bracts present; bracteoles present. Pedicels present. Flowers produced after leaves, (5–)6–8 mm diam.; hypanthium 3–4(–5) mm (including sepals), exterior tomentulose, interior pilose; sepals 5, spreading, ovate to triangular; petals 5, white, obovate to orbiculate; stamens (12–)15+ in 1 series, shorter or longer than petals; carpels tomentulose. Fruits aggregated follicles, 2(–3), ± ovoid to lanceoloid, 3–4 mm (excluding styles), stipitate-glandular, dehiscent adaxially; hypanthium persistent; sepals persistent or tardily falling, ± spreading. Seeds 2–4+, ± ellipsoid to fusiform, firm, ends rounded or truncate, faces smooth or minutely papillate, seed coats tight. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">California (Channel Islands).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: California (Channel Islands).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>California (Channel Islands).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Taxonomically, Lyonothamnus has been moved about within Rosaceae; here it is placed as an isolated taxon within Amygdaloideae. It is known from Miocene fossils from California, Nevada, and Oregon (D. M. Erwin and H. E. Shorn 2000).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Brandegee, T. S. 1890. The plants of Santa Catalina Island. Zoë 1: 107–115.</reference>
    <reference>Bushakra, J. M. et al. 1999. The extent of clonality and genetic diversity in the Santa Cruz Island ironwood, Lyonothamnus floribundus. Molec. Ecol. 8: 471–475.</reference>
    <reference>Erwin, D. M. and H. E. Shorn. 2000. Revision of Lyonothamnus A. Gray (Rosaceae) from Neogene of western North America. Int. J. Pl. Sci. 161: 179–193.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
