<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Joseph R. Rohrer</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle" date="1825">amygdaleae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">PRUNUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 473. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Plum , cherry , prunier , cerisier</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 213. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe amygdaleae;genus PRUNUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek Prunum , plum]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Amygdalus</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Scopoli" date="unknown">Armeniaca</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="unknown">Cerasus</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Duhamel" date="unknown">Lauro-cerasus</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="unknown">Padus</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="unknown">Persica</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>34.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, sometimes forming clonal thickets, 1–400 dm, glabrous or hairy. Stems 1–20+; bark reddish, reddish brown, gray-brown, or dark gray; long and short shoots usually present; thorns present or absent. Leaves deciduous or persistent, cauline; stipules caducous, linear to lanceolate, margins toothed to lobed, usually glandular; petiole present or absent, &lt;usually glandular near blade&gt;; blade elliptic, oblong, suborbiculate, ovate, lanceolate, linear, obovate, oblanceolate, spatulate, fan-shaped, or rhombic, seldom folded along midribs, 0.5–18 cm, membranous to leathery, margins flat, usually entire or toothed, sometimes undulate, &lt;teeth usually glandular, sometimes eglandular&gt;. Inflorescences terminal &lt;on short shoots or from axils of previous year’s leaves&gt;, 1–64(–90)[–100]-flowered, racemes, corymbs, umbellate fascicles, 2-flowered fascicles, or solitary; bracts sometimes present; bracteoles present. Pedicels usually present, sometimes absent. Flowers usually bisexual, sometimes unisexual (then plants usually dioecious, sometimes andropolygamous), blooming before or at leaf emergence, 4–40 mm diam.; hypanthium 1.5–8 mm, exterior glabrous or hairy; sepals 5, erect to reflexed, usually triangular, semicircular, ovate, or oblong, rarely ovate-elliptic, lanceolate, or obovate; petals 5(–50+ in doubled ornamentals), usually white to pink or dark pink, sometimes yellowish, usually suborbiculate to elliptic or obovate, sometimes oblong, rarely ovate, oblanceolate, or rhombic, &lt;base usually clawed&gt;; stamens 10–30, usually shorter than or equal to petals, sometimes longer. Drupes 1, greenish yellow to yellowish or orange to bright or dark red, reddish brown, or dark purple to black, globose to ovoid, ovoid-oblong, ellipsoid, or obovoid, 5–30(–80) mm; hypanthium deciduous, rarely persistent in fruit; sepals falling with hypanthium; &lt;mesocarps usually fleshy, sometimes leathery to dry, rarely splitting along suture to reveal stone; endocarps forming globose to ovoid or ellipsoid to fusiform stones, sometimes flattened laterally&gt;. Seed 1. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Australia; most abundant in north-temperate regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species 200+ (44 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Prunus is important economically; it includes almonds, apricots, cherries, nectarines, peaches, and plums. Most commercial species are of Old World origin; Native Americans made use of Prunus fruits, especially plums, long before the Eurasian species were introduced. North American Prunus was consumed fresh, dried, and prepared with meat to form pemmican. Even though native North American plums have never rivaled those of Eurasia for commercial significance, some species were sources for hundreds of named cultivars selected and developed by settlers, farmers, and horticulturists in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries (U. P. Hedrick 1911). Luther Burbank also made use of native plums in carrying out crosses with P. salicina Lindley that led to most of the commercial plum crop grown in California. Small-scale research into the commercial potential of native plums continues today (W. R. Okie 2001).</discussion>
  <discussion>European and Asian species of Prunus have been introduced into North America for their ornamental beauty and are used in the landscape as specimen and accent trees, foundation shrubs, hedges, and screens. Their fleshy fruits are favorites of birds and other frugivores, which disperse the seeds widely. Some species escape cultivation and their seedlings appear nearby, especially in disturbed soil. Included in this treatment are introduced species that not only escape frequently but also have become naturalized in the flora area, reproducing on their own. The following species are cultivated in North America and have been reported as rarely escaped or persisting; they are excluded here because they do not yet appear to be naturalized in the flora area: P. fruticosa Pallas, P. mume Siebold &amp; Zuccarini, and P. triloba Lindley.</discussion>
  <discussion>The taxonomic history of Prunus is long and complicated, in part due to the economic value of its fruit crops and also the ease with which some species hybridize. Here, Prunus is circumscribed in its broad sense based on the argument that when viewed on a worldwide scale, the morphologic discontinuities among the segregate genera diminish and they overlap with one another (R. McVaugh 1951). Included here are species that other botanists, from Linnaean times to the present (for example, Wu Z. and P. H. Raven 2003, vol. 9), have placed in Amygdalus, Armeniaca, Cerasus, Lauro-cerasus, Padus, and Persica. Systems of subgeneric classification have been proposed by those treating Prunus in the broad sense; as K. R. Robertson (1974) concluded, no consensus was reached on how many subgenera or sections should be recognized, or which species should be placed in which taxa. The most widely followed system has been that of A. J. Rehder (1940), who recognized five subgenera: Amygdalus, Cerasus, Lauro-cerasus, Padus, and Prunophora [= Prunus]. Phylogenetic studies employing DNA sequences from chloroplast and nuclear genes (E. Bortiri et al. 2001, 2002; S. Lee and J. Wen 2001) have shown that the five subgenera accepted by Rehder and his placement of individual species within them are not supported. So far, an alternative infrageneric classification of Prunus that accounts for the majority of its species has yet to be proposed. Character reconstruction, or the mapping of morphological characters onto phylogenetic trees based in large part on molecular data, shows that there is considerable homoplasy in most of the characters previously used to delimit subgenera, sections, and species (J. Shaw and R. L. Small 2004; Bortiri et al. 2006). Few new morphological characters useful in writing a key to the clades resolved by molecular phylogenetics have emerged. Prunus is presented here without division into subgenera or sections.</discussion>
  <discussion>At the species level, Prunus has been the object of the usual combining and splitting common among taxonomists with different philosophies and opinions. In particular, over-reliance on the indument of various vegetative and floral parts has led to the naming of numerous species and infraspecific taxa. Similarly, too much has been made of fruit color and palatability in naming taxa of Prunus. Fruits of some cherries and plums go through a progression of color changes as they mature. A typical series is green to red to purple to black. Often, an individual tree whose fruits would be nearly black when fully ripe has its fruits removed by birds when they are still red or purple. These same fruits, which may be highly astringent when red or purple, are often more palatable to humans when dark purple to black. In general, a conservative approach toward species circumscription is taken here, one that in many cases reflects current usage. Widespread hybridization among plums has made their taxonomy particularly troublesome. J. Shaw and R. L. Small (2005) have shown that chloroplast DNA data provide resolution for P. subcordata and P. texana, while the rest of the North American plums form three primary clades with little resolution within each clade and no resolution among them. Multiple accessions of most eastern species were scattered on more than one clade. Analysis of sequences from nuclear genes has not done much to resolve relationships among the plums (J. R. Rohrer et al. 2008). Surely, as more molecular and genetic data are analyzed and, more importantly, correlated with morphological data, circumscriptions will be redrawn and the number of North American plum species further reduced.</discussion>
  <discussion>Measurements of leaf size are from leaves on both long and short shoots. The larger values, especially those in parentheses, are found only on long shoots, and exceptionally fast-growing long shoots may have leaves that occasionally exceed the dimensions given. In the majority of Prunus, a true terminal bud is formed at the end of each vegetative shoot. In subgenera Emplectocladus Torrey and Prunus, the apical meristem aborts and leaves a nib of stem tissue soon surpassed distally by an enlarged axillary bud that assumes the end bud position and role in continuing longitudinal growth of the shoot during the next growing season. Such axillary end buds are called false terminal buds, or the twigs are described as lacking terminal buds. For clarity, the descriptions state that twigs have either terminal end buds or axillary end buds. The lengths of racemes were measured from the base of the peduncle to the distal end of the rachis (= central axis of inflorescence). For racemes terminal on leafy shoots, the length was measured from the node of the most distal leaf not subtending a flower. The number of flowers per umbellate fascicle was counted as the number of flowers emerging from one bud, rather than from a node or spur. Reports of more than six flowers in an umbellate fascicle are probably the result of counting flowers from more than one bud. Fruit sizes given in the descriptions are for fresh fruits. As fruits dry, they shrink to little more than the size of the stone.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bortiri, E. et al. 2001. Phylogeny and systematics of Prunus (Rosaceae) as determined by sequence analysis of ITS and the chloroplast trnL-trnF spacer DNA. Syst. Bot. 26: 797–807.</reference>
    <reference>Bortiri, E. et al. 2002. The phylogenetic utility of nucleotide sequences of sorbitol 6-phosphate dehydrogenase in Prunus (Rosaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 89: 1697–1708.</reference>
    <reference>Bortiri, E., B. Vanden Heuvel, and D. Potter. 2006. Phylogenetic analysis of morphology in Prunus reveals extensive homoplasy. Pl. Syst. Evol. 259: 53–71.</reference>
    <reference>Hedrick, U. P. 1911. The Plums of New York. Albany.</reference>
    <reference>Mason, S. C. 1913. The pubescent-fruited species of Prunus of the southwestern states. J. Agric. Res. 1: 147–178.</reference>
    <reference>McVaugh, R. 1951. A revision of the North American black cherries (Prunus serotina Ehrh., and relatives). Brittonia 7: 279–315.</reference>
    <reference>Shaw, J. and R. L. Small. 2005. Chloroplast DNA phylogeny and phylogeography of the North American plums (Prunus subgenus Prunus section Prunocerasus, Rosaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 92: 2011–2030.</reference>
    <reference>Wight, W. F. 1915. Native American species of Prunus. Bull. U.S.D.A. 179: 1–75.</reference>
    <reference>Lee, S. and J. Wen. 2001. A phylogenetic analysis of Prunus and the Amygdaloideae (Rosaceae) using ITS sequences of nuclear ribosomal DNA. Amer. J. Bot. 88: 150–160.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
