<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle" date="1825">amygdaleae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">prunus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1767">pumila</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mant. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 75. 1767</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Sandcherry , cerisier des sables EF</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe amygdaleae;genus prunus;species pumila</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>26.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, sometimes suckering, 1–15(–25) dm, not thorny. Twigs with terminal end buds, glabrous or sparsely to densely puberulent (var. susquehanae). Leaves deciduous; petiole 2–10(–13) mm, glabrous or hairy only when young, sometimes glandular distally or on margins at bases of blades, glands 1–2; blade elliptic, oblanceolate, or obovate, 2.5–8 × 0.8–3 cm, base obtuse, cuneate, or long-attenuate, margins crenulate-serrulate to serrate in distal 1/2–2/3, teeth sharp or blunt, callus-tipped, sometimes glandular, apex short-acuminate to rounded, surfaces glabrous. Inflorescences 2–5-flowered, umbellate fascicles. Pedicels 3–19 mm, glabrous. Flowers blooming before leaf emergence; hypanthium campanulate, 1.7–3 mm, glabrous externally; sepals erect to reflexed, semicircular, 1.3–2.8 mm, margins glandular-toothed, surfaces glabrous; petals white, oblanceolate, oblong, or suborbiculate, 3–9 mm; ovaries glabrous. Drupes dark purple to nearly black, subglobose or broadly ellipsoid, 6–12 mm, glabrous; mesocarps fleshy; stones subglobose, ovoid, or fusiform, not flattened.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora): North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Opinion has varied as to whether Prunus pumila is best treated as one variable species (for example, H. Groh and H. A. Senn 1940; H. A. Gleason 1952; J. R. Rohrer 2000) or as two, three, or four separate species (for example, W. F. Wight 1915; M. L. Fernald 1923b; P. M. Catling et al. 1999). The plants vary in stem posture, twig indument, leaf shape, fruit size and taste, pit size and shape, and ecologic preference. Even though the morphologic characters show almost continuous variation, four varieties are recognized here based largely on differences in ecologic habitat and geographic range.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Catling, P. M., S. M. McKay-Kuja, and G. Mitrow. 1999. Rank and typification in North American dwarf cherries, and a key to the taxa. Taxon 48: 483–488.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
