<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Luc Brouillet</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">Amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. Res. Inst. Texas</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 215. 2010</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily Amygdaloideae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees; unarmed. Leaves alternate, simple; stipules absent or caducous (Oemleria), (rudimentary) free; venation pinnate. Flowers: perianth and androecium perigynous; epicalyx bractlets absent; hypanthium campanulate to turbinate or obturbinate; torus absent or minute; carpels [1–]5, distinct or connate, free, styles terminal, distinct; ovules 1 or 2, apical, collateral. Fruits capsules or aggregated drupes; styles not persistent, not elongate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Tribes 9, genera 55, species ca. 1300 (9 tribes, 38 genera, 361 species, including 20 hybrids, in the flora): North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands (Madeira), Pacific Islands (Hawaii), Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Tribes 9, genera 55, species ca. 1300 (9 tribes, 38 genera, 361 species, including 20 hybrids, in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands (Madeira), Pacific Islands (Hawaii), Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Genera 3, species 8 or 9 (2 genera, 2 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The base chromosome number for Exochordeae is x = 8. Prinsepia Royle is Asian and is not present in North America. The tribal name Osmaronieae Rydberg, which pertains here, is illegitimate.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
