<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>James Henrickson,Bruce D. Parfitt†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Focke in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="1888">kerrieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey" date="1851">COLEOGYNE</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Assoc. Advancem. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 192. 1851</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Blackbrush [Greek koleos , sheath, and gyne , female, alluding to thin staminal tubelike sheath surrounding ovary and style] E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe kerrieae;genus COLEOGYNE</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>40.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, 2–6(–10) dm, herbage strigose, with appressed medifixed hairs. Stems 15–150, stiffly erect; bark dark russet, becoming gray, striate; long shoots divaricately and oppositely branched, short shoots present; unarmed (stiff dead branches resembling thorns). Leaves persistent (drought deciduous), cauline, opposite and clustered on short shoots; stipules persistent on distal leaf-base margins, deltate-lanceolate, margins entire; petiole obscure; blade oblanceolate-spatulate, 0.6–1.2 cm, thickened, leathery, margins thick, rounded (not revolute), entire. Inflorescences terminal &lt;on long- and short-shoot spurs&gt;, flowers solitary; bracts present, &lt;reduced, leaflike&gt;. Pedicels reduced. Flowers 11–14 mm diam.; epicalyx bractlets 0; hypanthium campanulate, 1–2 mm; sepals 4 (rarely 5), weakly spreading, &lt;abaxially yellow&gt;, outer narrowly ovate, inner broadly ovate, &lt;margins thin&gt;; petals usually 0, infrequently 1–4(or 5) on scattered flowers, &lt;caducous&gt;, translucent yellow, spatulate; stamens (16–)20–25(–30), equal to sepals; torus extending into tubelike sheath surrounding ovary and proximal style (interior sericeous, exterior bearing some stamens); carpels 1 (rarely 2), glabrous except at style base, styles lateral, &lt;exserted beyond sheath, sericeous most of length&gt;; ovule 1, &lt;lateral&gt;. Fruits achenes, 1(–2), &lt;brown&gt;, ovoid-reniform, distally narrower, 5.3–5.8 mm, &lt;shiny&gt;, glabrous; hypanthium persistent; sepals persistent, ascending. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States.</description>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Coleogyne is a xeromorphic desert shrub with floral features unusual within Rosaceae: a peculiar sheathlike torus surrounds the carpel and most of the style that bears some of the stamens, four sepals, and petals commonly absent but the inner sepal surface strongly yellow; vegetatively, Coleogyne is further distinguished by its opposite leaves and uniformly oriented medifixed trichomes. The single-ovuled, solitary ovary has a lateral style, suggesting relationship with multi-ovuled ancestors. Molecular data support relationships in the Kerrieae in subfam. Amygdaloideae (D. Potter et al. 2007).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
