<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Focke in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="1888">kerrieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey" date="1851">coleogyne</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey" date="1853">ramosissima</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6(2)[as 5(1)]: 8, plate 4. 1853</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>EF</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe kerrieae;genus coleogyne;species ramosissima</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Stems strigose, medifixed hairs to 0.5 mm; internodes 1–2 cm, short-shoot spurs to 7 mm, 1 mm thick. Leaves: 0.4–1(–1.2) mm, base clasping; stipules acute, free portion 0.2–0.5 mm; blade 3-angled in cross section, 0.6–1.4 mm wide, abaxially 5-ribbed, apex acute, surfaces strigose. Flowers: sepals ovate to broadly ovate or obovate, concave-convex, 5–7 mm, outer pair acuminate, inner cuspidate, abaxially red-green, strigose, adaxially yellow to orange-yellow, glabrous; petals, if present, 5–8 mm; stamens borne between sepals and on proximal 1/2 of torus sheath, filaments yellow, 5–8 mm; torus sheath light yellow, tubular, narrowly obconic, 4–6(–9) mm, thick-membranous, exterior glabrous, interior long-sericeous proximally, hair tips slightly protruding from orifice of sheath; styles 5–6 mm, slender, stigmas 3–5 mm. Achenes red-brown. 2n = 16.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Apr–May; fruiting Jun–Oct.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Arid scrub zones, Great Basin and Mojave deserts, pinyon-juniper, Joshua tree woodlands;</description>
  <description type="elevation">(300–)900–1800(–2400) m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., Calif., Colo., Nev.</description>
  <discussion>In the Great Basin and Mojave deserts, Coleogyne ramosissima is the dominant shrub in areas of shallow soils underlain by a caliche layer (S. A. Lei and L. R. Walker 1997). In deeper soils, grasses and other shrubs prevent dominance by C. ramosissima. The species has a notably long life span; seedling establishment is rare in arid sites but is more likely at higher elevations and in cooler portions of the species's range (R. H. Webb et al. 1987; S. E. Meyer and B. K. Pendleton 2005).</discussion>
  <discussion>In some areas Coleogyne ramosissima provides important cover and winter browse for mule deer and desert bighorn sheep (D. L. Jeffries and J. M. Klopatek 1987). It is used to a much lesser extent by domestic livestock. B. K. Pendleton and R. L. Pendleton (1998) show the species is wind pollinated.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
