<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">staphyleaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">Staphylea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 270. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Bladdernut , staphylier</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 130. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family staphyleaceae;genus Staphylea</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Abridged from Greek Staphylodendron , ancient name for the genus; Greek staphyle , cluster of grapes, alluding to disposal of flowers and fruits]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, rarely trees. Stems 1–10+. Leaves 3(–5)-foliolate [odd-pinnate]; stipules linear, papery; terminal leaflets long-petiolulate, laterals short-petiolulate or sessile; leaflet blades ovate to elliptic or obovate, base oblique, rounded, or cuneate, lateral ± asymmetric, apex ± acuminate to apiculate, glabrous or sparsely villous, densely when young; hairs unicellular. Thyrses 5–15[–25+]-flowered, on 2d-year wood, pedunculate, bracteate. Pedicels basally 2-bracteolate, with swollen point of disarticulation mid length. Flowers appearing before or with leaves, campanulate or cylindro-campanulate; sepals white or pale greenish pink to pale pink, petaloid, equal to or shorter than petals; petals white [pink]; stamens ± exserted, equal to or longer than petals; pistils short-stalked, stigmas (2–)3(–4)-lobed. Capsules brownish, ellipsoid or obovoid, trigonous, papery; carpels becoming distinct distally; sepals persistent; styles ± persistent. Seeds light brown, ± spheric. x = 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 10 (2 in the flora): North America, Mexico, Eurasia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 10 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, Eurasia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 10 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Staphylea species are cultivated as garden ornamentals.</discussion>
  <discussion>The two North American species of Staphylea differ in their floral biology: the flowers of S. trifolia are pinkish green (sepals) and campanulate with barely exserted stamens and styles; those of S. bolanderi are white and more tubular (cylindro-campanulate) with well-exserted stamens and styles. These differences appear to correlate with pollinators available in the eastern deciduous forest and in California, respectively.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
