<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="unknown">douglasia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Purpureofructus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sida</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 184. 1998</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section douglasia;series Purpureofructus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64c.1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, (20–)30–60(–100) dm. Stems: twigs: new growth glabrous or densely pubescent, 1-year old deep reddish brown, brown, or purple-brown, older gray to dark gray, sometimes orange-brown overlaid with gray; bark on younger 2–5 cm thick branches mainly dark gray-brown, conspicuous horizontal lenticels absent; thorns on twigs straight to recurved, 2 years old dark brown, red-brown, or blackish brown, shiny, slender to stout, 2–5(–7) cm. Leaves: petiole 1–3 cm, glabrous or sparsely hairy young, eglandular or glandular, &lt;glands black&gt;; blade ± rhombic to elliptic-oblong or ovate-rhombic, sometimes suborbiculate, 3–8 cm, coriaceous or thin, base cuneate to ± rounded, lobes (0 or)1–4 per side, obscure to evident, sinuses shallow to deep, lobe apex acute or ± subacute to ± rounded, margins serrate except at base, &lt;teeth with gland-dots&gt;, venation craspedodromous, veins (3 or)4–6(or 7) per side, &lt;± impressed in coriaceous-leaved plants&gt;, apex usually acute, sometimes subacute or obtuse, abaxial surface glabrous or glabrate, sometimes subglabrous or glabrescent, &lt;veins hairy or not&gt;, adaxial scabrous-hairy young, sometimes glabrescent. Inflorescences (5–)8–25-flowered; branches usually sparsely villous, sometimes glabrate; bracteoles caducous, linear, membranous, margins glandular, sometimes nearly eglandular. Flowers (10–)12–18(–22) mm diam.; hypanthium glabrous or pubescent; sepals (2.5–)4–7 mm, margins denticulate to finely, sometimes strongly, glandular-serrate; stamens 5 or 10(–20), anthers white to ivory, cream, or pink; styles 2–5. Pomes bright red to purple (late Aug), reddish purple to deep purple, often nearly black (late Sep), ± orbicular to ellipsoid, ellipsoid-urceolate, ± oblong, or ovoid, (7–)8–10(–15) mm diam., sparsely hairy or glabrous; sepals &lt;prominent, usually accrescent (except in C. williamsii)&gt;, erect-patent, sometimes ± reflexed; pyrenes 2–4(or 5), sides plane to deeply pitted.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <other_name type="past_name">Purpureofructi</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 8 (8 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Members of ser. Purpureofructus occur from the Okanagan Valley of British Columbia and Washington east to Montana and southern Saskatchewan. Most species are locally common.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of ser. Purpureofructus share characteristics with those of ser. Douglasianae, but the thorns are usually considerably longer, the partly ripe fruit color is more likely to be red, even bright red, in late August, and the fruiting sepals are usually accrescent. Crataegus williamsii is an exception (see comments there). Several species of ser. Purpureofructus have been shown to have alloploid origin between members of ser. Douglasianae and sect. Coccineae or Macracanthae (M. Zarrei and T. A. Dickinson, pers. comm.). In late summer and fall, the usually abundant fruit of ser. Purpureofructus may turn from bright red to deep purple, and the leaves in some manifest brilliant coloring in bronze, burgundy, and yellow.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
