<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Nuttall in J. Torrey and A. Gray" date="1840">rivularis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Torrey and A. Gray, Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 464. 1840</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Mountain river hawthorn EF</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;species rivularis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>17.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 30–50 dm. Stems: twigs: new growth greenish, sparsely pubescent, early glabrescent, 1–2-years old often red-purple; bark on younger 2–5 cm thick branches dark gray-brown, sometimes copper-colored; thorns on twigs straight or ± recurved, 2-years old black or purple-black, glossy, fine, 1.5–4 cm. Leaves: petiole 1–2.5 cm, &lt;glabrous&gt;; blade elliptic to narrowly elliptic, 3–8 cm, &lt;length 2+ times width&gt;, thin, base cuneate, lobes 0 or small apiculi at ends of some vein tips, margins serrate, teeth numerous, usually acute, fine to coarse, venation semicamptodromous, veins 4 or 5 per side, &lt;larger often branched proximal to ends&gt;, apex acute, abaxial surface glabrous, adaxial appressed-strigose young. Inflorescences 6–12-flowered; branches glandular-punctate; bracteoles early caducous, usually present, margins sessile-glandular. Flowers 14–17 mm diam.; sepals broadly deltate, 6–8 mm, margins entire, apex narrow, glabrous; stamens 10, anthers pink, sometimes ivory; styles 3–5. Pomes deep red (mid Aug), black or blackish purple mature, suborbicular, 10 mm diam.; sepals ± erect to strongly outcurved or ± patent, 2–3 mm; pyrenes 3 or 4, sides eroded.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering mid May–early Jun; fruiting Aug–Sep.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Intermontane streamsides, ditches, flood plains;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1300–2300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., Colo., Idaho, Nev., N.Mex., Utah, Wyo.</description>
  <discussion>Crataegus rivularis is most abundant in intermontane Colorado and Utah and is one of two hawthorns found in Arizona; it is rare in Nevada. There are reports from northwestern Texas (for example, D. S. Correll and M. C. Johnston 1970); they have not been verified. Crataegus rivularis is one of the more common woody species of mesic, valley bottom intermontane habitats. The species flowers early.</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus rivularis is superficially similar to the more or less sympatric, less common, C. saligna; it has larger leaves with fewer veins, larger flowers with ten stamens, and larger pomes. It differs from C. erythropoda little other than in leaf shape and ripe fruit color.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
