<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="unknown">douglasia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="1940">Douglasianae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Cult. Trees ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 368. 1940</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section douglasia;series Douglasianae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64c.3.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 25–100(–140) dm. Stems: twigs: new growth glabrous, sometimes pubescent, 1-year old usually tan to deep mahogany; bark on younger 2–5 cm thick branches mainly dark gray-brown or orange, conspicuous horizontal lenticels absent; thorns on twigs recurved or straight, dark brown, shiny young, usually ± stout, 1–3.5 cm. Leaves: petiole 0.7–1.5(–2.2) cm, glabrous or pubescent, eglandular or glandular; blade broadly elliptic or elliptic to ± obovate, rhombic, oblanceolate, or ovate, 3–5(–8) cm, chartaceous to coriaceous, base usually cuneate, lobes 0 or 2–4 per side, sinuses shallow, lobe apex obtuse to subacute, margins serrate, &lt;teeth apices glandular&gt;, venation craspedodromous to semicamptodromous (in some forms with lobes absent), veins (3 or)4 or 5 per side, apex usually acute, sometimes obtuse, abaxial surface usually glabrous except on veins, sometimes sparsely pubescent, adaxial usually appressed-pubescent. Inflorescences (7–)12–20(–25)-flowered; branches glabrous or pubescent; bracteoles caducous, linear, &lt;small&gt;, membranous, margins stipitate- or sessile-glandular. Flowers (10–)12–15(–20) mm diam.; hypanthium pubescent or glabrous; sepals 3–4(–5) mm, margins subentire, finely glandular distally; stamens 10(–20), anthers pink, sometimes puce; styles 3–5. Pomes black or dark purple mature, ellipsoid to suborbicular, 6–10(–12) mm diam., glabrous or sparsely pilose; sepals reflexed or patent-recurved; pyrenes 3–5, sides plane to pitted.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w, c North America.</description>
  <discussion>Species 5 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Douglasianae comprises mainly western, widespread, black-fruited hawthorns, one of which, Crataegus douglasii, extends disjunctly to central Ontario. Its species are notable for their usually laterally pitted pyrenes, relatively short thorns, short and often blunt fruiting sepals, and dark purple to black fruits at full maturity.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
