<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">macracanthae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="1940">Macracanthae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Cult. Trees ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 368. 1940</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section macracanthae;series Macracanthae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="unknown">Macracanthae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Arbor. Frutic. Brit.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 819. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64e.1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 20–70(–80) dm. Stems: 1–2-year old twigs usually very dark; thorns on twigs ± stout. Leaves: petiole glandular or eglandular; blade usually rhombic to rhombic-elliptic or broadly elliptic to ovate, lobes 0 or 3–5(–8) per side, lobe apex acute to obtuse, venation craspedodromous, veins (3–)6–8 per side, adaxial surface scabrous-pubescent young, glabrescent. Inflorescences (5–)12–30-flowered; bracteoles caducous, membranous, margins sessile- or stipitate-glandular. Flowers (12–)13–19(–22) mm diam.; sepal margins glandular-denticulate to glandular-laciniate, rarely nearly entire; stamens 7–10 or 20; styles 2 or 3(–5). Pomes orange to red, broadly ellipsoid to suborbicular, glabrous or hairy; pyrenes 2 or 3(–5), sides eroded.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <discussion>Species 5 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Three common core species comprise ser. Macracanthae: the similar Crataegus macracantha and C. succulenta and the somewhat dissimilar C. calpodendron. These are notable for their mid late to very late anthesis compared to sympatric hawthorns, stout thorns, and eglandular petioles. Crataegus sheridana and C. rubribracteolata are placed here for convenience, may not be closely related, and perhaps would better sit with ser. Anomalae. Series Macracanthae is one of only two series of red-fruited hawthorns in North America that has eroded pyrenes.</discussion>
  <discussion>Members of ser. Macracanthae form putative hybrids with members of ser. Crus-galli (Crataegus persimilis), ser. Parvifoliae (C. ×vailiae), ser. Pruinosae (C. chadsfordiana Sargent), ser. Punctatae (C. florifera), and ser. Rotundifoliae (C. laurentiana), at least. Some are treated here as interserial hybrid species numbers 154–169; C. laurentiana, C. persimilis, and C. ×vailiae key out in the eighth, first, and second couplets, respectively.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
