<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">Coccineae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Arbor. Frutic. Brit.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 816. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section Coccineae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64f.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, (5–)30–110(–150) dm. Stems: trunks 1–several, ± erect to oblique, bark usually flattened-scaly, sometimes corrugated or thin-exfoliating; compound thorns on trunks present or absent; thorns on twigs determinate, straight to recurved, slender to stout. Leaves: blade broadly lanceolate, elliptic, spatulate, obovate, obtrullate, rhombic-ovate, broadly ovate to suborbiculate, 1–8(–12) cm, &lt;length 1.6–2 times width&gt;, coriaceous to thin, lobes 0 or 1–4 or 5(–9), sinuses usually shallow, sometimes deep, veins 1–8(–10) per side, absent to sinuses, &lt;matte&gt;. Inflorescences: branches glabrous or pubescent; symmetric bracteoles present, basal stipuliform, falcate bracteoles absent. Flowers: post-mature petals pale paper brown; stamens (5–)10 or 20(–47), rarely ca. 15, anthers pink to purple or white to cream. Pomes usually red, sometimes yellow, orange, or pink mauve, sometimes remaining green until late, or green-blotched, &lt;sometimes ± conspicuously pruinose&gt;; pyrene sides plane (to shallowly concave in C. ursopedensis).</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico; introduced in Europe.</description>
  <discussion>Species 128 (119 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Section Coccineae includes 20 series and constitutes the main North American hawthorn diversification which comprises a single clade when sect. Macracanthae is included (E. Y. Y. Lo et al. 2009). Variation in habit, leaf shape, glandularity, and other characters, permits recognition of more or less distinct series; the delimitation of some series may warrant further attention. Most groups with leaf lobes absent, for example, ser. Aestivales, Crus-galli, Punctatae, and Madrenses, are found here, as are series that tolerate particularly extreme conditions for Crataegus, for example, ser. Aestivales (southeastern wetlands) and ser. Lacrimatae (southeastern xeromorphs).</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Anomalae and ser. Macracanthae are often included in sect. Coccineae; here they are placed in sect. Macracanthae because their pyrenes are pitted.</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Microcarpae (sect. Crataegus) is included at couplet 44 below to handle common forms that key out there with little lobing and, thus, no veins to sinuses. The interserial hybrids Crataegus persimilis and C. ×sicca key out at couplets 16 and 20, respectively; C. turnerorum keys out in part at couplets 18 and 31.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Phipps, J. B. et al. 2006b. Crataegus series Bracteatae and Triflorae (Rosaceae). Sida 22: 1009–1025.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
