<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">viridis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 476. 1753</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Green hawthorn EF</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;species viridis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>32.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 80–150 dm. Stems: mature trunk bark checked dark gray or black, rough or whitish to light gray, thin-exfoliating; twigs: new growth often reddish, glabrous, 1-year old gray to red-brown, older gray, smooth; thorns on twigs few to abundant, 2-years old blackish, 3–4 cm. Leaves: petiole 0.7–2.5 cm, length 33–40% blade, adaxially glabrous or pubescent, eglandular; blade narrowly elliptic to suborbiculate, narrowly rhombic to oblong and ovate, oblanceolate, 2–6(–7) cm, thin (except in vars. glabriuscula and nitens), base cuneate to rounded, lobes 0 or 1–3 per side, margins serrate (teeth 0–2 mm) to obscurely crenate-serrate in distal 1/2 only, venation craspedodromous, sometimes semicamptodromous, veins 3–5(–7) per side, apex ± acute to obtuse, surfaces usually glabrous, except with tufts of hair in abaxial vein axils. Inflorescences (3–)10(–50)-flowered; branches usually glabrous, sometimes densely hairy young; &lt;bracteoles ± eglandular, except somewhat glandular in var. glabriuscula&gt;. Flowers (10–)13–15(–18) mm diam.; hypanthium usually glabrous (hairy in C. viridis var. velutina); sepal margins ± entire; anthers cream or ivory. Pomes orange to deep red, rarely yellow, not pruinose, orbicular, 5–8 mm diam.; sepals recurved. 2n = 34, 51.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States.</description>
  <discussion>Varieties 6 (6 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus viridis ranges from southeastern Texas along the coastal plain and piedmont to central Florida and to tidewater Maryland; inland, it extends to near St. Louis, Missouri, and the Tennessee-Kentucky border. The species favors streamsides and moist, fertile, alluvial woodlands or agricultural derivatives of these.</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus viridis is variable in leaf shape and size. The varieties intergrade somewhat and most are sympatric; they are valuable for recognizing variation. Varieties glabriuscula and velutina are regional.</discussion>
  <discussion>Beyond the recognized varieties, sporadic forms exist with yellow or gold fruit or anthocyanic anthers. Crataegus arborescens Elliott from northern Florida is similar to C. viridis but has rose-purple anthers and slightly hairy inflorescence branches. Other local forms with red or pink anthers, such as C. antimina Sargent, C. enucleata Sargent, and C. pechiana Sargent, are found. Selected forms with bright, rather deep green foliage, and heavy crops of red fruit, for example, cultivar Winter King, are ornamentals.</discussion>
  <discussion>Rare putative interserial hybrids exist with ser. Crus-galli (for example, Crataegus ×permixta E. J. Palmer), ser. Molles (for example, C. ×anamesa Sargent, C. ×poliophylla Sargent, C. ×stenosepala Sargent), and ser. Punctatae (J. B. Phipps 2005).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
