<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">Coccineae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Cult. Trees ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 365. 1940</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section Coccineae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="unknown">Punctatae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Arbor. Frutic. Brit.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 818. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="unknown">Mexicanae</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Mexicanae (Loudon) Rehder" date="unknown">ser.</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64f.3.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, (30–)50–80 dm, main trunk usually dominant. Stems: trunk bark buff to gray-brown, fibrous, checked into longitudinal plates, freshly exposed bark orange-brown; &lt;compound thorns on trunks and larger branches often present&gt;; twigs: new growth pubescent, 1-year old pale gray or grayish brown to tan or reddish brown, older pale gray or gray; thorns on twigs absent or few to numerous, ± straight to slightly recurved, 2-years old gray to dark gray, rarely ± shiny dark brown or black, older gray, usually slender, sometimes stout, 2–6 cm. Leaves: petiole &lt;short&gt;, length 10–25(–50)% blade, pubescent, usually eglandular, sometimes sparsely sessile-glandular; blade broadly elliptic to narrowly obovate, oblanceolate (broader in C. jonesiae), or rhombic-elliptic, 3–6(–8) cm, ± thin, base usually cuneate, lobes 0 or 1–4(–9) per side, sinuses usually shallow, lobe apex usually acute, rarely obtuse, margins serrate to crenate except subentire base, venation craspedodromous, veins (4 or)5–10 per side, apex subacute to obtuse, abaxial surface hairy, veins pubescent or not, adaxial hairy, especially young. Inflorescences 5–25-flowered; branches usually pubescent; bracteoles caducous, linear, membranous or ± herbaceous, margins glandular. Flowers (10–)14–23 mm diam.; hypanthium usually pubescent, sometimes glabrous; sepals narrowly triangular, much shorter than petals, margins entire or glandular-serrate; stamens (5–)10–20, anthers rose, pink-purple, cream, white, or yellow; styles 2–5. Pomes red, yellow, orange, scarlet, or burgundy, usually suborbicular, sometimes oblong or obovoid, (8–)10–16[–25] mm diam., &lt;usually punctate&gt;, glabrous or pubescent; flesh mealy; sepals persistent, reflexed or erect-patent; pyrenes 2–5.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">e North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico.</description>
  <discussion>Species 5 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Punctatae consists of three widespread species (Crataegus collina, C. mexicana Mociño &amp; Sessé ex de Candolle, and C. punctata) plus two local ones (C. spes-aestatum and C. jonesiae), all found in typical hawthorn habitats.</discussion>
  <discussion>The common species are narrow-leaved with leaf lobes absent or obscure, usually 20 stamens, and 3–5 styles and pyrenes. Apparently no meaningful distinction exists between ser. Punctatae and ser. Mexicanae and the two have been united here. Crataegus jonesiae appears intermediate between ser. Punctatae and C. chrysocarpa (ser. Rotundifoliae).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
