<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Chapman" date="1892">collina</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. S.E. U.S. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2 repr. 2, 684. 1892</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Hillside hawthorn E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;species collina</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>40.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, 60–80 dm. Stems: twigs: new growth pubescent, 1–2-years old grayish brown, older gray; thorns on twigs few to numerous, ± straight, 1-year old dark gray, usually ± slender, 2–4 cm. Leaves: petiole 1 cm, length 10–20% blade, &lt;unwinged part often short or absent&gt;, pubescent, eglandular; blade rhombic-obovate or broadly elliptic, sometimes ± narrowly obovate, ± obtrullate, or broadly rhombic-elliptic, 3–5(–7.5) cm, 1.4–2.5 times as long as wide, base tapering into petioles, lobes 0, or 1 or 2(or 3) per side, lobe apex acute to subacute, rarely obtuse, margins serrate in distal 3/4, veins 5–7 per side, apex subacute to obtuse, abaxial surface scabrous-pubescent, especially on veins, adaxial scabrous-pubescent young, glabrescent. Inflorescences 5–10-flowered; branches appressed-pubescent; bracteoles membranous, margins sessile- or short-stipitate-glandular; &lt;flowering usually early, often before full leaf expansion&gt;. Flowers (10–)13–18(–20) mm diam.; hypanthium glabrous or ± sparsely pubescent; sepal margins usually glandular-serrate, abaxially glabrous; stamens (5–)20, anthers white, cream, or rose; styles (3–)5. Pomes orange or ruddy to deep red, orbicular, 8–14 mm diam., &lt;punctate&gt;, usually glabrous; sepals patent-reflexed; pyrenes (3–)5. 2n = 34, 51, 68.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States.</description>
  <discussion>Varieties 5 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus collina is found from Oklahoma and Kansas to the Atlantic. It is absent from middle and higher elevations in the Appalachians, where it is replaced by C. punctata.</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus collina is similar to its almost allopatric counterpart C. punctata, differing in its less tabulate growth habit, leaves on extension shoots not deeply incised, fewer-flowered inflorescences, fewer (5–7 vs. 7–10) and less impressed veins, often wider leaf shape (especially in var. hirtiflora), somewhat darker twig color, sepal margins more or less glandular-serrate, and sometimes different stamen number. Crataegus collina is one of the first hawthorns to flower in its area of distribution, unlike C. punctata, which is late mid season. Crataegus ×disperma (see Interserial Hybrids) is somewhat similar to C. collina; it is allopatric and usually has more lateral leaf veins and fewer pyrenes. Crataegus collina is apparently intolerant of drought and is often leafless by late August in dry summers.</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus collina is variable and has been divided into varieties. The varieties have been worked out in Missouri but not systematically recorded elsewhere; the varietal distributions provided here may be incomplete. Three putative hybrids between C. collina or C. punctata (C. ×collicola, C. ×disperma, and C. ×incaedua) are included in the following key.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
