<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">Coccineae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Monogr. N. Mex. Crataegus,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14. 1997</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section Coccineae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64f.5.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 40–80 dm, main trunk dominant. Stems: trunk bark not recorded; twigs: new growth pubescent at least initially, 1-year old brown, older dull gray; thorns on twigs numerous, straight to slightly recurved, 2-years old dark gray, ± shiny, ± slender, 2.5–5 cm. Leaves: petiole length 10–25% blade, pubescent, glandularity not recorded; blade broadly elliptic or elliptic-rhombic, rarely narrowly oblanceolate, 3–4 cm, subcoriaceous, base cuneate, lobes 0 or sinuses shallow, lobe apex acute, margins serrate except proximally, venation craspedodromous, veins 5 or 6 per side, apex acute to obtuse, abaxial surface glabrate except on veins, adaxial appressed-pilose, usually persisting. Inflorescences 6–15-flowered; branches canescent; bracteoles caducous, linear, membranous, margins stipitate-glandular. Flowers 15–17 mm diam.; hypanthium tomentose especially proximally; sepals narrowly triangular, 2/3 petal length, margins glandular-serrate to glandular-pectinate; stamens 10–20, anthers pink; styles 3–5. Pomes bright red, suborbicular, 8–10(–20) mm diam., pubescent; flesh not recorded; sepals patent-reflexed; pyrenes 3.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico; introduced in Europe.</description>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The two species of ser. Madrenses occur in northeastern Mexico. Crataegus tracyi extends to west-central Texas; C. aurescens J. B. Phipps is endemic to northeastern Mexico. Species of ser. Madrenses resemble those of ser. Crus-galli but have more styles and pyrenes (3–5) than is usual in the latter series, as well as strongly glandular-serrate to glandular-laciniate sepal margins.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 128 (119 in the flora)</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
