<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Sargent" date="1901">brazoria</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>31: 233. 1901</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* Brazos hawthorn CE</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;species brazoria</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>51.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 80–100 dm. Stems: &lt;older trunk bark gray and black, scaly&gt;; twigs: new growth densely white-hairy, 1-year old shiny brown, older pale gray; thorns on twigs absent or few, ± straight, 2-years old black, slender, 4–7 cm. Leaves: petiole length 35–40% blade, densely pubescent young, becoming sparsely to densely pubescent, eglandular; blade elliptic to narrowly ovate, 4–7 cm, thin, base curved-cuneate, lobes 0, or 1 or 2 apicula per side, margins serrate, &lt;teeth 1.5–2.5 mm&gt;, veins 4–6 per side, apex acute, abaxial surface woolly pubescent, glabrescent, adaxial scabrous young, variably glabrescent. Inflorescences 7–12-flowered; branches tomentose; bracteoles caducous, linear, subherbaceous, margins glandular, &lt;parallel veined, abaxially pubescent&gt;. Flowers 15–20 mm diam.; hypanthium tomentose; sepals narrowly triangular, 5–6 mm, margins glandular-laciniate to nearly entire, abaxially densely pubescent; stamens 20, anthers rose; styles 4 or 5. &lt;Infructescences: fruiting pedicels pubescent&gt;. Pomes usually red, sometimes bright yellow to golden or orange, suborbicular, 8–12 mm diam., often bearing residual hairs, particularly toward base or apex; sepals often broken or absent, broadly spreading; pyrenes 4 or 5.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Mar–Apr; fruiting Sep–Oct.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rich alluvial soil, brush;</description>
  <description type="elevation">10–100 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus brazoria is restricted to south-central and southeastern Texas.</discussion>
  <discussion>Crataegus brazoria was originally described as yellow-fruited with narrow leaves that more or less lack lobes. Such forms are very rare. The species is here expanded to include more abundant, red-fruited forms that extend into central Texas and are generally similar to C. texana except in leaf shape. It is plausible, because of sympatry and fruit color, that yellow-fruited C. brazoria represents introgression between its red-fruited form and C. mollis var. viburnifolia.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
