<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">coccineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="1974">Pulcherrimae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Arnold Arbor.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>55: 628. 1974</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section coccineae;series Pulcherrimae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="unranked" authority="Beadle" date="unknown">Pulcherrimae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. K. Small, Fl. S.E. U.S.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>532, 535. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64f.13.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 20–70 dm, usually main trunk dominant. Stems: trunk bark gray, often rough or corrugated; &lt;branches spreading; twigs ± straight&gt;, new growth glabrous, 1-year old reddish brown to blackish brown, often shiny, 2-years old deep gray, sometimes grayish red or gray-brown; thorns on twigs few to numerous, straight to slightly recurved, 2-years old very dark brown to black, ± slender, (1.5–)2–3(–5) cm. Leaves: petiole length 20–50(–55)% blade, glabrous, sparsely to densely sessile-glandular, sometimes stipitate-glandular; blade &lt;mid to dark green&gt;, narrowly elliptic and lanceolate to trullate or deltate, (2.5–)4–7(–8) cm, thin or chartaceous, base ± cuneate to rounded, lobes 0 or (1–)3 or 4(or 5) per side, sinuses usually shallow, lobe apex obtuse to acute, sometimes ± cuspidate, margins crenate to serrate, venation craspedodromous, veins 4–9 per side, apex acuminate to obtuse, surfaces glabrous. Inflorescences (2–)5–10(or 11)-flowered, slightly domed panicles; branches usually glabrous, sometimes sparsely pilose; bracteoles usually caducous, sometimes ± persistent, &lt;usually numerous&gt;, linear to narrowly oblong or very narrowly obovate, membranous to subherbaceous, margins stipitate-glandular. Flowers (13–)14–18(–25) mm diam.; hypanthium glabrous; sepals narrowly triangular or triangular, much shorter than petals, margins ± glandular-serrate; stamens 20, anthers usually pink to purple, sometimes ivory to cream; styles 3–5. Pomes yellow, orange, ruddy, red, red-purple, or green, broadly ellipsoid to suborbicular, 5–13(–14) mm diam., glabrous; flesh ± hard to mealy; sepals &lt;on collar&gt;, usually reflexed, sometimes spreading, or erose, &lt;non-accrescent&gt;; pyrenes 2–5.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 10 (10 in the flora): se United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 10 (10 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>se United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 10 (10 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Series Pulcherrimae has a southern limit along the Gulf Coast of eastern Texas to northern Florida. Its species are fairly common over much of Mississippi and Alabama, the panhandle of Florida, and the western part of Georgia. There are also sporadic records east to South Carolina, one record in southern Tennessee, and one locality for North Carolina in Buncombe County. Anthesis is in April through much of Alabama, Georgia, and Mississippi; in the panhandle of Florida, it may start late March, while in North Carolina or Tennessee, it is in May. Fruit is ripe anywhere from late August to early October.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species of ser. Pulcherrimae are mesophytes of woodland edge or woodlands, and if the latter, usually under oak or oak-mixed canopy but not in denser shade. They are recorded mainly on finer-grained soils.</discussion>
  <discussion>The deeply corrugated bark of several species, found in few other series, glabrous or nearly glabrous plant parts, about 20 stamens, more or less glandular-bracteolate inflorescences, usually reflexed, somewhat elevated sepals in fruit, and sometimes large numbers of lateral veins in the leaf make ser. Pulcherrimae distinctive. Series Intricatae differs in usually possessing ten stamens, having some very hairy species, northern limits much farther north and southern limits somewhat to the north. As in ser. Intricatae, yellowish fruited forms are at least as numerous as red-fruited ones. Because of the relative scarcity of many species, taxonomic limits are sometimes somewhat difficult to be certain about and may be resolved differently in the future. Crataegus pearsonii Ashe, a poorly understood member of ser. Lacrimatae, quite often has been used by Louisiana and Texas authors for species of ser. Pulcherrimae from those states.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Phipps, J. B. and K. A. Dvorsky. 2006b. Review of Crataegus series Pulcherrimae (Rosaceae). Sida 22: 973–1007.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
