<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">rosaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">amygdaloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Maximowicz" date="1879">gillenieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="1838">coccineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="1940">Intricatae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Cult. Trees ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 363. 1940</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rosaceae;subfamily amygdaloideae;tribe gillenieae;genus crataegus;section coccineae;series Intricatae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="unranked" authority="Sargent" date="unknown">Intricatae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Silva</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 32. 1902</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Loudon" date="unknown">Flavae</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Crataegus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Flavae (Loudon) Rehder" date="unknown">ser.</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64f.14.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 10–60(–80) dm, main trunk dominant. Stems: trunk bark gray and corrugated or buff to gray-brown and fibrous, checked into longitudinal plates, freshly exposed bark orange-brown; &lt;branches spreading; twigs ± straight, very rarely slightly flexuous&gt;, new growth usually glabrous, sometimes pubescent to tomentose, 1–2-years old gray to purple, purple-brown, reddish black or brown to very dark gray; thorns on twigs usually frequent, straight to recurved, 2-years old usually dark gray, almost black, sometimes purple- or chestnut-brown, usually slender, (1–)2–4(–6) cm. Leaves: petiole length 20–66% blade, glabrous or pubescent, usually sessile-, sometimes stipitate-, glandular (often conspicuously so); blade &lt;mid to dark green&gt;, ovate, rhombic, elliptic, or broadly elliptic, (1.5–)3–6(–9) cm, thin to chartaceous, base cuneate to rounded, sometimes truncate to subcordate, lobes 0 or 1–4(or 5) per side, sinuses shallow to ± deep, lobe apex usually acute, margins strongly serrate, &lt;often glandular, particularly toward base&gt;, venation craspedodromous, veins 3–5(–7) per side, apex acuminate to obtuse, surfaces glabrous or pubescent. Inflorescences (2 or)3–8-flowered, convex panicles; branches glabrous or hairy; bracteoles (not seen in 97. C. stonei and 98. C. ouachitensis), caducous, &lt;conspicuous&gt;, linear (oblong-linear in 96. C. biltmoreana), membranous (to nearly herbaceous in 90. C. intricata), margins stipitate-glandular, rarely shortly so. Flowers (12–)14–20(–22) mm diam.; hypanthium glabrous or hairy; sepals narrowly triangular (lanceolate in 95. C. nananixonii and 96. C. biltmoreana), much shorter than petals, margins glandular-serrate to glandular-pectinate; stamens (5–)10(–20), anthers ivory, cream, or pink to pale purple; styles 2–5. Pomes dull yellow to orange, ruddy, russet, or scarlet to red, sometimes green, suborbicular, pyriform, obovoid, or oblong, sometimes broadly ellipsoid, (7–)8–12(–15) mm diam., glabrous or hairy; flesh ± hard to mealy; sepals &lt;usually on collar&gt;, patent to reflexed, &lt;non-accrescent&gt;; pyrenes 2–5.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">e United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 12 (12 in the flora): c, e United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 12 (12 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>c, e United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 12 (12 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Members of ser. Intricatae are among the most characteristic hawthorns of the Appalachian foothills and valleys and extend beyond these areas less frequently. They are found in brush, open woodlands, and woodland edge habitats. The series includes the very rare Crataegus flava (the type of ser. Flavae), but ser. Intricatae is chosen for the name of the amalgamated series because, while both names have equal priority, the majority of ser. Flavae as previously understood are excluded from the combined series, and C. flava is now suspected of hybrid origin. Otherwise, ser. Intricatae is treated here in its traditional sense. Series Pulcherrimae, though always with 20 stamens, is similar to the glabrous inflorescence, southern elements of ser. Intricatae. This is seen particularly in the sometimes stipitate-glandular petioles, the usually densely bracteolate inflorescence, the bracteolar margins usually having relatively large, short-stipitate glands, and the fruiting calyx being usually elevated on a collar. Most varieties of C. chrysocarpa (ser. Rotundifoliae) also have similarities to hairy inflorescence members of ser. Intricatae but differ in lacking stipitate-glandular petioles, having less markedly glandular bracteoles, and having barely elevated fruiting calyx.</discussion>
  <discussion>The most widespread members of ser. Intricatae are the glabrate Crataegus intricata and the hairy C. biltmoreana, while extremes of variation are toward the nearly entire-leaved C. padifolia among the glabrous group and the diminutive C. nananixonii among the hairy group.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
