<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="M. Fleischer" date="unknown">theliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Sullivant in A. Gray" date="unknown">THELIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray, Manual ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 660. 1856</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family theliaceae;genus THELIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek thele , nipple, alluding to prominent leaf papillae]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized. Stems 1-pinnate or irregularly branched, branches erect-ascending, simple or irregularly branched; epidermal cells elongate; rhizoids reddish brown, densely branched, smooth. Leaves deltoid-ovate; base decurrent; apex broadly acute to obtuse, abruptly contracted, acumen long, apiculate or piliferous; costa single or sometimes double, 1/2–3/4 leaf length, sometimes spurred or 2-fid; alar cells quadrate or subrectangular; laminal cells rhombic to fusiform, stoutly 1-papillose abaxially, papillae columnar, simple or 3–6-branched. Seta yellowish when young, red when mature, flexuose when dry, smooth. Capsule cylindric to ovoid-cylindric, symmetric to somewhat curved, smooth to weakly wrinkled when dry; exothecial cells at mouth oblate to quadrate, proximal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, enlarged, red, walls thin to thick; stomata on neck; annulus rudimentary, persistent, 2- or 3-seriate, cell walls thin; operculum conic-subulate; exostome teeth united at base on short, smooth membrane, white, linear, external surface smooth basally, finely papillose distally, trabeculae and median line thickened, internal surface lightly papillose, trabeculae weak; endostome rudimentary, white, lightly papillose, basal membrane low or high, segments reduced to stubs or to 1/2 exostome length, cilia 1 or 2, nublike or absent. Spores smooth to lightly papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, ne Mexico, West Indies (Dominican Republic).</description>
  <discussion>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Thelia is remarkable in its glaucous, bluish green color, thick, densely tomentose mats, and tumid to julaceous stems and branches. The stem leaves are distinctively deltoid-ovate with rhombic cells, simple or 3–6-branched columnar papillae, and frequently long-ciliate margins. The sporophyte has a long seta and typically erect, symmetric, cylindric to ovoid-cylindric capsules. The diplolepidous peristome is yellowish white. The endostome segments and cilia are often reduced to nublike projections on a low or high basal membrane.</discussion>
  <discussion>In the field, Thelia could be confused with Myurella (Pterigynandraceae) because both genera have terete-foliate stems and branches that occur in mats or cushions, radiculose stems, and a similar color. Myurella rarely occurs in dense mats, and its leaves have short, double costae, serrate or sinuate-dentate margins, and lower, unbranched papillae.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaf laminal cell papillae simple</description>
      <determination>2. Thelia hirtella</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaf laminal cell papillae usually 3 – 6-branched.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems creeping, densely and regularly 1-pinnate, often densely tomentose, branches simple; leaf acumina usually spreading-piliferous</description>
      <determination>1. Thelia asprella</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems often ascending, sparsely and irregularly branched, lightly tomentose, branches irregularly branched; leaf acumina erect, apiculate</description>
      <determination>3. Thelia lescurii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
