<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="M. Fleischer" date="unknown">theliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Sullivant in A. Gray" date="unknown">thelia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Sullivant in A. Gray" date="1856">hirtella</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray, Manual ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 660. 1856</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family theliaceae;genus thelia;species hirtella</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pterigynandrum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">hirtellum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>83, plate 17, figs. 1 – 6. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Stems creeping, sparsely and irregularly 1-pinnate, lightly tomentose, branches simple; paraphyllia subfoliose; pseudoparaphyllia foliose-ciliate. Stem and branch leaves dimorphic. Stem leaves 1–1.3 mm; margins plane throughout or erect to somewhat incurved basally, plane distally, densely long-ciliate; apex broadly acute, acumen sometimes spreading-piliferous; laminal cells rhombic to fusiform, 14–30 × 3–10 µm, papillae simple. Branch leaves 0.6–0.9 mm; margins dentate-toothed basally, sharply serrate distally; medial and apical laminal cells rhombic, 14–20 × 3–8 µm; juxtacostal basal cells fusiform, smooth, walls sometimes porose. Seta 0.4–1.2 cm. Capsule 1–2 mm; operculum 0.8–1 mm. Calyptra 2–2.5 mm. Spores 12–16 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Tree trunks, rotting stumps, humus, soil, base of trees, rock;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations (0-1300 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.B., N.S., Ont., Que.; Ala., Ark., Conn., Del., Fla., Ga., Ill. Ind., Kans., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Miss., Mo., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Okla., Pa., R.I., S.C., Tenn., Tex., Va., W. Va., Wis.; Mexico (Tamaulipas); West Indies (Dominican Republic).</description>
  <discussion>Thelia hirtella has the broadest distribution of any Thelia species, ranging from southern Nova Scotia south to Florida and west to eastern Oklahoma, eastern Texas, and northeastern Mexico. The deltoid leaves of T. hirtella are decurrent and abruptly contracted distally into long, piliferous (at times spreading) apices. The stem leaf margins are long-ciliate, but those of the branch leaves are dentate-toothed at base and sharply serrate distally. Thelia hirtella has rhombic distal laminal cells with stout, unbranched, columnar papillae on the dorsal side, but the cell walls are smooth to somewhat bulging on the ventral side. The costae in T. hirtella are faint and often spurred or 2-fid.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
