<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">SchlotheimIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Recent., suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 16. 1812</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus SchlotheimIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Ernst Friedrich von Schlotheim, 1764 – 1832, German paleontologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized, in dense, tomentose mats. Stems creeping, branches ascending. Leaves appressed to loosely appressed, erect, often spirally twisted around stem when dry, erect-patent when moist, narrowly lanceolate to oblong-ligulate, sometimes rugose; margins entire or sometimes serrulate at apex; apex gradually acute, acuminate, or apiculate; costa percurrent or short-excurrent; basal laminal cells elongate; distal cells irregularly quadrate to rounded-elliptic or rounded-quadrate, 5–9 µm, &lt;in diagonal rows&gt;, usually smooth; marginal cells not distinct from basal. Sexual condition pseudautoicous; perichaetial leaves larger than stem leaves. Seta 2.5–5 mm. Capsule fully exserted, rarely immersed, elliptic to cylindric, usually smooth or slightly plicate, not constricted below mouth when dry; stomata superficial; peristome double; exostome teeth 16, densely papillose-striate; endostome segments 16, sometimes rudimentary. Calyptra mitrate, long-conic to campanulate, basal lobes 4–6, smooth or papillose distally, naked or hairy, not plicate, usually covering capsule. Spores anisosporous, &lt;unicellular&gt;.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, Africa, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia; pantropical.</description>
  <discussion>Species 100–150 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Schlotheimia is distinguished by the distinctive dark reddish coloration, habit in tree canopies and on tree trunks, and 4–6-lobed, campanulate calyptrae. The branches are stout and usually 2-fid; the basal laminal cells are porose; the seta is smooth; the exostome teeth are erect or recurved, well developed, linear-lanceolate, and often blunt; and the endostome segments are shorter than the exostome and pale. The dwarf male plants are found on the leaves of female plants.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 100-150 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices gradually acute or acuminate; leaves not rugose; calyptrae smooth</description>
      <determination>1. Schlotheimia lancifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices abruptly apiculate; leaves rugose; calyptrae papillose distally</description>
      <determination>2. Schlotheimia rugifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
