<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Greville &amp; Arnott" date="unknown">splachnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="unknown">TETRAPLODON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 211, plates 288 – 290. 1844</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family splachnaceae;genus TETRAPLODON</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[ Greek tetraplo - , fourfold, and odon , tooth, alluding to arrangement of exostome teeth]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>3.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense tufts, often brown proximally, bright green to yellow-green distally. Stems 0.5–3(–8) cm; often matted with rhizoids proximally. Stem leaves slender- to oblong-lanceolate, or obovate and acuminate; margins toothed or entire; apex acute, acuminate, or subulate; costa usually ending in subula; proximal laminal cells elongate, rectangular; distal cells rectangular, hexagonal, or oblong-hexagonal. Sexual condition autoicous or rarely dioicous. Seta 0.2–5 cm, not twisted. Capsule cleistocarpous or not, yellowish or reddish to dark brown or black, cylindric to ovoid or spindle-shaped; hypophysis same color or darker than urn, short to elongate, narrower to barely wider than urn; annulus usually absent; operculum hemispheric to bluntly conic; peristome single; exostome teeth 16, at first ± coherent in 4’s, later in 2’s, usually reflexed when dry, inflexed when moist, of 2 layers of cells. Calyptra conic-mitrate or cucullate, small, not constricted beyond base. Spores 8–12 µm, smooth or slightly papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide; alpine, subalpine, and temperate to subarctic regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species 10 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Species of Tetraplodon are entomophilous and coprophilous although apparently restricted to the dung of carnivores, bones, and owl pellets. The hypophysis is well developed, elongate, and usually wrinkled when dry; the exostome teeth are connate in 4’s when young but in 2’s as they age; and the seta is stout.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves long-lanceolate; margins with large teeth, occasionally entire</description>
      <determination>2. Tetraplodon angustatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ovate or oblong-ovate; margins entire or nearly so.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules cleistocarpous, clear pale yellow to stramineous; hypophysis conspicuously narrower than urn</description>
      <determination>1. Tetraplodon paradoxus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules not cleistocarpous, usually reddish to black, rarely yellow to stramineous; hypophysis usually as wide or wider than urn.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Setae shorter than 1 cm; leaf apices broadly acu te; costae ending before subula</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Setae 1–5 cm; leaf apices subulate or acuminate; costae ending in subula.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices abruptly subulate; capsules red, dark red to black with age</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices acuminate; capsules pale yellow to stramineous</description>
      <determination>5. Tetraplodon pallidus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <references>
    <reference>Steere, W. C. 1977b. Tetraplodon paradoxus and T. pallidus (Musci: Splachnaceae) in northern North America. Brittonia 29: 353–367.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
