<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">aulacomniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">aulacomnium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Schwagrichen" date="unknown">androgynum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond. Suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(1,1,Aulacomnion): 2. 1827</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>EF</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family aulacomniaceae;genus aulacomnium;species androgynum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">androgynum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>178. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 1–2 cm, in erect, basal tufts or cushions, green or brownish green. Stems yellow or brownish green; cross section irregularly pentagonal, cortical cells in 2–4 layers, medulla cell walls thick or thin, central strand cells small; rhizoids between leaves near base of plants. Leaves distant near base of plants, more congested toward apex, not much different when dry or moist, oblong-lanceolate, widest above base, somewhat concave to keeled; base slightly rounded to insertion; margins revolute to mid leaf, weakly serrulate proximally, irregularly serrulate toward apex; apex acute; costa flexuose; laminal cells round or nearly oblong, papillae blunt; basal cells 1-stratose, hyaline. Specialized asexual reproduction by small fusiform propagula in tight globose cluster. Perigonia budlike in series down stem; paraphyses of 7–10 cells. Perichaetia with paraphyses of 9–12 cells. Seta 1–1.5 cm. Capsule suberect or horizontal, 2.5–3 mm; operculum conic, rostrum short, blunt; endostome cilia nodose. Spores 10–20 µm, smooth.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Organic soil, rotting logs, mineral soil over rock;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C., N.B., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que.; Alaska, Calif., Colo., Idaho, Ill., Maine, Mich., Mont., N.H., N.Y., Oreg., S.Dak., Wash., W. Va., Wyo.</description>
  <other_name type="past_name">Aulacomnion</other_name>
  <discussion>The propagula of Aulacomnium androgynum, borne in spheric clusters at the ends of naked branches, are a distinguishing feature. This is the only species of Aulacomnium with small lanceolate leaves that are serrulate mainly beyond mid leaf and shortly rounded at the insertion. The species also lacks a hyalodermis. The distal laminal cells of A. androgynum are round or ± oblong, 1-papillose on abaxial and adaxial walls, with blunt, long papillae and thick walls. The basal laminal cells of the inner perigonial leaves are elongate to rhomboidal, large, and smooth.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
