<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bartramiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Swartz ex F. Weber &amp; D. Mohr in F. Weber" date="unknown">CONOSTOMUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in F. Weber, Naturh. Reise Schweden,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>121. 1804</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bartramiaceae;genus CONOSTOMUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek konos , cone, and stoma , opening, alluding to operculum]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense tufts, glaucous or yellow-green. Stems 0.5–3 cm, erect, simple or 2-fid; pentagonal in cross section, hyalodermis present, epidermis not prorulose; radiculose proximally, rhizoids smooth. Leaves in 5 distinct rows, imbricate, appressed when dry or moist, narrowly lanceolate, 1-stratose; base not sheathing; margins slightly revolute in distal 1/2, serrulate near apex, teeth single; apex acuminate or rarely blunt; costa percurrent to excurrent, sometimes subpercurrent in proximal leaves, abaxial surface mammillose-toothed; basal laminal cells more lax than distal cells; distal cells rectangular to short-rhomboidal, smooth or mammillose at distal ends on both surfaces, walls thick. Specialized asexual reproduction unknown. Sexual condition dioicous [or autoicous]; perigonia cupulate or gemmiform; perichaetial leaves larger than stem leaves. Seta single, elongate, flexuose. Capsule erect to inclined, ovoid, wrinkled and furrowed when dry, mouth not small, not oblique; annulus absent; operculum conic, rostrate; peristome single or rarely absent; exostome teeth reddish orange to dark brown, linear-lanceolate, smooth throughout or finely papillose basally, apically connate. Spores spheric to reniform, coarsely papillose [to smooth].</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands.</description>
  <discussion>Species 7–15 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Frahm, J.-P. et al. 1996b. Revision der Gattung Conostomum (Musci; Bartramiaceae). Trop. Bryol. 12: 97–114.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
