<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bartramiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">PLAGIOPUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Univ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 596, plate 5, fig. 5. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bartramiaceae;genus PLAGIOPUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek plagios , oblique, and pous , foot, alluding to curved seta]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense tufts, dull olive green to brownish. Stems 2–10 cm, erect to ascending, 2-fid; triangular in cross section, hyalodermis present, epidermis not prorulose; radiculose proximally, rhizoids papillose. Leaves in 3 rows, laxly erect or erect-spreading and somewhat curved when dry, erect-spreading when moist, narrowly lanceolate, 1-stratose, often 2-stratose at distal margins; base not sheathing; margins revolute nearly throughout, often serrate distally, teeth paired; apex acuminate; costa percurrent to short-excurrent, abaxial surface serrulate; basal laminal cells longer than distal cells; distal cells subquadrate or short-rectangular, faintly striate, walls thick. Specialized asexual reproduction unknown. Sexual condition synoicous; perigonia absent; perichaetial leaves scarcely distinct. Seta single, elongate, straight or flexuose. Capsule suberect, subglobose, furrowed when dry, mouth small; annulus absent; operculum short-conic or convex; peristome double; exostome teeth reddish brown, lanceolate, smooth or minutely papillose, apically free; endostome yellowish to hyaline, segments broad, cilia short, rudimentary, or absent. Spores ellipsoid, coarsely papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide</description>
  <description type="distribution">except Antarctica.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: nearly worldwide, except Antarctica.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>nearly worldwide, except Antarctica.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Plagiopus is distinguished by its triangular stems, striated laminal cells, and leaves appearing papillose in cross section.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
