<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bartramiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">BARTRAMIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>164. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bartramiaceae;genus BARTRAMIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For John Bartram, 1699 – 1777, Pennsylvania botanist, horticulturist, and explorer]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in lax to dense tufts, dull green to glaucous, sometimes yellowish or yellowish brown distally. Stems 0.5–15 cm, erect, 2-fid, lacking subfloral whorl of branches; rounded in cross section, hyalodermis present, indistinct to distinct, epidermis not prorulose; radiculose proximally, rhizoids papillose. Leaves not in distinct rows or rarely in 5 rows, erect-appressed to spreading or circinate, sometimes flexuose when dry, spreading when moist, narrowly lanceolate to linear, 2- or 3-stratose at margins or throughout; base ± sheathing; margins plane or revolute, entire proximally, serrate to serrulate distally, teeth single or paired; apex acuminate or subulate; costa subpercurrent to excurrent, abaxial surface prominent, rough, or sometimes obscure in distal limb; basal laminal cells elongate to rectangular or linear; distal cells subquadrate to oblong-linear, prorulose on both surfaces, walls firm. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition dioicous, autoicous, or synoicous; perigonia gemmiform; perichaetial leaves little differentiated from stem leaves (differentiated in B. ithyphylla). Seta single (often 2 or 3 per perichaetium in B. halleriana), elongate or rarely short, straight or sometimes curved. Capsule inclined or sometimes erect, subglobose, globose, ovoid, or pyriform, furrowed when dry, mouth oblique; annulus not distinct; operculum convex to conic; peristome double, single, or absent; exostome teeth reddish brown, lanceolate, smooth or papillose, apically free; endostome pale yellow, sometimes absent, segments keeled, cilia rudimentary or absent. Spores reniform to subspheric, coarsely to warty papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide</description>
  <description type="distribution">except Antarctica</description>
  <description type="distribution">especially diverse in montane tropics.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 90 (7 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Bartramia is generally recognized by its linear-lanceolate leaves and sheathing base with a distal lamina that is 2- or 3-stratose at the margins or throughout. The plants may be soft or rigid; the stem cortical cells have somewhat firm walls. The leaves are not plicate; the basal laminal cells are pale and smooth with walls thin or rarely thick toward the costa. The perichaetial leaves are usually less prorulose with more lax areolation; the exostome teeth are sometimes cleft distally and lack intermediate abaxial thickenings. Bartramia stricta lacks a sheathing leaf base but otherwise is in accord with the generic concept.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 4–7 mm; bases laxly or scarcely sheathing; stems to 10(–15) cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Setae short, equal to or slightly longer than capsule</description>
      <determination>1. Bartramia halleriana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Setae many times longer than capsule</description>
      <determination>2. Bartramia pomiformis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually 1.5–5 mm; bases sheathing (except B . stricta ); stems to 5 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases not sheathing, shoulders absent</description>
      <determination>3. Bartramia stricta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases sheathing, shoulders well developed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costae obscure in distal limb; distal laminal cells 25–45 µm, prorulae low</description>
      <determination>4. Bartramia ithyphylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costae prominent in distal limb; distal laminal cells 8–25 µm, prorulae high.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf shoulders delicate, often eroded; apices fragile, usually broken</description>
      <determination>5. Bartramia potosica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf shoulders firm, not eroded; apices usually intact.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal laminal cell walls thick toward costa, thin toward margins; leaf margins strongly revolute</description>
      <determination>6. Bartramia brevifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal laminal cell walls thin throughout; leaf margins plane distally</description>
      <determination>7. Bartramia subulata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
