<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bartramiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">bartramia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">halleriana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>164. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bartramiaceae;genus bartramia;species halleriana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in lax to dense tufts, greenish to yellowish brown. Stems 15 cm. Leaves crisped when dry, erect-spreading or sometimes secund when moist, narrowly lanceolate to linear, 4–7 mm; base laxly sheathing, shoulders well developed, firm; margins revolute from shoulders to high in acumen, denticulate in shoulders, spinose-dentate distally, teeth paired; apex long-subulate; costa excurrent, prominent, distal abaxial surface rough; basal laminal cell walls thin; medial and distal cells 5–12 × 4(–10) µm, prorulae high. Sexual condition autoicous or synoicous. Seta 0.2(–0.8) cm, curved. Capsule inclined, subglobose to pyriform, asymmetric, 1.5(–2.5) mm; operculum conic convex; peristome double; exostome teeth 500–550 µm, granulose proximally, papillose distally; endostome basal membrane high, segments slightly shorter than teeth, striate papillose, cilia rudimentary. Spores 15–24 µm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Spores 15-24 µm, mature Jun-Sep.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Crevices of shaded cliffs, rock outcrops in humid forests;</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate elevations (200-500 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C.; s South America; Europe; Asia; Pacific Islands (Hawaii, New Zealand); Australia (Tasmania).</description>
  <discussion>Bartramia halleriana is quite similar vegetatively to robust forms of B. pomiformis. However, the short, curved seta as long as or slightly longer than the capsule is distinctive.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
