<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bryaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="N. Pedersen" date="unknown">imbribryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hudson ex Withering) N. Pedersen" date="2005">alpinum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>108: 449. 2005</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bryaceae;genus imbribryum;species alpinum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hudson ex Withering" date="unknown">alpinum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Arr. Brit. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4, 3: 824. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized, dark red to red-green, rarely entirely green, sometimes black with age. Stems 0.5–2(–3) cm, somewhat julaceous, with metallic sheen, older stem sometimes densely radiculose. Leaves rigid, strongly imbricate when dry, red to red-green, sometimes green, broadly lanceolate to narrowly ovate or lingulate, occasionally narrowly triangular, weakly concave, 1–3 mm; base not decurrent; margins revolute proximally, plane distally, entire to finely serrulate distally, limbidium absent; apex acute, not cucullate; costa reddish, percurrent to short-excurrent, awn stout; basal laminal cells occasionally pigmented, in 1 row; proximal cells abruptly quadrate to short-rectangular, 1–2(–3):1; medial and distal cells elongate-hexagonal to vermicular, (50–)60–80 × (8–)10–12 µm, 6–8:1, walls strongly incrassate, parallel to costa. Specialized asexual reproduction rare, by rhizoidal tubers on rhizoids arising from leaf axils, red to red-brown, 100–300 µm. Seta ± straight, red, red-brown, or purple. Capsule inclined to nutant, red-purple, pyriform, 3–5 mm, neck short. Spores 10–15 µm, smooth to papillose, yellowish.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature spring-summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Moist acidic rock, soil over rock;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to high elevations (0-2500 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; Nfld. and Labr.; Alaska, Calif., Colo., Ill., N.H.; w, n Eurasia; n Africa.</description>
  <discussion>Imbribryum alpinum is a relatively rare boreal-temperate species characterized by narrow, shiny-metallic red leaves and incrassate, elongate distal laminal cells; capsules are rare. Most reddish plants similar to this species in the western United States do not conform well to this set of characters. Instead, most collections have red, broadly ovate leaves, shorter distal laminal cells, and short-excurrent costae. This material cannot be referred to either I. alpinum or I. muehlenbeckii, and apparently represents an undescribed species. Reports from southern Africa need to be verified as other red-colored species occur in the Southern Hemisphere. The Alaska collection is from St. Lawrence Island.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
