<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John R. Spence</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bryaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Müller Hal. ex Brotherus) J. R. Spence &amp; H. A. Ramsay" date="unknown">LEPTOSTOMOPSIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>87: 70. 2005</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bryaceae;genus LEPTOSTOMOPSIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Leptostomum and Greek -opsis , resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Brachymenium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Müller Hal. ex Brotherus" date="unknown">Leptostomopsis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl, Nat. Pflanzenfam.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>218[I,3]: 558. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, in dense cushions, sometimes turfs, or rarely gregarious, pale green-silver, pinkish, or yellow-silver. Stems 0.4–2 cm, sometimes julaceous, strongly branching by subfloral innovations; rhizoids many, micronemata and macronemata present on stems. Leaves imbricate when dry, erect to erect-spreading when moist, broadly ovate to spathulate, somewhat concave, 0.2–2 mm; base not decurrent; margins recurved or sometimes plane proximally, plane distally, serrulate to distinctly serrate near apex, 1-stratose, limbidium present or absent; apex broadly rounded to acute; costa long-excurrent, sometimes percurrent in proximal leaves, awn hyaline, denticulate to spinose, guide cells present; alar cells usually distinct in quadrate groups or sometimes transversely elongate in small groups; laminal areolation heterogeneous; proximal laminal cells usually quadrate to short-rectangular, 1–2:1; medial and distal cells hexagonal, rhomboidal, or almost vermicular, 3–6:1, walls thin to thick, not pitted. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition dioicous; perigonia and perichaetia terminal, leaves same size as vegetative leaves or usually larger, not forming rosette, inner leaves little differentiated. [Seta usually single, straight to somewhat twisted. Capsule erect, oblong or cylindric, 2–4 mm; hypophysis inconspicuous to well differentiated; operculum weakly convex, short-conic, not rostrate; peristome diplolepidous-alternate; exostome pale yellow or tan, sometimes reddish, teeth slender lanceolate; endostome separate or rarely adherent to exostome, basal membrane low, segments absent, cilia absent. Spores shed singly, not as tetrads, 17–25 µm, finely papillose, pale yellow-tan or brown].</description>
  <description type="distribution">s United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">se Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly subtropical to tropical environments.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 10 (2 in the flora): s United States, Mexico, Central America, South America, se Asia, Africa; mostly subtropical to tropical environments.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 10 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>s United States, Mexico, Central America, South America, se Asia, Africa; mostly subtropical to tropical environments.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 10 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Leptostomopsis is a distinctive genus superficially similar to Leptostomum. Recent molecular work suggests that the genus is basal to the remainder of Bryaceae. The genus was originally included in the polyphyletic Brachymenium. Although molecular work indicates that the genus should be placed in Bryaceae, morphologically it is close to Leptostomum and could be placed in Leptostomataceae. Plants of Leptostomopsis have reddish brown to yellow setae. The exostome teeth are not trabeculate.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants yellow-silver; leaf apices hyaline; costal awns hyaline; distal laminal cells 4–6:1, walls thick, somewhat sinuate</description>
      <determination>1. Leptostomopsis nivea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants green-silver to pink-silver; leaf apices not hyaline; costal awns pigmented proximally, hyaline distally; distal laminal cells 3–4+:1, walls not thick or sinuate</description>
      <determination>2. Leptostomopsis systylia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
