<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bryaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hornschuch" date="unknown">ptychostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Bridel) J. R. Spence" date="2009">CLADODIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>91: 498. 2009</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bryaceae;genus ptychostomum;subgenus CLADODIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">Cladodium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Univ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 620, plate suppl. 3, fig. 9. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>10a.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Stems 0.5–4(–12) cm, usually comose to evenly foliate; sparsely to densely radiculose. Leaves ovate or ovate-lanceolate, distal leaves usually somewhat enlarged; base red or pink, red sap not present in cell lumina; limbidium distinct to indistinct, narrow, pale to green or yellow, 1-stratose throughout; subalar cells inflated, pink, on gametoecial and inner comal leaves; proximal laminal cells rectangular, (short-rectangular in P. pseudotriquetrum), same length as medial, sometimes longer; distal cells rhomboidal to hexagonal, not lax, usually 3–4:1. Capsule pyriform, ovate, or obovate; endostome sometimes adherent to exostome, segments with narrowly to broadly ovate perforations. Spores 10–50 µm, finely to strongly papillose, yellow, green, brown, or black.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">arctic</description>
  <description type="distribution">montane</description>
  <description type="distribution">and boreal regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 35 (16 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Species in subg. Claodium are distinctive in a number of characters, including 1-stratose border, relatively short proximal laminal cells, and tufted or comose habits of many species. Most also have a small group of somewhat inflated pink cells at the leaf insertion in the gametoecial and larger comose leaves, a feature absent from subg. Ptychostomum. The cells at the leaf base usually have red to red-brown walls but clear sap. The leaves are erect-spreading when moist; the setae are red or red-brown (brown in P. salinum).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition dioicous, autoicous, synoicous, or polyoicous; peristome well developed; endostome basal membrane 1/2 exostome height; spores 10–26(–30) µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition autoicous; spores 18–22 µm; stems comose, innovations comose or somewhat elongate and evenly foliate</description>
      <determination>11. Ptychostomum pallescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition dioicous, synoicous, or polyoicous; spores 10–26(–30) µm; stems tufted or comose, rarely evenly foliate, innovations comose or somewhat elongate and evenly foliate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition dioicous; leaf bases strongly decurrent; stems tufted, weakly comose to evenly foliate, usually strongly radiculose well toward stem apices, innovations elongate and evenly foliate; specialized asexual reproduction occasional, by leaf axil gemmae</description>
      <determination>13. Ptychostomum pseudotriquetrum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition dioicous, synoicous, or polyoicous; leaf bases not or weakly decurrent; stems tufted and/or comose, strongly or weakly radiculose, innovations comose or somewhat elongate and evenly foliate; specialized asexual reproduction absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves strongly twisted to contorted when dry, concave; apices broadly acute to obtuse; costae usually not reaching apex to percurrent; sexual condition dioicous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves crowded; bases wide</description>
      <determination>9. Ptychostomum neodamense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves distant; bases narrow</description>
      <determination>16. Ptychostomum subneodamense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves somewhat twisted or contorted when dry, flat to weakly concave; apices acute to acuminate; costae short-to long-excurrent; sexual condition synoicous or polyoicous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Innovations elongate, evenly foliate; leaves not much enlarged toward stem apex; bases weakly decurrent; costae short-excurrent; distal laminal cell walls sometimes very incrassate, sometimes oblique to costa; sexual condition synoicous</description>
      <determination>2. Ptychostomum bimum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Innovations comose or somewhat elongate and evenly foliate; leaves usually enlarged towards apex; bases not or weakly decurrent; costae long-excurrent; distal laminal cell walls thin to firm, never oblique to costa; sexual condition synoicous or polyoicous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition synoicous; spores (18–)20–26(–30) µm</description>
      <determination>5. Ptychostomum intermedium (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition synoicous or polyoicous; spores 10–18(–20) µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition synoicous; limb idium in 2 or 3 rows, yellowish</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition polyoicous; limbidium in (2–)3–4(–6) rows, concolorous</description>
      <determination>7. Ptychostomum lonchocaulon</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition usually synoicous, rarely autoicous or polyoicous; peristome well developed or reduced; endostome basal membrane usually less than 1/2 exostome height; spores (8–)22–30(–50) µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Endostome strongly adherent to exostome; exostome teeth appearing chambered; leaf apices acuminate; costae long-excurrent; capsules pyriform; spores (22–)25–30(–36) µm</description>
      <determination>12. Ptychostomum pendulum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Endostome usually not adherent to exostome; exostome teeth not appearing chambered; leaf apices obtuse, acute, or acuminate; costae not reaching apex to long-excurrent; capsules pyriform or obovate; spores (15–)22–50 µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves strongly concave, ± imbricate to weakly contorted or shrunken when dry; costae not reaching apex to percurrent, rarely short-excurrent; spores 15–22(–25) µm; capsules short-pyriform, asymmetric, curved; endostome cilia usually present</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves flat or concave, twisted to contorted or shrunken when dry; costae percurrent to long-excurrent; spores (18–)22–50 µm; capsules obovate or short-to elongate-pyriform, symmetric (asymmetric, somewhat curved in P. intermedium ); endostome cilia present or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition autoicous; leaves concave; limbidium indistinct; costae percurrent in proximal leaves to sometimes short-excurrent in distal leaves; specialized asexual reproduction by leaf ax il gemmae; spores (28–)30–40 µm</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sexual condition synoicous; leaves flat to concave; limbidium strong; costae usually short-to long-excurrent; specialized asexual reproduction absent; spores (18–)20–50 µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsule mouths orange or yellow; endostome basal membrane 1/2 exostome height, cilia present, sometimes reduced; spores (18–)20–26(–30) µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cilia rudimentary or sometimes 1 or 2, long, appendiculate to nodose; capsules symmetric, mouths straight</description>
      <determination>4. Ptychostomum inclinatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cilia long, nodose; caps ules asymmetric, mouths oblique</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsule mouths yellow or red; endostome basal membrane usually less than 1/2 exostome height, cilia rudimentary or absent; spores (18–)20–50 µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices acute to obtuse; costae percurrent to short-excurrent, awns recurved; setae (2–)3–6(–8) cm; spores (18–)20–50 µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves strongly concave; apices acute to obtuse; costae percurrent to short-excurrent; spores (18–)20–30 µm; setae (2–)3–4 cm</description>
      <determination>6. Ptychostomum knowltonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves weakly concave; apices acute; costae short-excurrent; spores (38–)40–50 µm; setae 3–6(–8) cm</description>
      <determination>8. Ptychostomum longisetum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices acuminate; costae short-to long-excurrent, awns straight; setae 1–3 cm; spores (18–)22–30 µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spores dark brown to black; exostome teeth with pores absent along mid line; endostome sometimes weakly adherent to exostome at base; operculum short-convex, not or weakly apiculate</description>
      <determination>1. Ptychostomum archangelicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spores pale yellow-brown; exostome teeth with small pores present along mid line at base; endostome not adherent to exostome; operculum l ong-conic, distinctly apiculate</description>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
