<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Greville &amp; Arnott" date="unknown">splachnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">APLODON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Chlor. Melvill.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>41. 1823</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family splachnaceae;genus APLODON</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek haplo- , single, and odon , tooth, alluding to single layer of peristome teeth]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown ex I. Hagen" date="unknown">Haplodon</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>5.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in slender lax tufts, light green distally. Stems 6 cm; rhizoids dense proximally. Stem leaves broadly ovate or obovate; margins entire; apex obtuse to acute and abruptly short-acuminate; costa ending before apex; proximal laminal cells rounded-rectangular; distal cells oblong-hexagonal. Sexual condition autoicous. Seta 1–2 cm, twisted, flexuose. Capsule not cleistocarpous, reddish, black with age, shrunken and widest at mouth when dry, ovate when moist; hypophysis same color as urn, &lt;rounded&gt;, elongate, not or slightly wider than urn; annulus weakly differentiated; operculum hemispheric, sometimes apiculate; peristome single; exostome teeth 8–12, at first in pairs, then separate, erect or reflexed, rudimentary. Calyptra mitrate or cucullate, conic, not constricted beyond base. Spores 10–15 µm, smooth.</description>
  <description type="distribution">n North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">subarctic to Arctic regions.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: n North America, n Eurasia; subarctic to Arctic regions.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>n North America, n Eurasia; subarctic to Arctic regions.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Although plants of Aplodon have an inflated hypophysis, based upon the molecular data, placement of the genus is not well resolved within Splachnaceae, and its relationship to or within this family requires further study (B. Goffinet et. al. 2004).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Brassard, G. R. 1978. An extensive subfossil deposit of the Arctic moss Aplodon wormskioldii. Canad. J. Bot. 56: 1852–1859.</reference>
    <reference>Steere, W. C. 1973. Observations on the genus Aplodon (Musci: Splachnaceae). Bryologist. 76: 347–355.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
