<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bryaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hornschuch" date="unknown">ptychostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Müller Hal.) J. R. Spence" date="2005">lonchocaulon</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>87: 21. 2005</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bryaceae;genus ptychostomum;species lonchocaulon</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Müller Hal." date="unknown">lonchocaulon</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>58: 93. 1875</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense or open turfs, green or yellow-green. Stems 1–2(–3) cm, comose, innovations comose or somewhat elongate and evenly foliate; somewhat radiculose. Leaves green, twisted to contorted when dry, ovate-lanceolate, flat to weakly concave, (1–)2–3 mm, not much enlarged toward stem apex; base not decurrent; margins revolute to mid leaf or beyond, limbidium strong, in (2–)3–4(–6) rows, &lt;concolorous&gt;; apex acuminate; costa long-excurrent, awn ± smooth; proximal laminal cells 3–4:1, same width or sometimes wider than more distal cells; medial and distal cells rhomboidal, (12–)14–20 µm wide, 3–4:1, walls thin to firm, &lt;never oblique to costa&gt;. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition polyoicous, mixed synoicous and with male-only gametangia. Seta 1–2(–3) cm. Capsule brown, elongate-pyriform, symmetric, 2–4 mm, mouth yellow; operculum conic, apiculate; peristome well developed; exostome teeth yellow basally, hyaline distally, lamellae usually straight mid tooth, pores absent along mid line; endostome not adherent to exostome, basal membrane high, 1/2 exostome height, segments with broadly ovate perforations, cilia long, appendiculate. Spores (12–)14–18(–20) µm, finely papillose, pale brown-yellow or green.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature May-Sep.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Dry to damp soil;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to high elevations (0-3500 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Que.; Alaska, Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Maine, Minn., Mont., Nev., N.Mex., Oreg., Utah, Wash., Wyo.; Eurasia.</description>
  <discussion>Ptychostomum lonchocaulon is very similar to P. creberrimum, differing in sexual condition and its stronger, non-yellowish limbidium. In North America, P. lonchocaulon is primarily a western species, disjunct in Minnesota. The species has not generally been accepted by most workers, thus its world distribution is poorly known. V. I. Zolotov (2000) gave a good description of the species and its polyoicous sexual condition.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
