<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">bryaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hornschuch" date="unknown">ptychostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Sullivant) J. R. Spence" date="2005">wrightii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>87: 22. 2005</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bryaceae;genus ptychostomum;species wrightii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Sullivant" date="unknown">wrightii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 278. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>31.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense or open turfs, red-green or red-brown. Stems 0.5–1(–2) cm, fertile stems comose, innovations evenly foliate. Leaves yellow-green to red-green, distant proximally, crowded distally, somewhat contorted to shrunken when dry, ovate, concave, 0.5–2 mm, not enlarged toward stem apex; base green, not decurrent; margins revolute proximally, limbidium strong, in 2 or 3 rows; apex acute; costa percurrent to short-excurrent, awn absent; proximal laminal cells long-rectangular, 3–5:1; medial and distal cells 18–25 µm wide, 2–3:1, walls thin. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition synoicous. Seta red-brown, 1–3 cm, slender, straight to somewhat flexuose. Capsule yellow-red, red, or red-brown, often shiny, broadly ovate to pyriform, symmetric, 2–3 mm, mouth yellow-red; operculum short-conic, smooth or weakly apiculate; peristome reduced; exostome teeth yellow proximally, hyaline distally, lamellae somewhat curved proximally, pores absent; endostome not or weakly adherent to exostome, basal membrane low to rudimentary, segments very short, cilia absent. Spores 18–20(–22) µm, yellow.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature Jul-Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Damp calcareous soil, silt, tundra;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations (0-1500 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; Nfld. and Labr. (Labr.), N.W.T., Nunavut, Que., Yukon; Alaska; Eurasia.</description>
  <discussion>Ptychostomum wrightii is a small arctic species with distinctive capsules that are somewhat inflated, shiny red, and ovate to pyriform, and a poorly developed fragile endostome. The stems are sparsely radiculose; the costal awns are smooth. Capsules are needed for identification.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
