<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">mniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">mnium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="1846">spinulosum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 206, plate 394. 1846</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family mniaceae;genus mnium;species spinulosum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 0.5–1(–2.5) cm. Stems red or reddish brown. Leaves green to dark green, slightly contorted or undulate when dry, obovate or occasionally elliptic, 2.5–5 mm; base long-decurrent; margins reddish brown, multistratose with stereid band, toothed distally, teeth paired, long, sharp; apex acute, obtuse, or rounded-acute, cuspidate, cusp toothed; costa percurrent or excurrent, distal abaxial surface smooth, sometimes with few small teeth; medial laminal cells ± isodiametric or short-elongate, 25–40 µm, smaller towards margins, not in rows, not collenchymatous, blue postmortal color absent; marginal cells linear, in (3–)4–5 rows. Sexual condition synoicous. Seta single or multiple. Capsule pale yellow, 1.5–4 mm; operculum rostrate; exostome dark reddish brown, often purplish. Spores 16–24 µm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature late spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Forests, on humus, logs, rock, base of trees;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask., Yukon; Alaska, Ariz., Calif., Conn., Ga., Idaho, Ill., Ky., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Mont., N.H., N.Y., Oreg., R.I., S.Dak., Vt., Wash., Wis.; Europe; Asia.</description>
  <discussion>Mnium spinulosum is distinguished by usually obovate leaves with broad, thick, and pigmented margins, and dark reddish brown exostomes. The capsule mouths are dark reddish brown; H. A. Crum and L. E. Anderson (1981) referred to this species as the red-mouthed mnium.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
