<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">mniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">mnium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">stellare</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>191, plate 45, figs. 1–4. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family mniaceae;genus mnium;species stellare</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 0.5–2(–5) cm. Stems red or reddish brown. Leaves green to dark green, slightly contorted and undulate when dry, ovate-elliptic or elliptic, 1.5–2.5 mm; base short- to long-decurrent; margins green, 1-stratose, entire or weakly toothed distally, rarely to below mid leaf, teeth single, small, blunt (often rounded), occasionally somewhat paired; apex acute, rounded-acute, or obtuse, sometimes short-apiculate; costa ending well before apex, distal abaxial surface smooth; medial laminal cells ± isodiametric or short-elongate, (15–)20–32 µm, slightly smaller near margins, not in diagonal rows, sometimes in weak longitudinal rows, weakly collenchymatous, blue postmortal color present in cells; marginal cells indistinctly differentiated from medial cells, short-linear or rhomboidal, in 1 (or 2) rows. Sexual condition dioicous. Seta single. Capsule pale to dark brown, 2–3 mm; operculum conic-mammillate; exostome yellowish brown. Spores 20–29 µm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature late spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Base of trees, stumps, soil banks, soil over rock, moist shaded sites;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C., N.B., Nfld. and Labr., N.S., Ont., Que.; Ala., Ark., Ga., Iowa, Maine, Md., Mich., Minn., Mo., N.H., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., Tenn., Vt., Va., W.Va.; Europe; Asia; Africa.</description>
</bio:treatment>
