<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Terry T. McIntosh,Steven G. Newmaster</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwagrichen" date="unknown">mniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Kindberg) T. J. Koponen" date="unknown">PSEUDOBRYUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Bot. Fenn.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 147. 1968</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family mniaceae;genus PSEUDOBRYUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pseudes , false, and genus Bryum , alluding to similarity]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Mnium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">Pseudobryum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Eur. N. Amer. Bryin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 338. 1898 (as Pseudo-Bryum)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>6.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 3–10(–15) cm, in loose mats. Stems brown, erect, simple or sometimes branched distally, not dendroid; rhizoids brown, macronemata mainly proximal, scattered distally, micronemata present. Leaves green or yellow-green, dark brown when old, crisped and weakly contorted when dry, erect or erect-spreading, often weakly undulate when moist, broadly ovate, elliptic, or sometimes orbicular, (3–)4–6(–7) mm; base not or short-decurrent; margins plane, green or yellow-green, 1-stratose, entire or lightly toothed to below mid leaf, teeth single, blunt or sometimes rounded; apex rounded, obtuse, or rarely retuse, apiculate; costa subpercurrent, ending well before apex, or rarely percurrent, distal abaxial surface smooth; medial laminal cells elongate, often ± rhomboidal, usually 3+:1, (30–)40–80(–110) µm, in diagonal rows, not collenchymatous, walls pitted; marginal cells indistinctly differentiated from medial cells, short-linear or rhomboidal, in 1–2(–3) rows. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition dioicous. Seta single or rarely double, orange-yellow, 2–5.5 cm, flexuose. Capsule pendent, yellowish brown, ovate, 2–2.5 mm; operculum conic-apiculate; exostome dark brown; endostome yellowish brown. Spores 31–40 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumtemperate to circumboreal.</description>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Pseudobryum consists of two species of which one (P. cinclidioides; n = 6) is in the flora area and the other [P. speciosum (Mitten) T. J. Koponen; n = 7] is Asiatic. The latter is differentiated also by leaf characters and polysety.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
