<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Brotherus" date="unknown">rhizogoniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Mitten" date="unknown">PYRRHOBRYUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 174. 1868</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family rhizogoniaceae;genus PYRRHOBRYUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pyrrho , flame-colored, and bryon , moss, alluding to peristome]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Stems with exterior cells in 2 or 3 rows, small, walls thick, interior cells larger, walls moderately thick. Leaves with base undifferentiated or occasionally indistinctly decurrent; margins double-serrate from near base; costa stereid cells well developed on both sides of guide cells; juxtacostal basal cells often weakly differentiated, short- to long-rectangular, enlarged, lax or not; medial and distal laminal cells uniform, isodiametric, rounded to 4–6-sided, smooth, walls thick; marginal cells 2-stratose. Seta wiry. Capsule striate and flared at mouth when deoperculate; exothecial cells hexagonal [quadrate- to rectangular-rounded], walls moderately thick, somewhat weakly collenchymatous at base; stomata few at base and in neck, superficial.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa, Pacific Islands, Australia; pantropical and southern temperate regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species 10 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Pyrrhobryum is characterized by elongate stems, distal and spirally arranged, broadly to narrowly lanceolate or linear-lanceolate leaves with double-toothed, 2-stratose margins, costae distally toothed abaxially, laminal cells mostly isodiametric and similar to near bases, and sporophytes positioned somewhat midway on stems or at bases.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Frahm, J.-P. et al. 2003. Synopsis der Gattung Pyrrhobryum (Musci, Rhizogoniaceae). Trop. Bryol. 24: 115–127.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
