<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">daltoniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hooker &amp; Taylor" date="unknown">DALTONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Brit.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>80, plates 3 [near upper left], 22 [lower center left &amp; right]. 1818</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family daltoniaceae;genus DALTONIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Rev. John Dalton, 1764 – 1843, British botanist and bryologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants glossy. Stems prostrate or suberect, branches short, ascending. Leaves erect, sometimes flexuose-twisted and contorted when dry, flexuose when moist, ovate-lanceolate, ligulate- to lance-acuminate, symmetric, straight, keeled; margins entire, strongly bordered, cells linear, incrassate, in several rows; costa ending before apex in distal 1/4; laminal cells usually uniformly rhomboidal to elongate-hexagonal, walls usually incrassate; basal cells sometimes rounded, longer, smooth. Sexual condition autoicous or synoicous. Seta roughened distally [smooth]. Capsule erect to subinclined; exothecial cells strongly collenchymatous; exostome teeth hygrocastique (teeth incurved when dry and reflexed when moist), densely papillose, with zigzag longitudinal lines, not striate, not furrowed; endostome segments linear, narrow, same length as teeth, perforate along keel. Calyptra smooth to somewhat roughened distally, basal fringe hairs dense. Spores papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Atlantic Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Indian Ocean Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (New Zealand)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species ca. 22 (1 in the flora): nw North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Indian Ocean Islands, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species ca. 22 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>nw North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Indian Ocean Islands, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species ca. 22 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Majestyk, P. 2011. A taxonomic treatment of Daltonia (Musci: Daltoniaceae) in the Americas. J. Bot. Res. Inst. Texas 5: 553–575.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
