<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">pilotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Müller Hal.) Mitten" date="unknown">CALLICOSTELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Proc. Linn. Soc., Bot., suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 136. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pilotrichaceae;genus CALLICOSTELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin callum , hardened or thick, costa , rib, and -ella , diminutive, alluding to strong costae]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="unknown">Hookeria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Müller Hal." date="unknown">Callicostella</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Musc. Frond.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 216. 1851</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Hookeria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Müller Hal.) Hampe" date="unknown">Callicostella</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Schizomitrium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>name rejected</publication_title>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>3.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized, in flattened mats, sordid pale green, yellowish, brownish, sometimes bluish, dull. Stems regularly or irregularly pinnate; hyalodermis absent. Leaves ± complanate, shriveled, often crisped when dry, ovate-oblong to lingulate, somewhat asymmetric, ventral leaves often more acuminate, dorsal and lateral leaves broadly oblong to oblong-ovate; margins plane, entire in basal 1/4, crenulate, serrulate, or strongly toothed in apical 1/4; apex rounded-truncate, short-apiculate; costa ending in apex, subpercurrent, divergent from base, parallel or somewhat convergent distally, distal abaxial surface toothed; laminal cells isodiametric or slightly longer than wide, irregularly hexagonal to quadrate, 1-papillose on both surfaces; marginal cells forming obscure border or not forming border. Specialized asexual reproduction unknown. Sexual condition synoicous and autoicous, infrequently dioicous; perichaetial leaf apex gradually acuminate to acute. Seta red to reddish yellow, moderately to strongly papillose-scabrous. Capsule inclined, horizontal, or pendulous, ovoid or oblong-cylindric; annulus absent; operculum abruptly short-rostrate or subulate. Calyptra mitrate-campanulate, base narrowed and shortly or deeply lobed, smooth or sometimes split on one side from base, somewhat scabrous or with few hairs distally.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species ca. 95 (1 in the flora): se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Pacific Islands.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species ca. 95 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Pacific Islands.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species ca. 95 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Callicostella is characterized by broad and abruptly acuminate leaves with no border. Other distinctive features include the long, tough double costa and the small, isodiametric, firm-walled, 1-papillose laminal cells. The distal leaf margins are strongly serrate, with teeth often 2-fid. Callicostella may also be distinguished from closely related genera by its stem epidermis composed of small, thick-walled cells.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
