<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>William R. Buck</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="M. Fleischer" date="unknown">RUTENBERGIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>Family RUTENBERGIACEAE</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>52.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants usually large, green to golden. Stems creeping, slender, inconspicuous, sympodial, secondary stems ± erect, not or scarcely complanate-foliate; hyalodermis absent, central strand absent; paraphyllia absent; pseudoparaphyllia foliose. Primary stem leaves reduced, scalelike. Branch leaves lanceolate to oblong-ovate, not or slightly concave, not plicate; base sometimes auriculate; margins sometimes limbate from elongate cells; apex gradually short-acuminate; costa single, subpercurrent to excurrent; laminal cells long-hexagonal, walls firm, not or scarcely porose. Specialized asexual reproduction by flagellate branches. [Sexual condition dioicous. Seta short. Capsule immersed to emergent; annulus not differentiated; operculum long-rostrate; peristome single (endostome absent) or double; exostome teeth smooth; endostome basal membrane very low, segments smooth, cilia absent. Calyptra mitrate or cucullate, densely hairy. Spores spheric to irregular, large, smooth to roughened].</description>
  <description type="distribution">Florida</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">e Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Indian Ocean Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical regions.</description>
  <discussion>Genera 3, species 6 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Rutenbergiaceae are primarily eastern African mosses. The inclusion of Pseudocryphaea in the family is based primarily on molecular data, in part because it is not known in the fertile condition.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
