<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Lars Hedenäs</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="G. Roth" date="unknown">amblystegiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Sullivant) Spruce" date="unknown">CRATONEURON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cat. Musc.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21. 1867</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family amblystegiaceae;genus CRATONEURON</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek cratos , strong, and neuron , nerve, alluding to leaf costa]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Hypnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Sullivant" date="unknown">Cratoneuron</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray, Manual ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 673. 1856</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized, green, yellowish, or rarely brownish. Stems pinnate or irregularly branched; hyalodermis absent, central strand present; paraphyllia few to many, rarely absent, &lt;lanceolate&gt;; rhizoids or rhizoid initials on stem or abaxial costa insertion, often forming tomentum, usually strongly branched, smooth; axillary hair distal cells 1 or 2, hyaline. Stem leaves not recurved or squarrose, straight or falcate, narrowly to broadly triangular or rounded-triangular, sometimes ovate, not plicate, longer than 1 mm; base decurrent; margins plane or near base slightly recurved, denticulate or serrulate almost throughout, limbidia absent; apex acuminate, &lt;acumen plane or furrowed&gt;; costa strong, single, usually percurrent or excurrent, sometimes ending well before apex; alar cells differentiated, strongly inflated, hyaline, region well defined, transversely triangular; medial laminal cells elongate-hexagonal, short-rectangular, rectangular, short-linear, or rarely linear, &lt;smooth&gt;; marginal cells 1-stratose. Sexual condition dioicous. Capsule horizontal, cylindric, curved; peristome perfect; exostome margins slightly dentate distally; endostome cilia 2 or 3, well developed, nodose. Spores 14–21(–25) µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Atlantic Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (New Zealand).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 2 (1 in the flora): North America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Pacific Islands (New Zealand).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Pacific Islands (New Zealand).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Cratoneuron grows in slightly or strongly calcareous habitats that are at least periodically wet; plants have a strong leaf costa, relatively short, smooth laminal cells, and mostly lanceolate and leaflike paraphyllia. The differences between Cratoneuron and 2. Palustriella are described under the latter.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
