<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Alain Vanderpoorten</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="G. Roth" date="unknown">amblystegiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper in P. Bruch and W. P. Schimper" date="unknown">AMBLYSTEGIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in P. Bruch and W. P. Schimper, Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 45, plates 561–566, 568–573. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family amblystegiaceae;genus AMBLYSTEGIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek amblys , blunt, and stege , roof, alluding to obtuse operculum]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>11.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, green to yellowish. Stems freely and irregularly branched; hyalodermis absent, central strand present; paraphyllia absent; rhizoids or rhizoid initials on stem or abaxial costa insertion, rarely forming tomentum, slightly to strongly branched, smooth; axillary hair distal cells 1 (or 2), hyaline. Stem and branch leaves erect to spreading, straight or rarely subsecund, ovate to oblong-lanceolate, not plicate, 0.5–1 mm; base not decurrent; margins plane, entire or denticulate, limbidia absent; apex acuminate, &lt;acumen not furrowed&gt;; costa single, usually reaching mid leaf, sometimes shorter or to 3/4 leaf length; alar cells often well differentiated, subquadrate to transversely elongate, region broadly ovate or transversely triangular along margin; medial laminal cells short-oblong; marginal cells 1-stratose. Sexual condition autoicous. Capsule inclined to horizontal, cylindric, arcuate; peristome perfect; &lt;exostome teeth well developed, external surface cross striolate basally&gt;, margins dentate or slightly so; endostome &lt;basal membrane present&gt;, cilia usually well developed. Spores 9–18 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: nearly worldwide.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>nearly worldwide.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Amblystegium differs from Hygroamblystegium in its smaller size and weaker costa, this less than 30 µm wide at base, most often ceasing mid leaf; the costa rarely reaches 3/4 of leaf length but in such cases is straight, not curved as in Hygroamblystegium. Unlike the latter genus, Amblystegium lacks paraphyllia. Amblystegium is a terrestrial genus that sometimes occurs in swampy but never aquatic or subaquatic habitats.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Conard, H. S. 1959. Amblystegium. Bryologist 62: 96–104.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
