<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Steere" date="unknown">Groutiella</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>53: 145. 1950</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>not Austin 1870</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus Groutiella</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Abel Joel Grout, 1867 – 1947, American bryologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper ex Bescherelle" date="unknown">Micromitrium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Soc. Natl. Sci. Nat. Cherbourg</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>16: 190. 1872,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>3.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, in tomentose mats. Stems creeping, branches erect. Leaves contorted and spirally twisted around stem, ± undulate when dry, erect to wide-spreading when moist, lanceolate to lingulate, sometimes rugose; margins entire or denticulate; apex rounded-obtuse and mucronate or acute and subulate; costa percurrent or excurrent; basal laminal cells oblate to rounded; distal cells rounded-hexagonal or irregularly rounded to elliptic-hexagonal, 3–9 µm, smooth; marginal cells distinct from basal. Sexual condition dioicous or pseudautoicous; perichaetial leaves similar to stem leaves. Seta to 11 mm. Capsule exserted; oblong-ovate to cylindric, usually smooth or obscurely plicate when old, not constricted below mouth; stomata superficial; peristome rudimentary; exostome absent; endostome basal membrane usually low, papillose. Calyptra mitrate, conic, ± lacerate, or divided into many lobes, smooth, naked, plicate, covering less than 1/2 capsule. Spores isosporous or anisosporous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Florida, Mexico, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa, Australia; pantropical regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 20 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>In Groutiella, the branches are usually simple, to 2 cm; the leaf margins are plane or broadly reflexed; the basal laminal cells are yellowish; the distal cells are bulging; the marginal cells are elongate-linear basally, extending 1/4 or more the leaf length, sometimes nearly to the apex as a border; and the operculum is more or less convex-conic with a long rostrum.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal leaves widest distally; apex acute, ending in long, linear, fragile subula</description>
      <determination>1. Groutiella tomentosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal leaves widest mid leaf or distally; apex rounded-obtuse, mucronate, not fragile</description>
      <determination>2. Groutiella tumidula</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
