<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="G. Roth" date="unknown">amblystegiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Loeske" date="unknown">sanionia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedenas" date="1989">nivalis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Bot . Fenn .</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>26: 411 , f igs . 10 - –12. 1989</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family amblystegiaceae;genus sanionia;species nivalis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized to large. Stems unbranched, sometimes sparsely and irregularly branched, or rarely ± pinnate. Stem leaves falcate or strongly falcate, rarely straight or almost so, not plicate, plicate, or rarely strongly plicate, 0.5–1.7 mm wide; base ovate-triangular to broadly ovate; margins plane or sometimes partly recurved distally, strongly denticulate distally; apex acuminate to long-acuminate; costa in bottom of shallow, wide-angled fold (or not in fold); alar region ± isodiametric, transition to supra-alar cells gradual, alar and supra-alar cells together often in ± homogeneous ovate basal marginal group, supra-alar cells rectangular or long-rectangular, ± echlorophyllose, walls thin, eporose, region equal in size to or much larger than alar region; apical laminal cells with distal ends occasionally prorate abaxially. Perichaetia with inner leaves ± suddenly narrowed to apex, margins strongly denticulate to dentate distally, apex acute or short-acuminate. Capsule ± erect; exothecial cells ± isodiametric, in (1–)2–3 rows; exostome specialized, teeth long, or apical end of distal tooth portion somewhat reduced, narrow distally, border not widened at transitional zone in pattern of external tooth; endostome specialized, in recently dehisced capsules hyaline or slightly yellowish, basal membrane constituting 17–33% endostome height, processes and basal membrane with one or both cell wall layers strongly perforated all over, cilia rudimentary or absent.</description>
  <description type="habitat">large late snow beds shores of glacier-fed brooks</description>
  <description type="habitat">shores of glacier-fed brooks</description>
  <description type="distribution">low to high elevations</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="distribution">Yukon</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alaska</description>
  <description type="distribution">Colo.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mont.</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Europe.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Large late snow beds, shores of glacier-fed brooks; low to high elevations; Greenland; Nunavut, Yukon; Alaska, Colo., Mont.; n Europe.</text>
    <parsed>
      <habitat>Large late snow beds, shores of glacier-fed brooks;</habitat>
      <elevation>low to high elevations;</elevation>
      <distribution>Greenland; Nunavut, Yukon; Alaska, Colo., Mont.; n Europe.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Sanionia nivalis is easily separated from the other three species of Sanionia by its reduced and irregularly perforate endostome, the structure of the alar and supra-alar cells, and the acute to short-acuminate inner perichaetial leaves with strongly denticulate or dentate distal margins; the other three species have long-acuminate inner perichaetial leaves with finely denticulate or denticulate distal margins. In addition, the stem leaves of S. nivalis are more short-acuminate and have more strongly denticulate margins than in the three other species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
