<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Howard A. Crum†,Lars Hedenäs</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="G. Roth" date="unknown">amblystegiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="H. Robinson" date="unknown">CONARDIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>33: 294. 1976</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family amblystegiaceae;genus CONARDIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Henry Shoemaker Conard, 1874–1971, bryologist of Grinnell College, Iowa]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>17.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, occasionally minute, light green or yellow. Stems irregularly branched, ± in one plane; hyalodermis absent, central strand present; paraphyllia absent; rhizoids or rhizoid initials on stem and abaxial costa or on lamina near leaf apex, often forming tomentum, strongly branched, warty-papillose; axillary hair distal cells 1–4, hyaline. Stem leaves erect to spreading, straight or slightly falcate, lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, not plicate, 0.6–1.2 mm; base decurrent; margins plane or partly slightly incurved or recurved, finely denticulate, or often coarsely so near base, limbidia absent; apex acuminate, &lt;acumen plane or furrowed&gt;; costa single, ending in acumen, sometimes percurrent; alar cells differentiated, usually rectangular or sometimes quadrate, not inflated, region distinct but gradually delimited, transversely triangular; medial laminal cells linear or short-linear; marginal cells 1-stratose. Sexual condition autoicous. Capsule inclined, cylindric, slightly curved; peristome slightly reduced; exostome margins indistinctly dentate distally; endostome cilia usually 1 or 2. Spores 14–19 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Atlantic Islands (Iceland).</description>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Conardia has the appearance of a small Amblystegium, but can be distinguished by the warty-papillose, much branched rhizoids that are frequently inserted on the abaxial costa or near the leaf apex; rhizoids can mostly be found in the basal portions of at least some shoots. In addition, the distal parts of the axillary hairs consist of 1–4 cells that are shorter and broader than the 1 or 2 narrow and delicate ones found in Amblystegium. The capsule is only slightly curved rather than curved throughout as in Amblystegium species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hedenäs, L. 1989d. On the taxonomic position of Conardia Robins. J. Bryol. 15: 779–783.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
