<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John A. Christy</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="G. Roth" date="unknown">amblystegiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. L. Andrews" date="unknown">PLATYLOMELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>53: 58. 1950</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* [Genus name Platyloma and Latin -ella , diminutive, alluding to replaced later homonym] E</other_info_on_pub>
      <other_info_on_pub>not Rafinesque 1833 [Brassicaceae]</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family amblystegiaceae;genus PLATYLOMELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">Platyloma</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Eur. N.-Amer. Bryin.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>22. 1897,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sciaromium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Brotherus" date="unknown">Platyloma</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>20.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to somewhat large, dark green to blackish with yellowish green shoot apices. Stems &lt;fine, prostrate&gt;, irregularly branched or subpinnate; hyalodermis absent, central strand present; paraphyllia present, filiform; rhizoids basal or sometimes adventitious distally on decumbent shoots, forming tomentum, slightly branched, smooth; axillary hair distal cells 1 or 2, hyaline. Stem leaves erect-spreading, straight or incurved, cordate-ovate to ovate-lanceolate, not plicate, 0.5–1.5 mm; base not decurrent; margins plane, serrulate distally or to base, sometimes entire, limbidia conspicuous or sometimes inconspicuous, 2–4-stratose, cells incrassate; apex gradually or abruptly acuminate, sometimes apiculate, tips often obtuse; costa single, strong, percurrent to short-excurrent, usually confluent distally with limbidia; alar cells undifferentiated; basal laminal cells rectangular or oblong-hexagonal; distal cells short-rhomboidal to oblong-hexagonal, 6–12 × 15–40 µm. Branch leaves similar, slightly smaller and narrower. Sexual condition autoicous. Capsule horizontal to cernuous, oblong-cylindric, asymmetric, sometimes arcuate; peristome hypnoid; exostome margins dentate; endostome cilia appendiculate. Spores 12–17(–25) µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">e North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: c, e North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>c, e North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Platylomella has previously been included in Sciaromium (Mitten) Mitten, a synonym of Echinodium Juratzka (S. P. Churchill 1986).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Andrews, A. L. 1945. Taxonomic notes. IV. Sciaromium lescurii. Bryologist 48: 100–103.</reference>
    <reference>Ochyra, R. 1987. A revision of the moss genus Sciaromium (Mitt.) Mitt. III. The section Platyloma Broth. J. Hattori Bot. Lab. 63: 107–132.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
