<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Greville &amp; Arnott" date="unknown">splachnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hooker" date="unknown">TAYLORIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Sci. Arts (London)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(3): 144. 1816</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>not Smith 1808</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family splachnaceae;genus TAYLORIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Thomas Taylor, 1775 – 1848, British bryologist and coauthor of the Muscologia Britannica]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">Hookeria</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond. Suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(2): 340, plate 100. 1816,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in loose or dense tufts, green, yellowish, or sometimes brownish. Stems 0.5–3(–6) cm; sparsely to strongly radiculose. Stem leaves oblong-lanceolate to obovate; margins toothed to entire; apex obtuse, blunt, acute, or acuminate; costa ending well before apex to excurrent; proximal laminal cells long; distal cells oblong-hexagonal. Sexual condition autoicous, often dioicous, rarely synoicous. Seta 0.6–4 cm, flexuose or twisted. Capsule not cleistocarpous, brown, ovoid, oblong-cylindric, pyriform, or conic; hypophysis usually same color as urn, short to elongate, narrower than or occasionally as wide as urn; annulus present, not strongly differentiated; operculum flat, convex, conic, or hemispheric; peristome inserted at or below mouth, prostome absent (present in T. lingulata); exostome teeth 8 or 16, sometimes connate in pairs, rarely split, erect or reflexed, of 2 layers of cells. Calyptra mitrate, short, constricted at base. Spores 9–48 µm, smooth, slightly roughened, or papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical to subarctic regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species 45 (6 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Tayloria is the only genus of the family to include both anemophilous and entomophilous taxa; it is also the most polymorphic morphologically. All North American species of Tayloria are anemophilous and none are coprophilous, although the plants often grow on nutrient-enriched substrates. The hypophysis of sporophytes of Tayloria is usually tapered and constricted when dry; the stem leaves are erect to wide-spreading and imbricate to somewhat contorted when dry; and the capsules are erect to suberect or slightly asymmetric.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves lingulate or rarely obovate to oblong; apices obtuse to rounded, occasionally bluntly acute; margins entire or sometimes with blunt teeth.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Prostome present; setae slender, 1.5–4 cm</description>
      <determination>1. Tayloria lingulata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Prostome absent; setae stout, to 1 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves uniformly spaced along stem, slightly contorted when dry; columella included; hypophysis as long as urn; exostome teeth lanceolate, yellow to tan; operculum deciduous</description>
      <determination>3. Tayloria froelichiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves crowded at stem and branch apices, stiffly erect-imbricate when dry; columella exsert ed; hypophysis longer than urn; exostome teeth truncate to obtuse, red to red-brown; operculum systylius</description>
      <determination>4. Tayloria hornschuchii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves obovate, oblong, or ovate-lanceolate, rarely lingulate; apices acute or acuminate, not broadly rounded, sometimes obtuse; margins serrate distally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Exostome teeth not split</description>
      <determination>2. Tayloria serrata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Exostome teeth split at base into linear-lanceolate filaments.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 1–3 cm; leaf apices blunt or apiculate; setae 1.5–3 cm; capsule urns 2–3.5 mm when moist; columella exserted when dry; operculum long-conic</description>
      <determination>5. Tayloria splachnoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 0.5–1 cm; leaf apices long-acuminate; setae 0.6–1.5 cm; capsule urns 0.8–2 mm when moist; columella not or barely exserted when dry; operculum short-conic</description>
      <determination>6. Tayloria acuminata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <references>
    <reference>LaFarge-England, C. and D. H. Vitt. 1985. A taxonomic study of Tayloria hornschuchii and T. froelichiana in North America. Bryologist 88: 82–93.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
