<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Terry J. O’Brien</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ochyra" date="unknown">helodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="T. J. O'Brien" date="unknown">ECHINOPHYLLUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>103: 513, figs. 2, 3. 2000</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family helodiaceae;genus ECHINOPHYLLUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek echinos , sea-urchin or hedgehog, and phyllon , leaf, alluding to spinose proximal leaf margins]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized, green or yellowish. Stems creeping, 1-pinnate or sometimes irregularly 2-pinnate; paraphyllia polymorphous, filiform or sometimes narrowly lanceolate, branched or sometimes unbranched, cells oblong, smooth or papillose over end walls, apical cell bluntly conic by wall thickened at tip; pseudoparaphyllia lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, margins ciliate or serrate, proximal cells subquadrate, centrally papillose. Stem leaves spreading, broadly ovate or rarely elliptic; margins plane or recurved, spinose-serrate distally, entire or distantly serrulate in acumen; apex abruptly narrowed, acumen subulate; costa surface with coarse, spinose teeth over proximal 1/2; laminal cells with abaxial surface echinate, 1-papillose, papilla coarsely obliquely blunt-conic; medial cells subquadrate to short-rectangular; apical cell 20:1, smooth. Branch leaves differentiated from stem leaves, spreading or spreading-erect, slightly overlapping, ± catenulate when dry, broadly ovate, concave; apex abruptly acute; distal medial laminal cells irregular, rhombic, oblong, or subquadrate, walls incrassate; apical cell 7:1, with distal bluntly conic wall thickening. Sexual condition dioicous; perichaetia inner leaves cilia present. Seta 2–2.8 cm. Capsule with stomata present in proximal 1/2. Spores 10–16 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">e Asia.</description>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
