<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Hornschuch ex Müller Hal.) Grout" date="unknown">Macrocoma</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>47: 4. 1944</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus Macrocoma</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek macros , long, and kome , hair, alluding to long hairs on calyptrae of some species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Macromitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Hornschuch ex Müller Hal." date="unknown">Macrocoma</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Zeitung (Berlin)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 522. 1845</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, in mats. Stems creeping, branches ascending. Leaves closely erect-appressed, not contorted when dry, erect-spreading when moist, lanceolate to ovate-lanceolate, not rugose; margins entire; apex acute to narrowly obtuse [bluntly acuminate]; costa percurrent; basal laminal cells rounded to elliptic; distal cells rounded-quadrate, 7–12 µm, &lt;in vertical rows&gt;, smooth [papillose only over lumina]; marginal cells not distinct from basal. Sexual condition gonioautoicous; perichaetial leaves longer than branch leaves. Seta 4–6.5 mm. Capsule exserted, oblong-cylindric to fusiform, ± plicate distally or not, not constricted below mouth; stomata superficial; peristome single, of exostome or endostome; exostome teeth 16 blunt, short, papillose; or endostome basal membrane low, papillose. Calyptra mitrate, long elliptic-conic, basal lobes many, smooth, ± hairy, obscurely plicate, covering capsule. Spores isosporous, &lt;unicellular&gt;.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa, Indian Ocean Islands (Madagascar), Pacific Islands (Hawaii, New Zealand), Australia.</description>
  <discussion>Species 11 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Characters of Macrocoma include the rounded basal laminal cells, slender, irregularly branched stems, leaves erect-appressed when dry, cylindric capsules, peristome often reduced, and calyptra long conic-elliptic. There are often rhizoids present on the abaxial costa surface.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
