<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert E. Magill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">leskeaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Müller Hal.) Müller Hal." date="unknown">HAPLOCLADIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hedwigia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>38: 149. 1899</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family leskeaceae;genus HAPLOCLADIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek, haplos , simple, and kladion , branchlet, alluding to 1-pinnate branching]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Hypnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subsection" authority="Müller Hal." date="unknown">Haplocladium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>42: 459. 1879</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized, in dense mats, olive green, yellow-green, or brownish. Stems pinnate to subpinnate; paraphyllia few or many, filamentous to subfoliose, cells papillose; rhizoids often arising from axils of older leaves. Stem and branch leaves dimorphic. Stem leaves erect, curved, or subsecund when dry, erect-spreading when moist, ovate to sometimes triangular, plicate or not; margins plane to somewhat recurved basally, weakly serrulate to serrulate, &lt;limbidium absent&gt;; apex abruptly short- or long-acuminate, hair-point absent; costa single, ending in apex or subpercurrent, &lt;opaque&gt;, weakly flexuose distally; alar cells little differentiated to quadrate; medial laminal cells rectangular to rhomboidal, smooth, 1-papillose over lumen, or prorulose at distal end, walls thin to firm, rarely incrassate. Branch leaves smaller; margins more strongly serrate; laminal cells more strongly papillose. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition autoicous; perichaetial leaves pale, erect, longer, apex narrowly long-acuminate. Seta 1.5–3 cm. Capsule erect, inclined, or horizontal, oblong, curved; annulus present; operculum conic, short-rostrate; peristome perfect; exostome teeth lanceolate, densely cross striate-papillose proximally, papillose distally; endostome basal membrane high, segments broad, cilia well developed. Spores 8–14 µm, granulate to nearly smooth.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide except Antarctica.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 17 (3 in the flora): nearly worldwide except Antarctica.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 17 (3 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>nearly worldwide except Antarctica.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 17 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Haplocladium occurs on rock, humus, wood, and soil in open woodland habitats. The genus resembles Thuidium (Chryso-hypnum) but is only 1-pinnate, has fewer paraphyllia, and the apical laminal cell has a single papilla at the tip. The paraphyllia are filamentous; the proximal laminal cells are papillose and the distal cells usually smooth; the seta is smooth and frequently flexuose; the capsules are strongly contracted below the mouth when dry; and the endostome has nodose cilia in groups of two or three.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves 2-plicate basally; paraphyllia filamentous, infrequently branched; branch leaves somewhat distant</description>
      <determination>1. Haplocladium microphyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves not plicate; paraphyllia filamentous to subfoliose, frequently branched; branch leaves crowded.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems regularly pinnate; branch leaves oval; apices acute to apiculate; laminal cell papillae over lumen</description>
      <determination>2. Haplocladium virginianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems irregularly pinnate; branch leaves oval to ovate; apices acuminate; laminal cell papillae shifted distally</description>
      <determination>3. Haplocladium angustifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
