<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">Macromitrium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Recent., suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 132. 1818</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus Macromitrium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek macros , long, and mitra , cap, alluding to large calyptra]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>5.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to large, in dense mats. Stems creeping, branches ascending to erect. Leaves strongly crisped and inrolled, rarely erect-appressed when dry, erect-spreading to squarrose-recurved when moist, lanceolate to ligulate-lanceolate, not rugose; margins entire to crenulate; apex sharply acute, obtuse, or obtusely apiculate; costa percurrent to excurrent; basal laminal cells rectangular to elongate-linear; distal cells irregularly hexagonal to rounded-elliptic, 7–11 µm, &lt;in vertical rows&gt;, smooth to papillose or mammillose only over lumina, papillae 1 to many, conic; marginal cells not distinct from basal. Sexual condition autoicous; perichaetial leaves similar to stem leaves. Seta 5–12 mm. Capsule exserted, ovate, narrowly ovate to ovate-oblong when old and dry, plicate below mouth; stomata superficial; peristome single; exostome teeth 16, sparsely striate. Calyptra mitrate, lacerate, basal lobes many, smooth, naked or hairs few, plicate, covering entire capsule. Spores isosporous or anisosporous, &lt;unicellular&gt;.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 460 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Distinguishing characters for Macromitrium include prostrate creeping stems with many short, erect branches, terminal sporophytes, a mitrate, plicate calyptra, and a propensity for a chestnut brown color.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
