<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Paul L. Redfearn Jr.</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">leskeaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">LESKEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>211, plates 49 – 58, plate 59, figs. 1 – 5. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family leskeaceae;genus LESKEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Nathanael Gottfried Leske, 1751 – 1786, botanist of Lei p zig]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>5.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, in mats, pale green, dark green, or brownish. Stems freely branched to subpinnate; paraphyllia few, linear-lanceolate, cells smooth; sparsely radiculose. Stem and branch leaves similar or differentiated. Stem leaves erect or somewhat recurved when dry, erect-spreading when moist, oblong-ovate or ovate-lanceolate, plicate on one side, 2-plicate, or plane; margins plane or ± recurved proximally, entire to subserrulate distally, &lt;limbidium absent&gt;; apex acute, acuminate, or obtuse, hair-point absent; costa single, subpercurrent or ending before apex, &lt;opaque&gt;, often flexuose-curved distally; alar cells weakly differentiated, subquadrate; medial and distal laminal cells irregularly quadrate-hexagonal, ± 1-papillose on abaxial or both surfaces, walls thick; &lt;apical cells ± quadrate except at very tip&gt;. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition autoicous; perichaetial leaves pale brown, erect, elongate, apex acuminate. Seta 0.4–1.2 cm. Capsule erect, cylindric to oblong-cylindric, symmetric to distinctly curved; annulus narrow or absent; operculum conic; peristome reduced; exostome teeth linear-lanceolate, usually cross striolate near base, sometimes densely papillose throughout; endostome basal membrane low, segments long-linear, cilia absent or rudimentary. Spores 9–18 µm, smooth to very finely papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 24 (4 in the flora): North America, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 24 (4 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Central America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 24 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Leskea occurs in terrestrial habitats in temperate, subtropical, and tropical regions. The leaves are somewhat asymmetric with proximal laminal cells somewhat longer than the more distal cells, which are obscure; the exostome teeth are incurved when dry; and the endostome is erect, pale, and papillose.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves 0.2 – 0.5 mm; distal laminal cells 4 – 7 µm</description>
      <determination>1. Leskea australis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves 0.4 – 0.8 mm; distal laminal cells 6 – 11 µm .</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem and branch leaves differentiated, stem leaves longer than broad; apices ± obliquely acuminate and subsecund; branches somewhat curved at apices; ca p sules subcylindric, curved</description>
      <determination>4. Leskea polycarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem and branch leaves similar, not much longer than broad; apices not oblique or subsecund; branches not curved at apices; capsules o b long-cylindric, straight or slightly curved.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches ± tightly foliate; leaf apices acute or sometimes narrowly blunt; leaves ± 2-plicate; margins irregularly revolute proximally, especially when dry; e n dostome segments as long as exostome teeth; operculum ± pointed</description>
      <determination>2. Leskea gracilescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches loosely foliate; leaf apices rounded-obtuse to sometimes acute or acuminate; leaves not plicate (stem leaves occasionally slightly plicate); margins not revolute; endostome segments less than 1/3 exostome teeth length; operculum blunt</description>
      <determination>3. Leskea obs cura</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
