<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Paul L. Redfearn Jr.</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">leskeaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">LINDBERGIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Eur. N.-Amer. Bryin.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15. 1897</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family leskeaceae;genus LINDBERGIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Sextus Otto Lindberg, 1835 – 1889, Scandinavian br y ologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, in loose mats, dark green to yellowish or brownish. Stems irregularly branched; paraphyllia absent; rhizoids occasional on stem. Stem and branch leaves similar. Stem leaves crowded, imbricate when dry, wide-spreading to squarrose when moist, ovate or ovate-lanceolate, not plicate; margins plane, entire or faintly serrulate near apex; apex acute to short-acuminate, hair-point sometimes present; costa single, &lt;strong&gt;, ending below apex, straight to weakly flexuose; alar cells quadrate to short-rectangular; medial laminal cells oval, rounded, or rhombic, 1-papillose over lumen, walls thick. Specialized asexual reproduction sometimes present. Sexual condition autoicous; perichaetial leaves pale, erect, base sheathing, margins entire or finely toothed, apex long-acuminate, costa short. Seta 0.6–0.8 cm. Capsule erect, oblong-cylindric, symmetric or weakly curved; annulus sometimes present; operculum conic, blunt; peristome somewhat reduced; exostome teeth lanceolate, blunt, ± papillose, not striolate, external surface with low trabeculae at base; endostome basal membrane low, segments absent, cilia absent. Spores 18–24 µm, smooth to roughened.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America (Guatemala)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (New Zealand).</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 18 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The temperate-tropical genus Lindbergia is distinguished from other members of Leskeaceae by leaves that are wide-spreading to squarrose when moist, short laminal cells, and more or less erect capsules with the endostome reduced to a low membrane. The pseudoparaphyllia are few and foliose, or absent; the leaves are more or less decurrent and concave; the seta is yellow-brown; the capsule is brownish and narrower at the mouth; the exostome teeth are yellow and connate at the base; and the endostome is finely papillose.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems subjulaceous when dry, often curved; brood branches absent; costae broad, extending nearly to apex; medial laminal cells indistinctly 1-papillose</description>
      <determination>1. Lindbergia mexicana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems not subjulaceous when dry, ± straight; brood branches often present; costae slender, 1/2 – 2/3 leaf length; medial laminal cells bluntly 1-papillose</description>
      <determination>2. Lindbergia brachyptera</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <references>
    <reference>Crum, H. A. 1956. Lindbergia in North America. Bryologist 59: 203–212.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
