<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">leskeaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper in P. Bruch and W. P. Schimper" date="unknown">pseudoleskea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Lindberg) Kindberg" date="1894">patens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Canad. Rec. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 20. 1894</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>F</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family leskeaceae;genus pseudoleskea;species patens</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lescuraea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lindberg" date="unknown">patens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Meddeland. Soc. Fauna Fl. Fenn.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14: 75. 1888 (as Lesquereuxia)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized, in thin mats, dark green, olive green, black-green, or rarely yellow-green. Stems with branches slender to robust, julaceous, apices sometimes curving up; central strand present; paraphyllia many, filamentous to foliose, not branched. Leaves appressed to julaceous when dry, erect-spreading to patent when moist, dull, ovate, asymmetric, not or rarely falcate, (0.6–)0.7–1 mm; margins recurved proximally; apex abruptly acute to rarely short-acuminate, hair-point absent; costa not reaching acumen, green to orange-green, somewhat sinuate, &lt;terminal abaxial cells not or weakly projecting, not abaxially strongly dentate&gt;; alar cells quadrate to transversely elongate, region large; medial laminal cells quadrate, to 18 µm, 1(–2):1, opaque, moderately to strongly low rounded papillose over lumen or papillae sometimes off-centered, walls incrassate, not pitted; proximal juxtacostal cells usually shorter than medial, walls pitted or not. Capsule inclined, asymmetric, 0.5–2 mm; endostome basal membrane 1/3–1/2 exostome length, segments shorter than exostome, cilia well developed. Spores 10–14 µm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature summer (Jul-Aug).</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shaded to exposed rock and outcrops, mineral soil, near streams;</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate to high elevations (900-3500 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., N.S.; Alaska, Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., Nev., Oreg., Utah, Wash., Wyo.; Eurasia.</description>
  <discussion>Pseudoleskea patens is relatively small and usually dull, dark, or olive green, with short laminal cells with rounded centrally located papillae; it differs from P. tribulosa by the recurved margins, weaker and lower laminal cell papillae lacking projecting apical salient, larger leaves with stronger plicae, and lack of the Morningstar-shaped projections of the abaxial apex cells of the costa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
