<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert E. Magill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">PTERIGYNANDRACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>Family PTERIGYNANDRACEAE</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>59.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, in wiry wefts, prostrate mats, or threadlike, dark or olive green to yellowish. Stems erect to ± creeping, freely and irregularly branched to subpinnate; paraphyllia few or absent; pseudoparaphyllia foliose. Leaves erect to erect-spreading or occasionally squarrose, often homomallous, usually imbricate, concave, stem leaves often somewhat larger than branch leaves; margins entire, serrulate, or subentire; apex usually acuminate; ecostate or costa single, double, or 2-fid, short or to mid leaf; alar cells not or weakly differentiated; medial laminal cells quadrate, rhomboidal, or oblong-rhomboidal, smooth or papillose. Sexual condition dioicous. Capsule erect or horizontal, short-cylindric; operculum short-rostrate or conic, cucullate; peristome double.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate and tropical regions.</description>
  <discussion>Genera 6, species 28 (4 genera, 8 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Five of the genera of Pterigynandraceae are restricted to the Northern Hemisphere, including all genera found in the flora area. The one exception, Trachyphyllum A. Gepp, is widely distributed in tropical and subtropical areas throughout Africa, central parts of South America, and southern Asia.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices long-piliferous; ecostate or occasionally costae double, short; margins entire</description>
      <determination>1. Iwatsukiella , p. 367</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apices obtuse, acute, apiculate, or acuminate; costae single, double, or 2-fid, short, to mid leaf, or almost ecostate; margins serrulate, serrate, or dentate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves oblong-elliptic; laminal cells oblong-rhombic, prorulose; capsules erect</description>
      <determination>2. Pterigynandrum , p. 367</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ovate to broadly ovate; laminal cells quadrate or rhomboidal, papillose, prorulose, or smooth; capsules erect to horizontal.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costae single, short, usually 2-fid, or double to mid leaf; capsules horizontal, short-cylindric, curved</description>
      <determination>3. Heterocladium , p. 368</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costae short, usually double or indistinct; capsules erect to nearly horizontal, cylindric, symmetric</description>
      <determination>4. Myurella , p. 370</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
