<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hornschuch ex Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="1849">alpestre</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 75, plate 213. 1849</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus orthotrichum;species alpestre</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="James" date="unknown">alpestre</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Lesquereux &amp; James" date="unknown">majus</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">O.</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="James" date="unknown">alpestre</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(James) Grout" date="unknown">watsonii</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">O.</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">occidentale</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">O.</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">watsonii</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 0.5–2.3 cm. Stem leaves loosely erect-appressed and ± loosely twisted when dry, elongate- to ovate-lanceolate, 2–3.5 mm; margins revolute to below apex, entire; apex sharply acute, sometimes acuminate, cuspidate, or apiculate; basal laminal cells long-rectangular to rectangular, walls thin, sometimes nodose at insertion; distal cells 9–14 µm, 1-stratose, papillae 2 or 3 per cell, conic or 2-fid, large. Specialized asexual reproduction on leaves. Sexual condition gonioautoicous. Seta to 1.4 mm. Capsule 1/2–3/4 emergent, sometimes almost exserted, oblong-ovate when mature, oblong to short-cylindric when old and dry, to 1.4 mm, strongly 8-ribbed 2/3 to entire length, constricted below mouth when dry; stomata immersed, &lt;1/2 covered by subsidiary cells, cells projecting, inner walls thickened&gt;; peristome double; prostome absent; exostome teeth 8, reflexed, densely and evenly papillose, striate-reticulate distally; endostome segments 8 or 16, well developed, of 1 or 2 rows of cells, smooth or finely roughened. Calyptra oblong, smooth, ± hairy, hairs strongly papillose. Spores 10–15 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rock, trees, base of trees, moist crevices of large boulders, moist pine and deciduous forests;</description>
  <description type="elevation">high elevations (2100-3000 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; Alta., B.C., Nfld. and Labr., Ont., Yukon; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mich., Mont., Nev., N.Mex., Oreg., S.Dak., Utah, Wash., Wyo.; Europe; Asia; Pacific Islands (New Zealand).</description>
  <discussion>Orthotrichum alpestre is distinguished by the highly papillose distal laminal cells; slightly twisted, sharply pointed leaves; calyptra with papillose hairs; absence of prostome; and papillose or papillose-reticulate exostome. The endostome is always present in mature capsules and, because of enlarged cross walls, has a shiny appearance. The capsule is usually oblong and strangulate, although the shape depends on age. In some specimens, the capsule is short-cylindric and not much constricted below the mouth. The stomata are found just below mid capsule.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
