<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Howard A. Crum†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">thuidiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper in P. Bruch and W. P. Schimper" date="unknown">THUIDIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in P. Bruch and W. P. Schimper, Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 157, plates 481 – 486. 1852</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family thuidiaceae;genus THUIDIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Thuja and Latin -idium , diminutive, alluding to branched habit]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants large. Stems creeping to arched-ascending, 2- or 3-pinnate; paraphyllia mostly foliose, lanceolate or filiform-branched; axillary hairs 2–6(–7)-celled. Stem leaves ovate; margins plane, reflexed, or revolute, papillose-serrulate proximally, often serrulate distally by projecting cell ends; costa ending before apex; laminal cells rounded- to oblong-hexagonal, rhombic, or elliptic, coarsely 1-papillose abaxially, papillae sometimes 2-fid, appearing multipapillose. Branch leaves ovate; margins incurved, erect, or recurved, entire to denticulate; apex usually acute; costa ending before apex, not covered with cells apically; laminal cells rounded, hexagonal, elliptic, or oblong-rhombic, 1-papillose. Sexual condition dioicous; perichaetial leaves lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, margins sometimes ciliate, costa ending near apex, laminal cells smooth or somewhat papillose. Seta smooth or rarely papillose. Capsule inclined to horizontal, curved-cylindric, asymmetric; annulus 2–4-seriate; operculum conic or rostrate from convex-conic base; endostome segments not perforate, cilia in groups of 2–4.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia.</description>
  <discussion>Species ca. 230 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Thuidium is characterized by abundant, 2- or 3-pinnate paraphyllia; dioicous sexuality; dimorphic stem and branch leaves with short, thick-walled cells that are papillose abaxially and nearly always 1-papillose; stem leaves with base ± plicate and laminal cells ± uniform; apical cells of branch leaves usually truncate and multipapillose; and setae nearly always smooth. The capsule is smooth, with a short neck. The genus is treated here in a sense exclusive of Abietinella, Cyrto-hypnum, and Rauiella (see W. R. Buck and H. A. Crum 1990). Abietinella is relatively robust and has 1-pinnate branching, abundant paraphyllia, dioicous inflorescences, laminal cells 1-papillose on both surfaces, and 3- or 4-celled, brown axillary hairs. Cyrto-hypnum and Rauiella are small with autoicous inflorescences, paraphyllia short and not much branched, and laminal cells papillose on both surfaces (most commonly multipapillose). Cyrto-hypnum has mostly 2-pinnate branching, 2-celled axillary hairs, leaves incurved when dry, laminal cells plane, and setae often roughened. Rauiella has 1-pinnate branching, 3-celled axillary hairs, leaves not incurved when dry, strongly bulging laminal cells, and smooth setae.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually 3-pinnate; branch leaf apical cell acute, smooth</description>
      <determination>1. Thuidium tamariscinum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually 2-pinnate; branch leaf apical cell truncate, multipapillose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves incurved basally and spreading apically when dry, distinctly plicate; costae nearly filling acumen; paraphyllia papillose at cell ends</description>
      <determination>2. Thuidium recognitum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves ± erect when dry, not or somewhat plicate; costae not filling acumen; paraphyllia papillose at sides of cells or cell ends.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaf apices short-pointed; margins plane or sometimes reflexed basally; distal laminal cells appearing 1 – 3-papillose because papillae 2-fid</description>
      <determination>3. Thuidium alleniorum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaf apices acuminate; margins revolute throughout; laminal cells coarsely 1-papillose, not appearing multipapillose, papillae sometimes 2-fid</description>
      <determination>4. Thuidium delicatulum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
