<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hoffmann ex Bridel" date="1801">cupulatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Recent.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(2): 25. 1801</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>F</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus orthotrichum;species cupulatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">leiodon</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">O.</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lesquereux" date="unknown">utahense</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 1.2 cm. Stem leaves erect-appressed when dry, ovate-lanceolate to oblong-lanceolate, 2.5–4 mm; margins recurved or revolute to near apex, entire; apex acute or rarely narrowly obtuse; basal laminal cells long- to short-rectangular, walls thin, not nodose; distal cells 8–12 µm, 1-stratose, rarely 2-stratose in streaks, papillae 2 or 3 per cell, 2-fid and large, or sometimes conic and small. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition gonioautoicous. Seta 0.5–1 mm. Capsule immersed to 1/2 emergent when dry, ovate, 1.2–1.6 mm, 16-ribbed, constricted below mouth when dry; stomata immersed; peristome single, rarely double; prostome usually present; exostome teeth 16, usually absent when capsule is old, erect, spreading-reflexed with age, papillose-striate or papillose-reticulate; endostome segments absent or rarely 8, not well developed, of 1 row of cells, &lt;short&gt;, smooth. Calyptra oblong to oblong-conic, smooth, hairy, hairs papillose. Spores 9–16 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Calcareous and large boulders in coniferous forests, dry areas of Pinus ponderosa forests, dry cliff faces in canyons;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to high elevations (100-3000 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C., Ont.; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., Nev., Oreg., S.Dak., Tex., Utah, Wash., Wyo.; Mexico (Nuevo León); Europe; Asia; n Africa.</description>
  <discussion>Orthotrichum cupulatum is extremely variable but can be distinguished by: leaves ovate-lanceolate, broadly but sharply acute, and usually 1-stratose or occasionally partially 2-stratose; laminal cell papillae usually large and 2-fid, but if small and conic then the leaf is 1-stratose; leaf margins never thicker than lamina; peristome teeth always 16, erect or spreading, and yellow-brown; and capsule 16-ribbed, sometimes with eight short and eight long ribs. The stomata are found in one or two rows mid capsule.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
