<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Wilfred B. Schofield†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">brachytheciaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bescherelle" date="unknown">MYUROCLADA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Sci. Nat., Bot., sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7, 17: 379. 1893</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brachytheciaceae;genus MYUROCLADA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek mys , mouse, oura , tail, and clados , branch, alluding to resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>12.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized, in loose mats, pale silvery green. Stems creeping to erect-arcuate, &lt;often attenuate&gt;, strongly julaceous, unbranched to weakly irregularly branched, branches terete-foliate; central strand present; pseudoparaphyllia orbicular-triangular; axillary hairs of 2–4 cells. Stem leaves erect-appressed, crowded, imbricate, orbicular to broadly ovate, concave, not or indistinctly plicate; base moderately decurrent; margins nearly entire to serrulate; apex very broadly acute to rounded, short-apiculate when young, blunt when mature; costa to mid leaf or slightly beyond, moderately stout, terminal spine absent; alar cells smaller than basal juxtacostal cells; laminal cells short-rhombic to rhombic. Branch leaves similar. Sexual condition dioicous. [Seta red-brown, smooth. Capsule inclined to horizontal, nearly black when old, oblong, weakly curved; annulus separating in fragments; operculum long-conic, obliquely rostrate; peristome xerocastique, perfect. Calyptra naked. Spores 12–16 µm].</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alaska, e Asia (Japan, Korea, Russia); introduced in Europe. The above description of the sporophyte is from Asian material.</description>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>The above description of the sporophyte is from Asian material.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Steere, W. C. and W. B. Schofield. 1956. Myuroclada, a genus new to North America. Bryologist 59: 1–5.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
