<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Sullivant &amp; Lesquereux in W. S. Sullivant" date="1874">hallii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. S. Sullivant, Icon. Musc., suppl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>63, plate 45. 1874</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus orthotrichum;species hallii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>16.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 2.5 cm. &lt;Stems erect; leaves similar on vegetative and fertile stems&gt;. Stem leaves loosely erect-appressed when dry, elongate-lanceolate to lanceolate, 1.7–3.5 mm; margins revolute proximally, recurved to almost plane near apex, entire; apex ± narrowly obtuse, rarely bluntly acute; basal laminal cells rectangular to short-rectangular, grading to quadrate at margins, walls thin, not nodose; distal cells 7–13 µm, 2-stratose, rarely with few 1-stratose areas, papillae 1–3 per cell, conic, small; &lt;marginal cells mostly to completely 2-stratose&gt;. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition gonioautoicous. Seta 0.5–1 mm. Capsule 1/2 emergent when dry, immersed when moist, oblong or oblong-ovate, 1–1.8 mm, strongly 8-ribbed to mid capsule or entire length, rarely with 8 very short intermediate ribs, sometimes constricted below mouth when dry; stomata immersed; peristome double; prostome present, occasionally rudimentary; exostome teeth 8, sometimes irregularly split to 16, incurved becoming spreading or rarely reflexed when old, coarsely striate-reticulate or striate-papillose; endostome segments 8, not well developed, of 1 row of cells, &lt;short&gt;, finely longitudinally striate. Calyptra oblong, smooth, sparsely hairy, hairs papillose. Spores 10–17 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rock, usually limestone or calcareous sandstone, granite, quartzite, basalt, trunks of deciduous trees, open pine forests, spruce-fir forests, deciduous scrub oak-maple forests, vertical canyon walls, shaded cliff faces;</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate to high elevations (200-3000 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., Nev., N.Mex., S.Dak., Utah, Wyo.</description>
  <discussion>Orthotrichum hallii is distinguished by leaves that are completely or nearly 2-stratose in their distal portion, and emergent, oblong, 8-ribbed capsules. The peristome teeth vary from ridged-striate to papillose-striate; the proximal portions of the teeth are often coarsely papillose with the distal portions having striae mixed with papillae, and the papillae are always small and conic.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
