<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Michael S. Ignatov,William D. Reese†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">brachytheciaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Manuel" date="unknown">ZELOMETEORIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Hattori Bot. Lab.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>43: 110, figs. 5 – 9. 1978</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brachytheciaceae;genus ZELOMETEORIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek zelos , emulation, and genus Meteorium , alluding to similarity ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>19.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants large, in intricate tangles, sometimes distally filiform, green or more commonly yellowish to brownish, blackish in old parts. Stems both creeping and pendent flexuose, terete-foliate, unevenly branched, sometimes fairly regularly pinnate, branches terete-foliate; central strand weak, sometimes absent; pseudoparaphyllia broadly triangular; axillary hairs of 3 or 4 cells. Stem leaves in dense foliage erect-spreading to squarrose from clasping base, broadly ovate; base cordate; margins subentire to serrulate; apex acute to acuminate; costa to 60–80% leaf length, slender, terminal abaxial tooth small; laminal cells linear; basal juxtacostal cells short-rectangular; leaves in loose foliage erect to erect-spreading from clasping base, narrowly to broadly ovate; base auriculate; apex abruptly acuminate; costa to 30–70% leaf length, terminal spine absent; submarginal alar cells in leaf corners, usually only 2–4, sometimes slightly enlarged and pellucid; laminal cells linear; basal juxtacostal cells shorter. Branch leaves not differentiated. Sexual condition dioicous; perichaetial leaves erect, acumen erect to spreading, costa extending to base of acumen. [Seta reddish, &lt;short&gt;, rough. Capsule erect, brownish, cylindric, straight; annulus separating by fragments; operculum conic-rostrate; peristome hygrocastique, modified. Calyptra &lt;mitrate&gt;, pilose. Spores 14–23 µm].</description>
  <description type="distribution">Florida</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">c Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (Galapagos Islands).</description>
  <discussion>Species 5 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Zelometeorium has long been treated as a member of the tropical and subtropical family Meteoriaceae, although its closest relative, Meteoridium, was considered a member of Brachytheciaceae by some authors (M. A. Lewis 1992). Results of molecular phylogenetics (M. S. Ignatov and S. Huttunen 2002) definitely indicate the position of both within Brachytheciaceae, a sister family to Meteoriaceae. Sporophytes are very rare, and the description is based on Latin American plants.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Manuel, M. G. 1977. A monograph of the genus Zelometeorium Manuel, gen. nov. (Bryopsida: Meteoriaceae). J. Hattori Bot. Lab. 43: 107–126.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
