<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="W. R. Buck &amp; Ireland" date="unknown">stereophyllaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Mitten" date="unknown">STEREOPHYLLUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Proc. Linn. Soc., Bot., suppl.:</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>117. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family stereophyllaceae;genus STEREOPHYLLUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek stereos , thick, and phyllon , leaf]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Müller Hal.) Hampe" date="unknown">Glossophyllum</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Hypnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Müller Hal." date="unknown">Glossophyllum</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in thin to dense mats, pale to yellow-green, sometimes brownish, dull. Stems with central strand absent or poorly developed; axillary hair apical cells 4. Stem and branch leaves similar, stiff, close, imbricate and somewhat contorted when dry, erect-spreading when moist, oblong-ovate to nearly lingulate, symmetric, not plicate; margins plane, entire or serrulate near apex; apex abruptly acute to obtuse, sometimes apiculate; costa 2/3–3/4 leaf length; laminal cell walls thick; medial and distal cells quadrate to rhomboidal, 1-papillose over lumina on both surfaces or sometimes smooth. Perigonia with leaves costate. Perichaetia at base of stems, leaves oblong-lanceolate, costate, proximal laminal cells rectangular, distal cells linear-flexuose. Seta orange to reddish, straight to somewhat flexuose. Capsule cernuous or rarely erect, orange to brown, ellipsoid to ovoid; exothecial cell walls thin; annulus persistent, 2- or 3-seriate, cell walls firm; operculum short-rostrate, sometimes oblique; exostome teeth shouldered, internal surface projecting; endostome finely papillose, basal membrane high, segments almost as long as exostome teeth, cilia 1–3, shorter than segments. Spores spheric to ovoid, 12–24 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sc</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (Philippines)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 2 (1 in the flora): sc, se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa, Pacific Islands (Philippines), Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>sc, se United States, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa, Pacific Islands (Philippines), Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The second species in the genus, Stereophyllum linisii Enroth &amp; B. C. Tan, was described in 2007 from the Philippines.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
