<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Piers Majestyk</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">MYRINIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>Family MYRINIACEAE</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>64.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized, in loose or dense mats, yellowish or sometimes dark olive green. Stems creeping, pinnate or irregularly branched; branches horizontally spreading, short, blunt, terete-foliate to sometimes slightly flattened, often flagelliform-attenuate; paraphyllia absent. Stem and branch leaves similar or differentiated, loosely appressed when dry, somewhat spreading when moist, ovate to ovate-lanceolate, concave; base decurrent or not; margins entire or serrulate; apex bluntly acute, obtuse, or acuminate; ecostate, costa double and short, or single, faint, 1/4–1/2 leaf length, sometimes unevenly 2-fid distally; laminal cells smooth or mammillose abaxially by projecting distal ends, walls firm; proximal cells oblate to quadrate near margins; medial and distal cells short-rhomboidal or oblong-rhomboidal. Sexual condition autoicous or phyllodioicous; perigonial leaves ovate, short-acute, ecostate, proximal laminal cells bulging-rectangular, medial and distal cells rhombic to linear; perichaetial leaves sheathing, outer leaves ovate, short, inner leaves oblong-lanceolate, ecostate, proximal laminal cells rectangular to long-hexagonal, medial and distal cells rhombic to linear. Seta yellow to orangish red, elongate, twisted. Capsule erect to suberect, light to dark brown, oblong to oblong-cylindric, smooth; annulus absent; operculum convex-conic or obliquely conic-rostrate, blunt to short-pointed; peristome double; exostome teeth 16, bordered, yellow, cross striolate in proximal 3/4, slightly trabeculate, lightly papillose distally or nearly smooth; endostome basal membrane low, segments 16, yellow, equaling exostome length, lightly papillose, cilia rudimentary or absent. Calyptra cucullate, smooth, naked. Spores spheric, papillose, yellow.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia.</description>
  <discussion>Genera 7, species ca. 30 (2 genera, 2 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins entire; medial and distal laminal cells short-rhomboidal; costae single</description>
      <determination>1. Myrinia , p. 475</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins serrulate; medial and distal laminal cells oblong-rhomboidal; ecostate or costae double</description>
      <determination>2. Schwetschkeopsis , p. 475</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
