<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">fontinalaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper ex Cardot" date="unknown">BRACHELYMA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Soc. Sci. Nat. Math. Cherbourg</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>28: 37, 130. 1892</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>* [Greek brachys , short, and elyma , veil, alluding to diminutive calyptra] E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fontinalaceae;genus BRACHELYMA</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized, dull. Stems prostrate or pendent; rhizoids from clusters of initials abaxial to leaf insertions, not or weakly branched; axillary hairs 240–360 µm. Leaves distant proximally, crowded distally, oblong-lanceolate to lanceolate, keeled, conduplicate; margins sometimes narrowly reflexed, entire or serrulate proximally, serrulate to serrate at apex; apex obtuse to acute; costa subpercurrent to percurrent; alar cells quadrate or rectangular, slightly enlarged, walls firm; medial laminal cells rhomboidal, linear-rhomboidal, or elongate. Perigonia lateral in leaf axils. Perichaetia with leaves elongate, sheathing setae. Seta 0.7–1.5 mm. Capsule immersed, oblong-cylindric to oval; annulus massive; operculum long-conic or occasionally obliquely rostrate; endostome trellis imperfect. Calyptra cucullate, covering only operculum. Spores 13–18 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c, se United States.</description>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Brachelyma is semi-aquatic; as with many semi-aquatic mosses, the plants can be slender to almost robust. Distinctive features include long, narrow, keeled-conduplicate, sometimes obscurely bordered leaves; strong, single costae; firm-walled, non-bulging alar cells; serrate to serrulate distal leaf margins; often rhomboidal distal laminal cells; long, sheathing perichaetial leaves, and short setae with completely immersed capsules. Curiously, the surface cells of the setae are quadrate to oblate; the result of simple cell elongation in these cells would give the Brachelyma setae the same length as the Dichelyma setae, as well as immersed or exserted capsules.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
