<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Austin" date="1870">lescurii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Musci Appalach.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>163. 1870</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus orthotrichum;species lescurii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>21.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 1 cm, &lt;dull&gt;. Stem leaves stiff, erect-appressed when dry, narrowly lanceolate to lanceolate, 2–2.5 mm; margins revolute to just below apex, entire; apex acute; basal laminal cells quadrate to rectangular, walls thin, not nodose; distal cells 8–12 µm, 1-stratose, papillae 1–3 per cell, conic, small. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition gonioautoicous. Seta 0.5–0.7 mm. Capsule immersed, ovate, 1.1–1.8 mm, distinctly 8-ribbed, constricted below mouth when dry; stomata immersed; peristome single; prostome small or absent; exostome teeth 8, incurved-erect to spreading-recurved when dry, finely, densely papillose; endostome segments absent. Calyptra oblong-conic, smooth, hairy, hairs papillose. Spores 12–16 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Calcareous rock;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations (0- 1500 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont.; Conn., Ga., Ind., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Mo., N.J., N.Y., Vt., Va., W. Va.</description>
  <discussion>Orthotrichum lescurii is sparsely distributed across eastern North America. The species is distinguished from others of Orthotrichum that occur on calcareous rock in eastern and central North America by strongly revolute leaf margins and immersed, ovate, strongly 8-ribbed, strangulate capsules. Orthotrichum anomalum has exserted capsules, O. parvulum has plane, 1-stratose margins, and O. strangulatum has multistratose leaf margins. The stomata in O. lescurii are found in the proximal half of the capsule, partially covered by subsidiary cells.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
