<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="F. Lara" date="2008">norrisii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>111: 670, figs. 1 – 12. 2008</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus orthotrichum;species norrisii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>23.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 1.5 cm. Stem leaves stiff, erect-appressed when dry, narrowly lanceolate to lanceolate-ligulate, 1.3–3 mm; margins recurved, becoming incurved or plane at apex, entire; apex narrowly obtuse, acute to notched and channeled; basal laminal cells rectangular, occasionally polygonal, walls thin to occasionally thick, rarely nodose; distal cells 10–16 µm, 1-stratose, papillae 2 or 3 per cell, simple, low. Specialized asexual reproduction sometimes present by gemmae on leaves. Sexual condition gonioautoicous. &lt;Vaginula with hairs present&gt;. Seta 0.5–1 mm. Capsule emergent, cylindric when dry, 1.5–2 mm, slightly 8-ribbed entire length, &lt;ribs thin, delicate when dry&gt;, constricted below mouth when dry; stomata immersed, &lt;1/2 to completely covered by subsidiary cells, cells projecting, inner walls thickened&gt;; peristome double; prostome absent; exostome teeth 8, reflexed, finely papillose; endostome segments 8, well developed, of 1 (or 2) rows of cells, smooth to faintly papillose. Calyptra oblong-conic, smooth, hairy distally, hairs smooth. Spores 14–18 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">epiphytic in woodlands and chaparral</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate elevations (200–900 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Orthotrichum norrisii is somewhat similar to O. tenellum, both species having a well-developed peristome of eight reflexed exostome teeth and eight long-lasting endostome segments. Also, both species occur on tree trunks in Mediterranean-like climates of California. Orthotrichum norrisii differs in having some leaves with irregular, channeled apices (versus mostly obtuse in O. tenellum) and slightly ribbed capsules (compared to thick, broad ribs in O. tenellum). The stomata are found in the proximal third of the capsule.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
