<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ireland" date="unknown">pleuroziopsaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kindberg ex E. Britton" date="unknown">pleuroziopsis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Weinmann) Kindberg ex E. Britton" date="unknown">ruthenica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9: 39. 1906</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>F</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pleuroziopsaceae;genus pleuroziopsis;species ruthenica</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Hypnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Weinmann" date="unknown">ruthenicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Imp. Naturalistes Moscou</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 485. 1845</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Girgensohnia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Weinmann) Kindberg" date="unknown">ruthenica</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants light green, frondose-dendroid. Stems with primary stems stoloniferous, branches 1.5–3 cm, attenuate, branchlets 4–7 mm, attenuate; lamellae apical cells round, elliptic, square, or rectangular. Stem leaves clasping, ovate, smooth or wrinkled; base long-decurrent, 1-stratose; apex apiculate or obtuse to acute; medial laminal cells vermicular, 40–81 × 5–7 µm. Proximal branch leaves gradually grading distally into leaves similar to branchlet leaves; median branchlet leaves plicate; base long-decurrent; margins plane or narrowly recurved near base, serrate to entire proximally, irregularly and strongly toothed to serrate distally; apex broadly acute; medial laminal cells 28–45 × 5–7 µm. Sexual condition dioicous; archegonial and antheridial plants similar, perigonial and perichaetial buds on stem near branches; perigonial leaves broadly ovate, acute; perichaetial leaves ovate, apex acute to acuminate. Seta smooth. Capsule red, not contracted below mouth. Calyptra cucullate, covering 1/2 capsule.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Humus on ground or logs along creeks and rivers, moist, shaded habitats;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations (10-600 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Alaska, Wash.; e Asia.</description>
  <other_name type="past_name">ruthenicum</other_name>
  <discussion>Pleuroziopsis ruthenica is a distinctive species, somewhat reminiscent of Climacium; both have erect secondary stems arising from a creeping primary stem and occur in wet habitats. Pleuroziopsis is lighter green and more slender in appearance, with a frondose-dendroid habit, an ovoid, arcuate, cernuous capsule with a hypnaceous peristome and exostome teeth with fine cross striolations; Climacium has a coarser dendroid habit and a cylindric, straight, erect capsule with narrow, densely papillose endostome segments. Another important feature distinguishing Pleuroziopsis from Climacium is the nature of branching. In Pleuroziopsis, the plants are erect from a creeping primary stem, as in Climacium, but they are also frondose-dendroid, that is, they are flattened and the secondary and tertiary branches are divided, often several times, so the plants are noticeably frondose. In Climacium, the plants are not flattened; the branches arise around the distal end of the erect secondary stem and seldom, if ever, produce branchlets.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
