<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert R. Ireland Jr.</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">hypnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Ireland" date="unknown">BUCKIELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 55, figs. 1, 2. 2001</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hypnaceae;genus BUCKIELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For William Russel Buck, b. 1950, American bryologist, and Latin - ella , diminutive]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants large, in thin to loose mats, light green or whitish, sometimes yellowish, dull or somewhat glossy. Stems creeping or sometimes erect, sparingly and irregularly branched, occasionally simple; hyalodermis present, sometimes indistinct, central strand sometimes present; pseudoparaphyllia absent. Stem and branch leaves similar, imbricate, &lt;somewhat contorted, strongly undulate, especially near apex&gt;, ovate to ovate-lanceolate, rarely oblong-lanceolate, not plicate; base weakly decurrent; margins plane, entire or usually serrulate to serrate at apex; apex acute to acuminate, rarely somewhat obtuse; costa double, ending just beyond base, rarely one branch reaching 1/3 leaf length; alar cells differentiated, rectangular; laminal cells papillose, &lt;papillae minute, granular, cuticular, much more abundant on abaxial surface&gt;. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition dioicous; perichaetial leaves narrowly ovate- to oblong-lanceolate, apex acute to acuminate. Seta dark red, reddish, or light brown. Capsule inclined to pendulous, cylindric, arcuate or sometimes straight, wrinkled and contracted below mouth when dry; annulus 1- or 2-seriate, deciduous, cells large; operculum conic to rostrate; peristome double; exostome teeth with fine striations between lamellae proximally, papillose distally; endostome basal membrane rather high, segments broad, keeled, cilia 2 or 3, as long or nearly as long as segments. Calyptra naked. Spores globose to ovoid, smooth or minutely papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Europe, Asia, Pacific Islands (Hawaii, New Guinea).</description>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Buckiella occurs in terrestrial habitats in temperate, boreal, and rarely tropical woods. Buckiella draytonii (Sullivant) Ireland is endemic to the Hawaiian Islands.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
