<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Masanobu Higuchi</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">hypnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Brotherus in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="unknown">GOLLANIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl, Nat. Pflanzenfam.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>231[I,3]: 1054, fig. 755. 1908</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hypnaceae;genus GOLLANIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For William Gollan, 1855–1905, Scottish superintendent of Edinburgh Botanic Garden and collector in Kashmir]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Brotherus" date="unknown">Elmeriobryum</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants moderately large, densely caespitose, golden yellow to golden brown, somewhat glossy. Stems creeping, densely or rarely loosely pinnate; hyalodermis absent, central strand present, weak; pseudoparaphyllia foliose, lanceolate, never filamentous. Stem and branch leaves with dorsal, lateral, and ventral stem leaves often different in shape and size. Stem leaves closely imbricate, narrowly lanceolate, plicate; base not or short- to long-decurrent; margins recurved at base, entire to subentire proximally, serrate, serrulate, or rarely entire distally; apex narrowly acute [blunt]; costa double; alar cells differentiated, subquadrate to rectangular; laminal cells smooth, &lt;walls thick; medial cells linear&gt;. Branch leaves much smaller, narrower. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition dioicous; inner perichaetial leaves oblong-lanceolate, apex filiform-acuminate. [Seta reddish brown. Capsule inclined to horizontal, ovoid to cylindric, straight or weakly curved, not or weakly contracted below mouth; annulus little differentiated; operculum conic, sometimes short-rostrate; peristome double; exostome teeth with external surface transversely smooth to striolate proximally, papillose distally; endostome basal membrane 1/2 exostome teeth length, segments keeled, cilia 2–4. Calyptra naked. Spores rounded, finely papillose].</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw North America, Asia (Bhutan, China, India, Indonesia, Japan, Korea, Nepal, Pakistan, e Russia, Taiwan), Pacific Islands (Philippines).</description>
  <discussion>Species 20 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Higuchi, M. 1985. A taxonomic revision of the genus Gollania Broth. (Musci). J. Hattori Bot. Lab. 59: 1–77.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
