<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">hypnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">hypnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">curvifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>285, plate 75, figs. 4–9. 1801</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hypnaceae;genus hypnum;species curvifolium</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Stereodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Mitten" date="unknown">curvifolius</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>6</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized to large, light green to yellow-green, &lt;glossy&gt;. Stems 4–10 cm, orange-brown to reddish, procumbent to suberect, sparsely branched, regularly pinnate, branches 1.5 cm; hyalodermis absent, central strand weakly differentiated; pseudoparaphyllia foliose. Stem leaves falcate-secund, ovate, narrowing to apex, 1.5–2.5 × 0.7–0.8 mm; base slightly decurrent, auriculate, sometimes only on one side; margins plane, sinuate to entire basally, gradually weakly toothed near apex; acumen relatively broad; costa double, short; alar cells &lt;few&gt;, region well defined, &lt;often excavate&gt;, in 1–3 rows across base; basal laminal cells broader than medial cells, pigmented, walls not porose; medial cells 70–80 × 4–5 µm. Sexual condition dioicous; &lt;inner perichaetial leaves lanceolate to subulate&gt;. Seta orange-yellow to brownish when mature, 2–4.5 cm. Capsule inclined to horizontal, reddish, obovoid-cylindric, 2.5–3 mm; annulus broad, 2-seriate; operculum conic; endostome cilia 2 or 3.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature Jul-Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Terrestrial, decaying logs in woodlands, rock, peatlands;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to high elevations (0-2000 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.B., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que.; Ala., Ark., Conn., Del., D.C., Ga., Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Miss., Mo., Nebr., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Okla., Pa., R.I., S.C., Tenn., Tex., Vt., Va., W. Va., Wis.</description>
  <discussion>Hypnum curvifolium might be confused with H. lindbergii; it differs in its more plumose branching, more circinate leaves, and lack of stem hyalodermis. Also, H. lindbergii has a more extensive and often decurrent alar region. Hypnum imponens is distinguishable by its usually smaller habit size and toothed pseudoparaphyllia. Hypnum curvifolium has stems 0.5–3 mm wide; the leaves are curved to the insertion with enlarged, hyaline alar cells; the supra-alar cells are ovoid to triangular and smaller than the alar cells; the laminal cells are sometimes projecting abaxially at the distal ends; the capsules are plicate when dry; and the endostome cilia are nodulose. Sporophytes are produced in summer.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
