<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">hypnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper in P. Bruch and W. P. Schimper" date="unknown">orthothecium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bryhn" date="1906">acuminatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryoph. Itin. Pol. Norv.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>126, plate 1, fig. 4. 1906</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hypnaceae;genus orthothecium;species acuminatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>5</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants very small, in tufts, brownish proximally, golden green distally. Stems 3–4 cm, 0.5 mm wide, erect to ascending, sparsely branched. Leaves closely appressed-imbricate, straight, broadly ovate, not or slightly plicate, 0.6–0.8 mm; margins plane, slightly serrate distally; apex abruptly very short-acuminate to apiculate; ecostate; basal laminal cells shorter than medial cells, deeply pigmented; medial cells oblong to oblong-rhombic, 35–40 × 9 µm. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sporophytes unknown.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Wet calcareous habitats, Arctic tundra;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; N.W.T., Nunavut; Alaska.</description>
  <discussion>Orthothecium acuminatum is distinguished by stems 0.5 mm wide and up to 4 cm long, with straight, broadly ovate, abruptly short-acuminate to apiculate leaves. The branches are often slender and stoloniferous, bearing minute leaves. The species is known in mainland North America only from a few localities in the Northwest Territories and one locality in Alaska. W. A. Weber (pers. comm. to R. R. Ireland) suggested that O. diminutivum (Grout) H. A. Crum &amp; L. E. Anderson, described from Colorado, is synonymous with Isopterygiopsis pulchella (Hedwig) Z. Iwatsuki.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
