<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Clayton C. Newberry</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">leucodontaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">ANTITRICHIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Recent., suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 136. 1818</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family leucodontaceae;genus ANTITRICHIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek anti , opposite, and thrix , hair, alluding to endostome segments opposite exostome teeth]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants large, in thick mats or deep wefts, yellow-green to dark green, glossy. Stems irregularly branched. Stem leaves ovate-lanceolate to cordate-ovate; base rounded to subcordate, slightly decurrent; margins revolute, serrate, serrulate, or denticulate; apex acute, acuminate, or abruptly acuminate; costa subpercurrent, with 2 or more shorter, supplementary costae at base; alar cells quadrate to transversely elongate, region extending nearly to costa and an equal distance distally; laminal cells smooth; medial cells uniformly linear-flexuose; apical cells oval-rhombic. Branch leaves similar, narrower, smaller, 2–3 × 1 mm; margins more strongly denticulate; apex narrower, flagelliform, smaller; costa weaker. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Perigonia on secondary stems or sometimes on side branches, leaves deltoid-apiculate. Perichaetia on primary stems, leaves ecostate. Seta short. Capsule exserted, cylindric, oblong-cylindric, or oblong-ovoid; annulus scant or absent, adherent; operculum oblique-rostrate; exostome teeth subulate, trabeculate or papillose; endostome basal membrane absent, segments weakly developed, narrowly subulate, papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands.</description>
  <discussion>Species 5 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The stems of Antitrichia are densely foliose and internally divided into a strong 4–6-layered cortex of incrassate cells and a medulla of loose, thin-walled cells. The branches are procumbent or pendent, somewhat plumose, and usually elongate, with deltate to subfoliose pseudoparaphyllia investing the branch buds; the central strand is rudimentary or absent. The stem leaves are concave and 2–3 × 1–1.5 mm; the basal laminal cells are rounded-quadrate to elliptic, in a region filling the basalmost angles and extending up most of the margins. The endostome segments are fragile, evanescent, and 1/2–3/4 the exostome teeth length.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves julaceous when dry; supplementary costae absent or rudimentary, length less than 6 cells; laminal cell walls not or poorly pitted</description>
      <determination>1. Antitrichia californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves erectopatent when dry; supplementary costae well developed, length more than 6 cells; laminal cell walls pitted throughout</description>
      <determination>2. Antitrichia curtipendula</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
