<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">orthotrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">orthotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Leónsky-Haapasaari &amp; D. H. Norris" date="1998">shevockii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>101: 435, figs. 1 – 23. 1998</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>E</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orthotrichaceae;genus orthotrichum;species shevockii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>38.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 1.5 cm. Stem leaves rigid, erect when dry, ligulate- to elliptic-lanceolate, to 5 mm; margins recurved from just beyond base to near apex, entire; apex obtuse to rounded-acute; basal laminal cells short-rectangular, walls thin, not nodose; distal cells 13–16 µm, 1-stratose, papillae 2 or 3 per cell, simple to 2-fid, high; &lt;marginal cells 2- or 3-stratose&gt;. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition gonioautoicous. Seta to 0.5 mm. Capsule immersed, short-cylindric to oblong-ovate, 1–2 mm, strongly 8-ribbed entire length, constricted below mouth when dry; stomata immersed, &lt;2/3 to completely covered by subsidiary cells, cells projecting, inner walls thickened&gt;; peristome double; prostome absent; exostome teeth 8, reflexed, papillose to papillose-reticulate near apex; endostome segments 8, occasionally 16, well developed, of 1 row of cells, smooth or roughened. Calyptra oblong, smooth, hairy, hairs papillose. Spores 15–18 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">dry granitic rock</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate to high elevations (1100–1600 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Orthotrichum shevockii is known only from the southern Sierra Mountains. The species is distinguished by small, blackish tufts, obtuse to bluntly acute leaf apices, strongly multipapillose distal laminal cells, 2-stratose (or more) leaf margins, and completely immersed, strongly 8-ribbed capsules with immersed stomata, reflexed exostome teeth, well-developed endostome, and papillose calyptra hairs.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
