<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Íñigo Granzow-de la Cerda</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">ANOMODONTACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>Family ANOMODONTACEAE</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>80.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to large, in dense or loose mats, glaucous, green, brown, or yellowish brown, dull. Stems creeping, sparsely to profusely branched, irregularly pinnate; paraphyllia absent. Stem and branch leaves differentiated. Stem leaves scalelike, minute; apex acute-acuminate to rounded; costa single, long, ending below apex, thick, usually pellucid, or double and short; laminal cells short. Branch leaves with costa single, ending sharply at or near apex, pellucid. Sexual condition dioicous. Seta dark to light reddish or brown, flexuose. Capsule erect, exserted; operculum conic to obliquely short-rostrate; exostome whitish yellow to pale brown, often striolate at base and papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Europe, e Asia, Africa, Pacific Islands, Australia; circumboreal areas.</description>
  <discussion>Genera 4, species ca. 20 (2 genera, 9 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves broadly ovate to lanceolate, ± abruptly narrowed mid leaf; laminal cells with papillae 1 or many</description>
      <determination>1. Anomodon , p. 629</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves ovate-lanceolate, gradually tapered from bas e to apex; laminal cells smooth</description>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
  <references>
    <reference>Granzow-de la Cerda, Í. 1997. Revision and phylogenetic study of Anomodon and Herpetineuron (Anomodontaceae, Musci). Contr. Univ. Michigan Herb. 21: 205–275.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
