<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">anomodontaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hooker &amp; Taylor" date="unknown">Anomodon</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Brit.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>79, plates 3 [near upper right], 33 [upper center left &amp; right]. 1818</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family anomodontaceae;genus Anomodon</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek, anomalos , abnormal, and odon , tooth, alluding to reduced peristome]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Dozy &amp; Molkenboer" date="unknown">Haplohymenium</taxon_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to large, ± glaucous, green to rusty brown. Stems with branches erect to arcuate, sometimes attenuate to flagellate distally; central strand cells differentiated or not; pseudoparaphyllia absent in all but 2 species. Branch leaves appressed to moderately secund or crispate when dry, complanate or erect to imbricate when moist, broadly ovate to lanceolate, ± abruptly narrowed mid leaf, not plicate proximally (somewhat plicate in A. longifolius); margins plane, sometimes undulate or revolute, entire, papillose, crenulate, serrulate, or sometimes denticulate near apex; apex rounded, obtuse, acute, or narrowly acuminate; costa usually strong, sometimes obscured by laminal cells and ending before mid leaf, sometimes discreetly, asymmetrically 2-fid at end, abaxial costa cells smooth or papillose; laminal cells hexagonal, obscure to irregular, small, papillae 1 or many, high, on both surfaces, walls thin; basal cells sometimes oblong, pellucid, smooth, walls incrassate. Perichaetial leaves well differentiated. Seta to 2.2 cm. Capsule symmetric; stomata sometimes present; peristome reduced (well developed in A. rostratus); exostome teeth white to pale brown, densely papillose, occasionally cross striolate, sometimes slightly trabeculate; endostome sometimes very reduced or absent (sect. Haplohymenium), basal membrane 2–7 cells high, segments keeled to linear and reduced or absent. Calyptra smooth to papillose or hirsute (sect. Haplohymenium). Spores 9–20(–23) µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America (Bolivia)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">s Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (New Zealand)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumboreal regions.</description>
  <discussion>Species 16 (8 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Anomodon viticulosus grows mostly on shaded calcareous outcrops, but the other species are found on tree trunks, including their base, logs, or sometimes soil or rock. Anomodon attenuatus, A. minor, and A. rostratus may grow on the same tree, with A. rugelii sometimes joining them in submontane regions. Although A. tristis may be found growing with the above species, it usually forms much thinner, more delicate mats higher on the tree. In North America, at least two species (A. attenuatus and A. rostratus) fruit profusely; A. minor and A. rugelii fruit less abundantly and perhaps less frequently, while sporophytes of A. viticulosus are extremely rare in North America (only one fertile specimen of A. viticulosus seen, none of A. tristis).</discussion>
  <discussion>Haplohymenium was created to accommodate plants that resemble Anomodon but are more slender and have a papillose calyptra with long, hyaline scattered hairs. Segregating Haplohymenium would make the rest of Anomodon paraphyletic, as Haplohymenium is a sister group of A. minor, A. rugelii, and A. viticulosus, all of which are part of subg. Anomodon (Í. Granzow-de la Cerda 1997); these taxa are more distantly related to subg. Pseudoanomodon (Limpricht) Ochyra, to which A. attenuatus and A. rostratus belong.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves long-lanceolate; apices ending in hair-point or subulalike.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems profusely branched; primary branches erect</description>
      <determination>6. Anomodon rostratus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sparingly branched; primary branches prostrate or pendulous</description>
      <determination>8. Anomodon longifolius</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves ligulate; apices rounded, obtuse, acute, or apiculate, not ending in hair-point or subulalike.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants small; stems less than 1 mm thick when dry; branch leaves less than 2.1 mm; apices often broken off; costa ending much before apex, obscured by laminal cells distally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 0.3 – 0.5 mm thick when dry; leaves 0.5 – 0.9 mm; basal laminal cells few, region not reaching margin; costa weak, obscured by laminal cells almost throughout</description>
      <determination>4. Anomodon tristis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 0.5 – 1 mm thick when dry; leaves 1.2 – 1.8( – 2.1) mm; basal laminal cells many, region reaching margin; costa moderately strong, obscured by laminal cells distally</description>
      <determination>5. Anomodon thraustus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants small to large; stems usually more than 0.8 mm thick when dry; branch leaves sometimes greater than 2 mm; apices intact; costa ending near apex, not or rarely obscured by laminal cells distally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5 .</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5 .</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants dark green to rusty brown; leaves incurved-contorted when dry; bases auriculate; costae golden yellow to rusty brown; pseudoparaphyllia present</description>
      <determination>2. Anomodon rugelii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants green to yellowish; leaves erect, imbricate, appressed or rarely slightly crisped when dry; bases broadly decurrent; costae pellucid or light green; pseudoparaphyllia absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants large; stems 1 – 1.8 mm thick when dry; leaves flexuose, secund, spreading when moist, erect when dry, greater than 2 mm</description>
      <determination>1. Anomodon viticulosus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized to large; stems usually less than 1 mm thick when dry; leaves complanate when moist, appressed when dry, usually less than 2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems not pinnate, secondary branches not attenuate, often slightly clavate at apices; perichaetia on terminal branches, beyond distalmost branching points; leaves abruptly narrowed mid leaf; apices rounded; margins entire at apex; abaxial costa cells with rounded-simple papillae in rows</description>
      <determination>3. Anomodon minor</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems irregularly pinnate, secondary branches attenuate at apices; perichaetia never present beyond distalmost branching points; leaves slightly narrowed mid leaf; apices acute, sometimes obtuse or slightly apiculate; margins sometimes denticulate at apex; abaxial costa cells smooth</description>
      <determination>7. Anomodon attenuatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
