<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">ACONITUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 532. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 236. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae;genus ACONITUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[according to Pliny, the name "aconite" is taken from the ancient Black Sea port
        Aconis]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from tubers or elongate, fascicled roots. Leaves basal and
        cauline, proximal leaves petiolate, distal leaves sessile or nearly so; cauline leaves
        alternate. Leaf blade palmately divided into 3-7 segments, ultimate segments narrowly
        elliptic or lanceolate to linear, margins incised and toothed. Inflorescences terminal,
        sometimes also axillary, 1-32(-more) racemes or panicles, to 28 cm; bracts leaflike, not
        forming involucre. Flowers bisexual, bilaterally symmetric; sepals not persistent in fruit;
        lower sepals (pendents) 2, plane, 6-20 mm; lateral sepals 2, round-reniform; upper sepal
        (hood) 1, saccate, arched, crescent-shaped or hemispheric to rounded-conic or tall and
        cylindric, usually beaked, 10-50 mm; petals 2, distinct, bearing near apex a capitate to
        coiled spur, concealed in hood, long-clawed; nectary present, on spur; stamens 25-50;
        filaments with base expanded; staminodes absent between stamens and pistils; pistils 3(-5),
        simple; ovules 10-20 per pistil; style present. Fruits follicles, aggregate, sessile,
        oblong, sides prominently transversely veined; beak terminal, straight, 2-3 mm. Seeds
        deltoid, usually with small, transverse, membranous lamellae. x=8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumboreal, southward into n Mexico and n Africa.</description>
  <number>15.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Monkshood</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">aconite</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">wolfsbane</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">aconit</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 100 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The greatest concentration of species of Aconitum is in Asia, with a smaller group
        in Europe.</discussion>
  <discussion>Aconitum is phylogenetically most closely related to Delphinium Linnaeus as
        evidenced by similarities in karyotype, production of diterpene alkaloids, and similarities
        in floral morphology. Distinctive and unique floral morphology clearly distinguishes
        Aconitum from all other genera.</discussion>
  <discussion>The aconites have been of interest since ancient times because they contain
        diterpene alkaloids that range from relatively nontoxic to deadly poisonous. In various
        parts of the world they have been used medicinally and as a source of poisons throughout
        history (D. E. Brink 1982). Use of Aconitum alkaloids in modern medicine was largely
        discontinued by the late 1930s and early 1940s (E. E. Swanson et al. 1938; H. C. Wood and A.
        Osol 1943; A. Osol et al. 1960).</discussion>
  <discussion>Aconitum is a circumboreal arctic and alpine genus that extends into lower latitudes
        where there is suitable mesic habitat at high elevations along the north-south chains of
        mountains in eastern and western North America, and also in outlying, scattered, mesic,
        interglacial refugia, occasionally at low elevations.</discussion>
  <discussion>The genus Aconitum worldwide is notorious for complex patterns of morphologic
        intergradation that blur the lines between taxa. Aconites from different regions may be
        morphologically distinct but connected by a series of intermediate races. Aconitum
        columbianum exemplifies this in North America, and A. delphiniifolium may extend this
        complex of variation into Asia. Intergradation between A. columbianum and A. delphiniifolium
        should be more fully investigated.</discussion>
  <discussion>Cultivated aconites with origins outside North America sometimes persist in old
        gardens or are encountered as garden escapes, especially in eastern Canada (New Brunswick,
        Newfoundland, Nova Scotia, Ontario, and Quebec). These may include Aconitum lycoctonum
        Linnaeus, A. napellus Linnaeus, A. variegatum Linnaeus, and A.bicolor Schultes. Aconitum
        lycoctonum is similar to A. reclinatum of the southeastern United States in having the tall,
        conic-cylindric hood that is characterisitc of species in Aconitum sect. Lycoctonum de
        Candolle. Aconitum reclinatum has white flowers whereas A. lycoctonum has lilac-purple
        flowers.</discussion>
  <discussion>Aconitum napellus and A. variegatum are European introductions with leaves divided
        to the base as in A. delphiniifolium, which is native to Canada and Alaska. The introduced
        species have taller hoods and relatively short-petiolate leaves compared to A.
        delphiniifolium; in A. delphiniifolium petioles are longer, i.e., mostly as long as blades.
        Aconitum napellus has smooth seeds that lack the undulating membranous lamellae present in
        A. delpinifolium and A. variegatum.</discussion>
  <discussion>Aconitum bicolor is a reputed hybrid between A. napellus and A. variegatum, having
        leaves like the former and flowers similar to the latter. It is always sterile; seeds are
        not viable. Flowers of A. bicolor are frequently white with purple margins.</discussion>
  <discussion>A more complete treatment of the cultivated aconites likely to be encountered in
        North America can be found in H. J. Scoggan (1978-1979, part 3, pp. 718-720) and P. A. Munz
        (1945).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Brink, D. E. 1982. Tuberous Aconitum (Ranunculaceae) of the continental United
            States: Morphological variation, taxonomy and disjunction. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 109:
            13-23.</reference>
    <reference>Brink, D. E., J. A. Woods, and K. R. Stern. 1994. Bulbiferous Aconitum
            (Ranunculaceae) of the western United States. Sida 16: 9-15.</reference>
    <reference>Hardin, J. W. 1964. Variation in Aconitum of eastern United States. Brittonia
            16: 80-94.</reference>
    <reference>Kadota, Y. 1987. A Revision of Aconitum subgenus Aconitum (Ranunculaceae) of East Asia. Utsunomiya.</reference>
    <reference>Shteinberg, E. I. 1970. AconitumL. In: V. L. Komarov et al., eds. 1963+. Flora
            of the U.S.S.R. (Flora SSSR). Translated from Russian. 22+ vols. Jerusalem. Vol. 7, pp.
            143-184.</reference>
    <reference>Munz, P. A. 1945. The cultivated aconites. Gentes Herb. 6: 462-505.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
