<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>5a.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>columbianum</species_name>
        <species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority>
        <subspecies_name>columbianum</subspecies_name>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <illustrated>illustrated</illustrated>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>columbianum</species_name>
        <variety_name>ochroleucum</variety_name>
        <variety_authority>A. Nelson</variety_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>columbianum</species_name>
        <subspecies_name>pallidum</subspecies_name>
        <subspecies_authority>Piper</subspecies_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>geranioides</species_name>
        <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>infectum</species_name>
        <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>leibergii</species_name>
        <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>mogollonicum</species_name>
        <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>noveboracense</species_name>
        <species_authority>A.Gray</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Aconitum</genus_name>
        <species_name>uncinatum</species_name>
        <subspecies_name>noveboracense</subspecies_name>
        <subspecies_authority>(A. Gray) Hardin</subspecies_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Bulbils absent in leaf axils and inflorescences. 2n=16, 18.</description>
    <phenology>Flowering summer (Jul-Sep)</phenology>
    <phenology>Jul</phenology>
    <phenology>Aug</phenology>
    <phenology>Sep</phenology>
    <habitat> Spring-fed bogs, seep areas, meadows, along streams, and in other wet areas</habitat>
    <elevation> 300-3500 m</elevation>
    <ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Colo.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Idaho</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Iowa</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Mont.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Nev.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> N.Y.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Ohio</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> S.Dak.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Utah</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Wis.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Wyo.</us_distribution>
    <global_distribution> Mexico.</global_distribution>
    <discussion>Disjunct, outlying populations of Aconitum columbianum subsp. columbianum in Iowa,
        Wisconsin, Ohio, and New York occur at relatively low elevations (as low as 300 m),
        sometimes in frigid air drainages from caves, or in other microhabitats that simulate
        conditions of higher elevations. They are probably relict populations that have persisted
        locally since the last glacial period. These northern wild monkshoods have been treated as a
        species (Aconitum noveboracense, which has had U.S. federal conservation status), or as a
        subspecies of A. uncinatum. We find, however, that they are part of the A. columbianum
        complex. They have a single daughter tuber that is separated from the parent tuber by a
        connecting rhizome no more than 5mm long. This is like Acolumbianum, and unlike A.
        uncinatum, which has several daughter tubers separated from the parent by elongate
        connectives. Leaf morphology is also typical of A. columbianum, and unlike A. uncinatum.
        Floral morphology is similar to that found in diminutive races of A. columbianum in
        California, Wyoming, and South Dakota. Several populations in Iowa and Wisconsin are at the
        diminutive extreme of the range of variation in A. columbianum floral characters such as
        nectary depth and hood height. Data for Iowa and Wisconsin populations can be found in D. E.
        Brink (1982, also 1980). Plants in an Ohio population were too stressed and depauperate for
        data collection. Data collected in New York populations by Brink in 1982 are not
        published.</discussion>
    <discussion>Aconitum columbianum subsp. columbianum is exceedingly variable. Plants often occur
        in dense, highly localized populations; they are very similar morphologically within
        populations and within regional groups of populations. Extreme differences occur between the
        geographic races. Specimens of the most diminutive races rarely exceed 1 m in height,
        whereas plants of the largest races may exceed 3m, with correlated differences in size and
        number of plant parts. A complete range of variation exists between the extremes if many
        regional groups of populations are considered. Geographic patterns of morphologic variation
        have been considered too complex to accord formal taxonomic rank to the variants, so the
        group has been treated as one large, intergrading species complex, with bulbil-bearing and
        nonbulbil-bearing subspecies. White-flowered variants occur within populations, but
        white-flowered populations and groups of populations also occur. In each case, these seem to
        be sporadic variants within larger, regional patterns of morphologic variation.
        Consequently, white-flowered morphs are not accorded formal taxonomic rank.</discussion>
</treatment>
