<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">fumariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque ex de Candolle" date="1759">ADLUMIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Nat.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 111. 1821, name conserved</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fumariaceae;genus ADLUMIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For John Adlum, 1759-1836, a horticulturist born in York, Pa., died in Georgetown, D.C.]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Vines or vinelike caulescent herbs, biennial, perhaps also annual, from taproots. Stems developing in 2d year, climbing, usually simple. Leaves cauline, compound, petiolate; blade with 3-5 orders of leaflets and lobes; margins entire; surfaces glabrous; distal petiolules and reduced leaflets twining and tendril-like. Inflorescences axillary, cymose-paniculate, multifloral. Flowers bilaterally symmetric about each of 2 perpendicular planes; sepals caducous, peltate with attachment near base; corolla persistent, compressed-urceolate, becoming spongy; outer petals connate except at apex, base saccate, apex with erect or reflexed, ovate to deltate lobe; inner petals similar but with apical lobes connate over stigma; filaments basally connate and adnate to petals; ovary linear or narrowly oblong; style persistent; stigma ± 2-lobed. Capsules dehiscent, 2-valved. Seeds ca. 6, elaiosome absent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia (Korea).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 2 (1 in the flora): e North America, Asia (Korea).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>e North America, Asia (Korea).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The Asian members of the genus usually are considered to be a distinct species, Adlumia asiatica Ohwi.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
