<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>4.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Alnus</genus_name>
        <species_name>glutinosa</species_name>
        <species_authority>(Linnaeus) Gaertner</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title> Fruct. Sem. Pl. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>2: 54. 1790</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <common_name>Black alder</common_name>
    <common_name> European alder</common_name>
    <weedy>weedy</weedy>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Betula</genus_name>
        <species_name>alnus</species_name>
        <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
        <variety_name>(a) glutinosa</variety_name>
        <variety_authority>Linnaeus</variety_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Sp. Pl. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>2: 983. 1753</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Trees, to 20 m; trunks often several, crowns narrow. Bark dark brown, smooth,
        becoming darker and breaking into shallow fissures in age; lenticels pale, horizontal.
        Winter buds stipitate, ellipsoid to obovoid, 6--10 mm, apex obtuse; stalks 2--5 mm; scales
        2--3, outer 2 equal, valvate, usually heavily resin-coated. Leaf blade obovate to nearly
        orbiculate, 3--9 × 3--8 cm, leathery, base obtuse to broadly cuneate, margins flat, coarsely
        and often irregularly doubly serrate to nearly dentate, major teeth acute to obtuse or
        rounded, apex often retuse or obcordate, or occasionally rounded; surfaces abaxially
        glabrous to sparsely pubescent, often more heavily on veins, both surfaces heavily
        resin-coated. Inflorescences formed season before flowering and exposed during winter;
        staminate catkins in 1 or more clusters of 2--5, 4--13 cm; pistillate catkins in 1 or more
        clusters of 2--5. Flowering before new growth in spring. Infructescences ovoid to nearly
        globose, 1.2--2.5 × 1--1.5 cm; peduncles 1--10(--20) mm. Samaras obovate, wings reduced to
        narrow, thickened ridges. 2n = 28.</description>
    <phenology>Flowering early spring</phenology>
    <habitat> Stream banks, moist flood plains, damp depressions, borders of wetlands</habitat>
    <elevation> 0--200 m</elevation>
    <ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Conn.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Ill.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Ind.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Iowa</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Mass.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Mich.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Minn.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> N.J.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> N.Y.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Ohio</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Pa.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> R.I.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Wis.</us_distribution>
    <global_distribution> Europe.</global_distribution>
    <discussion>Alnus glutinosa is cultivated as an ornamental tree throughout eastern North America
        and is available in a variety of cultivars, including cut-leafed and compact-branching
        forms. This species has also been used extensively to control erosion and improve the soil
        on recently cleared or unstable substrates, such as sand dunes and mine spoils. It has
        escaped and become widely naturalized throughout the temperate Northeast, occasionally
        becoming a weedy pest. In Europe the black alder has served for many centuries as an
        important source of hardwood for timbers and carved items, including wooden
        shoes.</discussion>
    <discussion>Alnus glutinosa has been called A. vulgaris Hill in some older literature; that name
        was not validly published.</discussion>
</treatment>
