<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Gray" date="unknown">betulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">alnus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey in W. H. Emory" date="1859">oblongifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. H. Emory, Rep. U.S. Mex. Bound.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 204. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family betulaceae;genus alnus;species oblongifolia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees, to 30 m; trunks often several, crowns spreading. Bark dark gray, smooth,
        becoming blackish and breaking into shallow vertical plates in age; lenticels inconspicuous.
        Winter buds stipitate, ovoid, 4--8 mm, apex rounded; stalks 1.5--4 mm; scales 2, equal,
        valvate, sometimes incompletely covering underlying leaves, moderately resin-coated. Leaf
        blade narrowly ovate or lanceolate to narrowly elliptic, 5--9 × 3--6 cm, leathery, base
        narrowly to broadly cuneate or narrowly rounded, margins flat, sharply and coarsely doubly
        serrate, rarely evenly and densely short-serrate, major teeth sharp, acuminate, secondary
        teeth distinctly larger, apex long to short-acuminate, rarely acute; surfaces abaxially
        glabrous to sparsely pubescent or infrequently villous, moderately resin-coated.
        Inflorescences formed season before flowering and exposed during winter; staminate catkins
        in 1 or more clusters of 3--6, 3.5--10 cm; pistillate catkins in 1 or more clusters of 2--7.
        Flowering before new growth in spring. Infructescences ovoid, ellipsoid, or nearly
        cylindric, 1--2.5 × 0.8--1.5 cm; peduncles 5--10 mm. Samaras elliptic to obovate, wings
        narrower than body, irregular in shape, leathery.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering early spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy or rocky stream banks and moist slopes, often in mountain canyons;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1000--2300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex.; Mexico (n Chihuahua and n Sonora).</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Arizona alder</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">New Mexican alder</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">aliso (Mexico)</other_name>
  <discussion>Alnus oblongifolia is closely related to the Mexican and Central American A.
        acuminata, with which it has sometimes been confused. It is found only in scattered
        populations in the temperate deciduous forest vegetation zone of high mountains in the arid
        Southwest.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
