<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>20.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Anemone</genus_name><species_name>lyallii</species_name><species_authority>Britton</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Ann. New York Acad. Sci. </publication_title><place_in_publication>6: 227. 1891</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Little mountain anemone</common_name><endemic>endemic</endemic><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Anemone</genus_name><species_name>oligantha</species_name><species_authority>Eastwood</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Anemone</genus_name><species_name>quinquefolia</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><variety_name>lyallii</variety_name><variety_authority>(Britton) B.L. Robinson</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Aerial shoots 5-30(-40) cm, from rhizomes, rhizomes horizontal. Basal leaves 0-1, ternate; petiole 5-8 cm; terminal leaflet sessile to petiolulate, ovate to oblanceolate, (1-)1.5-3(-4) × (0.4-)0.7-1.5(-2) cm, base narrowly cuneate, margins serrate to crenate on distal 1/2-2/3, apex acuminate to narrowly acute, rarely obtuse, surfaces glabrous, rarely puberulous; lateral leaflets unlobed or occasionally nearly lobed. Inflorescences 1-flowered; peduncle distally puberulous or nearly glabrous throughout; involucral bracts 3, 1-tiered, ternate, ±similar to basal leaves, bases distinct; terminal leaflet sessile to petiolulate, ovate to oblanceolate, (1-)1.5-3(-4) × (0.4-)0.7-1.5(-2) cm, bases narrowly cuneate, margins serrate to crenate on distal 1/2-2/3, apex acuminate to narrowly acute, rarely obtuse, surfaces glabrous, rarely puberulous; lateral leaflets unlobed or occasionally nearly lobed. Flowers: sepals 5(-7), white, pink, or sometimes blue-tinged, oblong, rarely narrowly ovate, 3.5-8(-10) × 1.5-3(-3.5) mm, glabrous; stamens 10-30(-35). Heads of achenes nearly spheric; pedicel 1-3(-4) cm in fruit. Achenes: body elliptic, flat, 3-4 × 1-1.5 mm, not winged, white-puberulous; beak subulate, sometimes slightly curved, ca. 0.5 mm, glabrous. 2n=16.</description><phenology>Flowering spring-summer (Mar-Jul)</phenology><habitat> Shaded woods, subalpine ridges</habitat><elevation> 200-1900 m</elevation><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution><discussion>Anemone lyallii may occasionally intergrade with A. oregana west of the Cascades in northern Oregon (C. L. Hitchcock et al. 1955-1969, vol. 2). The area of probable intergradation should be extended to the southern limits of both species where they are sympatric.</discussion></treatment>
