<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>ANNONA</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 536. 175</place_in_publication></place_of_publication><place_of_publication><publication_title> Gen. Pl. ed. </publication_title><place_in_publication>5, 241. 1754</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Custard-apple</common_name><common_name> soursop</common_name><common_name> alligator-apple </common_name><etymology>[native Hispaniolan anon or hanon, given to A. muricata]</etymology><description>Trees or shrubs, taprooted; trunks buttressed or not buttressed at base. Bark thin, mostly broadly and shallowly fissured, scaly, fissures anastomosing. Shoots slender, stiff, terete; lenticels raised; buds naked. Leaves persistent or deciduous to late deciduous. Leaf blade leathery or membranous, glabrous to pubescent. Inflorescences axillary or supra-axillary, occasionally from axillary buds on main stem or older stems, solitary flowers or fascicles; peduncle bracteolate. Flowers: receptacle convex to ±globose or elongate, elevated; sepals deciduous, 3(-4), smaller than outer petals, valvate in bud; petals 6(-8) in 2 whorls, usually fleshy, those of outer whorl larger, valvate in bud, those of inner whorl more ascending, distinctly smaller or reduced, rarely absent, valvate or imbricate in bud; nectaries present as darker-pigmented, usually corrugate zones adaxially near petal bases; stamens very numerous, packed into ball, club-shaped, curved; connective dilated, hooded or pointed beyond anther sac; pistils numerous, sessile, partially connate to various degrees with at least stigmas distinct; ovules 1(-2) per pistil; style and stigma club-shaped or narrowly conic. Fruits fleshy syncarps, 1 per flower, usually ovoid to nearly globose, surface variable depending on orientation, structure, and relative connation of pistil apices. Seed usually 1 per pistil, ovoid to ellipsoid, beanlike, coat tough, margins various, narrow. x=7.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 110 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> mostly neotropic</global_distribution><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> 10 in Africa.</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Safford, W. E. 1914. Classification of the genus Annona, with descriptions of new and imperfectly known species. Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 18: i-ix, 1-68.</reference><reference> Sargent, C. S. 1922. Manual of the Trees of North America (Exclusive of Mexico), ed. 2. Boston and New York. Pp. 354-356. [Reprints in 2 vols., 1961, 1965. New York.] Wood, C. E. 1958. The genera of the woody Ranales in the southeastern United States. J.Arnold Arbor.39: 296-346.</reference></references></treatment>
