<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Annona</genus_name><species_name>squamosa</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 537. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Sweetsop</common_name><common_name> sugar-apple</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Annona</genus_name><species_name>asiatica</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs or trees, to ca. 8 m; trunks short, not buttressed at base. Principal leaves late deciduous; petiole 4-22 mm. Leaf blade narrowly elliptic to oblong or lanceolate, 5-17 × 2-5.5 cm, base broadly cuneate to rounded, apex acute to obtuse; surfaces glaucous, abaxially variably pubescent, adaxially glabrate. Inflorescences solitary flowers or fascicles; peduncle slender, to 2 cm, becoming enlarged in fruit. Flowers: sepals deltate, 1.5-2 mm, apex acute, surfaces abaxially pubescent or glabrous; outer petals pale green above purplish base, oblong or lance-oblong, 1.5-3 cm, base slightly concave, surfaces abaxially furrowed, pubescent, adaxially thickened, keeled; inner petals ovate, keeled, minute, nearly as long as stamens; stamens club-shaped, curved, 1-3 mm; connective dilated, flattened and truncate; pistils conically massed, separable at anthesis, later connate. Syncarp pendulous on thickened peduncle, greenish yellow, glaucous, mostly ±globose, 5-10 cm, muricate. Seed ellipsoid to obovoid, 1-1.4 cm.</description><phenology>Flowering spring-early summer</phenology><habitat> Dryish sandy substrates, dry hammocks</habitat><elevation> 0-50 m</elevation><introduced> introduced</introduced><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution> native to West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> naturalized or cultivated circumtropically.</global_distribution><discussion>The fruit of Annona squamosa (Annona sect. Atta C. Martius) has delicious whitish pulp, and it is popular in tropical markets.</discussion></treatment>
