<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ANNONACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus ANNONACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Custard-apple family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 128, species ca. 2300 (3 genera, 12 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The family has particular importance in the tropics because of the edible syncarps of some species of Annona; in the eastern United States the fruit of Asimina triloba (pawpaw) was once much gathered and appreciated. Programs in breeding from selected stock of Asimina have been undertaken (G. A. Zimmerman 1941).</discussion>
  <discussion>Currently, the Pawpaw Foundation is intensively researching means to develop commercially marketable fruits. Recent studies of the chemical properties of Asimina reveal its pesticidal possibilities, and its potential as an anticancer agent (E. M. Norman, pers. comm.) The warm-climate genera Cananga, Rollinia, and Artabotrys have been used as ornamentals.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fries, R. E. 1931. Revision der Arten einiger Annonaceen-Gattungen. Acta Horti Berg. 10: 1-341.</reference>
    <reference>Fries, R. E. 1934. Revision der Arten einiger Annonaceen-Gattungen. Acta Horti Berg. 12(1): 1-220.</reference>
    <reference>Fries, R. E. 1939. Revision der Arten einiger Annonaceen-Gattungen. Acta Horti Berg. 12(3): 289-577.</reference>
    <reference>Hutchinson, J. 1923. Contributions toward a phylogenetic classification of flowering plants. II. The genera of Annonaceae. Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew: 241-261.</reference>
    <reference>Kral, R. 1960. A revision of Asimina and Deeringothamnus (Annonaceae). Brittonia 12(4): 233-278.</reference>
    <reference>Rusby, H. H. 1935. The custard-apple family in Florida. J. New York Bot. Gard. 36: 233-239.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
