<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">AQUILEGIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 533. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 237. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae;genus AQUILEGIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[derivation disputed; possibly Greek aqua, water, and legere, to draw or collect, because of the wet habitat of some species or quantity of liquid nectar borne in spurs, or Latin aquila, eagle, because of similarity in shape of curved spurs of some European species to an eagle's talons]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from slender woody rhizomes. Leaves basal and cauline, proximal leaves petiolate, distal leaves sessile; cauline leaves alternate. Leaf blade 1-3×-ternately compound, leaflets lobed or parted, margins crenate. Inflorescences terminal, 1-10-flowered cymes or solitary flowers, to 30 cm; bracts leaflike, not forming involucre. Flowers bisexual, radially symmetric; sepals not persistent in fruit, 5, white to blue, yellow, or red, plane, narrowly ovate to oblong-lanceolate, short-clawed, 7-51 mm; petals 5, distinct, white to blue, yellow, or red, oblong to rounded or spatulate blade, 0-30 mm, base backward-pointing tubular spur, apex plane; nectary in ± enlarged tip of spur; stamens many; filaments filiform; scalelike staminodes usually present between stamens and pistils; pistils 5-10, simple; ovules many per pistil; beak present. Fruits follicles, aggregate, sessile, cylindric, sides prominently veined; beak terminal, straight, 3-26 mm. Seeds black, obovoid, smooth. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumboreal.</description>
  <number>21.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Columbine</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">ancolie</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 70 (21 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Species of Aquilegia are polymorphic and difficult to define adequately. Some of the variability is because of introgressive hybridization. Even distantly related species of columbine are often freely interfertile, and many cases of natural hybridization and introgression are known from North America. Only the most important are mentioned below. In arid areas Aquilegia species tend to form small populations often completely isolated from one another. This leads to local fixation of genes and therefore increased variability in species such as A. micrantha and A. desertorum. In addition, populations with spurless petals are occasionally found in many species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Munz, P. A. 1946. The cultivated and wild columbines. Gentes Herb. 7: 1-150.</reference>
    <reference>Payson, E. B. 1918. The North American species of Aquilegia. Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 20: 133-157.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
