<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">papaveraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey &amp; Frémont" date="unknown">ARCTOMECON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. C. Frémont,  Rep. Exped. Rocky Mts.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>312. 1845</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family papaveraceae; genus ARCTOMECON;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek arktos, bear, alluding to the long-pilose pubescence, and mekon, poppy]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, evergreen, cespitose, scapose or very short-caulescent and subscapose, from taproots. Stems (caudices) when present leafy, erect, branching, covered with marcescent leaf bases. Leaves all or mostly basal and rosulate, petiolate; blade cuneate to fan-shaped, 1×-lobed distally, glaucous, long-pilose, hairs flexuous, barbed; margins entire; lobes acute, long-bristled. Inflorescences terminal, cymiform, simple or branching; bracts present; buds nodding. Flowers: sepals 2 or 3, distinct; petals persistent, 4 or 6; stamens many; pistil 3-6-carpellate; ovary 1-locular; style 1 and short, or absent; stigmas 1 per carpel, connate, capitate, cordately 2-lobed. Capsules erect, 3-6-valved, dehiscing from apex leaving persistent placental ribs unseparated at apex, valve tips recurving. Seeds several to many, dark brown, shining, ovoid, 1.5-3 mm, aril present. x = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America (Mojave Desert).</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Desert bearclaw-poppy</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Janish, J. R. 1977. Nevada's vanishing bear-poppies. Mentzelia 3: 2-5.</reference>
    <reference>Mozingo, H. N. and Margaret Williams. 1980. Threatened and Endangered Plants of Nevada: An Illustrated Manual. [Washington.]</reference>
    <reference>Nelson, D. R. and S. L. Welsh. 1993. Taxonomic revision of Arctomecon Torr. &amp; Frem. Rhodora 95: 197-213.</reference>
    <reference>Raynie, D. E., D. R. Nelson, and K. T. Harper. 1991. Alkaloidal relationships in the genus Arctomecon (Papaveraceae) and herbivory in A. humilis. Great Basin Naturalist 51: 397-403.</reference>
    <reference>Welsh, S. L. and K. L. Thorne. 1979. Illustrated Manual of Proposed Endangered and Threatened Plants of Utah. [Washington.]</reference>
    <reference>Nelson, D. R. and K. T. Harper. 1991. Site characteristics and habitat requirements of the endangered dwarf bear-claw poppy (Arctomecon humilis Coville, Papaveraceae). Great Basin Naturalist 51: 167-175.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
