<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Asarum</genus_name><species_name>wagneri</species_name><species_authority>K. L. Lu &amp; Mesler</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Brittonia </publication_title><place_in_publication>35: 331. 1983</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><endemic>endemic</endemic><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Asarum</genus_name><species_name>caudatum</species_name><species_authority>Lindley</species_authority><variety_name>viridiflorum</variety_name><variety_authority>M. Peck</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Rhizomes horizontal, ± deeply buried, internodes 0.5-2.1 cm. Leaves: petiole 3-15 cm, sparsely crisped-hirsute. Leaf blade not variegate, broadly reniform to cordate-reniform, 3-8 × 4-11 cm, apex obtuse to rounded (broadly acute); surfaces abaxially sparsely hirsute, adaxially sparsely hirsute only along veins, marginal hairs mostly curved toward apex. Flowers erect or ascending; peduncle 0.8- calyx tube subglobose to cylindric-urceolate or urceolate, externally light green, sparsely to moderately hirsute, internally white or light green, bordered and occasionally striped with purple, with purple hairs; distal portion of sepal spreading perpendicularly from base at anthesis, bent abruptly upward at midpoint, 8-20 mm, apex filiform-acuminate, abaxially white to pale green, sparsely villous to villous, adaxially white or light green, at least distally, bordered with purple and occasionally with purple band across base, puberulent with crisped purple-tipped hairs; pollen sacs 1-2 mm, sterile tip of connective on inner stamens dark red, 0.25-1 mm, shorter than pollen sacs.</description><phenology>Flowering spring-summer (May-Jul)</phenology><habitat> Understory of Abies forests and open boulder fields in Tsuga forests near timberline</habitat><elevation> 1500-3200 m</elevation><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><discussion>Asarum wagneri is endemic to the Cascade Range of pouthern Oregon (K. L. Lu and M. R. Mesler 1983).</discussion></treatment>
