<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Asarum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Piper" date="unknown">marmoratum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Biol. Soc. Wash.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>29: 99. 1916</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Asarum;species marmoratum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes erect or ascending, deeply buried, internodes 0.2-1.5 cm. Leaves: petiole 5-20 cm, sparsely crisped-hirsute. Leaf blade almost always variegate with white or silver along veins, cordate to cordate-reniform, 4-14 × 3-12 cm, apex acute to broadly acuminate, rarely obtuse; surfaces abaxially sparsely hirsute, adaxially glabrous or sparsely hirsute along veins, marginal hairs ± perpendicular to margin. Flowers erect or nearly so; peduncle 1.2-1. calyx tube subglobose, externally mottled red, sparsely to moderately hirsute, internally dark red, with purple hairs; distal portion of sepal erect or spreading at anthesis, 17-52 mm, apex filiform-attenuate, abaxially pale green, hirsute, adaxially tan or brownish green, rarely red proximally, puberulent with crisped purple hairs; pollen sacs 0.8-2.4 mm, sterile tip of connective on inner stamens dark red-brown, 1.2-3.8 mm, longer than pollen sacs.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late winter-spring (Mar-Jun)</description>
  <description type="habitat">Understory of dry or mesic forests, or exposed rocky slopes or roadcuts</description>
  <description type="elevation">200-1800 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Oreg.</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <discussion>endemic</discussion>
  <discussion>Asarum marmoratum is found only in the Cascades and the Siskiyou Mountains of southern Oregon and extreme northwestern California (M. R. Mesler and K. L. Lu 1990).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
