<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Asimina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kral" date="unknown">longifolia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="unknown" date="unknown">longifolia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Asimina;species longifolia;variety longifolia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Primary shoots mostly stiff, straight, and erect to ascending, at first distally minutely tomentose. Leaf blade linear, elliptic-linear, rarely linear-oblanceolate, mostly broadest toward middle, less than 1.5 cm wide, margins revolute, apex acute to obtuse, rarely notched or rounded; surfaces sparsely hairy abaxially when young. Flowers: outer petals white or cream-white, sparsely hairy abaxially; inner petals white, rarely pink or red.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring-early summer, all year if disturbed</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sands and sandy peats or loams of yellow sandhills, sandy fields and pastures, open longleaf pine-turkey oak woods and savannas</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-100 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <number>8a.</number>
  <discussion>endemic</discussion>
  <discussion>Asimina longifolia var. longifolia hybridizes with A. incana (= A.  ×nashii Kral) to produce spectacular, fragrant flowers with red or pink inner petals, and the hybrid is frequent over their nearly identical ranges. Asimina longifolia var. longifolia crosses with A.  pygmaea, particularly along the Suwannee-Okefenokee axis, ultimately to form swarms, the individuals varying in height, degree of arching of branches, flower sizes, pigments, and fragrances. Some of those hybrids were noted by W. Bartram.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
