<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>7.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Asimina</genus_name><species_name>tetramera</species_name><species_authority>Small</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Torreya </publication_title><place_in_publication>26: 56. 1926</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Four-petaled pawpaw</common_name><conservation>of conservation concern</conservation><endemic>endemic</endemic><illustrated>illustrated</illustrated><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Pityothamnus</genus_name><species_name>tetramerus</species_name><species_authority>(Small) Small</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs, 1-3 m. Branches 1-several from base, nearly erect to arching; new shoots red-brown to tan, distally minutely red-tomentose, glabrate. Leaves: petiole 2-3 mm. Leaf blade spreading to upswept, oblong-oblanceolate to broadly spatulate, 5-10(-18) cm, leathery, base narrowly cuneate, margins slightly revolute, apex rounded to obtuse-angled; surfaces abaxially glabrate, adaxially glabrous. Inflorescences from axils of new shoots, solitary flowers; peduncle slender, 1-2 cm; bracteole 1, basal, lance-oblong, 5-7 mm, hairy. Flowers nodding to nearly erect, reddish, fetid; perianth (3-)4-merous; sepals elliptic or ovate, ca. 1 cm, abaxially sparsely rusty-hairy; outer petals ascending with spreading pale tips, lanceolate to oblong-lanceolate, 2-2.5 cm, margins slightly revolute, surfaces abaxially glabrate; inner petals ovate-acute or short-acuminate, ca. 1/2 length of outer petals, fleshier than outer petals, base large, saccate, corrugate zone adaxially deep purple; pistils 3-11. Berries yellow-green, 5-9 cm. Seeds chestnut brown, 1-2 cm. 2n=18.</description><phenology>Flowering spring-summer, all year if disturbed</phenology><habitat> Sands of ancient coastal dunes and adjacent open-wooded hammocks, flatwoods</habitat><conservation> of conservation concern</conservation><elevation> 0-50 m</elevation><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><discussion>Morphologically, Asimina tetramera is much like a tall A.  pygmaea in characters of flower and leaf.</discussion></treatment>
