<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">berberidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">BERBERIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 330. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 153. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family berberidaceae; genus BERBERIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Mediaeval Latin barbaris]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="unknown">Mahonia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>name conserved</publication_title>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Mahonia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">Odostemon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Odostemon;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or subshrubs, evergreen or deciduous, 0.1-4.5(-8) m, glabrous or with tomentose stems. Rhizomes present or absent, short or long, not nodose. Stems branched or unbranched, monomorphic or dimorphic, i.e., all elongate or with elongate primary stems and short axillary spur shoots. Leaves alternate, sometimes leaves of elongate shoots reduced to spines and foliage leaves borne only on short shoots; foliage leaves simple or 1-odd-pinnately compound; petioles usually present. Simple leaves: blade narrowly elliptic, oblanceolate, or obovate, 1.2-7.5 cm. Compound leaves: rachis, when present, with or without swollen articulations; leaflet blades lanceolate to orbiculate, margins entire, toothed, spinose, or spinose-lobed; venation pinnate or leaflets 3-6-veined from base. Inflorescences terminal, usually racemes, rarely umbels or flowers solitary. Flowers 3-merous, 3-8 mm; bracteoles caducous, 3, scalelike; sepals falling immediately after anthesis, 6, yellow; petals 6, yellow, nectariferous; stamens 6; anthers dehiscing by valves; pollen exine punctate; ovary symmetrically club-shaped; placentation subbasal; style central. Fruits berries, spheric to cylindric-ovoid or ellipsoid, usually juicy, sometimes dry, at maturity. Seeds 1-10, tan to red-brown or black; aril absent. x = 14.</description>
  <description type="distribution">almost worldwide.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Barberry</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">Oregon-grape</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">berbéris</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">algerita</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 500 (22 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Many species of Berberis are grown as ornamental shrubs. Some species harbor the black stem-rust of wheat (Puccinia graminis Persoon); the sale or transport of susceptible or untested species is illegal in the United States and Canada. Data on susceptibility of Berberis spp. to infection by Puccinia graminis was supplied by Dr. D. L. Long, U.S. Department of Agriculture (pers. comm.).</discussion>
  <discussion>The berries of many species are edible and frequently are used for jam and jelly.</discussion>
  <discussion>The genus Berberis as recognized below is divided into two genera, Berberis and Mahonia, by some authors (e.g., L. Abrams 1934). Species 1-5 below represent Berberis in the narrow sense (characterized by dimorphic stems, with elongate primary stems and short axillary shoots; leaves of primary stems modified as spines; foliage leaves simple; and inflorescences usually rather lax, with acuminate bracteoles and 1-20 flowers; most species susceptible to Puccinia). Species 13-22 represent the segregate genus Mahonia (with stems never regularly dimorphic; stem spines absent; leaves pinnately compound; and inflorescences dense, with rounded or obtuse [rarely acute] bracteoles and 25-70 flowers; never susceptible to Puccinia). Species 6-12, traditionally included in Mahonia when that genus is recognized (L. Abrams 1934), are actually intermediate, resembling Berberis proper in their dimorphic stems, inflorescence structure, and susceptibility to Puccinia, and Mahonia in their spineless stems and compound leaves. Species showing different combinations of the characteristics of the two groups are found in other parts of the world (J. W. McCain and J. F. Hennen 1982; R. V. Moran 1982), so these segregate genera do not seem to be natural. Mahonia is often recognized in horticultural works, but it is seldom recognized by botanists.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Abrams, L. 1934. The mahonias of the Pacific states. Phytologia 1: 89-94.</reference>
    <reference>McCain, J. W. and J. F. Hennen. 1982. Is the taxonomy of Berberis and Mahonia (Berberidaceae) supported by their rust pathogens Cumminsiella santa sp. nov. and other Cumminsiella species (Uredinales)? Syst. Bot. 7: 48-59.</reference>
    <reference>Moran, R. V. 1982. Berberis claireae, a new species from Baja California; and why not Mahonia. Phytologia 52: 221-226.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
