<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">betulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Betula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ehrhart" date="unknown">pubescens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Beitr. Naturk.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 160. 1790</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family betulaceae; genus Betula;species pubescens;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Betula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">alba</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Ehrhart) Spach" date="unknown">pubescens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Betula;species alba;variety pubescens;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees and shrubs; trunks 1--many. Bark when young dark reddish brown, in maturity light reddish brown to tan or brownish or grayish white, smooth, rather close or readily exfoliating in paper-thin sheets; lenticels pale, horizontal, in maturity dark, horizontally expanded. Twigs without taste and odor of wintergreen, usually covered with short bristly hairs. Leaf blade ovate or rhombic-ovate, margins serrate, apex acute; surfaces abaxially sparsely pubescent to velutinous, especially along major veins and in vein axils, without prominent resinous glands. Fruiting catkins pendulous or subpendulous, cylindric, shattering with fruits in late fall; scales puberulent to glabrous, often ciliate, lobes diverging at middle. Samaras with wings equal to or somewhat broader than body, broadest near summit, extended beyond body apically.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced elsewhere in North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Iceland</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia.</description>
  <number>9.</number>
  <discussion>Subspecies 3 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Betula pubescens was used medicinally by the Cree for chafed skin, and by the Ojibwa as a seasoner in medicines and a component in a maple syrup mixture used to relieve stomach cramps (D. E. Moerman 1986, as B. alba).</discussion>
  <discussion>Betula alba Linnaeus is a long-standing nomen ambiguum that had not been in use (until recently) because it included two taxa whose names had been widely adopted long ago. At this time a proposal to reject Betula alba is in press, and possibly a decision will be made before the end of the year (R. Brummitt, pers. comm.; Fred Barrie, pers. comm.)</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
