<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Carya</genus_name><species_name>myristiciformis</species_name><species_authority>(F. Michaux) Nuttall</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Gen. N. Amer. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 222. 1818</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Nutmeg hickory</common_name><common_name> nogal</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Juglans</genus_name><species_name>myristiciformis</species_name><species_authority>F. Michaux</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Hist. Arbr. Forest., </publication_title><place_in_publication>1(2): 211, plate 10. 1810</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Hicoria</genus_name><species_name>myristiciformis</species_name><species_authority>(F. Michaux) Britton</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Trees, to 35 m. Bark gray to brownish, fissured or exfoliating, separating freely into long strips or broad plates. Twigs brown to bronze, slender, without hairs, densely scaly. Terminal buds bronze, ovoid, 4-6 mm, essentially without hairs, densely scaly; bud scales valvate; axillary buds protected by bracteoles fused into hood. Leaves 3-6 dm; petiole 3-10 cm, densely scaly. Leaflets (5-)7-9, lateral petiolules 0-2 mm, terminal petiolules 2-3 mm; blades ovate or obovate to elliptic, not falcate, 3-17 × 1-8 cm, margins finely to coarsely serrate, without tufts of hairs, apex acuminate; surfaces abaxially with unicellular and 2-4-rayed fasciculate hairs along midrib in spring, densely scaly with coating of large peltate scales and small irregular, round, and 4-lobed peltate scales, imparting bronze color, adaxially pubescent along midrib and major veins in spring, with scattered peltate scales. Staminate catkins pedunculate, to 6 cm, stalks and bracts scaly; anthers hirsute. Fruits light tan to bronze, obovoid to ellipsoid, not compressed, 2-3 × 1.5-2 cm; husks rough, 2 mm thick, dehiscing to base, sutures winged; nuts reddish brown mottled with tan patches, ellipsoid, not compressed, not angled, smooth; shells thick. Seeds sweet. 2n = 32.</description><phenology>Flowering spring</phenology><habitat> River bottomlands, edges of streams, bluffs, and hillsides, often on calcareous prairie soils and marl ridges</habitat><elevation> 0-500 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ark.</us_distribution><us_distribution> La.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Miss.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Okla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico (Nuevo León).</global_distribution><discussion>Carya myristiciformis is the rarest species in the genus. It is patchily distributed from the mountains of northeastern Mexico to the coastal plain of North Carolina.</discussion></treatment>
