<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="unknown">CARYA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 220. 1818, name conserved</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus CARYA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek káryon, nut, kernel]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">Hicoria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Hicoria;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hickory</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">caryer</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">hicorier</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 18 (11 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Carya was widespread during the Tertiary; fossils have been reported from the states of Colorado and Washington, and from China, Japan, Europe, and western Siberia. Today two sections of the genus occur in southeastern Asia (sect. Rhamphocarya and sect. Sinocarya) and two in North America (sect. Apocarya, the so-called pecan hickories, and sect. Carya hickories). Both 2n = 32 and 2n = 64 chromosome numbers are known for the genus; tetraploidy, however, is confined to sect. Carya.</discussion>
  <discussion>The commercial use of Carya is substantial. The cultivated pecan, C. illinoinensis, is the most important nut tree native to North America, and the wood o hickories is unequaled for its use in tool handles because of the combined strength and shock resistance. Hickory nuts are also an important, high-quality food source for wildlife because they are high in proteins and fats. Carya cordiformis, C. glabra, and C. ovata are grown extensively in central Europe for timber.</discussion>
  <discussion>Characters of the buds and bark are taxonomically important in Carya, but shoots with terminal buds and information about bark characteristics are frequently absent on herbarium specimens. Phenotypic variation from tree to tree is often considerable and difficult to quantify. Most of this variation undoubtedly results from adaptation to local and regional conditions; hybridization has probably played a subtle role as well. Sympatry of two or more species is common, and artificial pollinations suggest that even diploid × tetraploid crosses produce viable seed.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hardin, J. W. and D. E. Stone. 1984. Atlas of foliar surface features in woody plants, VI. Carya (Juglandaceae) of North America. Brittonia 36: 140-153.</reference>
    <reference>Manning, W. E. 1950. A key to the hickories north of Virginia with notes on the two pignuts, Carya glabra and C. ovalis. Rhodora 52: 188-199.</reference>
    <reference>Manning, W. E. 1973. The northern limits of the distributions of hickories in New England. Rhodora 75: 34-51.</reference>
    <reference>Sargent, C. S. 1933. Manual of the Trees of North America, ed. 2, rev. Boston.</reference>
    <reference>Stone, D. E., G. A. Adrouny, and R. H. Flake. 1969. New World Juglandaceae. II. Hickory nut oils, phenetic similarities, and evolutionary implications in the genus Carya. Amer. J. Bot. 56: 928-935.</reference>
    <reference>Woodworth, R. H. 1930c. Meiosis of sporogenesis in the Juglandaceae. Amer. J. Bot. 17: 863-869.</reference>
    <reference>Stone, D. E. 1962. Affinities of a Mexican endemic, Carya palmeri, with American and Asian hickories. Amer. J. Bot. 49: 199-212.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
