<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">fagaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">CASTANEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict. Abr. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fagaceae;genus CASTANEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Classical Latin, from Greek kastanaion karuon, nut from Castania, probably referring either to Kastanaia in Pontus or Castana in Thessaly]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees or shrubs, winter-deciduous, sometimes rhizomatous. Terminal buds absent, pseudoterminal bud (axillary bud of youngest leaf) ovoid, with 2 unequal opposite outer scales enclosing several imbricate inner scales. Leaves: stipules prominent on new growth, soon deciduous. Leaf blade thin, somewhat leathery, secondary veins unbranched, ±parallel, extending to margin, each vein ending in sharp tooth or well-developed awn. Inflorescences staminate or androgynous, axillary, spicate, erect, rigid or flexible; androgynous inflorescences with pistillate cupules/flowers toward base and staminate flowers distally. Staminate flowers: sepals distinct; stamens 12(-18), typically surrounding indurate pistillode covered with silky hairs. Pistillate flowers 1-3 per cupule; sepals distinct; carpels and styles typically 6(-9). Fruits: maturation in 1st year following pollination (termed annual by many authors); cupule 2-4-valved, valves connate marginally until maturity, ±completely enclosing nut(s), spiny, spines irregularly branched, often interlocking, densely or sparsely covered in simple hairs; nuts 1-3 per cupule, plano-convex, or if 3, then central nut often reduced and flattened, or if solitary, then often rounded in cross section, not winged, adjacent nuts not separated by internal cupule valves. x = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species ca. 8-10 (3 in the flora, often interpreted as 2): North America, Europe, Asia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species ca. 8-10 (3 in the flora, often interpreted as 2)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Europe, Asia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Chestnut</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">châtaignier</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 8-10 (3 in the flora, often interpreted as 2):</discussion>
  <discussion>As evidenced by United States breeding programs, all species are probably interfertile (including American × Asian species). Local morphologic intergradation between species is to be expected.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hardin, J. W. and G. P. Johnson. 1985. Atlas of foliar surface features in woody plants, VIII. Fagus and Castanea (Fagaceae) of eastern North America. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 112: 11-20.</reference>
    <reference>Johnson, G. P. 1988. Revision of Castanea sect. Balanocastanon (Fagaceae). J. Arnold Arbor. 69: 25-49.</reference>
    <reference>Paillet, F. L. 1993. Growth form and life histories of American chestnut and Allegheny and Ozark chinquapin at various North American sites. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 120: 257-268.</reference>
    <reference>Paillet, F. L. and P. A. Rutter. 1989. Replacement of native oak and hickory tree species by the introduced American chestnut Castanea dentata in southwestern Wisconsin, USA. Canad. J. Bot. 67: 3457-3469.</reference>
    <reference>Tucker, G. E. 1975. Castanea pumila var. ozarkensis (Ashe) Tucker, comb. nov. Proc. Arkansas Acad. Sci. 29: 67-69.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
