<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">CERATOPHYLLUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 992. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 428. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus CERATOPHYLLUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek ceratos, horn, and phyllon, leaf]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hornwort</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cornifle</other_name>
  <discussion>Useful in identification of species of Ceratophyllum are leaf-forking characteristics. Leaves with no forking are "0-order"; they consist only of a primary segment. Those forking once are "1st-order"; their ultimate segments are secondary. Those in which at least one secondary segment forks are "2d-order"; their ultimate segments are tertiary. Those in which at least one tertiary segment forks are "3d-order"; their ultimate segments are quaternary. Those in which at least one quaternary segment forks are "4th order."</discussion>
  <discussion>Plumule features used in the key below are observable through dissection of softened (soaked) seeds removed from achenes.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fassett, N. C. 1953. North American Ceratophyllum. Comun. Inst. Trop. Invest. Ci. Univ. El Salvador 2: 25-45.</reference>
    <reference>Herendeen, P. S., D. H. Les, and D. L. Dilcher. 1990. Fossil Ceratophyllum (Ceratophyllaceae) from the Tertiary of North America. Amer. J. Bot. 77: 7-16.</reference>
    <reference>Jones, E. N. 1931. The morphology and biology of Ceratophyllum demersum. Stud. Nat. Hist. Iowa Univ. 13: 11-55.</reference>
    <reference>Les, D. H. 1985. The taxonomic significance of plumule morphology in Ceratophyllum (Ceratophyllaceae). Syst. Bot. 10: 338-346.</reference>
    <reference>Les, D. H. 1986. The phytogeography of Ceratophyllum demersum and C. echinatum in glaciated North America. Canad. J. Bot. 64: 498-509.</reference>
    <reference>Les, D. H. 1986b. The evolution of achene morphology in Ceratophyllum (Ceratophyllaceae), I. Fruit spine variation and relationships of C. demersum, C. submersum, and C. apiculatum. Syst. Bot. 11: 549-558.</reference>
    <reference>Les, D. H. 1988b. The evolution of achene morphology in Ceratophyllum (Ceratophyllaceae), II. Fruit variation and systematics of the "spiny-margined" group. Syst. Bot. 13: 73-86.</reference>
    <reference>Les, D. H. 1988c. The evolution of achene morphology in Ceratophyllum (Ceratophyllaceae), III. Relationships of the "facially-spined" group. Syst. Bot. 13: 509-518.</reference>
    <reference>Les, D. H. 1989. The evolution of achene morphology in Ceratophyllum (Ceratophyllaceae), IV. Summary of proposed relationships and evolutionary trends. Syst. Bot. 14: 254-262.</reference>
    <reference>Lowden, R. M. 1978. Studies in the submerged genus Ceratophyllum L. in the neotropics. Aquat. Bot. 4: 127-142.</reference>
    <reference>Muenscher, W. C. 1940. Fruits and seedlings of Ceratophyllum. Amer. J. Bot. 27: 231-233.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
