<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">fagaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hjelmquist" date="unknown">CHRYSOLEPIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Not., Suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(1): 117. 1948</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fagaceae; genus CHRYSOLEPIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chrysos, gold, and lepis, scale, referring to yellow glands on various organs
        of the plant]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees or shrubs, evergreen. Terminal buds present, ovoid or subglobose, scales
        imbricate. Leaves: stipules prominent on new growth, often persistent around buds. Leaf
        blade thick, leathery, margins entire or obscurely toothed, secondary veins obscure,
        branching and anastomosing before reaching margin. Inflorescences staminate or androgynous,
        axillary, clustered at ends of branches, spicate, ascending, rigid or flexible; androgynous
        inflorescences with pistillate cupules/flowers toward base and staminate flowers distally.
        Staminate flowers: sepals distinct; stamens (6-)12(-18), typically surrounding indurate
        pistillode covered with silky hairs. Pistillate flowers (1-)3 or more per cupule; sepals
        distinct; carpels and styles typically 3. Fruits: maturation in 2d year following
        pollination (termed biennial by many authors); cupule 2-several-valved, valves distinct,
        completely enclosing nuts, densely spiny, spines irregularly branched, interlocking, without
        simple hairs, with large, yellowish, multicellular glands; nuts (1-)3-several per cupule,
        3-angled to rounded in cross section, not winged, adjacent nuts separated from each other by
        internal cupule valves. x = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Western chinkapin</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2</discussion>
  <discussion>Nuts are sweet and edible but difficult to remove from the spiny cupules unless
        completely ripe. The two species of Chrysolepis have sometimes been included in Castanopsis;
        the latter, however, is a related genus of Fagaceae, native to Asia, with very different
        cupule structure (H.Hjelmquist 1948; L.L. Forman 1966).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
