<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Clematis</genus_name><species_name>orientalis</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 543. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><illustrated>illustrated</illustrated><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Viticella</genus_name><species_name>orientalis</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) W.A. Weber</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems climbing, 2-8 m. Leaf blade pinnately 5-7-foliolate, proximal leaflets sometimes 3-foliolate; leaflets lanceolate to elliptic or ovate, usually 2-3-lobed proximally, 1-5.5 × 0.5-3.5 cm, margins entire or coarsely few-toothed; surfaces at least abaxially pubescent, glaucous. Inflorescences axillary, sometimes terminal, 3-many-flowered cymes or flowers solitary. Flowers bisexual; pedicel (0.5-)1-11 cm; sepals wide-spreading and recurved, greenish yellow, ovate-lanceolate to elliptic, 0.8-2 cm, length ca. 2.5 times width, margins densely pubescent, abaxially and adaxially pubescent or abaxially glabrous; stamens 20-40; filaments pilose proximally; staminodes absent; pistils 75-150. Achenes turgid, not conspicuously rimmed, pilose; beak 2-5 cm.</description><phenology>Flowering summer-fall</phenology><habitat> Roadsides, other secondary habitats, open woods</habitat><elevation> 0-2600 m</elevation><introduced> introduced</introduced><ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Colo.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Utah</us_distribution><global_distribution> native to Eurasia.</global_distribution><discussion>Clematis orientalis has been reported from Idaho; it probably can be expected elsewhere.</discussion><discussion>This species has been divided by C. Grey-Wilson (1989) into five varieties, partly correlated with their distribution in Asia. Naturalized plants in North America seem best referred to C. orientalis var. robusta Grey-Wilson, native to Afghanistan.</discussion><discussion>Although Clematis orientalis has been naturalized in the Rocky Mountains since the late nineteenth century, it has spread especially rapidly since ca. 1975, becoming weedy and, in some localities, constituting a threat to young trees and native shrubby and herbaceous species.</discussion></treatment>
