<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">CLEMATIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 543. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 242. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus CLEMATIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek clema, plant shoot, ancient name of a vine]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>6.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Clematis</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">clématite</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 300 (32 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Clematis is highly diverse in vegetative and floral aspects and has been divided into three or more genera by some authors, the groups segregated in some literature being Clematis subg. Atragene as the genus Atragene and Clematis subg. Viticella as the genus Viticella. Species in Clematis subg. Viorna have been crossed with highly dissimilar species in Clematis subg. Clematis and Clematis subg. Viticella, and species in Clematis subg. Clematis have been crossed with species in Clematis subg. Viticella. Chromosome morphology is strikingly similar in all subgenera.</discussion>
  <discussion>The circumscription of subgenera in this work follows C. S. Keener and W. M. Dennis (1982). Major realignments have been proposed by F. B. Essig (1992) on the basis of seedling morphology, including the transfer of Clematis recta and C. terniflora to Clematis subg. Viorna.</discussion>
  <discussion>Many species are valued as ornamentals; some have escaped from cultivation and have become established in the flora.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Essig, F. B. 1992. Seedling morphology in Clematis (Ranunculaceae) and its taxonomic implications. Sida 15: 377-390.</reference>
    <reference>James, J. F. 1883. Revision of the genus Clematis of the United States. J. Cincinnati Soc. Nat. Hist. 6: 118-135.</reference>
    <reference>Keener, C. S. 1975. Studies in the Ranunculaceae of the southeastern United States. III. Clematis L. Sida 6: 33-47.</reference>
    <reference>Keener, C. S. and W. M. Dennis. 1982. The subgeneric classification of Clematis (Ranunculaceae) in temperate North America north of Mexico. Taxon 31: 37-44.</reference>
    <reference>Kuntze, O. 1885. Monographie der Gattung Clematis. Verh. Bot. Vereins Prov. Brandenburg 26: 6-202.</reference>
    <reference>Torrey, J. and A. Gray. 1838-1843. A Flora of North America. 2 vols. in 7 parts. New York, London, and Paris. Vol. 1, pp. 7-11.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
