<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">clematis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Clematis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae;genus clematis;subgenus Clematis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Woody vines (erect, herbaceous perennials in C. recta). Leaf blade 1-2-pinnate; leaflets lobed or unlobed, margins entire or toothed. Inflorescences terminal and/or axillary on current year's stems, cymes or panicles or flowers solitary or paired, bracteate. Flowers bisexual, or unisexual with staminate and pistillate on different plants, not nodding, or ± nodding in yellow-flowered species; perianth rotate; sepals spreading, not connivent, linear, oblong, elliptic, lanceolate, ovate, oblanceolate, or obovate, thin and white or somewhat thickened and yellow; filaments filiform, slender, glabrous or pubescent; staminodes absent from staminate flowers, usually present in pistillate flowers; pistils rudimentary or absent in staminate flowers. Achenes flattened or nearly terete; beak more than 1.5 cm, plumose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 50-100 (11 in the flora): worldwide.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 50-100 (11 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>worldwide.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>6a.</number>
  <discussion>Species 50-100 (11 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The Asian (Korean) species Clematis serratifolia Rehder, with light yellow sepals and purple stamens, may also escape from cultivation and spread locally.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Essig, F. B. 1990. The Clematis virginiana (Ranunculaceae) complex in the southeastern United States. Sida 14: 49-68. Grey-</reference>
    <reference>Hara, H. 1975. The identity of Clematis terniflora DC. J. Jap. Bot. 50: 155-158.</reference>
    <reference>Wilson, C. 1989. Clematis orientalis (Ranunculaceae) and its allies. Kew Bull. 44: 33-60.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
