<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Salisbury" date="unknown">COPTIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8:305. 1807</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae; genus COPTIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek, kopto, to cut, referring to dissected leaves]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from orange, yellow, or pale brown, slender rhizomes 0.5-2 mm thick. Leaves basal, petiolate. Leaf blade 1-2-ternately compound, 1-2-pinnately compound, or deeply divided; leaflets ovate or triangular, lobed or parted, margins sharply serrate to denticulate. Inflorescences scapose, 1-4-flowered cymes, to 3 cm (9 cm in fruit); bracts absent. Flowers bisexual and staminate (all bisexual in C. trifoliata), radially symmetric; sepals not persistent in fruit, 5-7, green to white, plane, linear-lanceolate, oblanceolate to obovate or elliptic, occasionally clawed, 4.2-11 mm; petals 5-7, distinct, green, plane or concave distally, either clavate with adaxial nectary at apex or linear with adaxial nectary near base, clawed, 2-7 mm; stamens 10-60; filaments filiform; staminodes absent between stamens and pistils; pistils 4-15, simple; ovules 4-10 per pistil; style present. Fruits follicles, aggregate, stipitate, forming umbel-like clusters, oblong to ellipsoid, sides not veined; beak present or absent, terminal, straight or apically hooked, 0-4 mm. Seeds dark brown to tan, ellipsoid, shiny, often appearing wrinkled. x=9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate and boreal regions of North America and Asia.</description>
  <number>18.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Goldthread</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">coptide</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 10 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1929. Coptis trifolia and its eastern American representative. Rhodora 31: 136-142. Hultén, E. 1937. Flora of the Aleutian Islands and Westernmost Alaska Pensinsula with Notes on the Flora of Commander Islands.... Stockholm.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
