<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">fumariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="de Candolle in J. Lamarck and A. P. de Candolle" date="1805">corydalis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. Gray" date="1874">caseana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 69. 1874</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fumariaceae;genus corydalis;species caseana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, glaucous, from large, fleshy roots. Stems 1-several, 10-15 dm or more. Leaves ca. 5, compound, to 10 dm; blade with 2-4 orders of leaflets and lobes; ultimate lobes of proximal cauline leaves narrowly to broadly elliptic, 1-5 cm, apiculate. Inflorescences paniculate, 50 or more flowers on primary axis; bracts inconspicuous, linear or narrowly elliptic, rarely wider, proximal bracts ca. 10 mm, distal greatly reduced. Flowers ascending or spreading; pedicel 3-5 mm; sepals persistent, round and irregularly dentate to ovate, lunate, or attenuate-lanceolate with broad, sometimes lobed base, 2-3 mm; petals light pink to white, inner ones tipped reddish purple; spurred petal often incurved, 16-25 mm, spur tapered or not, 9-16 mm, apex obtuse, crest absent, inconspicuous, or extending into beak beyond petal apices, marginal wing narrow to broad, conspicuous; unspurred outer petal 10-15 mm; inner petals 7-12 mm, claw 3-5 mm; nectariferous spur 1/2-3/4 length of petal spur; style 3-4 mm; stigma roughly rectangular, with 8 papillae. Capsules reflexed, ellipsoid, 10-15 × ca. 3-5 mm. Seeds ca. 2.5 mm diam., with numerous minute protuberances.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Fitweed</other_name>
  <discussion>weedy</discussion>
  <discussion>Subspecies 5 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Significant livestock losses have been caused by ingestion of Corydalis caseana, which is palatable to both cattle and sheep, despite the toxicity.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
