<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">fumariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="de Candolle in J. Lamarck and A. P. de Candolle" date="1805">CORYDALIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Lamarck and A. P. de Candolle,  Fl. Franç. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3, 4: 637. 1805, name conserved</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fumariaceae;genus CORYDALIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek korydallis, crested lark]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual, biennial, or perennial, caulescent, from taproots, tubers, or rhizomes. Stems erect to prostrate, simple or branching. Leaves basal and/or cauline, simple or usually compound; blade with 2-6 orders of leaflets and/or lobes. Inflorescences axillary or terminal, paniculate or racemose, multifloral, sometimes cleistogamous-flowered (in Corydalis flavula, occasionally C. micrantha). Flowers bilaterally symmetric about 1 plane; sepals caducous or persistent; petals distinct or somewhat coherent basally, not spongy; outer petals dissimilar, each with median adaxial keel or crest, sometimes with distal marginal wing, 1 basally spurred, the other sometimes gibbous but not spurred; inner petals connate apically; stamens with nectariferous spur projecting from near base of median filament in bundle opposite spurred petal and adhering to inner surface of petal spur; ovary broadly ovoid to obovoid; stigma persistent, with or without 2 lobes or apical horns, or 4-8 papillar stigmatic surfaces. Capsules dehiscent, 2-valved. Seeds few-many, reniform to subglobose, elaiosome usually present. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate North America, Eurasia, and Africa.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 100 (10 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Several native species of Corydalis have been grown as ornamentals, particularly C. scouleri, C. aurea, C. sempervirens, and C. caseana; they may be found as garden escapes in areas of the continent outside their natural ranges. Two Eurasian species that are widely cultivated in the flora area also escape sometimes, but evidently they are not truly naturalized here. Corydalis lutea (Linneaus) de Candolle, reported from New York and Oregon, can be distinguished from the native species that also are rhizomatous perennials by its yellow petals and axillary racemes. Corydalis solida (Linneaus) Swartz (sometimes identified as C. bulbosa Persoon), reported from Connecticut, Massachusetts, Vermont, and southern Ontario, can be distinguished from the native species that also are tuberous perennials by its lack of sepals, pedicels usually longer than 10 mm, and sometimes yellow petals.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ownbey, G. B. 1947. Monograph of the North American species of Corydalis. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 34: 187-260.</reference>
    <reference>Ownbey, G. B. 1951. On the cytotaxonomy of the genus Corydalis, section Eucorydalis. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 45(1): 164-186.</reference>
    <reference>Ryberg, M. 1955. A taxonomical survey of the genus Corydalis Ventenat, with reference to cultivated species. Acta Hort. Berg. 17(5): 155-175.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
