<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">annonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Small" date="1924">DEERINGOTHAMNUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>51: 389. 1924</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family annonaceae;genus DEERINGOTHAMNUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Charles Deering, frequent sponsor of J. K. Small in his botanical explorations]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, 2-3(-5) dm, from stout-linear or fusiform taproots. Bark thin, glabrate. Shoots arching to semidecumbent, simple or sparingly branched, glabrate; lenticels pale; buds naked. Leaves tardily deciduous. Leaf blade leathery, glabrate. Inflorescences from axils of new shoot leaves, solitary flowers; peduncle not bracteate. Flowers ascending to nodding; receptacle flat-surfaced; sepals persistent, (2-)3(-4), oblong to ovate, imbricate in bud; petals 6-9(-15) in 2 whorls, ±equal, fleshy, veins impressed adaxially, imbricate in bud; stamens 10-20(-25), erect in flat-topped mass; connective short-cylindric, extruding, blunt; pistils 1-5(-7), distinct, narrowly fusiform, glabrate; ovules 3-8 per pistil in 2 staggered rows. Fruits simple berries, 1-5 per flower, yellow-green, unevenly oblong-cylindric, pulpy, insipid. Seeds 3-8 per pistil, bean-shaped to ovoid, coat tough, margins absent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">peninsular Florida.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kral, R. 1983c. Deeringothamnus. In: R. Kral, ed. 1983. A Report on Some Rare, Threatened, or Endangered Forest-related Plants of the South. Washington. Pp. 452-456. [U.S.D.A. Forest Service Techn. Publ. R8-TP 2.]</reference>
    <reference>Wilbur, R. L. 1970. Taxonomic and nomenclatural observations on the eastern North American genus Asimina (Annonaceae). J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. 86(2): 88-96.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
