<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">delphinium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subsection" authority="Ewan" date="1936">Subscaposa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>63: 330. 1936</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae;genus delphinium;subsection Subscaposa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots 3-8(-12)-branched at least 1 cm from stem attachment, (4-)10-30(-40) cm, fibrous, twisted, dry, thin threadlike segments apparent nearly entire length; buds minute. Stems 1(-3) per root, unbranched, elongation delayed 4-10 weeks after leaf initiation; base often narrowed, firmly attached to root; proximal internodes much shorter than those of midstem. Leaves basal and cauline, largest near base of stem, others often abruptly smaller on distal stem; basal petioles spreading, cauline petioles ascending; basal leaves more rounded and with fewer, wider lobes than cauline leaves. Inflorescences usually 4-8 flowers per 5 cm, ± open, cylindric to narrowly pyramidal, seldom less than 4 times longer than wide, spurs rarely intersecting rachis; pedicel spreading to ascending, usually less than 2 cm, rachis to midpedicel angle more than 30°; bracts markedly smaller, fewer lobed than leaves. Fruits erect. Seeds rectangular to crescent-shaped, 1.3-3.3 × 1.1-2.3 mm, not ringed on proximal end, ± wing-margined; seed coats usually lacking wavy ridges (present only in D. purpusii), cells brick-shaped (less than 3 times longer than wide), cell margins undulate or straight.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">possibly others in Asia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 10+ (10 in the flora): North America, possibly others in Asia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 10+ (10 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, possibly others in Asia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>16b.4.</number>
  <discussion>Species 10+ (10 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
