<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">delphinium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subsection" authority="N. I. Malyutin" date="1987">Exaltata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Zhurn. (Moscow &amp; Leningrad)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>72: 688. 1987</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae;genus delphinium;subsection Exaltata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots 4-15-branched, 10-80 cm, twisted fibrous, dry; buds more than 3 mm, usually present throughout dormant season. Stems (1-)3-8(-19) per root, usually unbranched, elongation commencing within 2 weeks of leaf initiation; base not narrowed, firmly attached to root; proximal internodes similar in length to those of midstem. Leaves cauline, largest at or slightly below middle of stem, others gradually reduced into bracts; petiole ± ascending; blade shape and lobing similar throughout. Inflorescences usually 5-10 flowers per 5 cm, ± dense, cylindric (greatly shortened in some), spurs rarely intersecting rachis; pedicel ± spreading, usually less than 2 cm; rachis to midpedicel angle more than 30°; bracts ± similar to leaves but smaller. Fruits erect. Seeds rectangular to crescent-shaped, 1.5-3.5 × 1.2-2.5 mm, not ringed at proximal end, wing-margined or not; seed coats ± with small irregular wavy ridges or ripples, cells elongate, cell margins straight.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">at least 1 species and probably more in Asia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 13 or more (12 in the flora): North America, Mexico, at least 1 species and probably more in Asia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 13 or more (12 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, at least 1 species and probably more in Asia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>16b.1.</number>
  <discussion>Species 13 or more (12 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Members of Delphinium subsect. Exaltata are the typical tall larkspurs of poisonous-plant literature. Their abundance on some ranges, combined with their large size and toxicity, make them significant sources of livestock poisoning. Several of the species in this subsection (Delphinium andesicola, D. californicum, D. glaucum, D. novomexicanum, D. robustum, D. sapellonis, and the Mexican D. valens Standley) form a tightly knit group in which the degree of difference between members of the group and patterns of variation within the members appear largely determined by the degree and length of isolation in the various mountain ranges where the plants are found. Delphinium andesicola, D. novomexicanum, D. robustum, D. sapellonis, and D. valens form the southern Cordilleran complex.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
