<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">delphinium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subsection" authority="(N. I. Malyutin) M. J. Warnock" date="1995">Grumosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>78: 92. 1995</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae;genus delphinium;subsection Grumosa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Delphinium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="N. I. Malyutin" date="unknown">Grumosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Zhurn. (Leningrad &amp; Moscow)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>72: 689. 1987</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Delphinium;section Grumosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots 1-5(-9)-branched from within 1 cm of stem attachment, 2-7(-16) cm, cormlike to fascicled or fibrous, ± fleshy, ± succulent, usually brittle; buds minute. Stems 1(-2) per root, usually unbranched, elongation delayed 2-10 weeks after leaf initiation; base narrowed, tenuously attached to root; proximal internodes much shorter than those of midstem. Leaves basal and cauline, largest leaves near base of stem, others usually gradually smaller on distal portion of stem; basal petioles spreading, cauline petioles ascending; blade shape and lobing similar throughout. Inflorescences usually with 2-6 flowers per 5 cm, open, ± pyramidal, usually at least 3 times longer than wide, spurs rarely intersecting rachis; pedicel spreading, usually more than 1.5 cm, rachis to midpedicel angle more than 30°; bracts markedly smaller and fewer lobed than leaves. Fruits ± spreading. Seeds obpyramidal, 1.5-2.7 × 0.7-2 mm, ringed at proximal end, wing-margined or not; seed coats usually lacking wavy ridges, cells usually elongate (short and narrow in D. alabamicum, D. newtonianum, D. nuttallianum, and D. treleasei), smooth or roughened, cell margins straight.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, possibly others in Asia.</description>
  <number>16b.9.</number>
  <discussion>Species 13 or more (13 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Delphinium subsect. Grumosa is an extremely difficult complex, with many variations in a number of morphologic traits. Two divergent views of the complex were represented in the work of D. M. Sutherland (1967), in which the species recognized were large agglomerations, and that of P. A. Rydberg (1917), in which species rank was used for some edaphic variants. The complex has been and continues to be a major source of confusion for identification of Delphinium in North America. Most of the low larkspurs in poisonous-plant literature are members of this subsection.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
