<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>23b.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Delphinium</genus_name><species_name>parryi</species_name><species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority><subspecies_name>maritimum</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Davidson) M. J. Warnock</subspecies_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Phytologia </publication_title><place_in_publication>68(1): 2. 1990</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Maritime larkspur</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Delphinium</genus_name><species_name>parryi</species_name><variety_name>maritimum</variety_name><variety_authority>Davidson</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Muhlenbergia </publication_title><place_in_publication>4: 35. 1908</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Roots less than 10 cm. Stems 15-40 cm. Leaves well distributed; basal and cauline leaves present at anthesis; ultimate lobes 5-10, width usually more than 6 mm. Inflorescences: bracteoles 4-9 mm. Flowers: sepals usually spreading, lateral sepals 9-20 mm, spurs 8-21 mm; lower petal blades 4-11 mm. 2n = 16.</description><phenology>Flowering late winter-spring</phenology><habitat> Coastal chaparral</habitat><elevation> 0-300 m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico (Baja California).</global_distribution><discussion>Populations of Delphinium parryi subsp. maritimum are local, very near the coast. The species also occurs on islands off southern California and northern Baja California, Mexico. Occasional individuals with white to grayish blue sepals occur (mostly in Ventura and western Los Angeles counties, where entire populations may consist of such individuals). Collections of subsp. maritimum made before 1940 are numerous; recent collections are much less common. Population reductions have probably resulted from urbanization of its preferred habitat.</discussion><discussion>Confused with Delphinium variegatum, D. parryi subsp. maritimum lacks the long hairs of that species. Some plants of subsp. maritimum (unringed seeds, erect fruits, and arched hairs) from very near the coast appear superficially like some plants of D. nuttallianum (ringed seeds, spreading fruits, and no arched hairs).</discussion></treatment>
