<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">delphinium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subsection" authority="M. J. Warnock" date="1984">Wislizenana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>31: 243. 1984</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae;genus delphinium;subsection Wislizenana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots 3-8-branched, (5-)15-24(-80) cm, twisted fibrous, dry to fleshy, thin threadlike segments apparent nearly entire length; buds sometimes more than 3 mm, usually absent during dormant season. Stems 1(-4) per root, usually unbranched, elongation delayed 2-10 weeks after leaf initiation; base usually not narrowed, firmly attached to root; proximal internodes much shorter than those of midstem. Leaves basal and cauline, largest near base of stem, others usually abruptly smaller on distal portion of stem; basal petioles spreading, cauline petioles ascending; basal leaves more rounded and with fewer, wider lobes than cauline leaves. Inflorescences usually 2-9 flowers per 5 cm, open to dense, cylindric-narrow-pyramidal, spurs rarely intersecting rachis; pedicel spreading to ascending, often more than 2 cm, rachis to midpedicel angle more than 30°; bracts usually smaller and fewer lobed than leaves. Fruits erect. Seeds rectangular to crescent-shaped, 2-3.5 × 1.3-2.5 mm, not ringed on proximal end, wing-margined or not; seed coats ± covered with small irregular wavy ridges, cells short (less than 3 times longer than wide), cell margins usually straight.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico.</description>
  <number>16b.2.</number>
  <discussion>Species 12 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
