<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>23a.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Delphinium</genus_name><species_name>parryi</species_name><species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority><subspecies_name>parryi</subspecies_name></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Parry's larkspur</common_name><illustrated>illustrated</illustrated><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Delphinium</genus_name><species_name>hesperium</species_name><species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority><variety_name>seditiosum</variety_name><variety_authority>Jepson</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Delphinium</genus_name><species_name>parryi</species_name><subspecies_name>seditiosum</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Jepson) Ewan</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Roots 5-20 cm. Stems (35-)60-90(-110) cm. Leaves: basal leaves usually absent at anthesis; cauline leaves with ultimate lobes 7-27, width 1-6 mm. Inflorescences: bracteoles 3-7 mm. Flowers: sepals usually spreading, lateral sepals 9-15 mm, spurs 8-15 mm; lower petal blades 3-8 mm. 2n = 16.</description><phenology>Flowering spring</phenology><habitat> Locally abundant in oak woodland, chaparral</habitat><elevation> 200-1700 m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico (Baja California).</global_distribution><discussion>Two morphotypes may be recognized in Delphinium parryi subsp. parryi. That corresponding to the type specimen of subsp. parryi has larger flowers (especially lower petal blades), less abundant pubescence, and somewhat more coarsely dissected leaves; it is usually found in woodlands or relatively moist chaparral. The second morphotype, in its extreme represented by the type specimen of D. parryi var. seditiosum, has smaller flowers, more pubescence, and more finely dissected leaves and is usually found in chaparral and, less often, in dry woodlands. It may occur sporadically throughout the range of D. parryi subsp. parryi, although it is most common north of the Transverse Ranges. Hybrids with D. cardinale have been named D. ×inflexum. Hybrids are also known with D. gypsophilum subsp. parviflorum, D. hesperium subsp. pallescens, D. umbraculorum, and D. variegatum.</discussion><discussion>Delphinium parryi subsp. parryi may be confused with the blue-flowered phases of D. hesperium; see discussion under that species for distinguishing features.</discussion></treatment>
