<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. Jussieu" date="unknown">papaveraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Chamisso in C. G. D. Nees" date="1793">ESCHSCHOLZIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in C. G. D. Nees,  Horae Phys. Berol.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>73. 1820</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family papaveraceae;genus ESCHSCHOLZIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Johann F. G. von Eschscholtz, 1793-1831, Estonian physician and biologist who traveled with Chamisso on the Romanzoff (or Kotzebue) Expedition to the Pacific Coast]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, scapose or caulescent, from taproots; sap colorless or clear orange. Stems leafy. Leaves alternate, basal and sometimes cauline, petiolate; blade 1-4× pinnately deeply lobed, lobes of each order usually 3; ultimate lobes narrow. Inflorescences terminal, cymose with bracts present, or 1-flowered. Flowers: receptacle dilated, forming cup beneath calyx, sometimes with free rim; perianth and androecium perigynous; sepals 2, connate, calyptrate, deciduous as unit; petals 4, rarely more (doubled flowers), obovate to obcuneate, with satin sheen from microscopic linear grooves; stamens 12-many; pistil 2-carpellate; ovary 1-locular; style absent; stigmas 4-8, spreading, linear. Fruits capsular, cylindric, 2-valved, dehiscing from base along placentas, often explosively. Seeds many, tan, brown, or black, spheric to ovoid, reticulate, ridged and burlike, or pitted, aril absent. x = 6, 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America (United States)</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 12 (10 in the flora): w North America (United States), nw Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 12 (10 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w North America (United States), nw Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>7.</number>
  <discussion>Species 12 (10 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Eschscholzia species are introduced from cultivation elsewhere in warm-temperate regions worldwide.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Clark, C. and J. A. Jernstedt. 1978. Systematic studies of Eschscholzia (Papaveraceae). II. Seed coat microsculpturing. Syst. Bot. 3: 386-402.</reference>
    <reference>Ernst, W. R. 1964b. The genus Eschscholzia in the south Coast Ranges of California. Madroño 17: 281-294.</reference>
    <reference>Greene, E. L. 1905b. Revision of Eschscholtzia. Pittonia 5: 205-308.</reference>
    <reference>Lewis, H. and R. Snow. 1951. A cytotaxonomic approach to Eschscholzia. Madroño 11: 141-143.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
