<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">HAMAMELIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 124. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 59. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus HAMAMELIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek name used by Hippocrates for medlar, Mespilus germanica Linnaeus]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Witch-hazel</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 4 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>In Hamamelis, the explosively dehiscent capsules may eject the seeds to 10 m. The Japanese species H. japonica Siebold &amp; Zuccarini, with reddish to yellow flowers, suggests an affinity with H. vernalis. Both Asian species, H. japonica and H. mollis Oliver of China, and the hybrid H. ×intermedia Rehder (= H. japonica × H. mollis), with a number of cultivars, are widely cultivated.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bradford, J. L. and D. L. Marsh. 1977. Comparative studies of the witch hazels Hamamelis virginiana and H. vernalis. Proc. Arkansas Acad. Sci. 31: 29-31. De Steven, D. 1983. Floral ecology of witch-hazel (Hamamelis virginiana). Michigan Bot. 22(4): 163-171.</reference>
    <reference>Fulling, E. H. 1953. American witch hazel--History, nomenclature, and modern utilization. Econ. Bot. 7(4): 359-389.</reference>
    <reference>Jenne, G. E. 1966. A Study of Variation in North American Hamamelis L. (Hamamelidaceae). M.S. thesis. Vanderbilt University. Sargent, C. S. 1890-1902. The Silva of North America.... 14 vols. Boston and New York. Vol. 5, pp. 3-5.</reference>
    <reference>Sargent, C. S. [1902-]1905-1913. Trees and Shrubs.... 2 vols. Boston and New York. Vol. 2, pp. 137-138.</reference>
    <reference>Shoemaker, D. N. 1905. On the development of Hamamelis virginiana. Bot. Gaz. 39: 248-266.</reference>
    <reference>Steyermark, J. A. 1934. Hamamelis virginiana in Missouri. Rhodora 36: 97-100.</reference>
    <reference>Steyermark, J. A. 1963. Flora of Missouri. Ames.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
