<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Trees or shrubs, deciduous; pubescence stellate or sometimes simple. Dormant buds naked or scaly. Leaves alternate, simple, petiolate; stipules early deciduous. Leaf blade unlobed or deeply (3-)5-7-lobed, pinnately or palmately veined. Inflorescences axillary or terminal, capitate or spicate to ± racemose, bracteate. Flowers bisexual or unisexual; perianth epigynous, 1-2-seriate, 4-5-merous, often reduced or absent, hypanthium present; calyx persistent, 4-5(-7)-lobed, or absent; petals distinct or absent; stamens 4-34; anthers basifixed, latrorse, 2-locular, longitudinally dehiscent by simple slit or by 1-2 vertical valves; pistil 1, 2-carpellate; ovary half-inferior, 2-locular; placentation axile; ovules 1(-2) in each locule and apical, or many, anatropous, pendent; styles and stigmas persistent, 2 each, erect or contorted and recurved. Fruits capsular, with leathery exocarp and bony endocarp, loculicidal and 2-seeded or septicidal with most of many seeds per locule aborted; 1-2 viable seeds per locule (Liquidambar). Seeds fusiform, bony, lustrous, hilum apical, light colored, or seeds winged, hilum lateral (Liquidambar).</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Glaucium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Crantz" date="unknown">flavum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">HAMAMELIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Glaucium;species flavum;family HAMAMELIDACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="distribution">temperate to tropical regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">e North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">e Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa (including Madagascar)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">and Australia.</description>
  <other_name type="common_name">Witch-hazel Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 31, species ca. 100 (3 genera, 5 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bogle, A. L. 1970. Floral morphology and vascular anatomy of the Hamamelidaceae: The apetalous genera of Hamamelidoideae. J. Arnold Arbor. 51: 310-366.</reference>
    <reference>Britton, N. L. 1905. Hamamelidaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 22, pp. 185-187.</reference>
    <reference>Endress, P. K. 1987. Aspects of evolutionary differentiation of the Hamamelidaceae and the lower Hamamelidae. Pl. Syst. Evol. 162: 193-211.</reference>
    <reference>Endress, P. K. 1989. A suprageneric taxonomic classification of the Hamamelidaceae. Taxon 38(3): 371-376.</reference>
    <reference>Endress, P. K. 1989b. Phylogenetic relationships in the Hamamelidoideae. In: P. R. Crane and S. Blackmore, eds. 1989. Evolution, Systematics, and Fossil History of the Hamamelidae. 2 vols. Oxford. Vol. 1, pp. 227-248. [Syst. Assoc. Special Vol. 40A, B.]</reference>
    <reference>Godfrey, R. K. 1988. Trees, Shrubs, and Woody Vines of Northern Florida and Adjacent Georgia and Alabama. Athens, Ga.</reference>
    <reference>Ernst, W. R. 1963. The genera of Hamamelidaceae and Platanaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 44: 193-210.</reference>
    <reference>Goldblatt, P. and P. K. Endress. 1977. Cytology and evolution in Hamamelidaceae. J. Arnold Arbor. 58: 67-71.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
