<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">aristolochiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="1825">HEXASTYLIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Neogenyton,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3. 1825</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family aristolochiaceae;genus HEXASTYLIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hexastylis, with six styles]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, evergreen, rhizomatous, without aerial stems. Leaves alternate, 2-ranked; stipules absent; petiolate foliage leaves and sessile, triangular scale-leaves both present. Leaf blade membranous or leathery, glabrous. Inflorescences terminal on rhizome, solitary flowers, subtended by triangular bract. Flowers: sepals connate for most of length, usually mixture of brown, purple, or yellow, externally glabrous, inner surface glabrous, with weak to strong network of ridges, calyx tube never forming differentiated utricle or syrinx; vestigial petals absent; stamens 12, distinct; filaments shorter than pollen sacs; terminal appendage of anther absent or rudimentary; ovary superior or partly inferior, 6-locular; styles 6, distinct (except sometimes at extreme base). Capsule fleshy, dehiscence irregular. Seeds ovoid, not winged, with fleshy appendage. x = 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 10 (all in the flora): North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 10 (all in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Heartleaf</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 10 (all in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Hexastylis is very similar to the Asiatic genera Heterotropa C. Morren &amp; Decaisne and Asiasarum F. Maekawa; a strong case could be made for combining the three genera. Nevertheless, all three of these genera seem distinct from Asarum (in which they have been included by some authors; e.g., K. Barringer 1993) in their connate sepals, distinct styles, nonappendiculate anthers, and superior or partly inferior ovaries.</discussion>
  <discussion>Herbarium specimens of Hexastylis are difficult to work with. The form of the calyx is very important taxonomically, but the calyx is fleshy and brittle and does not press well. Allowing flowers to wilt for several hours before pressing may help to reduce distortion, because the calyx becomes more flexible and less likely to split in the press. Features of the inner surface of the calyx are also important, but collectors seldom cut open flowers and press them with the inside visible. For this reason, herbarium specimens of Hexastylis are difficult to identify reliably, and meaningful work on the group requires field studies. L. L. Gaddy (1987) and H. L. Blomquist (1957) gave photographs and drawings of flowers of all species, and an extensive collection of liquid-preserved flowers is housed to the University of Tennessee; these are very helpful in identifying Hexastylis specimens.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Blomquist, H. L. 1957. A revision of Hexastylis of North America. Brittonia 8: 255-281.</reference>
    <reference>Gaddy, L. L. 1987. A review of the taxonomy and biogeography of Hexastylis (Aristolochiaceae). Castanea 52: 186-196.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
