<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="(de Candolle) A. C. Smith" date="unknown">illiciaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1759">ILLICIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Nat. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10, 2: 1042, 1050, 1370. 1759</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family illiciaceae;genus ILLICIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin illicere, to allure]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kuntze" date="unknown">Badianifera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Badianifera;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Leaves sometimes appearing whorled at ends of branches. Flowers erect to drooping; peduncle smooth to rugulose; perianth white, yellow, yellow-green, pink, or red to maroon, often glandular; outer tepals often bractlike and reduced, sometimes ciliolate, inner tepals often much larger and ligulate, sometimes only slightly larger and broadly obtuse, innermost often reduced, sometimes transitional to stamens; pistils orbicular to deltoid, styles narrow and acute, often recurved. Fruits dark brown, woody to leathery at maturity; peduncle sometimes thickened. Seeds glossy, dark brown to tawny or golden. x = 13, 14.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, West Indies, Central America, and ne South America</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Star-anise</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 42 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Dirr, M. A. 1986. Hardy Illicium species display commendable attributes. Amer. Nurseryman 163: 92-100.</reference>
    <reference>Jones, S. B. and N. C. Coile. 1988. The Distribution of the Vascular Flora of Georgia. Athens, Ga.</reference>
    <reference>Thien, L. B., D. A. White, and L. Y. Yatsu. 1983. The reproductive biology of a relict--Illicium floridanum Ellis. Amer. J. Bot. 70: 719-727.</reference>
    <reference>Roberts, M. L. and R. R. Haynes. 1983. Ballistic seed dispersal in Illicium (Illiciaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 143: 227-232.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
