<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Trees, rarely shrubs, deciduous, with gray or brownish bark. Terminal buds larger than lateral buds. Leaves alternate [or opposite], aromatic, usually odd-, rarely even-, pinnately compound; stipules absent; petiole present. Leaflets 3-23, margins serrate or entire. Inflorescences: staminate catkins solitary or fasciculate, pendulous, elongate, on reduced shoots arising on branches of previous year or at base of current year's growth; pistillate catkins solitary or few-flowered spikes [or many-flowered racemes]. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on same plants; bract 1, bracteoles (0-)2. Staminate flowers: calyx 2-6-lobed or absent; corolla absent; stamens 3-50; filaments very short or absent; anthers usually pubescent. Pistillate flowers: calyx 4-lobed or absent; corolla absent; ovary 1, inferior, usually 2-carpellate, 1-locular distally; ovule 1; stigmas 2, fleshy or plumose. Fruits large nuts [or samaras], nuts enclosed in dehiscent or indehiscent, fibrous-fleshy or hard involucres (husks), thus ± drupelike. Seeds 1; endosperm absent; cotyledons fleshy and oily, variously lobed.</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Persoon" date="unknown">diphylla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. Richard ex Kunth" date="unknown">JUGLANDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>species diphylla</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="distribution">Western Hemisphere and Eurasia.</description>
  <other_name type="common_name">Walnut Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 7, species 59 (2 genera, 17 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The fruit in Juglandaceae superficially resembles a drupe, with a hard "stone" surrounded by a soft, often fleshy husk. The husk, however, is not part of the fruit wall (it develops from the involucre and calyx), and the fruit is actually a nut (T. S. Elias 1972; W. E. Manning 1978).</discussion>
  <discussion>The morphology and classification of the family were discussed by W. E. Manning (1978). The female inflorescences and fruits show considerable variation in Latin American and Eurasian taxa.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Elias, T. S. 1972. The genera of Juglandaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 53: 26-51.</reference>
    <reference>Manchester, S. R. 1987. The fossil history of the Juglandaceae. Monogr. Syst. Bot. Missouri Bot. Gard. 21: 1-137.</reference>
    <reference>Manning, W. E. 1978. The classification within the Juglandaceae. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 65: 1058-1087.</reference>
    <reference>Stone, D. E. 1993. Juglandaceae. In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 2 +vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 2, pp. 348-359.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
