<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Decaisne" date="unknown">LARDIZABALACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus LARDIZABALACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Vines [small trees or shrubs], woody, evergreen or deciduous. Stems without spines. Leaves alternate; stipules absent [except in Lardizabala]; petioles present. Leaf blade palmately compound [pinnately compound or 1-3-ternate]. Inflorescences axillary, racemes, occasionally solitary flowers, flowers pedicellate. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on same plants in same or different inflorescences [staminate and pistillate on different plants or flowers bisexual, staminate, and pistillate], showy, 3-merous; sepaloid bracteoles absent; sepals 3-6, distinct, usually petaloid, not spurred; petals absent [6; nectary present]. Staminate flowers: stamens 6(-8), distinct [proximally connate]; anthers with 2 pollen sacs, extrorse, dehiscing longitudinally; pistillodes sometimes present. Pistillate flowers: staminodes sometimes present; pistils 3-15 in 1-5 whorls of 3 each, 1-carpellate, 1-locular; placentation submarginal or laminar; ovules 100-several hundred [1-20]; stigma 1, sessile to nearly sessile. Fruits aggregates of berries or of fleshy follicles (sometimes only 1 pistil maturing). Seeds [1-]100-several hundred, never stalked; aril absent; endosperm abundant; embryo small, straight.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia.</description>
  <number>17.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Lardizabala Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 8, species ca. 30 (1 genus, 1 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Lardizabalaceae have a disjunct distribution. Two of the genera--Decaisnea and Lardizabala--are found in Chile; the others are Asiatic (Himalayas to Vietnam, Japan, and Korea).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ernst, W. R. 1964. The genera of Berberidaceae, Lardizabalaceae, and Menispermaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 45: 1-35.</reference>
    <reference>Matthews, V. A. 1989. Lardizabalaceae. In: S. M. Walters et al., eds. 1984+. The European Garden Flora. 3+ vols. Cambridge etc. Vol. 3, pp. 396-398.</reference>
    <reference>Prantl, K. 1888. Lardizabalaceae. In: H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl, eds. 1887-1915. Die natürlichen Pflanzenfamilien.... 254 fasc. Leipzig. Fasc. 19[III,2], pp. 67-70.</reference>
    <reference>Spongberg, S. A. and I. H. Burch. 1979. Lardizabalaceae hardy in temperate North America. J. Arnold Arbor. 60: 302-315.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
