<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Bentham" date="unknown">leitneriaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Chapman" date="1812">leitneria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Chapman" date="1860">floridana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. South. U.S.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>427. 1860</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family leitneriaceae;genus leitneria;species floridana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Myrica</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Chapman) A. W. Wood" date="unknown">floridana</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Myrica;species floridana;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or small trees, 1-4(-8) m, to 15 cm diam. at base. Stems unbranched or sparsely short-branched distally, slender, pubescent, becoming glabrous. Bark gray to dark reddish brown; lenticels numerous, gray. Leaves: petiole 2-7 cm, densely pubescent, becoming ± glabrous. Leaf blade lanceolate to elliptic-lanceolate, 5-20 × 3.5-6 cm, leathery, base acute, margins narrowly revolute, apex acute to acuminate; surfaces silky-pubescent when young, becoming glabrous and glossy adaxially. Inflorescences: staminate catkins cylindric in bud, lax and outward curving at anthesis, 2-6 × 1-1.5 cm; pistillate stiffly erect, 1-3 × 1 cm. Staminate flowers: stamens (3-)10-12(-15); filaments short; anthers basifixed, broadly oblong, 4-sporangiate, 2-locular at anthesis, dehiscing longitudinally. Pistillate flowers: sepals (3-)4(-8), irregularly inserted, unequal; ovary elliptic, ca. 2 mm, finely pubescent; style 4-5 mm; stigma exserted, often recurved or twisted, reddish. Drupes erect, green, becoming chestnut brown, elliptic to oblong-elliptic, often compressed on drying, 1-2.5 cm, glabrous, base and apex blunt, apex with conspicuous dark stylar scar, vascular bundles toughening the thin flesh; endocarp brown, bony, surface rough-reticulate. Seeds 1, compressed; seed coat membranous, hilum blackish, elongate; endosperm thin, starchy; embryo large, straight; cotyledons ovoid, slightly fleshy. 2n = 32.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late winter-early spring; fruiting spring-summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Open or forested swamps, wet thickets, roadside ditches, saw-grass-palmetto marshes, estuarine tidal shores;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-100 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ark., Fla., Ga., Mo., Tex.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
  <discussion>endemic</discussion>
  <discussion>illustrated</discussion>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
  <discussion>Vegetative reproduction is predominant, forming large clones from adventitious buds on shallow roots. Large, old plants ("small trees") are apparently rare in the field. Florida plants begin growth about a month before Missouri plants (J. W. Day 1975). Leitneria floridana is successfully cultivated as far north as Chicago, Rochester, and Boston.</discussion>
  <discussion>The wood (sp. gr. 0.21) is lighter than cork (sp. gr. 0.24); it is used locally for fishnet floats or bottle stoppers.</discussion>
  <discussion>endemic of conservation concern</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
