<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>27.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>LEITNERIACEAE</genus_name>
        <genus_authority>Bentham</genus_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <common_name>Corkwood Family</common_name>
    <description>Shrubs or small trees. Wood white to yellowish, soft, brittle, even-grained;
        secretory canals in outer pith; resin yellowish. Leaves alternate, not aromatic; stipules
        absent; petiole and veins with secretory canals. Inflorescences axillary catkins, erect or
        lax. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different (rarely on same) plants,
        inconspicuous, sessile; perianth absent or of small, undifferentiated sepals, hypogynous;
        pistils simple (rarely compound), 1(-2)-carpellate; ovary superior; placentation parietal;
        ovule 1, pendulous; style 1. Fruits drupes, leathery, dry.</description>
    <number_of_infrataxa>Genus 1, species 1</number_of_infrataxa>
    <global_distribution>se United States</global_distribution>
    <discussion>Leitneriaceae are a relict family confined to the flora area and occurring on
        coastal and riverine flood plains of the Atlantic and Gulf coasts. The fossil record of the
        family extends to the Middle Oligocene (32-30 M.Y.B.P.).</discussion>
    <discussion>Taxonomic affinities are uncertain. Various alliances have been suggested:
        Hamamelidales (A. Cronquist 1981), Sapindales (R. M. T. Dahlgren 1980), and Rutales (R. F.
        Thorne 1983) of the Rutiflorae. Biochemical studies (D. E. Giannasi 1986; F. P. Petersen and
        D. E. Fairbrothers 1983, 1985) suggest affinities with Simaroubaceae in
        Rutales.</discussion>
    <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES">
        <reference>Abbe, E. C. and T. T. Earle. 1940. Inflorescence, floral anatomy and morphology
            of Leitneria floridana. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 67: 173-193.</reference>
        <reference> Channell, R. B. and C. E. Wood Jr. 1962. The Leitneriaceae in the southeastern
            United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 43: 435-438.</reference>
        <reference> Giannasi, D. E. 1986. Phytochemical aspects of phylogeny in Hamamelidae. Ann.
            Missouri Bot. Gard. 73: 417-437.</reference>
        <reference> Jarvis, C. E. 1989. A review of the order Leitneriales Engler. In: P. R. Crane
            and S. Blackmore, eds. 1989. Evolution, Systematics, and Fossil History of the
            Hamamelidae. 2 vols. Oxford. Vol. 2, pp. 189-192. [Syst. Assoc. Special Vol. 40B.]
            Petersen, F. P. and D. E. Fairbrothers. 1983. A serotaxonomic appraisal of
            Amphipterygium and Leitneria--two amentiferous taxa of Rutiflorae (Rosidae). Syst. Bot.
            8: 134-148.</reference>
    </references>
</treatment>
