<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">hamamelidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">LIQUIDAMBAR</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 999. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 434. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hamamelidaceae;genus LIQUIDAMBAR</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin liquidus, fluid, liquid, and Arabic ambar, amber]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees, aromatic and resinous, glabrous or with simple hairs. Bark gray-brown, deeply furrowed; liquid, and Arabic ambar, [amber] twigs and branches sometimes corky-winged. Dormant buds scaly, pointed, shiny, resinous, sessile. Leaves long-petiolate. Leaf blade fragrant when crushed, (3-)5(-7)-lobed, palmately veined, base deeply cordate to truncate, margins glandular-serrate, apex of each lobe long-acuminate. Inflorescences terminal, many-flowered heads; staminate heads in pedunculate racemes, each head a cluster of many stamens; pistillate heads pendent, long-pedunculate, the flowers ± coalesced. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on same plant, appearing with leaves; calyx and corolla absent. Staminate flowers: anthers dehiscing longitudinally; staminodes absent. Pistillate flowers pale green to greenish yellow; staminodes 5-8; styles indurate and spiny in fruit, incurved. Capsules many, fused at base into long-pedunculate, spheric, echinate heads, 2-beaked, glabrous, septicidal. Seeds numerous, mostly aborting, 1-2 viable in each capsule, winged. x = 16.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, e Asia, and Turkey.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Species 3(-4) (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bogle, A. L. 1986. The floral morphology and vascular anatomy of the Hamamelidaceae: Subfamily Liquidambaroideae. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 73: 325-347.</reference>
    <reference>Duncan, W. H. 1959. Leaf variation in Liquidambar styraciflua L. Castanea 24: 99-111.</reference>
    <reference>Hill, A. F. 1952. Economic Botany. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Sargent, C. S. 1890-1902. The Silva of North America.... 14 vols. Boston and New York. Vol. 5, pp. 7-12.</reference>
    <reference>Schery, R. W. 1952. Plants for Man. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Wilson, P. 1905. Altingiaceae: Liquidambar. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 22, p. 189.</reference>
    <reference>Holm, T. 1930. Leaf-variation in Liquidambar styraciflua L. Rhodora 32: 95-105.</reference>
    <reference>Schmitt, D. 1966. Pistillate inflorescence of sweetgum (Liquidambar styraciflua L.). Silvae Genet. 15(2): 33-35.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
