<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>1.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Lithocarpus</genus_name>
        <species_name>densiflorus</species_name>
        <species_authority>(Hooker &amp; Arnott) Rehder</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>in L. H. Bailey, Stand. Cycl. Hort. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>6: 3569. 1917</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <common_name>Tanoak</common_name>
    <common_name> tanbark-oak</common_name>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
        <species_name>densiflora</species_name>
        <species_authority>Hooker &amp; Arnott</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Bot. Beechey Voy., </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>391. 1841</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Shrubs or trees, to 20(-45) m. Bark gray or brown, smooth or deeply furrowed. Twigs
        densely yellowish tomentose. Leaf blade adaxially convex, to 60-120 mm, leathery to brittle,
        margins often revolute, regularly toothed, teeth prominent to obscure; surfaces abaxially
        prominently and densely woolly, often glabrate at maturity, revealing gray or bluish green
        waxy surface, veins often distally impressed. Fruits: cup scales subulate, spreading to
        strongly recurved, hooked; nut yellowish brown, globose to cylindric-tapered, to 15-35 mm,
        extremely hard, densely tomentose, eventually glabrate.</description>
    <number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2: only in the flora.</number_of_infrataxa>
    <discussion>Sterile specimens of Lithocarpus densiflorus are often confused with Chrysolepis and
        vice versa. Nonfruiting material of L. densiflorus is recognizable by the loose tomentose
        pubescence of the leaves and inflorescences (although the leaves are often glabrate with
        age). Chrysolepis lacks this tomentose pubescence and has only a tight vestiture of
        glandular-peltate trichomes, except for some stellate and straight simple trichomes
        associated with the flowers.</discussion>
    <discussion>The Costanoan used infusions prepared from the bark of Lithocarpus densiflora (no
        varieties specified) as a wash for facial sores and to tighten loose teeth (D. E. Moerman
        1986).</discussion>
</treatment>
