<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>MAGNOLIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 535. 175</place_in_publication></place_of_publication><place_of_publication><publication_title> Gen. Pl. ed. </publication_title><place_in_publication>5, 240. 1754</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Pierre Magnol (1638-1715), professor and director of the botanical garden at Montpellier, France]</etymology><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Kobus</genus_name><genus_authority>Nieuwland</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Tulipastrum</genus_name><genus_authority>Spach</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Trees or shrubs, deciduous or evergreen. Pith homogeneous or diaphragmed. Leaves distinctly alternate or sometimes crowded in terminal whorl-like clusters; stipules early deciduous, free or adnate to and proximal on petiole. Leaf blade: base deeply cordate or auriculate or cuneate to abruptly narrowed or rounded, margins entire, apex obtuse or acute to acuminate; surfaces abaxially chalky white or green to glaucous, pubescent or glabrous. Flowers protogynous, appearing with or before leaves; tepals 9-15, petaloid, usually spreading, creamy white, rarely greenish, yellow, or orange-yellow, outermost tepals sepaloid, sometimes strongly reflexed, greenish; stamens on elongate torus, early deciduous; filaments white or purple, very short; anthers introrse or latrorse. Follicles persistent, coalescent, forming conelike aggregate, abaxially dehiscent. Seeds with red, pink, or orange oily aril, extruded from follicles and suspended by funiculi. x=19.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 120 (8 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> temperate and tropical regions</global_distribution><global_distribution> Western Hemisphere</global_distribution><global_distribution> Asia (Himalayas, China, Japan, Taiwan, Malaysia, and Indonesia).</global_distribution><discussion>All species of Magnolia in the flora are cultivated. Many of the Asiatic taxa are also grown in the flora area. Numerous hybrids and cultivars from those taxa have been introduced to horticulture.</discussion><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Callaway, D.J. 1994. The World of Magnolias. Portland. Coker, W.C. 1943. Magnolia cordata Michaux. J.Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. 59: 81-88.</reference><reference> Dandy, J.E. Notes on Magnolia and related genera. Unpublished manuscript. Botany Department, The Natural History Museum. London. Heiser, C.B. 1962. Some observations on pollination and compatibility in Magnolia. Proc. Indiana Acad. Sci. 72: 259-266.</reference><reference> Johnson, D.L. 1989. Species and Cultivars of the Genus Magnolia (Magnoliaceae) Cultivated in the United States. M.S. thesis. Cornell University. Johnson, D.L. 1989b. Nomenclatural changes in Magnolia. Baileya 23(1): 55-56.</reference><reference> McDaniel, J.C. 1966. Variations in the sweet bay magnolias. Morris Arbor. Bull. 17(1): 7-12.</reference><reference> Millais, J.G. 1927. Magnolias. London. Rockwell, H.C. 1966. The Genus Magnolia in the United States. M.S. thesis. West Virginia University. Santamour, F.S.Jr. 1969b. Cytology of Magnolia hybrids. I. Morris Arbor. Bull. 20(4): 63-65.</reference><reference> Thien, L.B. 1974. Floral biology of Magnolia. Amer. J. Bot. 61(10): 1037-1045.</reference><reference> Thien, L.B., W.H. Heimermann, and R.T. Holman. 1975. Floral odors and quantitative taxonomy of Magnolia and Liriodendron. Taxon 24(5/6): 557-568.</reference><reference> Tobe, J.D. 1993. A Molecular Systematic Study of Eastern North American Species of Magnolia L. Ph.D. thesis. Clemson University. Treseder, N.G. 1978. Magnolias. Boston. Vázquez-G., J.A. 1990. Taxonomy of the Genus Magnolia in Mexico and Central America. M.S. thesis. University of Wisconsin. Vázquez-G., J.A. 1994. Magnolia (Magnoliaceae) in Mexico and Central America: A synopsis. Brittonia 46(1): 1-23.</reference></references></treatment>
