<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>2.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Morus</genus_name>
    <species_name>microphylla</species_name>
    <species_authority>Buckley</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1862: 8. 1863</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Mountain mulberry</common_name>
  <common_name>littleleaf mulberry</common_name>
  <common_name>Texas mulberry</common_name>
  <description>Shrubs or trees, to 7.5 m. Bark gray, fissured, scaly. Branchlets greenish, pubescent; lenticels light colored, elliptic, prominent. Buds ovoid, slightly compressed, 3-4 mm, apex acute; outer scales dark brown, pubescent and minutely ciliate; leaf scars half round to irregularly circular, bundle scars numerous, in circle. Leaves: stipules linear-lanceolate, 3-5 mm, papery, pubescent; petiole 0.3-0.6(-1.5) cm, pubescent. Leaf blade ovate, sometimes 3-5-lobed, 2-7(-9) × 1-4(-7) cm, base rounded to nearly cordate, margins serrate or crenate-serrate, apex acute to acuminate; surfaces abaxially harshly scabrous or pubescent, somewhat paler than adaxial surface, adaxially harshly scabrous. Catkins: staminate, 1-2 cm; pistillate, 8-12 × 5-7 mm, peduncle 3-7 mm, pubescent. Flowers: staminate and pistillate on different plants. Staminate flowers: calyx lobes green to reddish, rounded, hairy; stamens 4; filiments filiform. Pistillate flowers: ovary dark green, broadly ovoid, slightly compressed, 1.5-2 × 1 mm, glabrous; style branches divergent, whitish, sessile, ca. 1.5 mm; stigma papillate. Syncarps red, purple, or black, short-cylindric, 1-1.5 cm; achenes yellowish, oval, flattened, ca. 2 mm, smooth.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering spring</phenology>
  <habitat>In canyons on limestone and igneous slopes, usually along streams</habitat>
  <elevation>200-2200 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Okla.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico.</global_distribution>
</treatment>
