<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Blume" date="unknown">myricaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">MYRICA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1024. 175</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 449. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family myricaceae;genus MYRICA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek my for tamarisk or another aromatic shrub; possibly from myrizein, to perfume]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Tidestrom" date="unknown">Cerothamnus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cerothamnus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Duhamel" date="unknown">Gale</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Gale;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Loureiro" date="unknown">Morella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Morella;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or small trees, often aromatic and resinous. Branches spreading, terete, glabrous or pubescent, often gland-dotted. Leaves persistent or deciduous; stipules absent. Leaf blade aromatic when crushed (except M. inodora), oblanceolate, elliptic, obovate, or oblong-ovate, membranous or leathery, margins entire or serrate-denticulate, especially in distal 1/2, pubescent or glabrous, usually gland-dotted. Inflorescences ± erect, ellipsoid to short-cylindric or ovoid, appearing before or with leaves; bracts ovate, glabrous or variously pubescent. Flowers unisexual, rarely bisexual, staminate and pistillate flowers usually on different plants, infrequently on same plants. Staminate flowers: stamens (2-)3-12(-22), shorter or longer than subtending bract; filaments mostly distinct, often connate into branching staminal column, each branch terminated by anther; rudimentary ovary occasionally present. Pistillate flowers: ovary subtended by 2-6 broadly ovate bracteoles, these sometimes persistent and accrescent, always shorter than fruit, sometimes completely absent; styles short. Fruits globose or ovoid to lenticular, smooth or more commonly with warty protuberances, usually covered with waxy coating that dries white. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Wax-myrtle</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">bayberry</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sweet gale</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">myrique</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 50 (7 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Myrica is often cultivated. Myrica species were used by various tribes of Native Americans for medicinal purposes. Leaves were used for a gynecological aid and an emetic; the bark, as a blood purifier and a kidney aid (D. E. Moerman 1986). Bayberry candles were used by early settlers, and they remain popular household items, both decorative and functional.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Davey, A. J. and C. M. Gibson. 1917. Note on the distribution of sexes in Myrica gale. New Phytol. 16: 147-151.</reference>
    <reference>Houghton, W. M. 1988. The Systematics of Section Cerophora of the Genus Myrica (Myricaceae) in North America. M.S. thesis. University of Georgia. Mac</reference>
    <reference>MacDonald, A. D. and R. Sattler. 1973. Floral development of Myrica gale and the controversy over floral concepts. Canad. J. Bot. 51: 1965-1975.</reference>
    <reference>Thieret, J. W. 1966. Habit variation in Myrica pensylvanica and M. cerifera. Castanea 31: 183-185.</reference>
    <reference>Donald, A. D. 1977. Myricaceae: Floral hypothesis for Gale and Comptonia. Canad. J. Bot. 55: 2636-2651.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
