<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Blume" date="unknown">myricaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">myrica</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Chamisso" date="1831">californica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 535. 1831</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family myricaceae;genus myrica;species californica</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Gale</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Chamisso) Greene" date="unknown">californica</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Gale; species californica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or small trees, evergreen, 2-10 m. Branchlets green when young, becoming red-brown, eventually black to gray with age, densely gland-dotted, glands colorless to black, pilose to villous, ultimately glabrous. Leaf blade fragrant when crushed, narrowly elliptic to elliptic-oblanceolate, 4-13 × 0.7-3.1 cm, sometimes membranous, more commonly leathery, base cuneate-attenuate, margins variable, from nearly entire (less common) to remotely and coarsely serrate entire length of blade, apex acute; surfaces abaxially pale green, adaxially dark green, shiny, both surfaces gland-dotted; glands colorless to black, considerably more dense abaxially, midrib pilose to glabrate adaxially. Inflorescences: staminate 0.6-1.7(-2.5) cm; bisexual 0.6-1.9(-3) cm; flowers bisexual, staminate, or pistillate within any 1 spike. Staminate flowers: bract of flower shorter than staminal column, margins opaque and densely ciliate; stamens (2-)6-12(-22). Pistillate and bisexual flowers: bracteoles usually persistent in fruit, 4-6, not accrescent or adnate to fruit wall, margins ciliate; stamens 1-5, in bisexual flowers hypogynous, free or often adnate to ovary, especially near styles; ovary ± villous, especially at apex. Fruits globose-ellipsoid, 4-6.5 mm; fruit wall glabrate to sparsely villous, obscured by enlarged, glabrous protuberances, with or without light to very heavy coat of white wax.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring-early summer, fruiting summer-early fall</description>
  <description type="habitat">Coastal conifer forests, bogs, sand dunes, stream banks, wet meadows, marshes, low, moist hillsides</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-1000 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wash.</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pacific bayberry</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">California wax-myrtle</other_name>
  <discussion>endemic</discussion>
  <discussion>On any one branchlet, staminate inflorescences are borne proximal to bisexual inflorescences; the most distal inflorescences may be completely pistillate.</discussion>
  <discussion>It is quite common for two or three pistillate or bisexual flowers to occur per bract and for the ovaries to fuse to form a syncarp. In the fruiting condition this can usually be detected by counting the number of style branches (two per ovary, therefore four for a syncarp derived from two fused ovaries). Many specimens apparently do not produce any wax, in which case the fruits appear purple-black rather than white.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
