<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Nymphaea</genus_name><species_name>ampla</species_name><species_authority>(Salisbury) de Candolle</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Syst. Nat. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 54. 1821</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><weedy>weedy</weedy><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Castalia</genus_name><species_name>ampla</species_name><species_authority>Salisbury</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Ann. Bot. (König &amp; Sims) </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 73. 1805</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Rhizomes unbranched, erect, ovoid; stolons absent. Leaves: petiole glabrous. Leaf blade abaxially purple, often spotted, adaxially green, ovate to nearly orbiculate, 15-45 × 15-45 cm, margins dentate to spinose-dentate; venation radiate and prominent centrally, without weblike pattern, principal veins 13-29; surfaces glabrous. Flowers emersed, 7-18 cm diam., opening and closing diurnally, only sepals and outermost petals in distinct whorls of 4; sepals green, abaxially flecked with short dark streaks, faintly veined, lines of insertion on receptacle not prominent; petals 12-21, white; stamens 50-190, yellow, outer with connective appendage projecting 3-10 mm beyond anther; filaments widest at or below middle, mostly equal to or shorter than anthers; pistil 14-25-locular, appendages at margin of stigmatic disk short-triangular, to 3 mm. Seeds nearly globose to ellipsoid, 1.2-1.6 × 0.9-1.3 mm, 1.2-1.5 times as long as broad, with longitudinal rows of hairlike papillae 40-180 µm.</description><phenology>Flowering all year</phenology><habitat> Ditches, canals, ponds, and freshwater tidal margins</habitat><elevation> 0-350 m</elevation><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America.</global_distribution><discussion>Reports of Nymphaea ampla in southern Texas by H. S. Conard (1905) are confirmed by specimens although no recent collections have been seen.</discussion><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Wunderlin, R. P. and D. H. Les. 1980. Nymphaea ampla (Nymphaeaceae), a waterlily new to Florida. Phytologia 45: 82-84.</reference></references></treatment>
