<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Salisbury" date="unknown">NYMPHAEACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family NYMPHAEACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
    
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, aquatic, rhizomatous; roots adventitious; air chambers conspicuous in vegetative portions of plant. Rhizomes branched or unbranched, erect or repent, tuberous-thickened, sometimes bearing stolons. Leaves arising directly from rhizome, alternate, floating, submersed, or emersed; stipules present or absent; petioles long. Leaf blade lanceolate to ovate or orbiculate, with basal sinus [peltate], margins entire to spinose-dentate. Inflorescences axillary or extra-axillary, flowers solitary. Flowers bisexual, protogynous [homogamous in some species of Nymphaea], diurnal or nocturnal, borne at or above water surface, occasionally submersed; peduncle long; involucre absent; perianth often persistent in fruit, hypogynous to perigynous [epigynous]; sepals usually (4-)5-12, distinct; petals numerous [rarely absent], often transitional to stamens; stamens numerous; filaments broad to slender; anthers dehiscing by longitudinal slits, with or without connective appendage; pistil 1, 3-35-carpellate and -locular; placentation laminar; ovules numerous per locule; stigma sessile, radiate on stigmatic disk. Fruits berrylike, indehiscent or irregularly dehiscent. Seeds several-numerous; aril present or absent; endosperm sparse; perisperm abundant; embryo minute; cotyledons 2, fleshy.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>12.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Water-lily Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 6 (including Barclaya), species ca. 50 (2 genera, 17 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Nymphaeaceae are insect-pollinated, often by beetles.</discussion>
  <discussion>Formerly Nymphaeaceae often have been treated to include Cabombaceae and Nelumbonaceae, but these are now generally segregated.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Schneider, E. L. 1979. Pollination biology of the Nymphaeaceae. In: D. M. Caron, ed. 1979. Increasing Production of Agricultural Crops through Increased Insect Pollination: Proceedings of the IVth International Symposium on Pollination. College Park, Md. Pp. 419-429. [Maryland Agric. Exp. Sta. Special Misc. Publ. 1.]</reference>
    <reference>Wood, C. E. Jr. 1959. The genera of the Nymphaeaceae and Ceratophyllaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 40: 94-112.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
