<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>2.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Nymphaea</genus_name>
    <species_name>elegans</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hooker</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Mag., plate</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4604. 1851</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Blue water-lily</common_name>
  <weedy>weedy</weedy>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Castalia</genus_name>
    <species_name>elegans</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Hooker) Greene</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizomes unbranched, erect, ovoid; stolons absent. Leaves: petiole glabrous. Leaf blade abaxially purple, adaxially green, ovate to nearly orbiculate, 8-20(-30) × 7-16(-25) cm, margins entire to sinuate; venation radiate and prominent centrally, without weblike pattern, compressed upon drying, principal veins 9-17; surfaces glabrous. Flowers emersed, 6-13 cm diam., opening and closing diurnally, only sepals and outermost petals in distinct whorls of 4; sepals green, abaxially flecked with short dark lines, faintly to obscurely veined, lines of insertion on receptacle not prominent; petals 8-27, pale violet to nearly white; stamens 55-145, yellow, connective appendage projecting to 1 mm, rarely more, beyond anther; filaments mostly widest above middle, shorter than anthers; pistil 12-20(-25)-locular, appendages at margin of stigmatic disk triangular, 1 mm or less. Seeds nearly globose, ca. 1.1-1.6 × 0.9-1.3 mm, 1.1-1.3 times as long as broad, with short appressed papillae absent or to 30 µm.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering spring-fall</phenology>
  <habitat>Freshwater ponds, lakes, sloughs, pools in swamps and marshes, ditches, and canals</habitat>
  <elevation>0-150 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>La.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>ne</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>w Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>West Indies (Bahamas).</global_distribution>
  <references>
    <reference>Schneider, E. L. 1982. Notes on the floral biology of Nymphaea elegans (Nymphaeaceae) in Texas. Aquatic Bot. 12: 197-200.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>
