<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>4.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Nymphaea</genus_name>
    <species_name>jamesoniana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Planchon</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Serres Jard. Eur.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8: 120. 1852</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Rhizomes branched or unbranched, erect, ovoid to cylindric; stolons absent. Leaves: petiole glabrous. Leaf blade abaxially and adaxially green, sometimes with darker flecks, elliptic, 8-25 × 7-19 cm, margins entire; venation conspicuously weblike centrally with cross veins between major veins, principal veins 11-17; surfaces glabrous. Flowers floating, 7-15 cm diam., opening and closing nocturnally, sepals, petals, and outer stamens in distinct whorls of 4; sepals uniformly green, obscurely veined, lines of insertion on receptacle not prominent; petals 12, 16, or 20, outer greenish at least abaxially, inner creamy white; stamens 35-85, creamy white, connective appendage projecting to 1 mm, rarely more, beyond anther; filaments widest below middle, longer than anthers; pistil 19-33-locular, appendages at margin of stigmatic disk slightly club-shaped, 3-7(-9) mm. Seeds nearly globose, 0.5-0.8 × 0.45-0.7 mm, 1.1-1.2 times as long as broad, with scattered papillae 10-50 µm. 2n = 28.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering late summer-fall</phenology>
  <habitat>Shallow water of mostly temporary ponds or ditches</habitat>
  <elevation>0-100 m</elevation>
  <global_distribution>native</global_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>South America.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>All material of the predominantly neotropical Nymphaea subg. Hydrocallis in the flora is referable to this taxon. D. B. Ward (1977b) and others listed N. blanda G. Meyer [= N. glandulifera Rodschied], a Central and South American taxon, for Florida.</discussion>
</treatment>
