<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>11d.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Papaver</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><section_name>Meconella</section_name><section_authority>Spach</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Hist. Nat. Vég. </publication_title><place_in_publication>7: 19. 1839</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Papaver</genus_name><section_name>Scapiflora</section_name><section_authority>Elkan</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Papaver</genus_name><section_name>Lasiotrachyphylla</section_name><section_authority>(Bernhardi) Pfeiffer</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, scapose. Leaf blades unlobed or 1-2×-lobed. Flowers: filaments white or yellow, filiform. Capsules obscurely valvate, ribbed, variously pubescent.</description><discussion>More study is needed for a comprehensive assessment of the North American scapose poppies in circumpolar context. The circumscriptions and interrelationships of the Alaskan and Asiatic members of this section are especially problematic.</discussion><discussion>Typification of Papaver radicatum Rottbfll also is problematic, and interpretation of its identity has significant consequences in the complex nomenclature of the arctic-alpine poppies. For details and discussion, see G. Knaben (1958); A. Löve (1962b, 1962c); and G. Knaben and N. Hylander (1970).</discussion><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Knaben, G. 1958. Papaver-studier, med et forsvar for P. radicatum Rottb. som en Islandsk-Skandinavisk art. Blyttia 16: 61-80.</reference><reference> Knaben, G. 1959. On the evolution of the radicatum-group of the Scapiflora Papavers as studied in 70 and 56 chromosome species. Part A. Cytotaxonomical aspects. Part B. Experimental studies. Opera Bot. 2(3), 3(3). Knaben, G. and N. Hylander. 1970. On the typification of Papaver radicatum Rottb. and its nomenclatural consequences. Bot. Not. 123: 338-345. Löve, A. 1962b. Typification of Papaver radicatum--A nomenclatural detective story. Bot. Not. 115: 113-136. Löve, A. 1962c. Nomenclature of North Atlantic Papavers. Taxon 11: 132-138. Löve, D. 1969. Papaver at high altitudes in the Rocky Mountains. Brittonia 21: 1-10. Rändel, U. 1974. Beitrage zur Kenntnis der Sippenstruktur der Gattung Papaver Sectio Scapiflora Reichenb. (Papaveraceae). Feddes Repert. 84: 655-732. Rändel, U. 1975. Die Beziehungen von Papaver pygmaeum Rydb. aus den Rocky Mountains zum nordamerikanischen P. kluanense D. Löve sowie zu einigen nordost-asiatischen Vertretern der Sektion Scapiflorae Reichenb. im Vergleich mit P. alpinum L. (Papaveraceae). Feddes Repert. 86: 19-37. Rändel, U. 1977. Über Sippen des subarktisch-arktischen Nordamerikas, des Beringia-Gebietes und Nordost-Asiens der Sektion Lasiotrachyphylla Bernh. (Papaveraceae) und deren Beziehungen zu einander und zu Sippen anderer Arealteile der Sektion. Feddes Repert. 88: 421-450. Rändel, U. 1977b. Über die grönländischen Vertreter der Sektion Lasiotrachyphylla Bernh. (Papaveraceae) und deren Beziehungen zu Vertretern anderer arktischer Arealteile der Sektion. Feddes Repert. 88: 451-464.</reference></references></treatment>
