<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">lauraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">PERSEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict. Abr. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4. 1754, name conserved</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family lauraceae;genus PERSEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[used by Theophrastus for an oriental tree]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">Tamala</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tamala;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs to medium-sized trees, evergreen. Bark reddish brown, thin, fissured. Leaves alternate, aromatic. Leaf blade pinnately veined; surfaces pubescent, especially abaxially, becoming glabrescent with age; domatia absent. Inflorescence appearing when mature leaves are present, axillary, flowers in pedunculate, compound cymes. Flowers bisexual; tepals persistent, yellowish, pubescent, outer tepals slightly shorter than inner; stamens 9, anthers 4-locular, 4-valved, anthers of outer 6 stamens introrse, anthers of inner 3 latrorse; staminodes 3, sagittate; ovary nearly globose. Drupe dark blue to black, nearly globose, borne on pedicel with tepals persistent at base; cupule absent. x = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">Western Hemisphere.</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Red bay</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 150 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Persea americana Miller, the avocado of commerce, with large, fleshy fruits and deciduous tepals, is widely grown in California and Florida. It may persist after cultivation.</discussion>
  <discussion>Pubescence type and density are the most reliable characteristics in identifying species and are best seen on young leaves and branches.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
