<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>73.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>durata</species_name><species_authority>Jepson</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Fl. Calif. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1(2): 356. 1909</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Leather oak</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>dumosa</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority><variety_name>bullata</variety_name><variety_authority>Engelmann</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>dumosa</species_name><variety_name>revoluta</variety_name><variety_authority>Sargent</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs, evergreen, 1-2(-3) m. Bark scaly. Twigs gray or yellowish, 1-3 mm diam., densely or sparsely tomentulose, often with prominent, yellowish, spreading hairs. Buds brown or reddish brown, ovoid or globose, 1-2 mm, glabrous or puberulent. Leaves: petiole 1-5 mm. Leaf blade cupped or convex, rarely somewhat planar, (10-)15-40 × 7-15(-20) mm, base cuneate, rounded-attenuate, or truncate, margins entire or irregularly toothed, sometimes spinose, usually unevenly revolute, secondary veins 4-6 on each side, apex rounded or subacute; surfaces abaxially densely to sparsely covered with erect, stipitate, (1-)2-4(-6)-rayed hairs 1-4 mm, felty to touch, secondary veins prominent, adaxially grayish or yellowish, with dense or scattered, semi-erect or appressed hairs, secondary veins obscure or somewhat impressed. Acorns solitary or paired, subsessile; cup reddish, hemispheric, deeply cup-shaped or turbinate, 4-6 mm deep × 12-18 mm wide, enclosing to 1/2 nut or more, scales reddish or yellowish, weakly to strongly tuberculate, often somewhat glandular; nut globose, ovoid or cylindric, 15-25 × 10-25 mm, apex rounded or obtuse, persistently minute-puberulent. Cotyledons distinct.</description><discussion>Chaparral, oak woodlands, open pine forests, on serpentine and nonserpentine soils; 150-1500 m.</discussion><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution></treatment>
