<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>6.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>hypoleucoides</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Camus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Mus. Natl. Hist. Nat., sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 4: 124. 1932</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Silverleaf oak</common_name>
  <illustrated>illustrated</illustrated>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>hypoleuca</species_name>
    <species_authority>Engelmann</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Trees or shrubs, evergreen, to 10 m. Bark black, deeply furrowed. Twigs dark reddish brown, 1.5-3 mm diam., pubescent. Terminal buds light chestnut brown, ovoid, 2.5-4.5 mm, glabrous except for ciliate scale margins, occasionally with tuft of hairs at apex. Leaves: petiole 1.5-13 mm, densely pubescent. Leaf blade narrowly ovate to ovate or elliptic, 45-120 × 15-40 mm, base cuneate to rounded, margins strongly revolute, entire or spinose with up to 11 awns, apex acute to attenuate; surfaces abaxially densely tawny- or white-tomentose, adaxially noticeably rugose, glabrous. Acorns annual or biennial; cup deeply saucer- or cup-shaped, 4.5-7 mm high × 6-13 mm wide, covering 1/3 nut or less, outer surface pubescent to sparsely puberulent, inner surface pubescent to floccose, scales appressed, blunt; nut ellipsoid to oblong, 8-16 × 5-10 mm, glabrous, scar diam. 2.5-5.5 mm.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering spring</phenology>
  <habitat>Common in moist canyons and on ridges</habitat>
  <elevation>1500-2700 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Quercus hypoleucoides reportedly hybridizes with Q. gravesii (Q. ×inconstans E. J. Palmer [= Q. livermorensis C. H. Muller]) (see C. H. Muller 1951). Several specimens from Pima County, Arizona, fall outside the range of typical Q. hypoleucoides, suggesting hybridization with the Mexican Q. mcvaughii Spellenberg (R. Spellenberg 1992).</discussion>
</treatment>
