<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>palustris</species_name>
    <species_authority>Münchhausen</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hausvater</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5(1): 253. 1770</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Pin oak</common_name>
  <endemic>endemic</endemic>
  <illustrated>illustrated</illustrated>
  <weedy>weedy</weedy>
  <description>Trees, deciduous, to 25 m. Bark grayish brown, fissures broad, shallow, inner bark pinkish. Twigs reddish brown, 1.5-3(-4) mm diam., soon becoming glabrous. Terminal buds brown to reddish brown, ovoid, 3-5 mm, glabrous or with a few fine hairs at apex. Leaves: petiole 20-60 mm, glabrous. Leaf blade elliptic to oblong, 50-160 × 50-120 mm, base cuneate to broadly obtuse or truncate with basal pair of lobes often somewhat recurved, margins with 5-7 lobes and 10-30 awns, lobes acute or attenuate or distally expanded, apex acute to acuminate; surfaces abaxially glabrous except for conspicuous axillary tufts of tomentum, veins raised, adaxially planar, glabrous. Acorns biennial; cup thin, saucer-shaped, 3-6 mm high × 9.5-16 mm wide, covering 1/4 nut, outer surface glabrous or puberulent, inner surface glabrous or with a few hairs around scar, scale tips tightly appressed, acute to obtuse; nut globose or ovoid, 10-16 × 9-15 mm, often conspicuously striate, glabrous, scar diam. 5.5-9 mm. 2n = 24.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering spring</phenology>
  <habitat>Bottoms and poorly drained upland clay soils</habitat>
  <elevation>0-350 m</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ark.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Conn.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Del.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>D.C.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ill.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ind.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Iowa</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Kans.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ky.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Md.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mass.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mich.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mo.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.J.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ohio</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Okla.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Pa.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>R.I.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tenn.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wis.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Quercus palustris is especially common in landscape and street plantings. Its persistent dead branchlets (pins) and branching pattern (drooping lower branches, horizontal middle branches, ascending upper branches) are quite distinctive.</discussion>
  <discussion>This species reportedly hybridizes with Quercus coccinea (E. J. Palmer 1948) and with Q. imbricaria (= Q. ×exacta Trelease), Q. marilandica, Q. nigra, Q. phellos (= Q. ×schochiana Dieck), Q. rubra, Q. shumardii, and Q. velutina.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some Native American tribes used infusions prepared from the bark of Quercus palustris to alleviate intestinal pains (D. E. Moerman 1986).</discussion>
</treatment>
