<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">fagaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="G. Don in J. C. Loudon" date="1830">Lobatae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hort. Brit.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>385. 1830</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fagaceae;genus quercus;section Lobatae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees or shrubs, evergreen or deciduous. Bark gray to dark brown or black, smooth or furrowed. Leaf blade lobed or unlobed, margins entire or toothed, teeth if present usually bristle-tipped. Staminate flowers: calyx 2-6-lobed; anthers usually retuse, rarely apiculate. Pistillate flowers: calyx free from ovary, forming free skirt or flange; styles linear-spatulate. Acorns: maturation biennial, rarely annual; cup with scales distinct, flat, thin, rarely somewhat keeled or tuberculate; nut with inner wall silky-tomentose, abortive ovules apical (rarely in some species variable in position or subbasal), seed coat adhering to seed at maturity. Cotyledons distinct, rarely partially connate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America (Colombia only).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species ca. 195 (35 in the flora): North America, Mexico, Central America, South America (Colombia only).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species ca. 195 (35 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, Central America, South America (Colombia only).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>5a.</number>
  <discussion>Cup dimensions in Quercus sect. Lobatae refer to height of the cup as seen in profile view. This measurement, taken from apex of peduncle to cup rim, has been used for those situations (quite common in herbarium specimens and fresh collections) in which the cup cannot be separated from the nut without seriously damaging one or both of these units. The depth of the cup will always be less than its height, but a simple translation of height to depth does not exist.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species ca. 195 (35 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
