<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>75.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>vaseyana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Buckley</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 91. 1883</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Vasey oak</common_name>
  <illustrated>illustrated</illustrated>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>pungens</species_name>
    <species_authority>Liebmann</species_authority>
    <variety_name>vaseyana</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Buckley) C. H. Muller</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>undulata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Torrey</species_authority>
    <variety_name>vaseyana</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Buckley) Rydberg</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Shrubs or small trees, evergreen or subevergreen, to 10 m. Bark dark brown, furrowed and exfoliating in long strips. Twigs reddish or grayish brown, 1-1.5 mm diam., short stellate-tomentose or tomentulose, later glabrate or persistently pubescent, rarely glabrous. Buds dark red-brown or gray, round-ovoid, 1-1.5 mm, apex obtuse, sparsely pubescent or glabrate. Leaves: petiole to 5 mm. Leaf blade narrowly lanceolate to usually oblong, mostly planar or slightly convex, 20-60(-90) × 10-20 mm, often rather leathery, base cuneate to rounded, margins coarsely 3-5-toothed on each side or shallowly lobed or entire, with teeth or lobes acute or obtuse, mucronate-tipped, secondary veins 4-6 on each side, usually branched, apex acute, rarely obtuse; surfaces abaxially densely stellate with minute appressed hairs, rarely glabrate and lustrous green, adaxially dark green, lustrous, glabrous or very sparsely stellate-puberulent. Acorns subsessile or on peduncle 2-3 mm; cup saucer-shaped to cup-shaped, 3-4 mm deep × 10 mm wide, margin thin, scales reddish brown, strongly, regularly tuberculate; nut light brown, ovoid to oblong or subcylindric, to 12 × 12 mm, glabrous. Cotyledons distinct.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering spring</phenology>
  <habitat>Dry limestone slopes, oak and mesquite woodlands, juniper woodlands, and canyons and ravines in otherwise dry, open grasslands, sometimes descending into margins of dry scrub</habitat>
  <elevation>300-600 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico (Chihuahua, Coahuila, and Nuevo León).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Apparent hybridization between Quercus vaseyana and Q. pungens is discussed under the latter species.</discussion>
</treatment>
