<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>74.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>rugosa</species_name><species_authority>Née</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Anales Ci. Nat. </publication_title><place_in_publication>3: 275. 1801</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Netleaf oak</common_name><illustrated>illustrated</illustrated><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>ariifolia</species_name><species_authority>Trelease</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>diversicolor</species_name><species_authority>Trelease</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>durangensis</species_name><species_authority>Trelease</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>reticulata</species_name><species_authority>Humboldt &amp; Bonpland</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>rhodophlebia</species_name><species_authority>Trelease</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>vellifera</species_name><species_authority>Trelease</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs or trees, evergreen, usually moderate-sized, rarely large. Bark light or dark brown, scaly. Twigs brown, turning gray with age, 1-2 mm diam., tomentose to tomentulose, variously glabrate or persistently pubescent. Buds brown, ovoid, 2-4 mm, apex obtuse, sparsely pubescent or eventually glabrate. Leaves: petiole to 7 mm. Leaf blade broadly obovate or panduriform to orbiculate or elliptic, rarely narrowly obovate, usually cupped, strongly concave proximally, sometimes planar, to 100 × 70 mm, stiff, leathery, base deeply or shallowly cordate, margins usually somewhat revolute, cartilaginously thickened, undulately crisped or flat with inconspicuous or coarse mucronate teeth near apex, secondary veins 8-10(-12) on each side, branched, apex broadly rounded, rarely subacute; surfaces abaxially dull, glaucous, or densely brownish tomentose, becoming nearly glabrate or pubescence persistent, especially about midribs, secondary veins very prominently raised, reticulate, adaxially dark green, lustrous, sparsely stellate-pubescent especially about base of midrib, secondary veins impressed. Acorns 1-3 or more on slender axillary peduncle 30-60 mm; cup deeply cup-shaped to saucer-shaped, to 9 mm deep × 15 mm wide, enclosing to 1/2 nut, scales loosely appressed, characteristically somewhat spreading, brown, ovate, tuberculate-thickened or only slightly so, tomentose or obscurely tomentulose; nut light brown, ovoid to elliptic, to 20 × l5 mm, glabrous or minutely villous. Cotyledons distinct, often reddish or purple.</description><phenology>Flowering early-late spring</phenology><habitat> Wooded slopes</habitat><elevation> 2000-2500 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America (Guatemala).</global_distribution><discussion>Quercus rugosa occurs on wooded slopes at high elevations in trans-Pecos Texas, southern New Mexico, and Arizona, and throughout most of the mesic montane parts of Mexico, south to Guatemala.</discussion></treatment>
