<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Nixon &amp; Dorr" date="unknown">buckleyi</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Taxon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>34: 225. 1985</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Quercus; species buckleyi;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees, deciduous, to 15 m. Bark gray and smooth or black and furrowed. Twigs grayish brown to red-brown, rarely somewhat yellowish or gray, 1.5-3 mm diam., glabrous. Terminal buds grayish brown to reddish brown, ovoid to subfusiform, (2.5-)3-7 mm, scales on apical 1/2 distinctly ciliate. Leaves: petiole 20-45 mm, glabrous. Leaf blade circular or broadly elliptic to obovate, 55-100 × 51-112 mm, base cuneate to truncate, often inequilateral, margins with 7-9 lobes and 12-35 awns, lobes oblong to distally expanded, apex acute to acuminate; surfaces abaxially light green or coppery green, glabrous or with small, axillary tufts of tomentum, adaxially shiny or glossy, glabrous, veins raised on both surfaces. Acorns biennial; cup goblet- to cup-shaped, rarely saucer-shaped, 5-11.5 mm high × 10-18 mm wide, covering 1/3-1/2 nut, outer surface glabrous to sparsely puberulent, inner surface glabrous except for a few hairs around scar, scales acute, less than 4 mm, occasionally tuberculate, especially at base of cup, tips appressed; nut broadly ovoid to broadly ellipsoid, rarely oblong, 12-18.5 × 8-14 mm, occasionally with faint rings of pits at apex, glabrous or sparsely puberulent, scar diam. 3.5-8 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring</description>
  <description type="habitat">Limestone ridges and slopes, creek bottoms, occasionally along larger streams</description>
  <description type="elevation">150-500 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Okla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <number>29.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Buckley's oak</other_name>
  <discussion>endemic</discussion>
  <discussion>illustrated</discussion>
  <discussion>For many years the names Quercus texana, Q. rubra var. texana, and Q. shumardii var. texana were erroneously used for Q. buckleyi (L. J. Dorr and K. C. Nixon 1985).</discussion>
  <discussion>Quercus texana reportedly hybridizes with Q. marilandica (= Q. ×hastingsii Sargent). Quercus ×hastingsii may be derived from Q. marilandica var. ashei (D. M. Hunt 1989). Hybridization with Q. shumardii may also occur (L. J. Dorr and K. C. Nixon 1985).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
