<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">fagaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Linneaus" date="unknown">quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Nixon &amp; C. H. Muller" date="1994">john-tuckeri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 391. 1994</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fagaceae;genus quercus;section quercus;species john-tuckeri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene" date="unknown">turbinella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="J. M. Tucker" date="unknown">californica</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Quercus; species turbinella; subspecies californica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, subevergreen or evergreen, 1-3(-5) m. Bark light gray or brown, scaly. Twigs yellowish or dingy gray, 1-1.5(-2) mm diam., densely tomentulose. Buds brown, ovoid or globose, 1.5-2(-3) mm, glabrous except for ciliate margins of scales; proximal scales often yellowish puberulent. Leaves: petiole 1-4 mm. Leaf blade unicolored, elliptic or obovate, (10-)15-30(-40) × (8-)10-15(-20) mm, thick and leathery, often brittle, base truncate or rounded-attenuate, rarely subcordate, margins irregularly spinose-toothed, occasionally shallowly lobate, secondary veins (3-)4-7, often some veins branching near margin and passing into more than 1 tooth, apex acute or rounded; surfaces abaxially waxy grayish, light green, or yellowish, sparse to moderately dense (8-)10-12-rayed, (loosely) appressed-stellate hairs, often 0.2-0.5 mm diam., and sparse to crowded, yellowish, glandular hairs, adaxially dull grayish, with stellate hairs, similar to abaxial surface. Acorns solitary or paired, subsessile; cup cup-shaped or obconic to hemispheric, 5-7 mm deep × 10-15 mm wide, thin, scales whitish or yellowish, moderately or scarcely tuberculate, puberulent; nut fusiform, ovoid, or conic, 20-30 mm, apex acute. Cotyledons distinct.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Dry slopes, chaparral, pinyon and juniper woodlands, margins of oak woodlands and sagebrush; 900-2000 m; Calif.</text>
    <parsed>
      <habitat>Dry slopes, chaparral, pinyon and juniper woodlands, margins of oak woodlands and sagebrush;</habitat>
      <elevation>900-2000 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Calif.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>64.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Tucker oak</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">desert scrub oak</other_name>
  <discussion>endemic</discussion>
  <discussion>illustrated</discussion>
  <discussion>Dry slopes, chaparral, pinyon and juniper woodlands, margins of oak woodlands and sagebrush; 900-2000 m; Calif.</discussion>
  <discussion>Endemic to California, Quercus john-tuckeri occurs from Los Angeles County northward in the interior Coast Ranges and Sierra Foothills to the northern edge of Sacramento Valley.</discussion>
  <discussion>Quercus john-tuckeri bears some resemblance to both Q. turbinella and Q. berberidifolia. Quercus turbinella has pedunculate fruit and cordate leaf bases, however, and Q. berberidifolia has a glabrate adaxial leaf surface, substantially smaller stellate trichomes with fewer rays on the abaxial leaf surface, heavier tuberculate acorn cups, and blunt or rounded (instead of acute) acorns.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
