<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Trelease) A. Camus," date="unknown">Protobalanus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Chênes</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 157. 1938</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Quercus; section Protobalanus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees or shrubs, evergreen. Bark grayish white to reddish brown, scaly to smooth with furrows. Leaf blade never lobed, margins entire or toothed, teeth if present usually spinose. Staminate flowers: calyx 5-6-lobed; anthers attenuate-apiculate. Pistillate flowers: calyx adnate to ovary, not forming flange; styles short and dilated to long and abruptly enlarged. Acorns: maturation biennial; cup pedunculate, cup scales distinct or laterally connate, base thickened and corky (tuberculate); nut with inner wall densely to sparsely tomentose, abortive ovules apical to lateral or basal, sometimes variable within individual plants, seed coats adhering to seed, sometimes to fruit wall at maturity. Cotyledons distinct.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw North America and nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>5b.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Intermediate oaks,</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">golden-cup oaks</other_name>
  <discussion>Quercus Linneaus subg. Protobalanus Trelease in P. C. Standley, Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. 23: 176. 1922</discussion>
  <discussion>Measurements for the cup of the acorn in the next two sections is for depth of cup, not height.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 5 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Manos, P. S. 1993. Foliar trichome variation in Quercus section Protobalanus (Fagaceae). Sida 15: 391-403.</reference>
    <reference>Tucker, J. M. and H. S. Haskell. 1960. Quercus dunnii and Q. chrysolepis in Arizona. Brittonia 12: 196-219.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
