<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>16.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>pumila</species_name><species_authority>Walter</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Fl. Carol., </publication_title><place_in_publication>234. 1788</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Runner oak</common_name><endemic>endemic</endemic><illustrated>illustrated</illustrated><weedy>weedy</weedy><description>Shrubs, deciduous or tardily deciduous, to 1 m. Bark gray to dark brown. Twigs gray-brown to reddish brown, 1-2 mm diam., sparsely to uniformly pubescent. Terminal buds brown to red-brown, ovoid, 2.5-4.5 mm, glabrous or with ciliate scale margins. Leaves: petiole 1.5-4.5 mm, pubescent. Leaf blade oblong to narrowly obovate, 25-100 × 10-33 mm, base acute to rounded, margins entire, revolute, with 1 apical awn, apex acute or obtuse to rounded; surfaces abaxially uniformly gray-brown pubescent, rarely glabrate, adaxially somewhat convex, rugose, glabrous or with scattered hairs along midrib. Acorns annual; cup deeply saucer-shaped to turbinate, 5-12 mm high × 10-15 mm wide, covering 1/3-1/2(-2/3) nut, outer surface pubescent, inner surface densely pubescent, scales rarely involute, often tuberculate, tips tightly appressed, acute; nut globose to ovoid or broadly oblong, 9.5-15 × 9-12 mm, glabrate, scar diam. 5-8 mm.</description><phenology>Flowering spring</phenology><habitat> Dry sandy soils of savannahs, low ridges and oak-pine scrub, occasionally at margins of poorly drained sites</habitat><elevation> 0-100 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Miss.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution><discussion>Although no hybrid combinations have been formally proposed, D. M. Hunt (1989) has reported evidence of hybridization with Quercus hemisphaerica, Q. incana, Q. myrtifolia, and Q. phellos.</discussion></treatment>
