<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>44.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>michauxii</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Gen. N. Amer. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 215. 1818</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Basket oak</common_name><common_name> cow oak</common_name><common_name> swamp chestnut oak</common_name><endemic>endemic</endemic><illustrated>illustrated</illustrated><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Quercus</genus_name><species_name>houstoniana</species_name><species_authority>C. H. Muller</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Trees, deciduous, to 20 m. Bark light brown or gray, scaly. Twigs brown or reddish brown, 2-3 mm diam., with sparse spreading hairs or glabrate. Buds reddish brown, ovoid, apex rounded or acute, glabrous or minutely puberulent. Leaves: petiole 5-20 mm. Leaf blade broadly obovate or broadly elliptic, (60-)100-280 × 50-180 mm, base rounded-acuminate or broadly cuneate, margins regularly toothed, teeth rounded, dentate, or acuminate, secondary veins 15-20 on each side, parallel, straight or somewhat curved, apex broadly rounded or acuminate; surfaces abaxially light green or yellowish, felty to touch because of conspicuous or minute, erect, 1-4-rayed hairs, adaxially glabrous or with minute simple or fascicled hairs. Acorns 1-3, subsessile or more often on axillary peduncle to 20-30 mm; cup hemispheric, broadly hemispheric or even short-cylindric, 15-25 mm deep × 25-40 mm wide, enclosing 1/2 nut or more, scales very loosely appressed, distinct to base, gray or light brown, moderately to heavily tuberculate, tips silky-tomentose; nut light brown, ovoid or cylindric, 25-35 × 20-25 mm, glabrous. Cotyledons distinct.</description><phenology>Flowering early-late spring</phenology><habitat> Bottomlands, rich sandy woods and swamps, on variety of soils</habitat><elevation> 0-600 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ark.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Del.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ill.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ind.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ky.</us_distribution><us_distribution> La.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Miss.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mo.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.J.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Pa.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tenn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Va.</us_distribution><discussion>Quercus michauxii is easily distinguished from other chestnut-leaved oaks by the felty hairs of the abaxial leaf surface and rather large acorn cups with attenuate-acute, loose scales. This species is no longer extant in Oklahoma. Historical reports from Connecticut, Massachusetts, and New York have not been confirmed; possibly populations are no longer extant. (See Quercus montana for a discussion of nomenclature and the uncertain application of the name Q. prinus).</discussion></treatment>
