<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">fagaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Linneaus" date="unknown">quercus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey in L. Sitgreaves" date="1853">oblongifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in L. Sitgreaves,  Rep. Exped. Zuni Colorado Rivers,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>173, plate 19. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fagaceae;genus quercus;section quercus;species oblongifolia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees, evergreen, to 10 m. Bark gray or whitish, closely furrowed. Twigs light brown, 1-1.5 mm diam., densely or sparsely stellate-tomentose, soon glabrate. Buds reddish brown, subspheric to broadly ovoid, 1-2 mm, glabrous or basal scales pubescent; stipules persistent about terminal buds. Leaves: petiole 2-5(-8) mm. Leaf blade oblong to elliptic, occasionally lanceolate or ovate, (20-)30-60(-80) × (5-)10-25(-30) mm, base cuneate to cordate, margins entire, undulate, sometimes irregularly toothed especially toward apex, secondary veins 7-8(-10) on each side, branched, apex acute or broadly rounded; surfaces abaxially densely and loosely glandular-tomentose, quickly glabrate or persistently floccose, especially about base of midrib, at maturity strongly glaucous, adaxially dull pale green, bluish green, or glaucous, sparsely stellate-tomentose, quickly glabrate. Acorns solitary or paired, subsessile or on peduncle 4-12 mm; cup cup-shaped, about 6-8(-l3) mm deep × 10-13 mm wide, enclosing ca. 1/3 nut, scales to 1-1.5 mm wide, moderately, regularly tuberculate near base of cup, gray-pubescent; nut light brown, ovoid or oblong, 12-17(-19) × (7-)10-12 mm, glabrate or puberulent about apex. Cotyledons connate.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering in spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Common in high grasslands and midelevation woodlands, mesas, and canyons;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1300-1650 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex., Tex.; Mexico (Baja California South, Sonora, Chihuahua, and Coahuila).</description>
  <number>80.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sonoran blue oak</other_name>
  <discussion>illustrated</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
