<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>84.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>chihuahuensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Trelease</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Natl. Acad. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20: 85. 1924</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Chihuahua oak</common_name>
  <common_name>felt oak</common_name>
  <illustrated>illustrated</illustrated>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>infralutea</species_name>
    <species_authority>Trelease</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>jaliscensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Trelease</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Quercus</genus_name>
    <species_name>santaclarensis</species_name>
    <species_authority>C. H. Muller</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Shrubs or trees, deciduous, to 10 m. Bark gray, furrowed, checkered, or scaly. Twigs gray, 2-3(-4) mm diam., densely tomentose. Buds reddish brown, broadly ovoid, distally rounded, 2-2.5 mm, densely yellowish pubescent; scales gray-puberulent; stipules persistent, 1-4, subulate, pubescent, at base of terminal buds. Leaves: petiole 3-5(-8) mm. Leaf blade elliptic or oblong to ovate or obovate, (25-)40-50(-85) × (18-)20-30(-50) mm, base rounded or shallowly cordate, margins entire or toothed to sublobate, secondary veins 8 to 10 on each side, somewhat branching, apex broadly rounded to acute; surfaces abaxially yellowish or grayish, densely stellate with velvety hairs, adaxially green, sparsely soft-pubescent with prominent, spreading, stellate hairs, felty to touch, secondary veins somewhat prominent on both surfaces, even under dense tomentum. Acorns 1-3 on tomentose peduncle 15-35(-60) mm; cup hemispheric, 7-10 mm deep × 10-15 mm wide, enclosing 1/2 nut, scales proximally thickened, distally appressed, densely gray-puberulent, tips reddish, ultimately glabrate; nut ovoid, 14-18 × 10-12 mm, puberulent, eventually glabrate. Cotyledons connate.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering spring</phenology>
  <habitat>Oak and pinyon-juniper woodlands, grassy hills, sometimes extending into dry thorn scrub and bursera woodland (Mexico)</habitat>
  <elevation>400-2000 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico (Chihuahua, Sonora, Zacatecas, and San Luis Potosí).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Quercus chihuahuensis is a distinctive species throughout its range, mostly in dry montane western Mexico; it occurs in the United States only as putative hybrids with Q. grisea (the Eagle and Quitman mountains) and Q. arizonica (Hueco Tanks) in Texas.</discussion>
</treatment>
