<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Ranunculus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ranunculus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Prantl) L. D. Benson" date="unknown">Epirotes</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. J. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>23: 169. 1936</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ranunculus; subgenus Ranunculus; section Epirotes;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ranunculus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Prantl e. Epirotes Prantl" date="unknown">Marsypadenium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Jahrb. Syst.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9: 266. 1888</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ranunculus; section Marsypadenium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants glabrous or sometimes pilose or pubescent. Stems erect, not bulbous-based, without bulbils. Roots basal, sometimes tuberous. Leaves basal and cauline, simple or compound; basal leaves petiolate, blades variously divided, unlobed to deeply parted, compound, or filiform-dissected, segments undivided or again lobed or parted, margins entire or crenate, never serrate; cauline leaves sessile to nearly sessile or sometimes with much shorter petioles than basal leaves, blades lobed to compound or dissected (rarely unlobed in R. macauleyi and R. glaberrimus). Inflorescences 1-50-flowered cymes. Flowers pedicellate; sepals deciduous soon after anthesis, 5; petals yellow (rarely absent in R. pedatifidus); nectary scale joined with petal on 3 sides, forming pocket enclosing nectary (sometimes with apex free, forming flap shorter than pocket), glabrous or setose, free margin entire or fringed; style present. Fruits achenes, 1-locular; achene body thick-lenticular or asymmetrically thick-lenticular to compressed-globose, 1.2-2 times as wide as thick, not prolonged beyond seed; wall thick, smooth; margin low narrow ridge, often inconspicuous; beak much shorter than achene body.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide except lowland tropics.</description>
  <number>2a.3.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 70 (22 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
