<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">ranunculaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Ranunculus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ranunculus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">Hecatonia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 30. 1824</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ranunculaceae; genus Ranunculus; subgenus Ranunculus; section Hecatonia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants glabrous or sometimes hirsute. Stems creeping (erect in Ranunculus sceleratus), not bulbous-based, without bulbils. Roots basal and usually also nodal, never tuberous. Leaves all cauline or both basal and cauline; basal and lower cauline leaves similar, petiolate, blades lobed to divided or (submerged leaves) deeply dissected, segments undivided or lobed. Inflorescences 2-25-flowered cymes or axillary solitary flowers. Flowers pedicellate; sepals deciduous soon after anthesis, 3-5; petals 3-14, yellow; nectary scale variable, forming crescent-shaped ridge surrounding but not covering nectary, or funnel-shaped tube surrounding nectary, or distal margin of funnel expanded to form large flap, then nectary sometimes displaced onto flap, glabrous, free margin entire; style present or absent. Fruits achenes, 1-locular; achene body thick-lenticular or compressed-ellipsoid to discoid, 1.2-3 times as wide as thick, not prolonged beyond seed; achene wall thick, smooth or with weak transverse wrinkles, glabrous; margin a thick, low or high corky band or ridge; beak much shorter than achene body or sometimes absent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">widespread</description>
  <description type="distribution">in marshy or aquatic habitats.</description>
  <number>2a.5.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 15 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
