<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">RANUNCULACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family RANUNCULACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, sometimes woody or herbaceous climbers or low shrubs, perennial or annual, often rhizomatous. Stems unarmed. Leaves usually basal and cauline, alternate or sometimes opposite, rarely whorled, simple or variously compound; stipules present or absent; petioles usually present, often proximally sheathing. Leaf blade undivided or more commonly divided or compound, base cordate, sometimes truncate or cuneate, margins entire, toothed, or incised; venation pinnate or palmate. Inflorescences terminal or axillary, racemes, cymes, umbels, panicles, or spikes, or flowers solitary, flowers pedicellate or sessile. Flowers bisexual, sometimes unisexual, inconspicuous or showy, radially or bilaterally symmetric; sepaloid bracteoles absent; perianth hypogynous; sepals usually imbricate, 3-6(-20), distinct, often petaloid and colored, occasionally spurred; petals 0-26, distinct (connate in Consolida), plane, cup-shaped, funnel-shaped, or spurred, conspicuous or greatly reduced; nectary usually present, rarely absent; stamens 5-many, distinct; anthers dehiscing longitudinally; staminodes absent (except in Aquilegia and Clematis); pistils 1-many; styles present or absent, often persistent in fruit as beak. Fruits achenes, follicles, or rarely utricles, capsules, or berries, often aggregated into globose to cylindric heads. Seeds 1-many per ovary, never stalked, not arillate; endosperm abundant; embryo usually small.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Genera ca. 60, species 1700 (22 genera, 284 species in the flora): worldwide.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Genera ca. 60, species 1700 (22 genera, 284 species in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>worldwide.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>15.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Crowfoot Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 60, species 1700 (22 genera, 284 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The flowers of many species of Ranunculaceae begin to open long before anthesis, while the floral organs are just partly expanded. Only mature flowers with open anthers should be used for determination of diagnostic characteristics (especially measurements).</discussion>
  <discussion>The literature is inconsistent about the term for the whorl of organs between sepals and stamens; these may be conspicuous and petaloid, or reduced to stalked nectaries, or intermediate between the two states. They have been called petals, honey-leaves, or (when they are inconspicuous) staminodes or nectaries. We follow M. Tamura (1993) and treat as petals all organs between the sepals and stamens, except in Clematis and Aquilegia where they usually bear rudimentary anthers and clearly represent staminodes.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Brayshaw, T. C. 1989. Buttercups, Waterlilies, and Their Relatives (the Order Ranales) in British Columbia. Victoria. [Roy. Brit. Columbia Mus. Mem. 1.]</reference>
    <reference>Tamura, M. 1963. Morphology, ecology and phylogeny of the Ranunculaceae I. Sci. Rep. Coll. Gen. Educ. Osaka Univ. 11: 115-126.</reference>
    <reference>Tamura, M. 1993. Ranunculaceae. In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 2+ vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 2, pp. 563-583.</reference>
    <reference>Ziman, S. N. and C. S. Keener. 1989. A geographical analysis of the family Ranunculaceae. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 76: 1012-1049.</reference>
    <reference>Duncan, T. and C. S. Keener. 1991. A classification of the Ranunculaceae with special reference to the Western Hemisphere. Phytologia 70: 24-27.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
