<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2e.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Ranunculus</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><subgenus_name>Batrachium</subgenus_name><subgenus_authority>(de Candolle) A. Gray</subgenus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts </publication_title><place_in_publication>21: 363. 1886</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Ranunculus</genus_name><section_name>Batrachium</section_name><section_authority>de Candolle</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Syst. Nat. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 233. 1817</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><subgenus_name>Batrachium</subgenus_name><subgenus_authority>(de Candolle) Gray</subgenus_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants glabrous (or sheathing leaf bases sometimes pubescent). Stems creeping or floating, not bulbous-based, without bulbils. Roots nodal, never tuberous. Leaves cauline, either simple and laminate (with expanded blade), or completely dissected into filiform segments, or with proximal leaves filiform-dissected and distal leaves laminate; laminate leaves petiolate, undivided or 3-parted, segments entire to shallowly cleft and crenate; filiform-dissected leaves petiolate or sessile. Inflorescences axillary, solitary flowers. Flowers pedicellate; sepals deciduous soon after anthesis, 5; petals 5, white or white with yellow claws; nectary scale attached on 3 sides, forming ridge or shallow pocket not covering nectary, glabrous, free margin entire; style present. Fruits achenes, 1-locular; achene body ellipsoid or flattened-ellipsoid, 1-2 times as wide as thick, not prolonged beyond seed; wall thick, with coarse transverse ridges; margin low narrow ridge; beak much shorter than achene body.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 15 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> widespread except lowland tropics.</global_distribution><discussion>Unlike most species of Ranunculus, members of this subgenus are not poisonous.</discussion></treatment>
