<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>11.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Thalictrum</genus_name>
    <species_name>texanum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(A. Gray) Small</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. S.E. U.S.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>446. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <conservation>of conservation concern</conservation>
  <endemic>endemic</endemic>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Thalictrum</genus_name>
    <species_name>debile</species_name>
    <species_authority>Buckley</species_authority>
    <variety_name>texanum</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>A. Gray</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray et al., Syn. Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 18. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Roots becoming black when dry, tuberous, not ribbed, irregular. Stems erect, 10-45 cm, rigid, glabrous. Leaves: distal cauline long-petiolate. Leaf blade 2×-ternately compound; leaflets cuneate to reniform, undivided, cleft, or lobed, 2-7 mm wide, margins entire or sometimes weakly crenate, surfaces glabrous, somewhat glaucous. Inflorescences terminal, racemes, several flowered. Flowers: sepals lanceolate to obovate, in staminate flowers 1.7-3 mm, in pistillate flowers 0.7-1.5 mm; filaments colored, not white, ca. 1.5 mm; anthers 1.4-2 mm; stigma color unknown. Achenes few, not reflexed, nearly sessile; stipe 0.1-0.3 mm; body ovoid, not laterally compressed, adaxial surface 2.7-3.7 × 1.4-1.6 mm, glabrous, prominently 6-8-veined, veins not anastomosing-reticulate; beak 0.5-1 mm.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering early spring (Mar-Apr)</phenology>
  <habitat>Margins or openings of mesic woodlands or forests</habitat>
  <conservation>of conservation concern</conservation>
  <elevation>10-100 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Somewhat difficult to locate in the field, Thalictrum texanum is currently known from only two populations. It is closely related to T. arkansanum and T. debile and sometimes treated as a variety of the latter.</discussion>
  <discussion>Thalictrum confine is quite similar to T. occidentale and T. venulosum; it has been treated as a variety or synonym of the latter (R. S. Mitchell 1988).</discussion>
</treatment>
