<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">ulmaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">ulmus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Jacquin" date="1798">parvifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pl. Hort. Schoenbr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 6, plate 262. 1798</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ulmaceae;genus ulmus;species parvifolia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees, 25 m; crowns rounded, open. Bark olive green to gray, shedding in irregular, tan to orange plates. Branches long-pendulous, not winged; twigs tan to dark brown, glabrous to pubescent. Buds acute to obtuse; scales brown, pubescent. Leaves: petiole 2-6(-8) mm, glabrous or sparsely pubescent with short hairs. Leaf blade elliptic to ovate-obovate, (3.5-)4-5(-6) × 1.5-2.5 cm, base oblique, margins mostly singly serrate (some doubly serrate), apex acute; surfaces abaxially pale, glabrate, adaxially dark green, lustrous, glabrous; lateral veins forking 5 or more times per side. Inflorescences fascicles, (2-)3-4(-8)-flowered; pedicel 8-10 mm. Flowers: calyx reddish brown, deeply lobed, lobes (3-)4-5, glabrous; stamens 3-4; anthers reddish; stigma lobes white-pubescent, exserted, recurved and spreading with maturity. Samaras green to light brown, elliptic to ovate, ca. 1 cm, not winged, seeds nearly filling samara, notched at apex, glabrous. Seeds thickened, not inflated. 2n = 28.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late summer-early fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">In woods and in disturbed sites;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Calif., D.C., Ga., Ky., Maine, Md., Mass., Va.; native to Asia (China and Japan).</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Chinese elm</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">lacebark elm</other_name>
  <discussion>Ulmus parvifolia appears to naturalize more easily than U. procera or U. glabra. It has been reported but not documented from Idaho and West Virginia.</discussion>
  <discussion>Ulmus parvifolia is valued in cultivation for its pleasing form and ornamental bark. It is ruderal primarily in the southeastern United States.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
