<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Warnstorf" date="unknown">russowii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hedwigia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>25: 225.  1886,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species russowii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">acutifolium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Russow" date="unknown">robustum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species acutifolium;variety robustum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>81.</number>
  <discussion>Sporophytes are uncommon in Sphagnum russowii.  This species is associated with S. centrale, S. fallax, S. fimbriatum, S. girgensohnii, and S. squarrosum.  Because of its not particularly distinct phenotype as well its strong tendency to produce hemiisophyllous stem leaves, S. russowii is probably the most frequently misidentified Sphagnum species.  The combination of the flat, stellate capitulum, unranked branch leaves, and lingulate stem leaf will usually suffice to identify it.  Sphagnum capillifolium has a rounded capitulum and a pointed stem leaf while S. subtile also has a rounded capitulum but a shorter and more triangular stem leaf.  In montane and arctic mires it can be confused with S. warnstorfii but the latter usually has conspicuously 5-ranked branch leaves.  As one might expect in such a widespread and common species, the characters can vary considerably.  For example, one regularly finds plants that are consistent in every respect with the description except that they lack stem cortical pores.  Some stem leaves have almost no septations in the hyaline cells while other forms have most of the cells septate.  As with similar variation in the likewise common S. fuscum, there is no consistent pattern and so taxonomic recognition of the variants is unwarranted.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
