<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Judith A. Harpel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">TETRAPHIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family TETRAPHIDACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants minute and budlike or merely small, forming dense turfs or scattered patches; protonema producing chlorophyllose, perpendicular protonematal flaps, which are persistent or disappear after the development of the gametophores.  Stems erect, to 1.5 cm.  Leaves ovate or lanceolate, erect, three-ranked and appressed or spreading, costate or ecostate, cells smooth, rounded-hexagonal or oblong-rhomboid, basal cells elongate.  Sexual condition autoicous; archegonia and antheridia on short stems at the plant base.  Seta straight or flexuose, smooth or papillose.  Capsule exserted, single, cylindric, ovate or shortly oblong-cylindric; peristome of four, single, unsegmented, narrowly triangular, multicellular teeth; annulus absent.  Calyptra mitrate, smooth or plicate, naked.  Spores green to yellowish, 10–16 µm, spheric, smooth or finely papillose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">circumboreal</description>
  <description type="morphology">disjunct to the Southern Hemisphere.</description>
  <number>5.</number>
  <discussion>Genera 2, species 4 (2 genera, 4 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants with conspicuous stems to 1.5 cm, forming dense turfs or scattered patches, leaves costate, protonematal flaps not persistent, stalked asexual structures often present</description>
      <determination>1.   Tetraphis, p. 111</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants minute, bud-like, stems less than 0.05 cm, leaves weakly costate in distal leaves or costa absent, protonematal flaps persistent and usually present, specialized asexual structures absent</description>
      <determination>2.   Tetrodontium, p. 113</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
