<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Russow" date="unknown">imbricatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Beitr. Torfm.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>99. 1865,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species imbricatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants moderate-sized, weak-stemmed, lax; yellowish to golden brown; forming loose
        carpets; branches loosely imbricate. Stems yellow to brown, superficial cortical layer with
        spiral reinforcing fibrils visible, 1 or more pores/cell, comb-fibrils on interior wall.
        Stem leaves short-rectangular, 0.8–1.1 mm, hyaline cells mostly non-septate and absent
        comb-fibrils. Branch fascicles with 2 spreading and 1–2 hanging branches. Branch stems with
        hyaline cells non-ornamented, no or weak funnel-like projections on the end walls of
        cortical cells, cortical cell walls usually with large round pores. Branch leaves ovate to
        ovate-elliptic, 1.4–1.8 mm; hyaline cells on convex surface with numerous pores along the
        commissures; comb-lamellae obvious only in proximal 1/2 of leaf; chlorophyllous cells
        broadly triangular in transverse section and well-enclosed on the convex surface. Sexual
        condition dioecious. Spores (22) 24–27(–28) µm, surface granulate.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ecology poorly known;</description>
  <description type="morphology">moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska.</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <discussion>K. I. Flatberg (1984) considered Sphagnum imbricatum to be East Asian in
        distribution but a recent collection in Selawik National Wildlife Refuge places it in the
        North American flora. It will undoubtedly be found elsewhere. Sphagnum imbricatum is closest
        in morphological detail to S. steerei, but the latter is a very dark colored and densely
        branched species whereas S. imbricatum is quite light in color and not particularly
        dense.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
