<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">tetraphidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schwägrichen" date="1824">TETRODONTIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond. Suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(1,2): 102.  1824·   [Greek tetra, four, and odontos, tooth, alluding to peristome],</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family tetraphidaceae;genus TETRODONTIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants very small, budlike, dull dark-green to brownish green, in scattered, gregarious or sometimes very small clumps.  Thallose protonematal flaps persistent and usually present.  Stems few, very short, less than 0.05 cm; flagelliform shoots may occur at the base of the stem, 0.2–0.5 cm, with 3-ranked, tightly appressed linear to lanceolate leaves.  Leaves of main stem few, appressed, ovate, acuminate, or obtuse, margins entire or dentate, to 1.2 mm; costa single, weak or absent; laminal cells rhombic or rectangular.  Specialized asexual structures  absent.  Sexual condition: perichaetial and perigonial buds occurring on the same protonema; perichaetial leaves ovate to ovate-lanceolate, concave.  Seta 3–8 mm, straight, smooth, slightly twisted when dry.  Capsule 0.6–1 mm, ovate to shortly oblong-cylindric, straight; operculum conic, obliquely apiculate; peristome usually not splitting or appearing to be more than four.  Calyptra smooth or somewhat plicate, yellowish.  Spores smooth or finely papillose, 10–16 µm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, South America (Chile); Eurasia, Pacific Islands (New Zealand).</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants with numerous flagelliform shoots, protonematal flaps less than 0.5 mm</description>
      <determination>1.   Tetrodontium repandum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants without flagelliform shoots, protonematal flaps 0.5–2.5 mm</description>
      <determination>2.   Tetrodontium brownianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
