<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichastrum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) G. L. Smith" date="unknown">formosum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. New York Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21(3): 37.  1971,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichastrum;species formosum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">formosum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>92, plate 19, fig. 1a.  1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichum;species formosum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Menzies" date="unknown">attenuatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichum;species attenuatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium and slender to large and robust, green to dark olive green to blackish, in loose tufts.  Stems (2–)3–8(–20) cm, mostly unbranched.  Leaves 6–8(–12) mm, erect to erect-spreading when dry, spreading to subsquarrose and broadly recurved when moist; sheath ovate to elliptic, yellowish, hyaline-margined, gradually tapering or abruptly contracted to the blade, the cells at the shoulders forming a differentiated hinge; blade lanceolate to linear; costa prominent abaxially and toothed near the tip; excurrent as a short, toothed point; marginal lamina erect, (2–)3–5(–10) cells wide, plane or erect, sharply toothed from apex nearly to the sheath; lamellae (3–)4–5(–7) cells high, margins ± entire to finely serrulate in profile, the marginal cells in section rounded to narrowly elliptic and somewhat taller than the cells beneath, the cell walls not or moderately thickened; median cells of sheath 8–12 µm wide, narrowly rectangular, 5–7(–10):1; cells of marginal lamina subquadrate, 10–15 µm.  Sexual condition dioicous or polygamous; perichaetial leaves similar to the foliage leaves, or somewhat longer, with a longer sheath.  Seta 3–6 cm, yellowish to reddish brown.  Capsule 4–7 mm, rather slender or short-rectangular, acutely 4(–6)-angled, inclined to almost horizontal, pale yellowish brown to brownish; hypophysis cylindric, indistinctly delimited or set off by a shallow groove; exothecium smooth or the cells weakly convex, quadrate to hexagonal, without a central thin spot; peristome 600 µm, divided to 0.6, the teeth 64 and highly regular in form or fewer and somewhat irregular, pale to brownish; epiphragm absent marginal teeth.  Spores 12–16 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">widespread</description>
  <description type="morphology">temperate to cool temperate latitudes in the Northern Hemisphere.</description>
  <number>5.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 3 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>European treatments often assert a similarity between Polytrichastrum formosum and Polytrichum commune, which cannot be said of the North American expression of the species. The habitat and ecology of the European plants are also distinct: A. J. E. Smith (2004) described P. formosum in Britain as a common and weedy species of heaths, moorland, woods, outcrops, and old walls.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants often robust, 5–10(–20) cm; leaves subsquarrose and broadly spreading- recurved when moist; lamellae 5–7 cells high, entire, the marginal cells in section rounded, moderately thick-walled; capsule short rectangular; hypophysis delimited by a shallow groove; peristome teeth 64, regular in form; dioicous var. formosum</description>
      <determination>5a.   Polytrichastrum formosum var. formosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants rather slender, 3–6(–10) cm; leaves spreading when moist; lamellae (3–)4–6 cells high, the marginal cells narrowly elliptic, not or only slightly thickened; capsule slender; hypophysis not sharply delimited; peristome teeth 50–64, somewhat irregular in size and shape; monoicous (polyga- mous)</description>
      <determination>5b.   Polytrichastrum formosum var. densifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
