<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichastrum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Renauld &amp; Cardot) G. L. Smith" date="unknown">ohioense</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. New York Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21(3): 35.  1971,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichastrum;species ohioense;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Renauld &amp; Cardot" date="unknown">ohioense</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 11.  1885</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichum;species ohioense;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>6.</number>
  <discussion>Polytrichastrum ohioense is endemic to eastern North America, and is common in the Appalachian mixed oak (formerly oak-chestnut) forest, the oak-hickory forest of the interior United States (to eastern Kansas and Oklahoma), the oak-pine forests of the Atlantic coastal plain, and the maple-beech forest in Indiana, Ohio, southern Michigan, and Ontario.  At higher elevations and in more northerly latitudes in coniferous forests, it is replaced by P. pallidisetum.  An isolated population of P. ohioense occurs in a wooded canyon in the San Andres Mountains, northeast of Las Cruces, New Mexico.  In the field, P. ohioense has a distinctive appearance.  The seta typically far exceeds the leafy shoots in length, and the perichaetial leaves have conspicuous rough, golden yellow awns.  The transversely elliptical, thick-walled marginal cells of the lamellae are also unique to this species.  In side view the lamellae are entire, and the lumen greatly restricted.  In P. pallidisetum the terminal cells of the lamellae are flat-topped to shallowly retuse, and in side view the lamellae are crenulate, their marginal cells not notably thick-walled.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
