<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">commune</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>88.  1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichum;species commune;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Widely distributed in the North America, throughout temperate and boreal latitudes in the Northern Hemisphere, Mexico, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia.</discussion>
  <discussion>The only North American species likely to be confused with Polytrichum commune is Polytrichastrum pallidisetum.  When sterile, Polytrichum commune is easily distinguished by cross-sections of the leaves, particularly by the greatly broadened costa, and the notched marginal cells of the lamellae.  In Polytrichastrum pallidisetum the marginal cells of the lamellae are broadened and shallowly retuse, but not distinctly notched, and in Polytrichum commune the arc of guide cells (seen in section below mid-point of blade) is broad, 18–24 cells wide, compared with 8–12 cells wide in Polytrichastrum pallidisetum.  When capsules are present, the two species can be distinguished at a glance.  A striking form of Polytrichum commune growing in wetlands, var. uliginosum, has greatly elongate stems and tightly sheathing, glossy leaf bases, the blades are flexuose and squarrose-recurved.  Recent European genetic studies (R. J. Bijlsma et al. 2000) suggest that it should be recognized as a separate species.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (2–)5–10(–70) cm; apical cells of lamellae broader than those beneath, in section deeply grooved; inner perichaetial leaves not much longer than the foliage leaves, toothed distally, ending in a rather short, roughened awn var. commune</description>
      <determination>1a.   Polytrichum commune var. commune</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants to 6 cm; marginal cells of lamellae narrow, in section shallowly grooved; inner perichaetial leaves ribbon-like, exceeding the foliage leaves, denticulate to subentire, gradually tapering to long, nearly smooth awn</description>
      <determination>1b.   Polytrichum commune var. perigoniale</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
