<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gary L. Smith Merrill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">polytrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(G. L. Smith) G. L. Smith" date="unknown">MEIOTRICHUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>95: 271.  1992  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polytrichaceae; genus MEIOTRICHUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek meio-, fewer, and trichos, hair, alluding to calyptra]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichastrum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="G. L. Smith" date="unknown">Meiotrichum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. New York Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21(3): 40.  1971</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichastrum;section Meiotrichum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants robust, polytrichoid.  Stems simple to freely branched.  Leaves with a sheathing base and divergent blade; sheath entire, hyaline margined; limb firm, serrate-toothed to the sheath, broadly lamellate on the adaxial surface; lamellae entire in profile, the marginal cells with the free wall thickened, the cuticle longitudinally striate and pitted.  Capsule ventricose, 4–6-angled; hypophysis rugose, with conspicuous stomata; exothecial cells with rounded to slit-like thin spots in the external wall; operculum hemispherical, with a stout, hooked beak; peristome present, leiodont, teeth 64, simple.  Calyptra sparsely hairy.  Spores papillose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">w North America.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Meiotrichum was originally placed in Polytrichadelphus (Müller Hal.) Mitten (not present in our area) because of the fastigiate habit and sparsely hairy calyptra.  All Polytrichadelphus species have lamellae which are crenulate in profile, the marginal cells smooth and flask-shaped in section, a dorsiventral capsule with two sharp angles, and multiple stomata dispersed over the exothecium, none of which occurs in Meiotrichum.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
