<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">polytrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="1805">oligotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="1805">hercynicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Franç. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3, 2: 492.  1805,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polytrichaceae;genus oligotrichum;species hercynicum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Polytrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">hercynicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>94.  1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Polytrichum;species hercynicum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Oligotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Bridel) Lindberg" date="unknown">incurvum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Oligotrichum;species incurvum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants bright green, somewhat glaucous, becoming reddish brown with age.  Stems 1–2.5(–3) cm.  Leaves 2.5–5 mm, lanceolate from a weakly sheathing base, broadly incurved and subtubulose when dry, somewhat spreading but remaining incurved and strongly channeled distally when moist; margins entire to finely and distantly serrulate; costa percurrent or shortly excurrent as a short mucro, the adaxial surface with several low continuous or interrupted abaxial lamellae; abaxial surface of lamina smooth or sporadically with scattered short lamellae near the apex of leaf; adaxial lamellae 8–20, 6–13 cells high, restricted to the costa, crispate-undulate, extending to the middle of the leaf or below, the margins finely and irregularly crenulate with bulging marginal cells, smooth; median cells of lamina 15–20 µm, somewhat smaller towards the margins, rounded subquadrate, thick-walled; marginal teeth distant, minute, unicellular; perichaetial leaves 3–3.5 mm, narrowly lanceolate.  Seta stout, pale brown, 2–4 cm.  Capsule 2–4 mm, cylindric, slightly larger at the base, terete or irregularly angled or ridged; peristome teeth 32, double, somewhat irregular.  Spores 10–15 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Soil, gravel, and moist peaty embankments, open disturbed sites, roadcuts, beside paths, on lake shores, stream banks, late snow areas, also aquatic in rapidly flowing glacier melt streams;</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate to high elevations (500-2200 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; Alta., B.C., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Yukon; Alaska, Mont., Oreg., Wash.; Europe (southward to Spain, Turkey); e Asia (Japan).</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>An arctic-alpine species widespread in northern latitudes, Oligotrichum hercynicum is a pioneer species, typically forming bright green patches on disturbed soil but, like O. falcatum, also in aquatic habitats.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
