<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bescherelle" date="unknown">crispulum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Sci. Nat., Bot., sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7, 17: 351.  1893,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atrichum;species crispulum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>5.</number>
  <discussion>Atrichum crispulum is a large, handsome, dioicous species, distinguished by its broad leaves with few, low lamellae, long, narrow, curved capsules, and by its growth in shaded, wet environments on banks along streams and at margins of fens and swamps.  Atrichum undulatum, on the other hand, prefers dry weedy habitats, and when sterile can be distinguished from A. crispulum by the reddish brown rhizoids more or less confined to the base of the plant, instead of matted whitish rhizoids often extending well up the stem in A. crispulum.  As suggested by R. R. Ireland (1969), the “paraphyllia” in the type of A. paraphyllium Wareham are innovations probably caused by the plants being buried in sand.  In recent North American literature this species has been called A. oerstedianum (Müller Hal.) Mitten, but comparisons with the type of A. oerstedianum indicate that the two are distinct.  Atrichum oerstedianum, a species of Mexico and Central America, has leaves broadly elliptic-lanceolate with an obtuse apex, only sporadically toothed on the abaxial surface and not undulate, lamellae (2–)4–5, 1–2 cells high, often interrupted, and a colored border.  The cells of the lamina are irregular in size and shape, with a “disordered” arrangement as opposed to the more regular arrangement of cells in longitudinal rows in A. crispulum.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
