<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gary L. Smith Merrill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="P. Beauvois" date="unknown">POGONATUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mag. Encycl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 329.  1804  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus POGONATUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek  pogon, beard, alluding to hairy calyptra]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <discussion>Species 52 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>North American species of Pogonatum vary greatly in size and habit from tall, laxly tufted plants to protonema mosses with individual plants scattered and only a few millimeters high.  Pogonatum contortum of the Pacific Northwest, with leaves strongly crisped and contorted when dry, is the most “typical” of the genus as a whole.  Pogonatum brachyphyllum and P. pensilvanicum are protonema-mosses, the gametophyte consisting of a persistent felted mat of protonema and leafy plants small and scattered.  The other two species are distinctly polytrichoid in habit, with the margins of the lamellae thick-walled and coarsely papillose.  Pogonatum dentatum is an arctic-montane species, whereas P. urnigerum has a somewhat more southerly distribution and occurs as well in the Himalayas and New Guinea.  The sporophytes of our species are more uniform, with a scabrous exothecium, deeply pigmented peristome with compound peristome teeth, and no stomata.  The exothecial “papillae” are projections of the cell wall, unlike the wart-like cuticular papillae often seen on the leaf surfaces of many Polytrichaceae.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hyvönen, J.  1989.  A synopsis of genus Pogonatum (Polytrichaceae, Musci).  Acta Bot. Fenn. 138: 1–87.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants to 0.6 cm, scattered over a green, persistent protonema.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lamellae 25–40, compact, the leaf appearing thick and fleshy; leaf margins entire</description>
      <determination>2.   Pogonatum brachyphyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lamellae 11–16, the leaf membranous; leaf margins irregularly notched</description>
      <determination>3.   Pogonatum pensilvanicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 3–8(–12) cm, in loose pure tufts or growing among other bryophytes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves toothed from the apex nearly to the base; marginal cells of lamellae not differentiated, smooth</description>
      <determination>1.   Pogonatum contortum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves toothed above the shoulders, the margins of the sheath entire; marginal cells of lamellae thick-walled and coarsely papillose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins with multicellular, hooked teeth; leaf sheath not hyaline-margined; marginal cells of lamellae ± rectangular, flat-topped, the lumen quadrate; peristome divided nearly to the base</description>
      <determination>4.   Pogonatum dentatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins with mostly 1-cellular teeth; leaf sheath hyaline-margined; marginal cells of lamellae rounded to transversely elliptical, the lumen pentagonal; peristome divided to ca. 0.6</description>
      <determination>5.   Pogonatum urnigerum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
