<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gary L. Smith Merrill</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">polytrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown" date="1819">LYELLIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 561.  1819  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polytrichaceae;genus LYELLIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Sir Charles Lyell, 1767–1849]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants robust, polytrichoid.  Stems simple or rarely branched.  Leaves with a sheathing base and divergent blade; sheath entire, hyaline-margined; limb firm, serrate-toothed in distal 1/3–1/2, with lamellae restricted to median portion of the limb, the lamina ± uniformly 2-stratose; lamellae entire, the marginal cells in section not differentiated, smooth.  [Capsule ovoid,  strongly dorsiventral, the upper surface flattened and concave with a narrow winged margin, lower surface rounded-convex, with hypophysis short, with conspicious stomata, guard cells surrounded by a circle of thin-walled, hyaline cells; operculum compressed-conic, with elongated oblique beak; peristome none; columella apex flattened and protruding from the central opening of a concave, thickened disc.  Calyptra sparsely hairy to almost smooth.  Spores echinulate.]</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">e Asia (including Siberia).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 4 (1 in the flora): North America, e Asia (including Siberia).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 4 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, e Asia (including Siberia).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>Species 4 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Lyellia is a small genus with a disjunctive distribution, with representatives occurring in the Himalayas and eastward, and a single species, L. aspera, at high latitudes in arctic America and eastern Asia.  The capsules are strongly dorsiventral, resembling those of Dawsonia in shape, but without a peristome.  The flattened columella apex projects from the center of the disc like a stopper in a wash basin (Gary L. Smith 1971, fig. 25); the epiphragm remains embedded in the operculum.  The hypophysis has prominent stomata, the guard cells surrounded by a ring of thin-walled, hyaline subsidiary cells, which are sharply differentiated from the surrounding cells of the exothecium.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
