<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>9.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>BARTRAMIOPSIS</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Kindberg</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21: 33.  1894  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[Genus Bartramia and Greek -opsis, resembling]</etymology>
  <author>Gary L. Smith Merrill</author>
  <description>Plants slender, not distinctly polytrichoid.  Stems simple.  Leaves with a sheathing base and divergent limb; sheath ciliate on the shoulders, not hyaline-margined; limb serrate-toothed to the sheath (or ciliate near the base), with lamellae restricted to the adaxial surface of the costa; lamina 2-stratose, with sporadic 1-stratose patches, the adaxial layer of cells bulging-mammillose; lamellae serrate in profile, the marginal cells in section not differentiated, smooth.  Capsule short-cylindric, terete, flaring at the mouth when old and empty, weakly contracted at the base, the long-tapering neck merging with the seta; exothecial cells without thin spots or pits; stomata present, confined to the neck; operculum conic; peristome none; columella flaring at the tip, persisting and elevated above the rim of the capsule.  Calyptra naked.  Spores papillose.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>northern Pacific Radiant distribution</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>nw North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia (Japan, e Siberia).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Diagnostic features of Bartramiopsis include the serrate lamellae, the ciliate sheath, the terete capsule, which is flared at the mouth and tapers toward the base, the absence of a peristome, and the naked calyptra.  The genus occupies an isolated position in the family, and the gametophyte has a curious un-polytrichoid appearance.  The bistratose lamina and the absence of even a rudimentary peristome have led to its association with Lyellia, but the capsule in that genus is strongly dorsiventral with 2 sharp angles, with a bowl-shaped disc at the capsule mouth and the blunted columella apex forming a “stopper” in the small central opening.  In Bartramiopsis, the exserted columella is broadly flared, extends to the capsule rim, and persists long after the operculum is shed.</discussion>
</treatment>
