<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">polytrichaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kindberg" date="1894">bartramiopsis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(James) Kindberg" date="1894">lescurii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21: 35.  1894,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family polytrichaceae;genus bartramiopsis;species lescurii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="James" date="unknown">lescurii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 33.  1875</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atrichum;species lescurii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lyellia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(James) E. S. Salmon" date="unknown">lescurii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lyellia;species lescurii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in loose to rather dense pure tufts, dull olive green, becoming dark reddish brown with age.  Stems 3–10 cm, arising from a short, erect tuberous rhizome, slender and thread-like, distantly bracteate and appearing almost leafless proximally, ± abruptly leafy distally.  Leaves loosely imbricate, 4–6 mm, linear-lanceolate from a sheathing base, the sheath yellowish and nitid, clasping stem; limb reflexed at the shoulders, subtubulose, twisted and contorted when dry, widely spreading and almost plane when moist; costa slender, percurrent, smooth abaxially, ending in a short spine; margins of sheath entire proximally, not hyaline-margined, at shoulders cilia 1-seriate, 0.4–0.6 mm, cells distinctly papillose; no hinge tissue; margins of limb plane, serrations ending in a conical tooth cell, sometimes with 1–2 short cilia near the shoulders; lamina 2-stratose except for a narrow strip just within the margin and locally 1-stratose streaks and patches, adaxial layer of cells strongly bulging mammillose in indistinct longitudinal rows; lamellae 4–5(–9), restricted to the costa, 4–8(–10) cells high, serrations ending in a small toothed cell; sheath cells linear at margin, the median short-rectangular, 23–28 × 6–9 µm; abaxial laminal cells irregularly arranged, subquadrate, 6–10(–12) µm, walls evenly thickened and firm; abaxial costal cells sharply differentiated, narrowly elongate to linear, 25–33(–55) × 5–6 µm.  Sexual condition dioicous; male plants like the female, male inflorescence inconspicuous, several to a shoot, separated by sectors with normal vegetative leaves, perigonial bracts with a broader sheath, but otherwise like the leaves; perichaetial leaves scarcely differentiated.  Seta rather stout, 7–12 mm.  Capsule yellowish brown, erect, 2.5–4 mm, widest at the mouth; exothecial cells short-rectangular, 40–62 × 26–30 µm, smaller and ± isodiametric below mouth, smooth; stomata superficial, confined to the tapering neck; operculum almost as large as urn, beak about 1 mm; peristome none; columella broadly flaring, extending to capsule rim.  Calyptra cucullate.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Soil banks or soil over rock, exposed tree roots;</description>
  <description type="morphology">usually low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">e Asia (Japan, Russia in Kamtschatka).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Soil banks or soil over rock, exposed tree roots; usually low to moderate elevations; B.C.; Alaska, Wash.; e Asia (Japan, Russia in Kamtschatka).</text>
    <parsed>
      <habitat>Soil banks or soil over rock, exposed tree roots;</habitat>
      <elevation>usually low to moderate elevations;</elevation>
      <distribution>B.C.; Alaska, Wash.; e Asia (Japan, Russia in Kamtschatka).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>1.</number>
</bio:treatment>
