<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">timmiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">timmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">megapolitana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>176.  1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family timmiaceae;genus timmia;species megapolitana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants without deciduous distal leaves.  Leaf apex acute; costa subpercurrent; sheath clear or yellowish; limb green, pellucid; limb-sheath transition abrupt, not sharply angled; limb margins strongly dentate in distal half, with fewer and smaller teeth below, and a few small sharp teeth at limb-sheath transition; limb lamina cells (5–)7–16(–21) × (6–)7–12(–14) µm, with low rounded or flattened mamillae on the adaxial surface, abaxial surface smooth; abaxial surfaces of sheath lamina cells smooth or with 1–6 papillae over lumen; cells at leaf insertion not fragile and hyaline; abaxial surface of limb costa smooth (rarely papillose near leaf apex), adaxial cells with rounded or somewhat flattened mamillae.  Sexual condition monoicous; perichaetial leaves narrower than vegetative leaves.  Calyptra with a median longitudinal split, sometimes persistent on the neck of the capsule or seta.  Capsule plicate or puckered when dry; exothecial cells with non-sinuose walls; stomata on urn; endostome cilia with numerous spine-like or branched-stellate appendiculations on the interior surfaces.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="morphology">n Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Atlantic Islands (Iceland)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pacific Islands (Hawaii).</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Timmia megapolitana is a distinct species within the genus, separated by its monoicous sexuality, distinct but pale leaf sheaths, and elaborately appendiculate endostome cilia.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cells of mid-limb lamina (8–)9–12(–14) µm wide; cells of distal part of leaf sheath papillose; calyptra often remaining attached to seta at base of capsule</description>
      <determination>2a.   Timmia megapolitana subsp. megapolitana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cells of the mid-limb lamina (6–)7–10(–12) µm wide; cells of distal part of leaf sheath smooth; calyptra not persistent on seta</description>
      <determination>2b.   Timmia megapolitana subsp. bavarica</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
