<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">encalyptaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1901">BRYOBRITTONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. New York Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 115.  1901  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family encalyptaceae;genus BRYOBRITTONIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek bryon, moss, and for Elizabeth G. Knight Britton, 1858–1934, American botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants medium-sized, gregarious.  Stems rarely branched; central strand absent or weakly differentiated.  Leaves oblong, elliptic or narrowly obovate; apex broadly acute, mucronate; margins plane to weakly incurved, crenulate distally, entire proximally; costae subpercurrent, smooth; distal laminal cells more or less rhomboidal, bulging on both exposed surfaces, but stronger adaxially; basal cells long-rectangular; marginal cells sometimes longer proximally forming a very weak border.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Seta very long, smooth, reddish brown to black.  Capsule long-exserted, erect, furrowed; peristomate, stomata numerous; peristome double, exostome teeth long, narrow; endostome with basal membrane, segments filiform, almost as long as teeth, papillose.  Operculum long conic-rostrate.  Calyptra generally smooth, erose or lacerate at base.  Spores small, round.</description>
  <description type="distribution">n North America, Europe, c Asia.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Found on open, calcareous soil across the northern reaches of the flora area, Bryobrittonia closely resembles Encalypta in its habitat preferences and growth form.  Fruiting specimens produce the large, brownish calyptra diagnostic of the family, but, perhaps associated with dioicy, sporophytes are rare.  Bryobrittonia can be separated from Encalypta, the only other genus in the family, by bulging distal laminal cells and crenulate distal leaf margins.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
