<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">encalyptaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">encalypta</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Magill" date="2006">texana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>109: 399, figs. 1–11. 2006,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family encalyptaceae;genus encalypta;species texana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems 5–10 mm, central strand small. Leaves broadly oblong to elliptic, 3–4 mm;
        apices broadly acute, mucronate; margins plane to erect or incurved distally or weakly
        recurved proximally; costa percurrent to subpercurrect, narrow, papillose distally on
        adaxial surface; laminal cells 15–25 µm; basal cells 25–75 µm, walls thickened, smooth;
        basal marginal cells weakly differentiated, longer than laminal cells, in 3–5 rows.
        Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Seta 4–6 mm, yellow-brown. Capsule cylindric, 1.8–2
        mm, smooth to weakly wrinkled when dry, gymnostomous, yellowish brown; exothecial cells
        quadrate, walls thickened; peristome absent; operculum 0.5 mm. Calyptra 3–4 mm, irregularly
        fringed at base, weakly papillose to essentially smooth. Spores 30–35 µm, finely pitted,
        reddish brown.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Igneous soil in rock crevices;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Encalypta texana was previously identified as a North American specimen of E.
        sibirica (Weinmann) Warnstorf. Several distinct characters and important habitat and
        distributional factors, however, set it apart from that Asian species: costa ending just
        before the apex, capsule length, calyptra ornamentation, spore ornamentation, and
        differences in gametophyte and calyptra color. Encalypta texana could be confused with
        another species with gymnostomous capsules and costae ending before the leaf apex, E.
        flowersiana, which is also present in the mountains of western Texas. Encalypta flowersiana
        is smaller, with leaf margins plane, capsule furrowed, and spores have distinct ridges,
        while E. texana has laminal margins incurved to plane distally and recurved proximally,
        capsule smooth to weakly wrinkled, and spores finely pitted.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
