<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Entosthodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Steere" date="unknown">wigginsii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>41: 36, figs. 1–8.  1938,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Entosthodon;species wigginsii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 2–5 mm, yellow green, the main axis often arising from a fleshy rhizome.  Leaves shriveled and distorted when dry, obovate to oblong-spathulate, imbricate, somewhat concave, mostly 2–3 mm; margins serrulate by projecting ends of thin-walled cells; apices acute, sometimes with a short apiculus; costa ending 4–6 cells before the apex; basal laminal cells  rectangular (85–120 × 25–30 µm), distal cells irregularly polygonal to hexagonal or oblong-rectangular, a little longer but not otherwise differentiated at the margins.  Seta brownish basally and paler distally, 5–8 mm, straight, not hygroscopic.  Capsule pyriform to elongate-pyriform from an apophysis about half the total length, 1.5–2 mm, becoming sulcate when dry and empty; exothecial cells thickened, narrowly oblong and transversely elongate in 4–5 rows proximal to the mouth; operculum planoconvex; peristome double, exostome teeth bright red becoming paler at the tip, lanceolate with 7–8 articulations, obliquely striate basally, papillose at the tips, endostome well developed from a pale basal membrane bearing irregular segments.  Calyptra cucullate, long-beaked, inflated around the capsule, large, smooth.  Spores 20–24 µm, bacculate-insulate often in persistent tetrads at maturity.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Fine soil, crevices of rocks, base of cliffs;</description>
  <description type="morphology">moderate to high elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Utah.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
</bio:treatment>
