<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>6.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Entosthodon</genus_name>
    <species_name>sonorae</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Cardot) Steere</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>41: 39.  1938,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Funaria</genus_name>
    <species_name>sonorae</species_name>
    <species_authority>Cardot</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 110.  1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Entosthodon</genus_name>
    <species_name>bartramii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Grout</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 2–4 mm, pale yellow green.  Leaves variously contorted when dry, ovate to oblong to obovate, imbricate, somewhat concave, mostly 1.5–2 mm; margins serrulate by projecting ends of thin-walled cells; apices acute, terminating in a 1–2-celled apiculus, costa ending 7–10 cells before the apiculus; basal laminal cells rectangular (50–70 × 18–25 µm), distal cells irregularly short- to oblong-rectangular, somewhat inflated marginally.  Seta pale yellow, 4–5 mm, straight, not hygroscopic.  Capsule yellow, elongate-cylindrical from a neck half or more the total length, 2.5–3 mm, weakly sulcate when dry and empty; exothecial cells scarcely thickened, narrowly oblong (3–4:1) near the mouth and transversely elongate in 4–6 rows proximal to the mouth; operculum conic-rounded; peristome pale brownish yellow, lanceolate with thin trabeculae proximally and terminating in a 1–2-celled hyaline evanescent tip, striate basally and nearly smooth at the tips, endostome not seen.  Calyptra cucullate, long-beaked, inflated around the capsule, large, smooth.  Spores 18–25 µm, smooth.</description>
  <habitat>Mineral soils, probably in shade of rocks or in crevices;</habitat>
  <elevation>moderate to high elevations;</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico (Sonora).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Enthosthodon sonorae is restricted to the Sonoran Region of southwestern United States and northern Mexico.</discussion>
</treatment>
