<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Entosthodon</genus_name><species_name>planoconvexus</species_name><species_authority>(Bartram) Grout</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Moss Fl. N. Amer. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 80.  1935,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Funaria</genus_name><species_name>planoconvexa</species_name><species_authority>Bartram</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bryologist </publication_title><place_in_publication>31: 94, plate 9, figs. G–L.  1928</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 2–7 mm, yellowish green, the main axis often arising from a short fleshy rhizome.  Leaves variously contorted when dry, oblong to obovate or spathulate, imbricate, somewhat concave, mostly 2–3 mm; margins serrulate distally; apices acute, abruptly narrowing to a short filiform point about 250 µm in length; costa ending 5–9 cells before the apiculus; basal laminal cells rectangular (50–55 × 20–35 µm), distal cells irregularly quadrate to elongate-hexagonal to short-rectangular, little differentiated along the margins.  Seta 6–10 mm, straight, twisted, hygroscopic.  Capsule yellowish to brownish, ovoid-pyriform with about half the length in the apophysis, 2–3 mm, sulcate when dry and empty; exothecial cells scarcely thickened, narrowly oblong and transversely elongate in 5–7 rows proximal to the mouth; operculum planoconvex; peristome well developed, exostome teeth reddish brown to brownish yellow, lanceolate, striate papillose, trabeculate basally, terminating in a coarsely papillose tip, endostome evanescent with low, broad, segments.  Calyptra cucullate, long-beaked, inflated around the capsule, large, smooth.  Spores 20–25 µm, bacculate-insulate.</description><habitat>Sandy soil, canyons and desert washes;</habitat><elevation> moderate to high elevations;</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Utah.</us_distribution></treatment>
