<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">sphagnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Russow) Schimper" date="1876">squarrosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Flatberg &amp; Thingsgaard" date="2003">mirum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>106: 501.  2003,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family sphagnaceae;genus sphagnum;section squarrosa;species mirum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants fairly slender to moderate-sized, green; forming low dense hummocks.  Stems yellowish green; 3 layers of superficial cortical cells.  Stem leaves generally longer than branch leaves, 1.1–1.7 mm, lingulate to lingulate-spathulate, hyaline cells mostly non-septate.  Branches terete.  Branch fascicles of 2 spreading and 1–2 hanging branches.  Branch stems with 1–2 layers of cortical cells.  Branch leaves 1–1.4 mm, broadly ovate, with a narrow involute tip; hyaline cells only slightly bulging on either surface, in proximal half of leaf aporose on convex surface and with large faint pores on concave surface; internal commissural walls distinctly papillose; chlorophyllous cells elliptical to elliptical-triangular in transverse section, enclosed on both surfaces with the widest part in the leaf middle.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Spores ca. 31 µm, ornamented by small somewhat amalgamated granulae.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Sporophytes abundant, capsules mature August.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Ecology poorly known but probably quite minerotrophic;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low elevations;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alaska.</description>
  <number>16.</number>
  <discussion>Sphagnum mirum has only been recently discovered and so far is known only from its type locality, where it was growing in a fen mixed with S. teres.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
