<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>PHYSCOMITRELLA</genus_name><genus_authority>Bruch &amp; Schimper</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Bryol. Europ. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 13.  1849  ,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Genus Physcomitrium and Latin -ella, diminutive]</etymology><author>Bernard Goffinet</author><description>Plants small, scattered to gregarious.  Stems 3–3.5 mm, erect, simple or forked.  Leaves somewhat crisped when dry, erect-spreading when moist, lanceolate, ovate-lanceolate, or obovate, plane to weakly concave, 2–2.5 mm; margins entire to serrulate distally; apices acuminate; costa single, extending 1/2–2/3 of the leaf length, occasionally slightly forked at apex, or percurrent; proximal laminal cells rectangular, distal cells short-rectangular to rhombic with narrow ends.  Sexual condition paroicous.  Seta erect, to 0.2 mm.  Capsule cleistocarpous, erect, immersed, symmetric, globose and apiculate, to 0.8 mm, wrinkled upon aging; exothecial cells irregular in shape, usually thin-walled; stomata with single guard cell, restricted to base of capsule, superficial; annulus none; operculum not differentiated, dehiscence irregular; peristome absent.  Calyptra conic-mitrate, not or slightly lobed, small, covering apiculus of capsule only, smooth.  Spores spherical to slightly elliptical, densely papillose to slightly spinulose.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> c</global_distribution><global_distribution> n Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution> Asia (China, Japan, w Siberia)</global_distribution><global_distribution> Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution> Australia.</global_distribution><discussion>Physcomitrella is distinguished from other Funariaceae by the immersed capsule with irregular dehiscence, and the thin-walled, translucent exothecial cells.  The generic name implies a resemblance to Physcomitrium, which is named, however, for its large calyptra, unlike that of Physcomitrella.</discussion><key><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Costa extending to at most 2/3 the length of the leaf</statement><determination>1.   Physcomitrella readeri</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Costa extending to leaf apex</statement><determination>2.   Physcomitrella patens</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
