<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Wilfred B. Schofield</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">DISCELIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus DISCELIACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, minute, arising from a perennial persistent protonema.  Stems erect, to 0.2 mm, completely enveloped in leaves.  Leaves with costa weak or absent, brownish or with little chlorophyll, exterior leaves 0.2–0.4 mm, interior to 1 mm, acuminate, ovate to oblong-lanceolate, margins entire to crenulate by bulging cells; laminal cells elongate-hexagonal to rectangular, thin-walled, 85–100 × 12–16 µm, smooth.  Specialized asexual reproduction by 2-celled starch-filled rhizoidal gemmae.  Sexual condition functionally dioicous; perigonium of 3–6 leaves surrounding a few short antheridia and yellow, club-shaped paraphyses; perichaetium with few brownish, weakly chlorophyllose leaves, these representing the plant.  Seta erect, twisted to right when dry, 4–30 mm or more.  Capsule wide-mouthed, 0.4–0.7 mm, pale to dark brown when mature, stomata absent; annulus in 1–2 cell rows, deciduous; peristome of 16 reddish brown to orange-yellow lanceolate exostomial teeth, to 0.3 mm, with vertical striations on exterior face, often with longitudinal perforations, endostome delicate, as a sometimes discontinuous membrane adhering to exostomial teeth; operculum conic.  Calyptra smooth, sometimes persistent on seta proximal to capsule.  Spores 20–30 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia.</description>
  <number>13.</number>
  <discussion>Genus 1, species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Disceliaceae is widely distributed in the Northern Hemisphere but always rare.  It is predominantly temperate, but also boreal at lower elevations.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Duckett, J. G. and S. Pressl.  2003.  Studies of protonemal morphogenesis in mosses.  IX.  Discelium nudum: Exquisite pioneer of unstable clay banks.  J. Bryol. 25: 241–245.</reference>
    <reference>Shaw, A. J. and B. H. Allen.  1985.  Anatomy and morphology of the peristome in Discelium nudum (Musci: Disceliaceae).  Bryologist 88: 263–267.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
