<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Schistidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Mogensen &amp; H. H. Blom" date="unknown">cryptocarpum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Lindbergia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 75, figs. 1, 2.  1990,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Schistidium;species cryptocarpum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in cushions or low, sometimes extensive tufts, olivaceous or yellowish brown.  Stems 0.8–2.5 cm, central strand distinct.  Leaves erect or curved, rarely falcate, imbricate when dry, lanceolate to ovate-lanceolate, strongly keeled distally, (0.9–)1.4–2(–2.3) mm, 1-stratose; margins usually recurved to just before the apex, proximally often more broadly recurved on one side of leaf, distal 1/3 often plane, smooth, 1-stratose with 2-stratose sections; apices acute or sub-obtuse; costa excurrent as a denticulate, flexuose, usually strongly decurrent awn, often embracing part of the lamina, smooth; basal marginal cells short-rectangular, occasionally with transverse walls thicker than longitudinal walls; distal cells mainly short-rectangular or quadrate, 7–10(–11.5) µm wide, smooth, usually strongly sinuose.  Sexual condition autoicous.  Capsule orange-brown or reddish brown, campanulate, 0.5–0.6 mm; exothecial cells short-elongate or isodiametric, often more or less quadrate, thin-walled or slightly thickened, small trigones usually present; stomata present; operculum rostrate; peristome rudimentary, consisting of basal segments, or absent, yellowish, papillose.  Spores 8–12 µm, verruculose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Shallow crevices and cavities on basalt cliffs;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations (60–1200 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">Greenland</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska.</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <discussion>The long, usually strongly decurrent awns and the campanulate capsules absent a distinct peristome separate  Schistidium cryptocarpum from other arctic species of the geunus.  Mogensen and Blom provided further details on this species.  It should be confused only with S. flaccidum, a more southern species, which differs in having a mamillate rostrum and a cupulate capsule.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
