<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Schistidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Lindberg ex Brotherus) G. Roth" date="unknown">flexipile</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Eur. Laubm.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 563.  1904,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Schistidium;species flexipile;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lindberg ex Brotherus" date="unknown">flexipilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Soc. Sci. Fenn.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>19(12): 92.  1892</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species flexipilis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in compact tufts or mats, (yellow-) green or olivaceous.  Stems 1.3–3(–4) cm, central strand weak or absent.  Leaves usually curved, often falcate-secund, sometimes erect, imbricate when dry, narrowly ovate-lanceolate, keeled distally, 1.7–2.4 mm, 1-stratose to, rarely, 2-stratose in striae distally; margins usually recurved to apex, smooth, usually 2-stratose, sometimes 1-stratose or multistratose; apices acute or sub-obtuse; costa percurrent or excurrent as a smooth or weakly denticulate, usually non-decurrent, flexuose awn, sometimes embracing part of the lamina, smooth; basal marginal cells quadrate or short-rectangular; distal laminal cells quadrate or short-rectangular, 8–10 µm wide, smooth, sinuose.  Sexual condition autoicous.  Capsule orange-brown or red-brown, short-cylindric to cylindric, 0.8–1.3 mm; exothecial cells usually a mix of isodiametric, short-elongate, and oblate cells, thin-walled, walls often curved, usually trigonous; stomata present; peristome recurved to squarrose-recurved, sometimes twisted, 260–430 µm, orange or reddish orange, weakly papillose, usually strongly perforated.  Spores 11–17 µm, granulose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Dry to seasonally moist rocks and ledges;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations (0–500 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">Greenland</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Eurasia.</description>
  <number>13.</number>
  <discussion>The falcate, often distally secund leaves as well as the green color readily characterize Schistidium flexipile.  Its short, narrow, and smooth-margined leaves also help to distinguish is from the closely related S. apocarpum.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
