<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>15.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Schistidium</genus_name>
    <species_name>frisvollianum</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. H. Blom</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryophyt. Biblioth.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>49: 87, fig. 25.  1996,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants in cushions or tufts, orange-brown or olivaceous.  Stems 0.5–2(–3.5) cm, central strand distinct.  Leaves erect or slightly curved when dry, ovate-lanceolate to ovate-triangular, sharply keeled distally, 1.3–2.4 mm, 1-stratose; margins usually recurved to apex, often sharply denticulate distally, 1-stratose or 2-stratose; apices acute; costa excurrent as a coarsely denticulate, usually decurrent, straight or flexuose awn, rarely percurrent, abaxial surface of the awn usually papillose; basal marginal cells rectangular, quadrate, or ovate; distal laminal cells quadrate or short-rectangular, 8–11 µm wide, papillose, strongly sinuose often with pale yellowish walls.  Sexual condition autoicous.  Capsule orange-brown or yellow when old, sometimes red-brown, ovoid-cylindric, 0.65–1.1 mm, occasionally striate; exothecial cells isodiametric or oblate, often somewhat angular, thin-walled; stomata present; peristome patent revolute, 220–330 µm, red, densely papillose, usually weakly perforated.  Spores 8–11 µm, granulose or nearly smooth.</description>
  <phenology>Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</phenology>
  <habitat>Fissures, limestone and dolomites in Arctic fellfields, polygon fields, and on dry ridges in tundra;</habitat>
  <elevation>low to moderate elevations (0–300 m);</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nunavut</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Eurasia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Schistidium frisvollianum is the most ornamented species of the genus in the flora area.  Its strongly papillose lamina, decurrent and usually spiny-denticulate awns, and denticulate leaf margins combine with its distinctive orange-brown color to make it an easily recognizable taxon.  See the comments under 5. Schistidium boreale regarding differences among the North American species of Schistidium with papillose laminal cells.</discussion>
</treatment>
