<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">grimmiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Schistidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="H. H. Blom" date="unknown">grandirete</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryophyt. Biblioth.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>49: 50, fig. 7.  1996,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grimmiaceae; genus Schistidium;species grandirete;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in open, occasionally compact tufts, yellow-brown or dull red, often with yellowish or olivaceous tones.  Stems 1.2–7 cm, central strand weak or absent.  Leaves erect or slightly curved when dry, ovate-lanceolate, occa-sionally linear-lanceolate, keeled distally, 1.7–2.6 mm, 1-stratose; margins usually recurved to apex, smooth or weakly toothed, 2-stratose or 1-stratose in spots; apices acute; costa percurrent or short-excurrent as a smooth or weakly denticulate, occasionally decurrent awn, abaxial surface sometimes papillose; basal marginal cells short-rectangular or quadrate; distal cells mostly short-rectangular, 11–14 µm wide, strongly sinuose.  Sexual condition autoicous.  Capsule orange- or red-brown, short-cylindric or cupulate, 0.7–1.1 mm; exothecial cells usually isodiametric, quadrate or irregularly angular, usually mixed with a few elongate cells, thin-walled, trigonous; stomata present or absent; peristome patent to squarrose-recurved, often twisted, 330–530 µm, bright red, papillose, usually strongly perforated.  Spores 15–21 µm, granulose or verruculose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Rocks and on moist mineral soil;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations (0–600 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">Greenland</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Eurasia.</description>
  <number>16.</number>
  <discussion>Schistidium grandirete is an arctic species characterized by a distinctive orange-brown or dull red color and large laminal cells.  Differences between S. grandirete and the  similar arctic species 18. S. holmenianum are discussed thereunder.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
