<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>20.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Schistidium</genus_name><species_name>maritimum</species_name><species_authority>(Turner ex Robt. Scott) Bruch &amp; Schimper</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Bryol. Europ. </publication_title><place_in_publication>3: 102.  1845,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Grimmia</genus_name><species_name>maritima</species_name><species_authority>Turner ex Robt. Scott</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Trans. Dublin Soc. </publication_title><place_in_publication>3: 158, plate 1.  1803</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Schistidium</genus_name><species_name>maritimum</species_name><subspecies_name>piliferum</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(I. Hagen) B. Bremer</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants in tufts, olivaceous, often brownish.  Stems 0.8–5 cm, central strand absent.  Leaves usually curved, sometimes erect, often somewhat contorted when dry, ovate-lanceolate to linear-lanceolate, keeled, (1.2–)1.5–2.6(–4) mm, usually 2-stratose distally; margins usually plane distally, recurved proximally, smooth or papillose, 2-stratose or 3-stratose, rarely 4-stratose distally; apices acute or blunt, sometimes ending in a short, fleshy, multistratose apiculus; costa percurrent, rarely excurrent as a short denticulate awn, with guide cells and one or two stereid bands, abaxial surface usually slightly papillose; basal marginal cells quadrate or short-rectangular, often trigonous; distal laminal cells isodiametric, rounded or angular, sometimes short-rectangular, 7–11 µm wide, smooth or weakly papillose, sometimes weakly bulging-mammillose, straight or slightly sinuose.  Sexual condition autoicous.  Capsule dark reddish brown or dark brown, ovoid, cupulate, or campanulate, 0.6–1.3 mm; exothecial cells usually angular, isodiametric, occasionally elongate, thick-walled; stomata present; peristome patent to revolute, 200–500 µm, red, papillose, often strongly perforated.  Spores 15–30 µm, granulose.</description><phenology>Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</phenology><habitat>  Rocks within or near the spray zone along coasts;</habitat><elevation> low elevations (0–20 m);</elevation><global_distribution> Greenland</global_distribution><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.B.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.S.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> P.E.I.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Que.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Alaska</us_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Maine</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mass</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia.</global_distribution><discussion>Schistidium maritimum is one of the easiest species of the genus to identify.  Its usually 2-stratose distal laminae, well developed stereid bands, usually small and often campanulate capsules, and coastal habitat are distinctive.  Subspecies piliferum, characterized by the presence of awns and a single stereid layer, is not recognized here; further study is needed.</discussion></treatment>
