<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>25.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Schistidium</genus_name><species_name>robustum</species_name><species_authority>(Nees &amp; Hornschuch) H. H. Blom</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Bryophyt. Biblioth. </publication_title><place_in_publication>49: 149.  1996,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Grimmia</genus_name><species_name>robusta</species_name><species_authority>Nees &amp; Hornschuch</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in C. G. D. Nees et al., Bryol. Germ. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2(1): 123, plate 20, fig. 9.  1827</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants in open to compact tufts, olivaceous, sometimes brownish or yellowish.  Stems 1–5 cm, central strand distinct.  Leaves erect or curved when dry, narrowly ovate-lanceolate to ovate-lanceolate, sharply keeled distally, 1.6–3 mm, 1-stratose, rarely with 2-stratose striae distally; margins recurved to near apex, smooth, 1- or 2-stratose; apices acute, rarely somewhat obtuse; costa usually long-excurrent as a spinulose-denticulate, usually decurrent awn, rarely percurrent, smooth; basal marginal cells quadrate or oblate, trigonous; distal laminal cells short-rectangular, occasionally isodiametric, 8–11 µm wide, strongly sinuose.  Sexual condition autoicous.  Capsule light brown or red-brown, cylindric to elongate-cylindric, (0.8–)1–1.6 mm, sometimes striated; exothecial cells mostly irregularly shaped, mainly elongate, with numerous isodiametric and, sometimes, a few oblate cells, walls thin-walled to unevenly thickened and somewhat curved, usually trigonous; stomata present; peristome patent to squarrose, sometimes twisted, 300–430 µm, red or orange-red, densely papillose, entire or weakly perforated.  Spores 8–11 µm, nearly smooth.</description><phenology>Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</phenology><habitat>  Dry to periodically moist calcareous rock;</habitat><elevation> moderate to high elevations (400–2100 m);</elevation><ca_distribution> Alta.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.W.T.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Que.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Yukon</ca_distribution><us_distribution> N.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Europe.</global_distribution><discussion>The long, spinulose-denticulate and decurrent awns, strongly sinuose laminal cells, and brown or red-brown, cylindrical capsules with primarily elongate exothecial cells are characteristic features of Schistidium robustum.</discussion></treatment>
