<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>29.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Schistidium</genus_name>
    <species_name>trichodon</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Bridel) Poelt</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Svensk Bot. Tidskr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>47: 253. 1953,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Grimmia</genus_name>
    <species_name>trichodon</species_name>
    <species_authority>Bridel</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Univ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 171. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants in open tufts or extensive mats, black, dark olivaceous, or
        brownish-olivaceous. Stems 1.8–12 cm, central strand weak or absent. Leaves usually somewhat
        curved, rarely secund, ovate-lanceolate, sharply keeled distally, 1.7–2.7 mm, 1-stratose;
        margins usually recurved throughout and denticulate distally, 1-stratose or 2-stratose;
        apices acute; costa percurrent or excurrent as a short, denticulate, weakly decurrent awn,
        abaxial surface usually weakly papillose; basal marginal cells quadrate or
        short-rectangular, sometimes trigonous; distal laminal cells mostly short-rectangular, 8–10
        µm wide, usually trigonous, sinuose. Sexual condition autoicous. Capsule red-brown,
        cylindric to short-cylindric, rarely cupulate, 0.7–1.2 mm, sometimes ribbed when dry;
        columella persistent within capsule; exothecial cells mainly isodiametric, sometimes mixed
        with short-elongate cells, thin-walled, trigonous; stomata present; peristome erect or
        ascending, often twisted inwards and overlapping distally, forming a dome, 400–700 µm, red,
        finely papillose, rarely with a few narrow slits. Spores 9–13(–19) µm, granulose or nearly
        smooth.</description>
  <phenology>Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</phenology>
  <elevation>low to high elevations (0–3500 m);</elevation>
  <habitat>Usually on calcareous rock (collected once on acidic rock in Washington
        State)</habitat>
  <habitat>open to shaded habitats</habitat>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.B.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.S.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Colo.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Eurasia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>The habitat, almost always on calcareous rock, its black or dark olivaceous color,
        the lack of long awns, the long, often domed peristome, and the persistence of the columella
        within the capsule make Schistidium trichodon a distinctive species.</discussion>
</treatment>
