<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">grimmiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Brotherus in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="1902">grimmioideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="1845">schistidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="H. H. Blom" date="1996">venetum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryophyt. Biblioth.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>49: 192, fig. 76.  1996,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grimmiaceae;subfamily grimmioideae;genus schistidium;species venetum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in small or sometimes extensive tufts, olivaceous, often with a yellowish or brownish tinge.  Stems 1–3.8 cm, central strand distinct.  Leaves erect or curved, usually imbricate, ovate-lanceolate to ovate-triangular, broadly keeled distally, 1.2–1.7(–2) mm, 1-stratose with 2-stratose patches or evenly 2-stratose distally; margins recurved to near apex, smooth, usually 2-stratose, occasionally multistratose; apices acute or blunt; costa sub-percurrent or excurrent as a lightly denticulate, usually broad-based, and flexuose awn that often embraces a portion of the leaf apex, smooth; basal marginal cells quadrate or short-rectangular; distal laminal cells ovate or short-rectangular, 6–10 µm wide, sinuose, trigonous.  Sexual condition autoicous.  Capsule red- or orange-brown, short-cylindric, 0.8–1.1(–1.3) mm; exothecial cells mostly elongate, mixed with isodiametric and a few oblate cells, thin-walled, sometimes trigonous; stomata present; peristome patent to recurved, sometimes twisted, 270–440 µm, bright red or orange, densely papillose, strongly perforated with uneven margins.  Spores 8–12 µm, granulose or nearly smooth.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature late spring to early summer.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wet ground of arctic fens, tundra, and drainage channels;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low elevations (0–100 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">Greenland</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe.</description>
  <number>30.</number>
  <discussion>Schistidium venetum is a distinctive, rather small species characterized by patchy or completely 2-stratose distal laminae, a lightly denticulate and usually broad-based awn that frequently embraces the upper portions of the lamina, and strongly perforated, uneven-sided peristome teeth.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
