<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Grimmia</genus_name><species_name>plagiopodia</species_name><species_authority>Hedwig</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Musc. Frond., </publication_title><place_in_publication>78, plate 15,  figs. 6–13.  1801,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Grimmia</genus_name><species_name>brandegeei</species_name><species_authority>Austin</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants in dense cushions to hoary tufts, dark green to brown.  Stems 0.3–0.5(–1) cm.  Leaves oblong-ovate, 1–1.7 × 0.4–0.8 mm, concave-keeled, awn 0.3–1 mm; basal juxtacostal laminal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, straight, thin-walled; basal marginal laminal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, straight, thin-walled; medial laminal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, slightly sinuose, slightly thick-walled; distal laminal cells 1-stratose, marginal cells 1–2-stratose.  Sexual condition gonioautoicous.  Seta sigmoid, 0.2–0.3 mm.  Capsule usually present, exothecial cells thin-walled, annulus absent, operculum mammillate, peristome present, fully developed, perforated and split in distal half.</description><habitat>Exposed calcareous sandstone, limestone, occasionally concrete, and glacio-lacustrine silt;</habitat><elevation> low to high elevations (50–2400 m);</elevation><global_distribution> Greenland</global_distribution><ca_distribution> Alta.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.W.T.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Nunavut</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Sask.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Alaska</us_distribution><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Colo.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ill.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Iowa</us_distribution><us_distribution> Minn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mont.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Nebr.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.Dak.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Utah</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wis.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wyo.</us_distribution><global_distribution> South America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia</global_distribution><us_distribution> Pacific Islands (New Zealand)</us_distribution><global_distribution> Antarctic.</global_distribution><discussion>Grimmia plagiopodia has a widespread and continuous distribution on calcareous rock across the northern Great Plains, reaching as far east as Illinois.  It is rare in eastern North America, with a disjunct site in southern Ontario.  In the west it reaches into the mountains on limestone and basic sandstone deposits, but its continuous range does not extend west of a line from Utah to south-central British Columbia.  There is a disjunct location near Carson City, Nevada and Lake Tahoe, California.  In the Arctic it is known from a few scattered localities extending from northwestern Greenland and nearby Ellesmere Island to the North Slope of Alaska.  Compared to G. anodon, G. plagiopodia tends to occupy more prairie-like sites and is typically found at lower elevations.  Commonly fertile, it is recognized by its immersed, peristomate capsule on a sigmoid seta with fully-developed teeth that are perforated and split distally.  Grimmia americana is similar but has a short, straight to arcuate seta and a large annulus.  The other widespread species in the group, G. anodon, has an annulus and is gymnostomous.</discussion></treatment>
