<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kaulfuss" date="unknown">elongata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Sturm et al., Deutschl. Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(15): plate 14.  1816,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species elongata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dryptodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Kaulfuss) Hartman" date="unknown">elongatus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dryptodon;species elongatus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>9.</number>
  <discussion>Grimmia elongata is a widely distributed species mainly occurring above 2000 m, and with a preference for acidic sandstones and volcanic, damp, north-facing outcrops and ledges.  It seems to be uncommon in North America, having been collected only occasionally and from widely separated localities.  However, the wide distribution of G. elongata across the Northern Hemisphere suggests that it may be more common on this continent than collection records indicate.  Cao T. and D. H. Vitt (1986b) noted that in North America, specimens of G. elongata would be confused most likely with G. donniana, as they considered the two species to be closely related.  However, these species are distinctly different in a number of clear characters: G. elongata is reddish brown, muticous or short-awned, has one leaf margin recurved and is dioicous.  In contrast, G. donniana is green to black, long-awned, has plane leaf margins and is autoicous.  These characters lead us to believe that these species are not closely related; H. C. Greven (2003) believed that G. elongata is most closely related to the Himalayan endemic G. redunca Mitten.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
