<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="P. Beauvois" date="unknown">pilifera</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Prodr. Aethéogam.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>58.  1805,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species pilifera;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">pensylvanica</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species pensylvanica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>16.</number>
  <discussion>Grimmia pilifera is most commonly found in the Appalachian Mountains from Nova Scotia to New York and south to northern Georgia and Alabama.  It extends into the Midwest on the Ozark Plateau northward to southern Illinois and Indiana.  It is rare in western North America, being found in mountainous areas in southeastern Arizona to the Rocky Mountain Front Ranges of New Mexico and Colorado, with disjunct sites in Montana, western South Dakota, and Minnesota.  It occupies a broader range of habitats than does either G. longirostris or G. arizonae in that it is common on limestone and sandstone, as well as granites, in shaded as well as exposed sites, and at much lower elevations throughout much of its range, while still reaching the alpine in Colorado.  Grimmia pilifera is most closely related to a group that includes G. longirostris and G. arizonae.  Its lack of a central strand, and its leaves with a small, well-defined ovate base recurved on both margins, which are also distinctly thick, will separate it from G. arizonae.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
