<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Müller Hal. &amp; Kindberg) Kindberg" date="unknown">attenuata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Eur. N. Amer. Bryin.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 228.  1898,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species attenuata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Müller Hal. &amp; Kindberg" date="unknown">alternuatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Macoun and N. C. Kindberg, Cat. Canad. Pl., Musci,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>73.  1892</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;species alternuatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>27.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Grimmia attenuata resembles forms of the extremely variable Racomitrium heterostichum (= Bucklandiella heterosticha), and because G. N. Jones (1933) mentioned five varieties of the latter, it is not surprising that in some herbaria, e.g. NY, all specimens of G. attenuata have been filed as varieties of R. heterostichum.  In 1898, Kindberg realized that his species is not a Racomitrium, but a Grimmia, and wrote: “Habit of G. elatior.”  In spite of Kindberg’s correct transfer to Grimmia, T. C. Frye (1917–1918) synonymized G. attenuata with R. macounii.  Adding to the confusion, H. A. Möller (1929) synonymized it with G. elatior, and J. Muñoz (1999b) cited it as G. arcuatifolia, which is a synonym of G. lisae.  Grimmia elatior is characterized by ellipsoid striate capsules, leaf margin broadly recurved on just one side, and an opaque 2-stratose distal lamina with rounded usually mammillose to papillose cells, the mid leaf cells quadrate to short-rectangular with slightly sinuose, thick walls.  Like Grimmia leibergii, G. attenuata is characterized by its elongate to linear, strongly nodulose and thick-walled basal juxtacostal cells, its extremely thick-walled and sinuouse medial cells, leaf margins both recurved, and stem central strand absent. However, the two differ in costa shape and basal marginal cell shape.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
