<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Paris" date="unknown">leibergii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Actes Soc. Linn. Bordeaux, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 9: 528.  1895,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species leibergii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="E. Ignatova" date="unknown">jacutica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>H. Bednarek-Ochyra, O. Afonina &amp; J. Muñoz</publication_title>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species jacutica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Leiberg" date="unknown">pachyphylla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species pachyphylla;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>33.</number>
  <discussion>Grimmia leibergii, formerly thought to be endemic to western North America, has the habit of Racomitrium heterostichum.  Nearly all specimens of G. leibergii in NY, and probably also in other North American herbaria, have been filed as varieties of R. heterostichum (= Bucklandiella heterosticha).  This confusion probably accounts for G. leibergii not being commonly recognized in North America.  J. B. Leiberg (1893) stated that it is most closely related to G. decipiens, a species that does not occur in North America.  Both taxa share broadly ovate-lanceolate leaves with both margins recurved, rectangular mid leaf cells with extremely thick and sinuose lateral walls and elongate to linear, nodulose, thick-walled basal juxtacostal cells.  However, G. decipiens is autoicous, it is a much smaller species, with long, sharply denticulate awns.  The gametophytes form comal tufts, so the distal leaves are 2–3 times longer than the lower leaves, and are not secund.  Grimmia jacutica has been described separately from eastern Asia and Alaska but all specimens of it that we have examined are just slightly smaller forms of G. leibergii with slightly more sinouse mid leaf cells.  The extension of G. leibergii into eastern Asia is a significant find and speaks to our poor knowledge of Grimmia distribution patterns on a worldwide basis.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
