<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">grimmiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greville" date="unknown">trichophylla</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Edin.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>235. 1824,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grimmiaceae; genus Grimmia;species trichophylla;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense to loose patches, yellowish green to dark green. Stems 2–4 cm,
        central strand present. Leaves loosely appressed, slightly twisted when dry, erecto-patent
        when moist, lanceolate to oblong-lanceolate, tapering to acute apex, 2–3.5 × 0.3–0.4 mm,
        usually sharply keeled, margins recurved on one or both sides, plane to erect distally, awns
        variable, short to long, smooth to denticulate, not conspicuously flattened at base, costa
        firm, projecting on abaxial side; basal juxtacostal laminal cells long-rectangular (rarely
        short-rectangular), ± nodulose, thick-walled; basal marginal laminal cells short- to
        long-rectangular, with thickened transverse walls; medial laminal cells quadrate to
        short-rectangular, slightly sinuose, thick-walled; distal laminal cells 1-stratose,
        occasionally with 2-stratose ridges. Gemmae clusters occasionally present in distal leaf
        axils. Sexual condition dioicous. Seta arcuate, 2–4 mm. Capsule occasionally present,
        exserted, oblong-ovoid, yellowish green to stramineous, striate when dry, exothecial cells
        thin-walled, annulus present, operculum rostrate, peristome teeth yellowish, papillose,
        deeply split and perforated. Calyptra mitrate.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Dry, acidic rock;</description>
  <description type="morphology">moderate to high elevations (200–2000 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Colo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Idaho</description>
  <description type="morphology">Maine</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nev.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Okla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="morphology">S.Dak.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Utah</description>
  <description type="morphology">Vt.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wyo</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico</description>
  <description type="morphology">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pacific Islands (Hawaii)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Australia.</description>
  <number>41.</number>
  <discussion>In North America, Grimmia trichophylla is principally a lowland species, occurring
        in the mountains up to about 1000 m., rarely higher. In the Southern Hemisphere, it may be
        found up to 4000 m. In New Zealand, the species is common, and in contrast to G.
        trichophylla in North America, frequently bears capsules. The New Zealand plants are usually
        smaller than American specimens, and the leaves are frequently contorted. The nearly
        cosmopolitan G. trichophylla has many phenotypes, and numerous subspecies and varieties have
        been described. In damp and shaded habitats, the awns may be short, just as in dry
        unfavorable habitats at high altitudes, where stunted specimens may occur with small, short
        leaves and reduced awns, or even with muticous leaves. Grimmia trichophylla has frequently
        been confused with related species such as 36. G. muehlenbeckii and 34. G. lisae (see
        discussions thereunder for identification details). Robust forms of G. trichophylla have
        been mistaken for G. austrofunalis (H. C. Greven 1997, 2003), which does not occur in North
        America. Although some of those plants have leaves of equal length along the stem,
        characteristic of G. austrofunalis, they also have both leaf margins recurved, and the
        medial and outer basal laminal cells are longer and more robust than in that
        species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
