<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. E. Andrus" date="unknown">atlanticum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>110: 274, figs.  2007,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species atlanticum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants robust and weak-stemmed; green, golden brown to dark brown; capitulum often flat-topped and with a visible terminal bud; flaccid and plumose in submerged forms to more compact in emergent or stranded forms.  Stems green to brown; superficial cortex of 1–2 layers of moderately thick-walled and poorly differentiated cells.  Stem leaves triangular, large, less than 1.7 mm, mostly appressed to stem, apex weakly apiculate to narrowly obtuse; hyaline cells efibrillose and seldom to often septate at base and sides.  Branches unranked, long and tapering, leaves greatly elongate at distal end.  Branch fascicles with 2 spreading and 2 pendent branches.  Branch stem green, cortex enlarged with conspicuous retort cells.  Branch leaves ovate-lanceolate to lanceolate in aquatic forms, ovate to ovate-lanceolate in emergent forms, greater than 2.5 mm, often falcate-secund, especially in submerged forms, weakly undulate and recurved when dry; margin entire, hyaline cells on convex surface with 0–1 pores per cell, concave surface with round wall thinnings in the cell apices and angles; chlorophyllous cells narrowly triangular in transverse section and well-enclosed on the concave surface.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Sporophytes not seen.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Forming loose carpets in pools in weakly minerotrophic fens;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.B.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.S.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Conn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Del.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Maine</description>
  <description type="morphology">Md.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mass.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.H.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.J.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pa.</description>
  <description type="morphology">R.I.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Vt.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Va.</description>
  <number>24.</number>
  <discussion>Sporophytes of Sphagnum atlanticum are rare.  The other large North American Atlantic coastal plain species of sect. Cuspidata, S. torreyanum, is typically more yellow, has a more rounded capitulum, and has straight rather than subsecund branch leaves.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
