<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>1.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Coscinodon</genus_name>
        <species_name>calyptratus</species_name>
        <species_authority>(Drummond) C. E. O. Jensen</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>in N. C. Kindberg, Eur. N. Amer. Bryin. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>2: 241. 1897,</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Grimmia</genus_name>
        <species_name>calyptrata</species_name>
        <species_authority>Drummond</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Musc. Amer., </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>60. 1828</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Coscinodon</genus_name>
        <species_name>hookeri</species_name>
        <species_authority>Hampe</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Grimmia</genus_name>
        <species_name>columbica</species_name>
        <species_authority>Kindberg</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Plants 7–10 mm, olivaceous. Leaves ovate to ovate-lanceolate, 1.4–2.4 × 0.4–0.7 mm,
        margins plane or one margin recurved at mid leaf, apex plane, awn 0.4–1.4 mm, lamina
        non-plicate; basal juxtacostal laminal cells long-rectangular, 15–80 × 7–10 µm, evenly
        thin-walled; basal marginal laminal cells quadrate to long-rectangular, 16–60 × 7–15 µm,
        thin or thick end walls and thin lateral walls; medial laminal cells 1-stratose; distal
        laminal cells 1-stratose. Sexual condition autoicous. Seta 1.4–2.4 mm. Capsule exserted,
        cylindric, commonly constricted at rim; peristome present, solid,
        xerocastique.</description>
    <habitat>Most common on dry sandstone and granitic boulders and bedrock exposures but also
        limestone and volcanic outcrops;</habitat>
    <elevation> moderate to high elevations (300–3000 m);</elevation>
    <ca_distribution> Alta.</ca_distribution>
    <ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Colo.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Idaho</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Minn.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Mont.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Nev.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> S.Dak.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Utah</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Wash.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Wis.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Wyo.</us_distribution>
    <discussion>Coscinodon calyptratus is common and widespread in the dry interior mountain areas
        of western North America. To the east it is largely bounded by the front ranges of the Rocky
        Mountains and acidic outliers such as the Black Hills of South Dakota. Two disjunct sites in
        Wisconsin and Minnesota define the eastward extent of the species. It is not found along the
        west coast mountains. Specimens from central Asia and New Zealand attributed to this North
        American endemic by J. Muñoz (1998c) instead represent an undescribed species of Coscinodon
        and a Grimmia. The non-plicate, 1-stratose leaves with plane or one revolute margin, and
        exserted capsule clearly separate this species from all other North American Coscinodon. The
        autoicous sexual condition is unique in the genus but often difficult to ascertain on any
        particular specimen. This species is more commonly confused with G. longirostris (formerly
        G. affinis) than with any other Coscinodon. Both species are autoicous, have a similar
        robust habit, have leaves that are strongly keeled and may have recurved margins, and have
        long-exserted capsules. If fertile and with capsules, the species are easily distinguished,
        as C. calyptratus has large, plicate calyptra and has a thin-walled filmy annulus. In
        contrast, G. longirostris has smaller, smooth calyptra and a large, prominent annulus.
        Gametophytically, C. calyptratus has 1-stratose areolation across the distal and medial
        lamina except for a 2-stratose margin. Its basal cells tend to be evenly thin-walled.
        Grimmia longirostris has a 2-stratose distal lamina and a wide 2-stratose margin at mid
        leaf. Its basal cells tend to be thicker walled.</discussion>
</treatment>
