<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>1.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Bucklandiella</genus_name>
    <species_name>microcarpa</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Hedwig) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>146. 2003,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Trichostomum</genus_name>
    <species_name>microcarpon</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hedwig</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>112, plate 23, figs. 8–12. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
    <species_name>canadense</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Michaux) Bridel</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
    <species_name>heterostichum</species_name>
    <variety_name>microcarpon</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Hedwig) Boulay</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
    <species_name>heterostichum</species_name>
    <variety_name>ramulosum</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Lindberg) G. N. Jones</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
    <species_name>microcarpon</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Hedwig) Bridel</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Trichostomum</genus_name>
    <species_name>canadense</species_name>
    <species_authority>Michaux</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants small to medium-sized, rarely fairly large, forming loose or dense tufts or
        mats, green, yellowish or olive green to light yellowish or sometimes grayish in the upper
        part, brown to blackish proximally, not or hoary. Stems prostrate to erect-ascending,
        (1–)2–4(–7) cm, copiously branched, mostly with short lateral, tuft-like subpinnate
        branchlets giving the plants a nodose appearance. Leaves loosely imbricate and often secund
        on drying, erect-spreading to recurved when moist, (1.5–)2–3.4(–3.8) × (0.4–)0.5–0.7(–0.8)
        mm, keeled in the distal part, narrowly canaliculate basally, piliferous or seldom epilose;
        hair-point erect, hyaline, capillaceus, flexuose, 0.3–0.7(–1.1) mm, not or slightly
        decurrent down the leaf margins; margins broadly recurved to revolute on one or both sides
        for 1/2–3/4 the leaf length, rarely to the apex, 1-stratose throughout, sometimes with
        2-stratose patches; costa percurrent, convex abaxially, (50–)60–80(–100) µm wide near the
        base, (35–)40–55 µm wide distally, 2–3-stratose basally with (2–)3–4(–5) markedly enlarged
        adaxial cells, 2–3-stratose in the middle with 2–3(–4) large adaxial cells and 2-stratose
        distally with (1–)2(–3) adaxial cells; laminal cells 1-stratose, smooth or often strongly
        pseudopapillose; distal and median cells strongly sinuose, rectangular, 20–30 × 9–10 µm,
        becoming shorter or oblate towards the margins; basal cells elongate to linear, 25–95 × 8–12
        µm, with strongly incrassate and porose walls; alar cells not or weakly differentiated;
        basal marginal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, rarely long-rectangular, esinuose or
        very seldom sinuose, hyaline or very rarely chlorophyllose, forming pellucid, 1(–2)-seriate
        border of (5–)10–20(–25) cells, very occasionally not transparent. Innermost perichaetial
        leaves (4–6), markedly modified, ovate, acuminate, epilose or very seldom piliferous,
        hyaline to yellowish hyaline in the proximal half, chlorophyllose in the distal half with
        strongly incrassate cell walls. Seta dark red to reddish brown, (2.5–)4.5–8 mm. Capsule
        obloid-cylindric to elongate-ovoid, (1.2–)1.5–2 × 0.3–0.6 mm, brown, dull to weakly
        lustrous; peristome teeth yellow-reddish, 310–350 µm, papillose, irregularly divided nearly
        to the base into 2 prongs, sometimes only with elongate perforations, without or with a low
        basal membrane, 10–15 µm high. Operculum conical-rostrate, to 1 mm, with a straight or
        slanted beak. Spores (10–)12–14(–16) µm.</description>
  <habitat>Acidic rocks, boulders and cliffs, as well as on soil or gravel, often in late snow
        areas, on stony mossy tundra, stony slopes and granite rock underhangs on talus slopes,
        mostly in exposed, dry or moist sites;</habitat>
  <elevation>low to high elevations (0–1700 m);</elevation>
  <global_distribution>Greenland</global_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.B.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.S.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Minn.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.H.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.J.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Vt.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>arctic</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>temperate Asia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Bucklandiella microcarpa is a temperate moss, occasionally penetrating into the
        Arctic. It has a bicentric distribution in North America, being most common and widespread
        in the eastern part of the continent and less frequent in the west, where it occurs mostly
        in the Rocky Mountains from the Yukon to Montana. It is principally a Euro-American species,
        with some scattered records in Siberia. In Europe it shows distinct continental tendencies
        and is absent from the oceanic western part, including the British Isles.</discussion>
  <discussion>Bucklandiella microcarpa is an unmistakable species that is at once distinct from
        other North American congeners by its long, pellucid basal marginal border of esinuose cells
        and markedly modified innermost perichaetial leaves, with chlorophyllose distal cells having
        strongly incrassate walls and basal laminal cells that are esinuose and have porose and
        prominently thickened lateral walls. Also, it is worth noting that the laminal cells are
        usually pseudopapillose in B. microcarpa and the pseudopapillosity is especially pronounced
        in the western North American populations.</discussion>
  <discussion>Bucklandiella microcarpa resembles B. affinis, B. heterosticha, B. sudetica, and B.
        venusta in leaf shape and in having pilose leaves. The first two species are also similar in
        having typically 1-stratose leaf margins. In addition to their less well developed or absent
        basal marginal border, these species differ from B. microcarpa in having broader costae:
        80–100 µm versus 60–80 µm in the proximal portion. Bucklandiella sudetica and B. venusta
        also differ from B. microcarpa in having regularly 2-stratose leaf margins. In Alaska, B.
        microcarpa is likely to be mistaken with Dryptodon jacuticus (= Grimmia leibergii), which
        has long-pilose leaves and similar costal anatomy, with 3–4 much enlarged adaxial cells.
        However, D. jacuticus has 2-stratose leaf margins and subquadrate to short-rectangular
        laminal cells in the distal part, straight or only slightly flexuose hair-points, and
        undifferentiated basal marginal cells.</discussion>
</treatment>
