<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bucklandiella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra" date="unknown">heterosticha</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>145.  2003,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Bucklandiella;species heterosticha;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Trichostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">heterostichum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>109.  1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Trichostomum;species heterostichum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Dickson" date="unknown">heterostichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Bryum;species heterostichum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Müller Hal." date="unknown">heterosticha</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species heterosticha;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Bridel" date="unknown">heterostichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;species heterostichum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>4.</number>
  <discussion>Bucklandiella heterosticha is a core species of a complex of several more closely or remotely related taxa which have been interpreted variously in the past.  Consequently, depending on the taxonomic interpretation, the global range of this species has been variously defined.  As presently conceived, B. heterosticha is characterized by a combination of several stable characters, including strongly modified, entirely hyaline innermost perichaetial leaves; broad costa that is canaliculate throughout the adaxial side and moderately convex on the abaxial surface, with as many as 5–9 enlarged cells on the adaxial side in the basal part; sinuose-nodulose, moderately thick-walled basal leaf cells; undifferentiated alar cells and basal marginal border; 1-stratose leaf margins with occasional 2-stratose spots distally that are recurved to the apex, at least on one side, and long, erect, and weakly flexuose awns that are strongly flattened and low-denticulate and spinulose.  As so defined, B. heterosticha is confined to the Pacific Northwest, where it occurs throughout the Aleutian Islands, along the coastal regions southwards to Oregon, and to Montana in the Rocky Mountains.</discussion>
  <discussion>Bucklandiella heterosticha is closely related to and most likely to be mistaken for B. affinis, with which it shares its western North American range.  Although both species differ by their gross morphology, B. heterosticha being grayish green and B. affinis a more yellowish green, the safest characters discriminating these species are the costal anatomy.  Bucklandiella heterosticha has a canaliculate costa that is 2-stratose in the middle and in the lower distal part, whereas in B. affinis the costa is 3-stratose in the same portions and is more convex on the abaxial side.  Bucklandiella sudetica is different from B. heterosticha in its shorter capsules, narrower leaf with shorter awns, costal anatomy, and undifferentiated innermost perichaetial leaves.  Bucklandiella pacifica is distinct in its consistently epilose leaves and from muticous ecads of B. heterosticha in having distinctly keeled costa in the distal part.  Bucklandiella obesa is a strikingly more robust plant, less branched than B. heterosticha, and has both shorter awns and seta.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
