<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Lindberg) J. Röll" date="unknown">brevifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Centralbl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>39: 340.  1889,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species brevifolium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">cuspidatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Lindberg" date="unknown">brevifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Braithwaite, Sphagnac. Europe,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>84.  1878</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species cuspidatum;variety brevifolium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>26.</number>
  <discussion>Details of the distribution of Sphagnum brevifolium are unclear because of confusion with S. fallax and S. isoviitae.  This seems to be a species of poor to medium fens, where it occurs in depressions and floating mats; it does not appear to form extensive fast-growing mats as do S. fallax, S. isoviitae, and S. pacificum.  Sphagnum brevifolium is one of five species in the S. recurvum complex with apiculate stem leaves.  On the Pacific coast it seemingly co-occurs only with S. pacificum, from which it differs in having branch leaves less sharply recurved and more strongly 5-ranked.  In eastern North America it is quite uncommon but can occur with both S. fallax and S. isoviitae of S. recurvum, in the broad sense.  Sphagnum fallax has more sharply recurved branch leaves.  Sphagnum splendens has a distinct shiny look.  The much more common S. isoviitae has a distinctly flatter capitulum, narrower branch leaves and wider stem leaves.  In fact, the relatively broad branch leaves of S. brevifolium sometimes can give it the appearance of a slender S. pulchrum, but the latter has much more strongly 5-ranked branch leaves and lacks paired pendent branch buds.  See also discussion under 22. S. angustifolium.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
