<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bucklandiella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Bednarek-Ochyra) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra" date="unknown">Lawtonia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>143.  2003 (as Lawtoniae),</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Bucklandiella;section Lawtonia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Bednarek-Ochyra" date="unknown">Lawtonia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fragm. Florist. Geobot. Ser. Polon.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 65.  1995</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;section Lawtonia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants fairly large to robust, coarse and rigid, yellowish, olivaceous or brownish in the upper part.  Stems often more than 10 cm long.  Leaves lanceolate; margins recurved on both sides to 1/3–1/2(–3/4) of the leaf length, 1-stratose; long pilose, awns erect-recurved to squarrose, flattened, distantly sharply denticulate at the margins, distinctly decurrent; costa predominantly 3-stratose basally; alar cells undifferentiated; basal marginal border absent or present.  Inner perichaetial leaves strongly modified, yellowish hyaline, chlorophyllose distally, sometimes with a short hyaline hair-point.  Capsule peristome teeth without a basal membrane.</description>
  <description type="morphology">nw North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">e Asia (China, Japan, Korea, Russian Far East).</description>
  <number>6c.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The strongly modified innermost perichaetial bracts with thick-walled, chlorophyllose distal portion and sometimes also with a short hyaline hair-point, as well as not flexuose and distinctly erect-recurved to squarrose hyaline leaf hair-points are diagnostic for sect. Lawtonia.  Apart from Bucklandiella lawtoniae, it contains only B. laeta, a closely related East Asian counterpart of the American species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
