<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">grimmiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra in R. Ochyra et al." date="2003">racomitrioideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Roivainen" date="1972">bucklandiella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Bednarek-Ochyra) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra in R. Ochyra et al." date="2003">lawtonia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Ireland) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra in R. Ochyra et al." date="2003">lawtoniae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>145.  2003 (as lawtonae),</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grimmiaceae;subfamily racomitrioideae;genus bucklandiella;section lawtonia;species lawtoniae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ireland" date="unknown">lawtoniae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>73: 707, figs. 1–12.  1971 (as lawtonae)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;species lawtoniae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants rather robust or less often moderately sized, loosely tufted, coarse and rigid, slightly glist-ening, yellow, yellow-green, olivaceous, sometimes grayish, in the upper part, brown proximally.  Stems 5–10(–15) cm, curved-ascending to erect, simple or sparingly, irregularly branched.  Leaves erect-appressed to falcate-secund when dry, erect-spreading when wet, straight or curved, sometimes almost circinate, (3.5–)4–5.5(–6) × (0.5–)0.6–0.8(–0.9) mm; margins broadly recurved on one side and more narrowly on the other side to 1/3–1/2(–3/4) of the leaf length, 1-stratose throughout or seldom with some bistratose patches distally; pilose, awns hyaline, not flexuose, erect-recurved to squarrose, 0.4–1.5(–2.6) mm, rarely almost absent, flattened, with a distinct cell areolation, remotely sharply denticulate at the margins, distinctly decurrent; costa percurrent, strongly convex abaxially, reniform in the median and proximal portions, 75–100(–115) µm wide basally, 40–50 µm wide distally, 3(–5)-stratose basally with (3–)4–5 enlarged adaxial cells, 2(–3)-stratose distally, with 2–3(–4) enlarged adaxial cells; laminal cells 1-stratose throughout, smooth; basal laminal cells elongate, 25–55 × 9–11 µm, with incrassate, sinuose-nodulose lateral walls; alar cells not or slightly differentiated, sometimes slightly yellowish; supra-alar cells hardly differentiated, not forming a distinct basal marginal border; medial and distal cells rectangular, 12–35 × 5–7 µm.  Inner perichaetial leaves (2–3) broadly ovate, convolute, yellowish haline, shortly obtusely pointed or pilose, with thick-walled, chlorophyllose distal cells.  Seta 4.5–7.5 mm, straight, brown, twisted clockwise.  Capsule obloid to short-cylindric, (1.2–)1.5–2.5 × 0.6–0.8 mm; operculum rostrate, straight, 1–1.5 mm; peristome teeth 250–480 µm, brown, deeply cleft into to branches, strongly papillose, erect.  Spores 12–17 µm, granulose.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Humid or wet, mostly shaded acidic rocks, boulders, cliffs and rock outcrops near streams and waterfalls;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations (0-800 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.; Alaska, Wash.</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>Bucklandiella lawtoniae occurs along the coastal region from Kodiak Island and southern Alaska southwards to the Cascade Range in central Washington, with a highly isolated site on Attu Island in the Aleutians.  The largest species of the genus, it can be recognized by its characteristic, long and not flexuose, erect-recurved to squarrose, hyaline awns that are distinctly decurrent.  Some elongate and pilose plants of B. affinis may imitate B. lawtoniae but that species, apart from a number of differences in structural characters including the hyaline innermost perichaetial leaves, has erect-flexuose awns and leaf margins recurved on both sides towards the apex.  The same differences exist between B. lawtoniae and B. heterosticha, in which, additionally, the costa is usually broad, 2-stratose, and canaliculate in the middle and distal parts of the leaf.  Additional diagnostic characters of B. lawtoniae are undifferentiated alar cells and the absence of both a basal marginal border and a basal membrane in the peristome.  The species appears to be strongly isolated in the genus and on account of its peculiar innermost perichaetial leaves it is positioned in a separate section.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ireland, R. R.  1976.  Alar cells of Rhacomitrium lawtonae.  Bryologist 79: 238–241.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
