<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bucklandiella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Ireland) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra" date="unknown">lawtoniae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>145.  2003 (as lawtonae),</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Bucklandiella;species lawtoniae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ireland" date="unknown">lawtoniae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>73: 707, figs. 1–12.  1971 (as lawtonae)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;species lawtoniae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>Bucklandiella lawtoniae occurs along the coastal region from Kodiak Island and southern Alaska southwards to the Cascade Range in central Washington, with a highly isolated site on Attu Island in the Aleutians.  The largest species of the genus, it can be recognized by its characteristic, long and not flexuose, erect-recurved to squarrose, hyaline awns that are distinctly decurrent.  Some elongate and pilose plants of B. affinis may imitate B. lawtoniae but that species, apart from a number of differences in structural characters including the hyaline innermost perichaetial leaves, has erect-flexuose awns and leaf margins recurved on both sides towards the apex.  The same differences exist between B. lawtoniae and B. heterosticha, in which, additionally, the costa is usually broad, 2-stratose, and canaliculate in the middle and distal parts of the leaf.  Additional diagnostic characters of B. lawtoniae are undifferentiated alar cells and the absence of both a basal marginal border and a basal membrane in the peristome.  The species appears to be strongly isolated in the genus and on account of its peculiar innermost perichaetial leaves it is positioned in a separate section.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ireland, R. R.  1976.  Alar cells of Rhacomitrium lawtonae.  Bryologist 79: 238–241.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
