<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>10.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Bucklandiella</genus_name>
        <species_name>macounii</species_name>
        <species_authority>(Kindberg in Macoun) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses</publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>146. 2003,</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
        <species_name>brevipes</species_name>
        <species_authority>Kindberg</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>16: 93. 1889</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
        <species_name>heterostichum</species_name>
        <variety_name>macounii</variety_name>
        <variety_authority>(Kindberg) G. N. Jones</variety_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
        <species_name>robustifolium</species_name>
        <species_authority>Kindberg</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Plants medium-sized to moder-ately robust, rigid, in dense or loose tufts or
        patches, reddish green, reddish brown, brown or olivaceous at the apices, reddish brown to
        blackish proximally. Stems 3.5–6(–13) cm, ascending to erect or prostrate, simple or
        sparsely branched. Leaves erect-appressed, straight to distinctly contorted when dry,
        erect-patent to spreading when moist, narrowly lanceolate, (1.5–)2.2–3(–3.2) × (0.3–)0.5–0.8
        mm; margins broadly or narrowly recurved to 1/2–2/3 of the leaf length on one side, plane or
        faintly recurved in the broadest part of the leaf on the other side, strongly thickened and
        bulging, 2(–4)-stratose in (1–)2–3(–6) cell rows distally, 2-stratose in 1–3(–4) cell rows
        in the median and upper basal parts and 1-stratose close the base; apices gradually tapering
        at an attenuate point, muticous or piliferous, awns short, to 0.2 mm, terete, reddish or
        yellowish hyaline, erect to recurved when dry, strongly spinulose, not decurrent; costa
        percurrent, robust, strongly convex abaxially and rounded to elliptical in outline,
        60-100(–150) µm wide basally, 40–70 µm wide near the apex, (3–)4(–5)-stratose with 3–6
        larger adaxial cells in the basal part, 3–4-stratose with 3–5(–6) adaxial cells in the
        middle and (2–)3–4-stratose with 2–4 adaxial cells in the distal part; laminal cells
        1-stratose with 2-stratose streaks, smooth or moderately papillose; basal laminal cells
        rectangular, 25–55 × 8–9 µm, with sinuose-nodulose, thick walls; alar cells
        undifferentiated; basal marginal cells absent or more or less distinct, composed of 15-40
        short, transparent, not or moderately sinuose cells; medial and distal laminal cells
        irregularly isodiametric to short-rectangular or oblate near the margins, 5–25 × 8–9 µm.
        Inner perichaetial leaves ovate-lanceolate, without or with a very short hair-point, not or
        weakly differentiated. Seta brown, 4–7 mm. Capsule brown, slightly glistening,
        obloid-cylindric, 1–1.9 × 0.5–0.8 mm; operculum stout, convex-conical to shortly rostrate;
        peristome teeth lanceolate, 330–450 µm, reddish or orange-brown, densely spiculate
        papillose, variously split into 1–3 prongs, perforated or undivided, arising from a fairly
        short basal membrane, 35–50 µm high. Spores 12–14 µm.</description>
    <number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
    <global_distribution> North America</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution> Eurasia.</global_distribution>
    <discussion>Bucklandiella macounii is a prominent species that is diagnosed by its regularly
        2-stratose or sometimes in places 3–4-stratose leaf margins in 2–4 or even as many as six
        cell rows forming bulging thickenings, very short, to 0.2 mm, stout, terete, strongly
        spinulose and recurved, subhyaline or hyaline awns, as well as very strong costae that are
        strongly convex, rounded to elliptical in outline on the abaxial side, 4-stratose in the
        basal and median parts, and plants typically reddish tinged. The species is most similar to
        the highly variable B. sudetica, especially to plants designated as forma kindbergii; the
        differences between these taxa are discussed under 12. B. sudetica.</discussion>
    <key>
        <key_statement>
            <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
            <statement>Plants usually dull and olivaceous; leaves contorted when dry; muticous or
                awns less than 0.1 mm long; distal laminal cells predominantly oblate and quadrate;
                costa 80–100(–150) µm wide basally subsp. macounii</statement>
            <determination>10a. Bucklandiella macounii subsp. macounii</determination>
        </key_statement>
        <key_statement>
            <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
            <statement>Plants usually lustrous and reddish; leaves erect-imbricate, awns present,
                usually longer, to 0.2 mm; distal laminal cells predominantly quadrate to
                short-rectangular; costa 60–85 µm wide basally subsp. alpina</statement>
            <determination>10b. Bucklandiella macounii subsp. alpina</determination>
        </key_statement>
    </key>
</treatment>
