<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ryszard Ochyra,Halina Bednarek-Ochyra</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Bednarek-Ochyra) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra" date="unknown">NIPHOTRICHUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>137.  2003 ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus NIPHOTRICHUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek nipha, snow, and trichos, hair, alluding to hoary appearance owing to hyaline hair-pointed leaves]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Bednarek-Ochyra" date="unknown">Niphotrichum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fragm. Florist. Geobot., Ser. Polon.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 70.  1995</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;subgenus Niphotrichum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>7.</number>
  <discussion>Species 8 (6 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Niphotrichum comprises species from the traditionally conceived genus Racomitrium centered around R. canescens.  It is characterized by strongly papillose laminal cells with tall conical papillae that are situated over the lumina.  This type of papillosity is common, for example, in the Pottiaceae but is unique in the Grimmiaceae.  This exceptional diagnostic character is coupled with very long peristome teeth that are regularly cleft to the base into 2–3 filiform segments, and hyaline or yellowish hyaline and thin-walled alar cells that form convex and often decurrent auricles.  Moreover, species of this genus possess massive, papillose, and denticulate awns; costae forked or branched at the tip, ending at mid leaf or extending to the leaf apex; triangular, elliptic, or broadly ovate-lanceolate leaves; innermost perichaetial leaves hyaline, sheathing, and sometimes pilose; setae smooth, sinistrorse on drying; operculum with a subulate beak as long as the urn or longer; and capsules often plicate when dry.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves obtusely keeled to broadly canaliculate in the distal part, elliptical to broadly ovate-lanceolate; costa mostly distinctly branched, extending 1/2–3/4 of the way up the leaf; papillae tending to be relatively large and conspicuous in the distal part of the leaf lamina</description>
      <determination>7a.   Niphotrichum sect. Niphotrichum, p. 286</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves sharply keeled to narrowly canaliculate in the distal part, ovate-lanceolate to triangular; costa mostly unbranched, extending 3/4 of the way up the leaf to percurrent; papillae tending to be relatively small and inconspicuous in the distal part of the leaf lamina</description>
      <determination>7b.   Niphotrichum sect. Elongata, p. 289</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
