<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Niphotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Müller Hal.) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra" date="unknown">panschii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish  Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>138.  2003,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Niphotrichum;species panschii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Müller Hal." date="unknown">panschii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in K. Koldewey et al., Zweite Deutsche Nordpolarfahrt</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(1): 72.  1873</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species panschii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Niphotrichum panschii is fairly frequent in the high Arctic of Alaska, the Yukon Territory, and Nunavut, as well as in Greenland (except for the southernmost part), only occasionally southwards to latitude ca. 55º N in Labrador.  It is closely related to N. canescens, but the possibility of confusion with the typical subspecies of the latter is rather minimal since that is a temperate taxon and its range does not overlap that of N. panschii.  The taxa have a similar leaf shape, although N. panschii always has straight leaves that are not hyaline in the distal part and it is less robust than subsp. canescens.  Niphotrichum panschii is externally more similar to N. canescens subsp. latifolium, and they are more likely to be confused, especially because they often grow together.  However, they can be recognized by their awns, which in N. panschii are less papillose but more strongly spinulose and serrate at the apex, relatively short, less flexuose, and directed upwards.  In contrast, the awns of subsp. latifolium are strongly papillose throughout and only faintly serrulate, long, distinctly flexuose, and consequently spreading from the shoot.  The stems of N. panschii are sparingly branched to almost unbranched, and the branches are usually erect and fragile, whereas those of subsp. latifolium are more profusely branched, and the branches are non-fragile.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
