<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>7b.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Niphotrichum</genus_name>
    <section_name>Elongata</section_name>
    <section_authority>(Bednarek-Ochyra) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish  Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>138.  2003,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Racomitrium</genus_name>
    <section_name>Elongata</section_name>
    <section_authority>Bednarek-Ochyra</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fragm. Florist. Geobot., Ser. Polon.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 94.  1995</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants small, medium-sized to robust, green, olive or grayish green distally, brown.  Leaves ovate-lanceolate, lanceolate to triangular, sharply keeled to narrowly canaliculate in the distal part; costa in most leaves unbranched or only occasionally forked in some leaves, extending to three quarters of the leaf length to percurrent; leaf cell papillae tending to be relatively small and inconspicuous in the distal lamina.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 6 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>temperate Asia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Atlantic.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Section Elongata is fairly homogeneous.  Its members are readily recognized by their leaves, which are sharply keeled to narrowly canaliculate or canaliculate-keeled in the distal part, and their costae, which cease mostly at three quarters of the leaf length or are subpercurrent to percurrent and are generally undivided at the tip.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf margins recurved to 1/2–3/4 of the way up the leaf</statement>
      <determination>3.   Niphotrichum muticum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf margins recurved to the apex.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants small; leaves 1.5–1.8 mm long; costa not grooved; laminal cells opaque, coarsely papillose, yellowish; alar cells forming a small and weakly inflated group; awns absent papillae or only faintly papillose at the base</statement>
      <determination>4.   Niphotrichum pygmaeum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants medium-sized to large; leaves 2–3 mm long; costa lying in a shallow or deeper furrow; laminal cells coarsely to slightly papillose, mostly transparent, not yellowish (except the base); alar cells forming a conspicuous and distinctly inflated group; awns mostly coarsely papillose.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Supra-alar cells elongate, thin-walled and not sinuose, forming a transparent marginal border; awns erect-flexuose when dry, not or indistinctly decurrent, faintly papillose to epapillose in the distal part</statement>
      <determination>5.   Niphotrichum ericoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Supra-alar cells short, thick- and sinuose-walled, not forming a translucent border; awns recurved when dry, conspicuously decurrent, coarsely papillose throughout</statement>
      <determination>6.   Niphotrichum elongatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
