<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Niphotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Bridel) Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra" date="unknown">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in R. Ochyra et al., Cens. Cat. Polish Mosses,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>138. 2003,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Niphotrichum;species ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Trichostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(2): 290. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Trichostomum;species ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Bryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Bridel) Dickson" date="unknown">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Bryum;species ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grimmia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Müller Hal." date="unknown">canescens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Bridel) Müller Hal." date="unknown">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grimmia;species canescens;variety ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">brevipes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Bridel) Kindberg" date="unknown">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;species brevipes;variety ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Bridel) Bridel" date="unknown">canescens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Bridel) Hampe" date="unknown">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;species canescens;variety ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;species ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Trichostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">canescens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="unranked" date="unknown" authority="(Bridel) Hartman">ericoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Trichostomum;species canescens;unranked ericoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants moderately sized to fairly large, occasionally small, loosely or densely
        caespitose or forming extensive mats, yellow- or olive green, rarely dark green in the
        uppermost part, brown to blackish brown proximally. Stems (1–)3–8(–12) cm, prostrate to
        ascending, mostly pinnately branched, occasionally almost unbranched. Leaves appressed and
        slightly twisted when dry, erect-spreading to somewhat recurved when moist, ovate-lanceolate
        to subtriangular, 2–3 × 0.9–1.2 mm; margins broadly recurved to revolute throughout; apices
        gradually long-acuminate, sharply keeled, plicate, piliferous or not infrequently muticous,
        awns erect or sometimes reflexed-flexuose, capillaceous, slightly decurrent, weakly
        denticulate, slightly papillose to epapillose distally, slightly to strongly papillose in
        the basal part with low or sometimes high and narrow papillae; costa percurrent, lying at
        the bottom of a shallow and wide-angled furrow and strongly flattened in the basal part,
        (65–)75–100 µm wide; basal laminal cells elongate, 40–50 × 4–6 µm, with moderately
        thickened, nodulose and porose longitudinal walls, papillose with relatively low and narrow
        papillae, except for 1–4 epapillose cells at the insertion; alar cells rounded, thin-walled
        and hyaline in 3–5 rows, forming rounded and convex auricles; supra-alar cells elongate,
        with thin, straight or weakly sinuose walls, forming a transparent marginal border
        consisting of 10–15 cells; medial and distal laminal cells rectangular, 10–20 × 6–10 µm,
        papillose with relatively low and narrow papillae. Inner perichaetial leaves membranous,
        hyaline to yellowish hyaline, piliferous. Seta dark to reddish brown, lustrous, 12–15 mm.
        Capsule brown, long-cylindric, 1.5–2 mm, sulcate when dry; peristome teeth 600–800 µm,
        reddish brown to red, split to the base into 2 filiform branches, finely densely papillose.
        Spores 9–12 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Dry or intermittently moist sites that are generally shaded, less often open and
        insolated, sandy, gravelly or gritty soil, humus and soil over rocks, boulders and rock
        ledges, grassland, stony ground and roadside banks, floor in mesic to dry woodlands and
        forests, stabilized dunes and disturbed places, various tundra communities, predominantly
        non-calcareous substrates;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations (0–1600 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">Greenland</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.B.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.S.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Yukon</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Idaho</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mich.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pa.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wyo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Arctic and temperate Asia</description>
  <description type="morphology">Atlantic Island (Azores, Iceland).</description>
  <number>5.</number>
  <discussion>Niphotrichum ericoides is a fairly frequent species, with a bicentric distribution
        in North America. It is most common in the western part of the continent, from Alaska to
        northern California and in the Rocky Mountains of Idaho and Wyoming. In eastern North
        America it is less frequent, and scattered from northern Labrador south to Pennsylvania.
        Apart from N. panschii, it is the only species of the genus that penetrates into the high
        Arctic in Nunavut, the Yukon Territory, and Alaska. The global range of N. ericoides also
        includes arctic, boreal, and temperate Europe, southwards to the Azores; in Asia, it is very
        rare in the Arctic, Siberia, and Japan. The material reported from Santiago, Chile, as
        Racomitrium canescens (He S. 1998; Mahu 10543, MO) also represents N. ericoides, but that
        attribution is fairly suspicious and possibly a result of a confusion of herbarium
        labels.</discussion>
  <discussion>Niphotrichum ericoides has been considered to be very close to N. canescens and is
        usually recognized under the latter. However, the two taxa are not likely to be mistaken.
        The sharply keeled leaves in the distal portion, a percurrent costa, and the epapillose awns
        will safely discriminate N. ericoides. This species is more likely to be confused with N.
        elongatum, with which it often grows in mixed stands and shares the regularly pinnately
        branched habit with short, tuft-like lateral branchlets, which gives them both a nodose
        appearance. However, in N. ericoides the branchlets are erect-spreading when dry, whereas in
        N. elongatum they are recurved to squarrose at their apex. The awn in N. ericoides is
        erect-flexuose when dry, not or indistinctly decurrent, and often faintly denticulate to
        smooth. In contrast, the awns in N. elongatum are distinctly recurved, long-decurrent, and
        often sharply denticulate. Microscopically these species are easily separated by the shape
        of their supra-alar cells. In N. ericoides they are elongate and thin- and straight-walled,
        and form a distinct, transparent basal marginal border; in N. elongatum they are short,
        thick- and sinuose-walled, and opaque and not markedly different from the adjacent laminal
        cells.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
