<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Arnott" date="unknown">grimmiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Bednarek-Ochyra &amp; Ochyra in R. Ochyra et al." date="2003">racomitrioideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="P. Beauvois" date="1822">codriophorus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Codriophorus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grimmiaceae;subfamily racomitrioideae;genus codriophorus;section Codriophorus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Racomitrium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Chevallier" date="unknown">Papillosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Racomitrium;section Papillosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Trichostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Stenotrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Trichostomum;section Stenotrichum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stem sparingly or freely irregularly, dichotomously or fasciculately branched, sometimes filiform and almost unbranched, absent short, lateral tuft-like branchlets.  Leaves lingulate, elliptic, broadly ovate, ovate- or oblong-lanceolate to broadly or occasionally narrowly lanceolate; margins 1–2(–4)-stratose, recurved, reflexed, incurved or plane on both sides; apices narrowly to broadly rounded-obtuse or long acuminate to acute, muticous or very rarely shortly hyaline-tipped, entire or sharply to bluntly, remotely irregularly toothed, erose-dentate, sinuate to cristate in the upper 1/5–1/4; costa strong and broad, ceasing in mid leaf to subpercurrent, in transverse-section 2–4-stratose in the distal and medial parts, weakly to strongly convex, reniform, crescent-shaped to semi-terete abaxially, flat or convex on the adaxial side, in the basal part 3–6(–7)-layered, situated at the bottom of a shallow or deeper, usually wide-angled groove, lunate, reniform or rectangular and distinctly flattened, strongly convex on the abaxial side; basal marginal laminal cells not differentiated; distal laminal cells 1- to variously 2-stratose, irregularly rounded-quadrate, subquadrate, oval to rounded-hexagonal, strongly papillose to smooth, straight-walled in the distal part.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America (Colombia)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="morphology">n Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Atlantic Islands (Azores, Canary Islands, Iceland, Madeira).</description>
  <number>9a.</number>
  <discussion>Species 9 (6 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Members of sect. Codriophorus are recognized by their lingulate, broadly ovate to ovate- or oblong-lanceolate leaves, isodiametric and straight-walled distal laminal cells, and costa that is broad and robust, usually over 100 µm wide at the base.  The costa is situated in a shallow, wide-angled groove and is mostly 2–4-stratose in the distal and medial parts, 3–6(–7)-stratose in the basal part, and anatomically strongly differentiated.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal cells smooth or very slightly papillose on young leaves; leaf margins entire or with a few irregular teeth at the apex</description>
      <determination>5.   Codriophorus depressus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal cells distinctly papillose; leaf margins remotely irregularly toothed, erose-dentate, sinuate to cristate in the distal 1/5–1/4, if entire then broadly rounded-obtuse.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves lanceolate; apex irregularly bluntly erose-dentate; costa markedly convex and crescent-shaped abaxially</description>
      <determination>6.   Codriophorus ryszardii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves lingulate, elliptical to broadly ovate or ovate-lanceolate; apex broadly rounded-obtuse to acute, irregularly dentate to entire.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costa subpercurrent, entire and only shortly forked at the tip.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal cells strongly papillose, 1- or very rarely 2-stratose; leaves unbordered</description>
      <determination>1.   Codriophorus acicularis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal cells indistinctly papillose over the cell walls, always variously 2-stratose in the distal part; leaves distinctly bordered with fleshy and broad limbidia</description>
      <determination>4.   Codriophorus norrisii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costa extending 1/2–3/4 way up the leaf, distinctly spurred.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex broadly rounded, flat to subcucullate, always entire or sometimes sinuate to remotely bluntly erose-dentate</description>
      <determination>2.   Codriophorus mollis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex broadly rounded-obtuse to subacute, often tubular, strongly dentate or very rarely subentire</description>
      <determination>3.   Codriophorus aduncoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
