<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Archidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Austin" date="unknown">donnellii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 190.  1877,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Archidium;species donnellii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Archidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">ohioense</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Austin) Lesquereux &amp; James" date="unknown">donnellii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Archidium;species ohioense;variety donnellii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 2–10 mm, perennial, in dense turfs, yellow-green.  Stems simple or usually branched by several sterile innovations, becoming prostrate with age.  Stem leaves erect to erect-spreading, lanceolate to narrowly ovate-lanceolate, acuminate, 1–2.5 mm; costa percurrent or short-excurrent, sometimes somewhat subulate; laminal margins recurved, smooth or finely serrulate distally; median and distal laminal cells irregular in shape, mixed quadrate, trapezoidal, short-rectangular, short- to long-rhomboidal, 14–75 × 8–13 µm, proximal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, similar to median and distal cells; leaves of innovations similar to stem leaves, not much reduced  proximally.  Perichaetial leaves broadly ovate-lanceolate, narrowly acuminate to subulate, sometimes flexuose to secund, same size as stem leaves; costae short to long excurrent, hairpoint pellucid, sometimes finely spinose; laminal margins recurved, smooth to finely serrulate; distal and median laminal cells similar to stem leaves, proximal laminal cells lax, wider, rectangular, 2–4:1, 35–115 × 12–25 µm, sometimes somewhat hyaline.  Specialized asexual gemmae absent.  Sexual condition autoicous; antheridia terminating axillary leaf buds.  Capsule terminal, 425–750 µm.  Spores typically 28(4–60) per capsule, angular to irregularly polyhedral, 120–230 µm, smooth or finely granulose, yellow to orange-red.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature early spring (Mar), more rarely in autumn or winter (Oct–Dec).</description>
  <description type="morphology">Uncommon on moist to dry soil along roadsides, in fields, rarely on rock;</description>
  <description type="morphology">0–250 m;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ill.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Md.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Okla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">S.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tex.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Va.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Archidium donnellii usually can be distinguished from other species by irregular areolation in median and distal portions of lamina, proximal lamina cells not strongly differentiated, and sexuality autoicous.  It tends to grow in drier habitats than do other species of the genus.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
