<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">archidiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bridel" date="1827">archidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Austin" date="1877">hallii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 145.  1877,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family archidiaceae;genus archidium;species hallii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 3–10 mm, perennial, in dense short turfs, pale-green to yellow-green.  Stems branched by several innovations from axils of stem leaves or outer perichaetial leaves, often becoming prostrate with age.  Stem leaves erect-spreading, lanceolate to ovate-lanceolate, acuminate, 0.7–1.5 mm, becoming reduced  proximally; costa percurrent to slightly excurrent; laminal margins smooth, weakly recurved; median and distal laminal cells rhomboidal to hexagonal, 3–4:1, 35–70 × 12–18 µm, proximal cells rectangular, 2–4:1, 40–70 × 18–24 µm, short-rectangular to quadrate in alar region in 2–6 rows extending 7–15 cells along proximal laminal margin; leaves of innovations similar to distal stem leaves except being smaller, gradually reduced  proximally.  Perichaetial leaves larger, 1.5–3 mm, elongate-triangular, lanceolate or ovate-lanceolate, gradually acuminate; costa percurrent to short-excurrent; laminal margins smooth, weakly recurved distally; median and distal laminal cells uniformly rhomboid to hexagonal, 3–7:1, 35–130 × 15–28 µm, proximal cells rectangular, 4–6:1, 70–140 × 15–28 µm, sometimes hyaline in alar region but cells not strongly differentiated.  Specialized asexual reproduction absent.  Sexual condition autoicous, antheridia terminating axillary leaf buds.  Capsule terminal, 450-700 µm.  Spores typically 20(8–36) per capsule, triangular to rounded-polyhedral, 140–250 µm, smooth to granulose, yellow.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature early spring (Mar) or rarely late fall (Nov).</description>
  <description type="morphology">Uncommon to rare on moist open sandy or loamy soil, along roadsides and in grassy often disturbed areas;</description>
  <description type="morphology">0–200 m;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Fla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ga.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tex.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Archidium hallii can be distinguished from similar-looking forms of  A. tenerrimum by autoicous sexuality and leafy bracts enclosing the antheridia.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
