<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>19.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>SELIGERIACEAE</genus_name>
        <genus_authority>Schimper</genus_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <author>Dale H. Vitt</author>
    <description>Plants minute and gregarious, or larger, forming compact tufts and cushions,
        unbranched to rarely 2–3-branched, on rock, acrocarpous. Leaves twisted-spreading to stiffly
        erect when dry, generally erect-spreading to spreading-recurved, sometimes slightly curved
        when moist, linear to stoutly subulate from clasping base; margins plane, entire to
        denticulate; costa single, homogenous in transverse-section, ending near the apex to
        long-excurrent, distal leaf cells smooth, short; alar cells not differentiated to somewhat
        enlarged and colored. Seta straight, flexuose or cygneous. Capsule mostly erect, symmetric,
        cylindric-ovate to turbinate; peristome haplolepideous, of 16 triangular entire teeth, these
        reduced in some species, or absent.</description>
    <number_of_infrataxa>Genera 4, species ca. 44 (3 genera, 16 species in the
        flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
    <global_distribution> widespread in temperate and polar regions.</global_distribution>
    <discussion>Sporophytes are necessary for identifying the species of Seligeriaceae.</discussion>
    <key>
        <key_statement>
            <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
            <statement>Capsules striate; peristome finely papillose or absent; annulus
                well-developed; calyptra mitrate</statement>
            <determination>3. Brachydontium, p. 327</determination>
        </key_statement>
        <key_statement>
            <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
            <statement>Capsules smooth; peristome smooth or absent; annulus ill-formed; calyptra
                cucullate.</statement>
            <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
        </key_statement>
        <key_statement>
            <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
            <statement>Alar cells not differentiated or sometimes enlarged; autoicous; calcareous
                rocks</statement>
            <determination>1. Seligeria, p. 320</determination>
        </key_statement>
        <key_statement>
            <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
            <statement>Alar cells reddish and inflated; dioicous; acid rocks</statement>
            <determination>2. Blindia, p. 327</determination>
        </key_statement>
    </key>
</treatment>
