<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>32.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><species_name>jensenii</species_name><species_authority>H. Lindberg</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Acta Soc. Fauna Fl. Fenn. </publication_title><place_in_publication>18(3): 13.  1899,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><species_name>annulatum</species_name><variety_name>porosum</variety_name><variety_authority>(Warnstorf) W. S. G. Maas</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants moderate-sized to robust, weak-stemmed; pale brown to chestnut brown; capitulum flat-topped and generally 5-radiate, branches straight to somewhat curved, terminal bud often visible.  Stems pale green to brown, superficial cortex of 2 layers of thin-walled and well differentiated cells.  Stem leaves triangular, ovate-triangular to triangular-lingulate, 1–1.3 mm; appressed to spreading; apex obtuse, hyaline cells usually fibrillose near apex.  Branches straight to somewhat curved, leaves moderately elongate at distal end.  Branch fascicles with 2 spreading and 1–2 pendent branches.  Branch stems green, cortex enlarged with conspicuous retort cells.  Branch leaves ovate-lanceolate; usually more than 2 mm; straight; weakly undulate and slightly recurved when dry, margins entire; hyaline cells on convex surface with numerous small free pores in proximal 2/3 of leaf and in apical region with numerous pseudopores along commissures, on concave surface with numerous round free pores; cells relatively long and narrow in basal region, much longer than in mid region; chlorophyllous cells triangular in transverse section and well-enclosed on concave surface.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Spores 29–33 µm; both surfaces very smooth; proximal laesura long, more than 0.6 spore radius.</description><habitat>Predominantly in wet carpets in poor to medium fen habitats, mostly in mire-wide vegetation;</habitat><elevation> low to moderate elevations;</elevation><ca_distribution> Alta.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.W.T.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Que.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Sask.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Yukon</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Alaska</us_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia.</global_distribution><discussion>Sporophytes of Sphagnum jensenii are uncommon.  For more information, see discussion under 23. S. annulatum.</discussion></treatment>
