<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ronald A. Pursell</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Bescherelle" date="unknown">BRYOXIPHIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family BRYOXIPHIACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
    
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small. Stems unbranched or infrequently branched subapically, bulblike or
        not at proximal end, erect or pendent, loosely to densely tufted, rarely solitary; axillary
        hairs filiform, hyaline, or basal and adjacent cell pale tan or pale rose-violet;
        paraphyllia none; pseudoparaphyllia none; rhizoids basal, light brown to reddish, smooth.
        Leaves distichous, tightly imbricate, changing little when dry, conduplicate; 1-costate,
        costae supporting low abaxial lamellae; laminal cells firm-walled, 1-stratose, smooth,
        somewhat bulging. Sexual condition dioicous; perigonia and perichaetia terminal, indistinct,
        without and with paraphyses, respectively, archegonia about 1/2 length of paraphyses;
        antheridia and archegonia few. Sporophytes single. Seta short, erect or somewhat curved.
        Capsule subglobose, emergent, erect or somewhat inclined, radially symmetric, stomatose;
        annulus absent; peristome absent; operculum persistent, obliquely rostellate, attached to
        columella after dehiscence. Calyptra cucullate. Spores spheric.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico</description>
  <description type="morphology">West Indies</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Bryoxiphiaceae are found primarily in temperate regions.</description>
  <number>20.</number>
  <discussion>Genus 1, species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Britton, E. G. 1913. Bryoxiphiaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North
            American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 15, pp. 69–70.</reference>
    <reference>Löve, Á. and D. Löve. 1953.
            Studies on Bryoxiphium. Bryologist 56: 73–94, 183–203.</reference>
    <reference>Steere, W. C. 1937. Bryoxiphium norvegicum, the sword moss, as a preglacial and
            interglacial relic. Ecology 18: 346–358.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
