<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Pohle" date="unknown">lenense</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trudy Glavn. Bot. Sada</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>33: 14.  1915,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species lenense;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">lindbergii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Warnstorf" date="unknown">microphyllum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hedwigia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>32: 16.  1893</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species lindbergii;variety microphyllum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants compact, short-branched and small; strongly reddish to golden brown, glossy when dry; flat-topped capitulum with moderately differentiated terminal bud.  Stems dark brown; super-ficial cortex of 3–4 layers of enlarged thin-walled cells.  Stem leaves lingulate,small, equal to or less than 0.8 mm, appressed to stem; apex with strong lacerate split in the middle; hyaline cells efibrillose, aporose, and nonseptate.  Branches strongly 5-ranked, short and blunt, not much elongated at distal end.  Branch fascicles with 2 spreading and 2–3 pendent branches.  Branch stems green, with cortex enlarged with retort cells.  Branch leaves ovate; usually less than 1.5 mm; stiff and slightly reflexed, straight to slightly subsecund; margins entire; hyaline cells moderately long and narrow (6–8:1), convex surface with one small round pore per cell at apex and numerous pseudopores on the margin, concave surface with large round wall thinnings in the cell angles and ends; chlorophyllous cells triangular in transverse section, with apex reaching concave surface.  Sexual condition unknown.  Spores not seen.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Common forming hummocks and carpets in a variety of weakly minerotrophic to ombrotrophic mires including Eriophorum tussock fens, dwarf shrub fens, polygon peatlands, string mires and raised bogs;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Greenland</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Yukon</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska</description>
  <description type="morphology">Eurasia.</description>
  <number>34.</number>
  <discussion>Sporophytes are rare in Sphagnum lenense.  This species is easily distinguished from the similar S. lindbergii by its compact growth form and reddish brown color.  Sphagnum lenense also is a hummock former in the tundra whereas S. lindbergii forms carpets.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
