<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">fissidentaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Fissidens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lesquereux" date="unknown">ventricosus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Calif. Acad. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 7.  1868,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family fissidentaceae; genus Fissidens;species ventricosus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 25 × 3.5 mm.  Stem unbranched and branched; axillary hyaline nodules absent; central strand weak.  Leaves as many as 35 pairs, lanceolate to oblong-lingulate, acute to obtuse-apiculate; to 5 × 0.9 mm; dorsal lamina narrowed proximally, ending at insertion, not decurrent; vaginant laminae 1/2–2/3 leaf length, equal; margin ± entire, limbate on all laminae, limbidium reaching apex or ending a few cells before apex and a few cells above insertion of dorsal lamina, limbidial cells 3- to 6-stratose; costa ± percurrent, bryoides-type; laminal cells 1-stratose, or variably 2-stratose, smooth, slightly bulging, firm-walled, irregularly quadrate to hexagonal, 8–13 µm, ± twice as deep as wide.  Sexual condition probably rhizautoicous; perigonia not seen; perichaetia on elongate stems.  Sporophytes 1–2 per perichaetium.  Seta stout, to 3 mm, geniculate.  Capsule theca emergent, erect, radially symmetric, to 1.2 mm; peristome bryoides-type; operculum 0.4 mm.  Calyptra not seen.  Spores 23–40 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Attached to rocks and other substrates in rapidly running streams, infrequently on wet rocks beside streams;</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Idaho</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <number>15.</number>
  <discussion>Fissidens ventricosus occurs along the Pacific Coast of North America and at a disjunct site in northern Idaho (see map in R. R. Ireland and W. B. Schofield 1967).  It is distinguished by its aquatic habitat, strongly limbate leaves, variably 2-stratose laminal cells, short, thick, geniculate seta, and emergent capsule.  Plants usually become black and covered with diatoms.  The species might be confused with F. rigidulus Hooker f. &amp; Wilson, but the latter, found in wet sites in the Americas from Chile north to Mexico but not known in the United States, has much smaller laminal cells and a long seta characteristic of terrestrial species.  The calyptra of F. ventricosus is cucullate according to Ireland and Schofield.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
