<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>36.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><species_name>majus</species_name><species_authority>(Russow) C. E.O. Jensen</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Botaniske Forening København, Festskrift, </publication_title><place_in_publication>106.  1890,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><species_name>cuspidatum</species_name><variety_name>majus</variety_name><variety_authority>Russow</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Arch. Naturk. Liv- Ehst- Kurlands, Ser. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2, Biol. Naturk. 7: 136.  1865</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants moderate-sized to robust, fairly weak-stemmed, lax in submersed forms, ± sprawling in emergent froms; golden brown to dark brown; capitulum weakly 5-radiate, branches straight to strongly laterally curved.  Stems green to pale brown, superficial cortex only weakly differentiated.  Stem leaves triangular-lingulate, 0.8–1.4 mm, spreading to appressed; apex acute to narrowly obtuse, hyaline cells nonseptate and fibrillose near apex.  Branches unranked or weakly 5-ranked, straight to strongly curved, leaves moderately elongated at distal end.  Branch fascicles with 2 spreading and 1–2 pendent branches.  Branch stems green but sometimes reddish at proximal end, with cortex enlarged with conspicuous retort cells.  Branch leaves ovate-lanceolate to narrowly ovate-lanceolate, 1.8–3.4 mm; straight to strongly subsecund; weakly undulate and recurved when dry; margins entire; hyaline cells on convex surface with 1–2 free pores per fibril interval, concave surface aporose or rarely with a few wall thinnings in cell ends and angles; chlorophyllous cells trapezoidal in transverse section and narrowly exposed on concave surface.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Spores 33–40 µm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia.</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCE"><reference>Flatberg, K. I.  1987.  Taxonomy of Sphagnum majus (Russ.) C. Jens.  Kongel. Norske Vidensk. Selsk. Skr. (Trondheim) 2: 1–42.</reference></references><key><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Branch leaf hyaline cells on convex leaf surface with 1–2 pores per fibril interval, these usually less than 1/3 the cell diameter</statement><determination>36a.   Sphagnum majus subsp. majus</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Branch leaf hyaline cells on convex leaf surface with 1 pore per fibril interval, these more than 1/3 the cell diameter</statement><determination>36b.   Sphagnum majus subsp. norvegicum</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
