<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>32.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Fissidens</genus_name>
        <species_name>littlei</species_name>
        <species_authority>(R. S. Williams) Grout</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title> Moss Fl. N. Amer. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>1: 249. 1939,</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Moenkemeyera</genus_name>
        <species_name>littlei</species_name>
        <species_authority>R. S. Williams</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Bryologist </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>39: 40, plate 4. 1936</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Plants to 3 × 2 mm. Stem un-branched and sparingly branched; axillary hyaline
        nodules absent; central strand absent. Leaves as many as 8 pairs, ligulate, obtuse-apiculate
        to acute, to 1.5 × 0.25 mm; dorsal lamina narrowed proximally, ending at insertion or
        slightly decurrent; vaginant laminae 1/2–2/3 leaf length, ± equal, minor lamina ending on or
        near margin; margin crenulate, often irregularly so on vaginant laminae, elimbate; costa
        ending 3–5 cells before apex, bryoides-type; lamina cells 1-stratose, distinct, mammillose,
        firm-walled, irregularly quadrate to hexagonal, oblate on margin, 8–10 µm, somewhat larger,
        ± oblong in proximal parts of vaginant laminae. Sexual condition rhizautoicous and
        gonio-autoicous; perigonia gemmiform and on elongate stems. Sporophytes 1 per perichaetium.
        Seta 1.4–1.8 mm. Capsule theca exserted, erect, radially symmetric, to 0.5 mm long;
        peristome teeth anomalous, undivided, papillose; operculum to 0.3 mm. Calyptra cucullate,
        smooth, 0.3 mm. Spores 8–11 µm.</description>
    <habitat>Walls of small pockets in gypsum sinkholes</habitat>
    <us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution>
    <discussion>This rare Fissidens, named in honor of the American botanist Elbert Little, is known
        only from the type locality and was recently re-discovered there by K. W. Allred (1998). The
        plants are pale green, probably the result of their occurrence in small pocketlike
        depressions where direct sunlight does not penetrate. The species has been confused with F.
        amoenus, but differs from the latter by its elimbate leaves, slightly smaller, mammillose
        laminal cells, oblate marginal cells, absence of enlarged pellucid cells in the proximal
        parts of the vaginant laminae, and undivided, papillose peristome teeth.</discussion>
</treatment>
