<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>33.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Fissidens</genus_name>
    <species_name>pauperculus</species_name>
    <species_authority>Howe</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Erythea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 97, fig. 1. 1894,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 2–3 × 1.5–2.5 mm. Stems unbranched; axillary hyaline nodules absent; central
        strands weak. Leaves as many as 5 pairs, oblong to oblanceolate to lanceo-late, acute to
        short-acuminate, to 2.1 × 0.6 mm; margin crenulate-serrulate but often sharply serrate on
        distal parts of vaginant laminae, elimbate; dorsal lamina usually narrowed proximally,
        ending at insertion, not decurrent; vaginant laminae ± 1/2–2/3 leaf length, unequal, minor
        lamina ending near margin; costa ending 6–15 cells before apex, bryoides-type; laminal cells
        1-stratose, distinct, smooth, plane, firm-walled, long-hexagonal to oblong to regularly
        quadrate, decreasing in size from costa to margin, medial cells 10–54 × 12–25 µm, largest
        along costa, marginal cells 9–15 µm, juxtacostal cells in vaginant laminae pellucid, greatly
        enlarged. Sexual condition rhizautoicous and gonioautoicous. Sporophytes 1 per perichaetium.
        Seta 2.5–5 mm. Capsule theca exserted, usually inclined, slightly arcuate, bilaterally
        symmetric, infrequently erect, nearly radially symmetric, 0.7 mm; peristome scariosus-type;
        operculum 0.3–0.8 mm. Calyptra cucullate, smooth, 0.4 mm. Spores 9–13 µm.</description>
  <habitat>Bare gravelly soil in dried stream beds and on banks</habitat>
  <habitat>sometimes found with F. crispus</habitat>
  <habitat>often associated with the Coast Redwood Forest (L. F. Koch
        1951)</habitat>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Fissidens pauperculus is distinguished by its short costa, and smooth, plane laminal
        cells that gradually decrease in size outwardly. P. A. Florschütz (1964) equated specimens
        from Suriname with this species. R. A. Pursell (1994b) demonstrated, however, that the North
        American plants are different from those of South America. Although close to the South
        American plants that belong to F. inaequalis Mitten, the North American species differs by
        its slightly smaller laminal cells and in the absence of truncate-retuse vaginant laminae in
        the perichaetial leaves.</discussion>
</treatment>
