<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Patricia M. Eckel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">dicranaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="1846">AONGSTROEMIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 171.  1846  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dicranaceae;genus AONGSTROEMIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Johan Ångström, 1813–1879, Swedish bryologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, gregarious or in loose thin mats or tufts, yellowish green, orange-red to brown-green, rather dull.  Stems erect, 3–6(–12) mm, simple or occasionally forked, central strand present; scarcely radiculose, rhizoids red, smooth.  Leaves ovate or shortly lanceolate-acuminate, concave proximally, tubulose when acuminate, erect and appressed-imbricate when dry, somewhat loosely so when moist; apices in proximal leaves broadly acute grading to obtuse to acuminate-subulate in distal leaves; margins plane to incurved, entire, notched at the apex; costa prominent, single, ending before the apex, smooth on all surfaces, guide cells in 1 row, stereid bands 2, the adaxial band reduced, abaxial and adaxial epidermis prominent; laminal cells convex in section, without pits, smooth, mostly elongate throughout, shorter in the apex, walls in surface view thick-walled, irregularly elongate-hexagonal, rhomboid or rectangular, alar cells undifferentiated.  Specialized asexual reproduction absent.  Sexual condition dioicous; perigonial plants similar to the perichaetial, perigonium terminal, conspicuous, perigonial leaves larger than the cauline leaves, broadly lanceolate-triangular with an abrupt acumination, broadly tubulose; perichaetium terminal, conspicuous, leaves larger than stem leaves, convolute-sheathing, abruptly long-acuminate to subulate.  Seta elongate, smooth, erect, yellow-orange to red.  Capsule erect, globose, ovate or short-cylindric, straight, symmetric, smooth wet or dry, annular cells weakly differentiated in one layer; operculum conic to short-rostrate, oblique; peristome variably absent or present, single, 16 teeth ± cleft to 1/2 the length, vertically pitted-striolate basally, weakly papillose to smooth distally, reddish brown to nearly hyaline.  Calyptra cucullate, smooth, naked, fugacious.  Spores 12–20 µm, smooth to finely papillose.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, Eurasia, Atlantic Islands.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Species 7 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The highest diversity for Aongstroemia is in Mexico, Central America, and South America.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
