<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Cynodontium</genus_name><species_name>glaucescens</species_name><species_authority>(Lindberg &amp; Arnell) Paris</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Actes Soc. Linn. Bordeaux, sér. </publication_title><place_in_publication>5, 6: 306.  1894,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Oncophorus</genus_name><species_name>glaucescens</species_name><species_authority>Lindberg &amp; Arnell</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Kongl. Svenska Vetensk. Acad. Handl., n. s. </publication_title><place_in_publication>23(10): 93.   1890</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems ca. 0.5 cm.  Leaves 1–1.2 mm, broadly lanceolate, mostly bluntly rounded at the tips to broadly acute; leaf margins broadly recurved often to near the apex, 1-stratose; laminal cells essentially smooth, somewhat mammillose-papillose on the margins with a single mammilla per cell, more strongly mammillose-papillose at the leaf apex, with thick walls, firm, rounded at the angles, distal cells around 10 µm wide.  Perigonium short-stalked.  Seta to 0.7 cm, straight wet or dry.  Capsule symmetrical, erect, struma small but conspicuous; annulus weakly developed, adherent.</description><phenology>Capsules mature summer.</phenology><habitat>  Rock crevices, tundra hummocks, soil banks, both acid and calcareous substrates;</habitat><elevation> moderate to high elevations;</elevation><global_distribution> Greenland</global_distribution><ca_distribution> Alta.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Man.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.W.T.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Que.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Yukon</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Alaska</us_distribution><global_distribution> Asia (Siberia).</global_distribution><discussion>Cynodontium glaucescens is separated from C. schisti and C. alpestre by less strongly mammillose-papillose leaves, and laminal cell walls decidedly thicker.  The species was reported for North America by W. C. Steere (1977, 1978) and C. D. Bird et al. (1977); a synopsis and complete list of specimens throughout its range was presented by G. S. Mogensen and Steere (1979).</discussion><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCE"><reference>Mogensen, G. S. and W. C. Steere.  1979.  The taxonomic position of Cynodontium glaucescens (Lindb. et Arn.) Kindb. (Dicranaceae, Musci).  Lindbergia 5: 19–24.</reference></references></treatment>
