<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">sphagnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Lindberg" date="1862">cuspidata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Flatberg" date="1989">pacificum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>92: 116, figs. 1–20.  1989,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family sphagnaceae;genus sphagnum;section cuspidata;species pacificum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants moderate-sized and fairly strong-stemmed; green, yellow to yellowish brown; capitulum 5­radiate in shade forms to hemispherical in open grown or drier growing forms.  Stems pale green to pale brown, sometimes with red branch bases; superficial cortex of 2 layers of enlarged, clearly differentiated and thin-walled cells.  Stem leaves triangular to lingulate-triangular, 0.8–1.3 mm; typically appressed; apex acute to apiculate; hyaline cells efibrillose and nonseptate to rarely septate.  Branches straight and somewhat tapered, usually 5-ranked; leaves little elongate at the distal branch end.  Branch fascicles with 2 spreading and 2–3 pendent branches.  Branch stems green but often reddish at proximal end, with cortex enlarged with conspicuous retort cells.  Branch leaves ovate to narrowly ovate-lanceolate; (1.1–)1.4–1.8(–3.1) mm; slightly undulate and sharply recurved when dry, somewhat subsecund; margins entire; hyaline cells on convex surface with usually 1 round pore on apical end, on concave surface with wall thinnings in the cell ends and angles; chlorophyllous cells broadly triangular in transverse section and very deeply enclosed on the concave surface.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Spores 19–25 µm; finely papillose on both surfaces.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Forested and open poor fen habitats, often as a ruderal species in extensive mats;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Forested and open poor fen habitats, often as a ruderal species in extensive mats; low to moderate elevations; B.C.; Alaska, Oreg., Wash.</text>
    <parsed>
      <habitat>Forested and open poor fen habitats, often as a ruderal species in extensive mats;</habitat>
      <elevation>low to moderate elevations;</elevation>
      <distribution>B.C.; Alaska, Oreg., Wash.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>41.</number>
  <discussion>Sporophytes in Sphagnum pacificum are uncommon.  See discussion under 26. S. brevifolium.  Characters of the spores are taken from Flatberg’s description.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
