<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Swartz" date="unknown">polysetum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Monthly Rev., ser.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 34: 538.  1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species polysetum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Funck) Bridel" date="unknown">rugosum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species rugosum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>W. L. Peterson (1979) recorded Dicranum polysetum from Nunavut.  It is one of the largest, most conspicuous, and most easily recognized species in the genus in North America.  The species is immediately recognized by the large stems, 4–15 cm, with a dense mat of whitish or reddish tomentum, giving the stems a thickened appearance, by the shiny, strongly undulate, wide-spreading leaves with margins strongly toothed in the distal half and by the clustered sporophytes (3–6 per perichaetium).  Microscopically, the species is readily distinguished by the elongate, abundantly pitted cells throughout the leaf and by the toothed ridges on the abaxial surface of the costa in the distal part of the leaf.  Dicranum polysetum is one of the few species in North America that has no apparent intergradations with any other species of the genus.  It is common in southeastern Canada, northeastern United States, and the Canadian Rocky Mountains, where it extends south to Wyoming and Colorado, occurring in both states in a small number of localities.  It is rare west of the Rockies, where it is known from only a few localities in northwestern Montana, southern Idaho and northeastern Washington and Oregon.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
