<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Renauld &amp; Cardot" date="unknown">howellii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 70.  1888,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species howellii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Dicranum howellii occurrs only in the northwestern part of North America.  It is closely related to the common and nearly ubiquitous D. scoparium.  The shape of the interior perichaetial leaves is the most reliable way to distinguish the two.  Gradually acuminate perichaetial leaves that loosely surround the seta are characteristic of D. howellii.  Dicranum scoparium has abruptly acuminate exterior perichaetial leaves, interior ones that are abruptly acuminateto blunt at the apex and are convolute-sheathing around the seta.  The interior perichaetial leaves of D. howellii are also longer and narrower than those of the D. scoparium.  Other less significant features of D. howellii are the consistently glossy, long leaves, mostly 8–10 mm, with long distal cells, averaging 54–90 µm, and the common occurrence of only two, rarely four, serrated ridges on the abaxial surface of the costae.  Dicranum scoparium by comparison has glossy to sometimes dull leaves that are often shorter, mostly 5–8.5 mm, with shorter distal cells, averaging 27–43 µm, and the costae usually have four, rarely two, serrated ridges on the abaxial surface.  The perichaetial leaves are undoubtedly the most important feature separating the two species, as well as being the easiest to observe.  Eastern North American plants of D. scoparium all have the abruptly acuminate perichaetial leaves that are characteristic of the species, as do plants elsewhere in the world.  The perichaetial leaf character was one reason D. howellii was believed to be a distinct species by F. Renauld and J. Cardot (1889, plate 12B) who first illustrated that character and this remains the most significant reason for maintaining it as a distinct species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
