<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>42.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><species_name>pulchrum</species_name><species_authority>(Lindberg) Warnstorf</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Bot. Centralbl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>82: 42.  1900,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><species_name>intermedium</species_name><variety_name>pulchrum</variety_name><variety_authority>Lindberg</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in R. Braithwaite, Sphagnac. Europe, </publication_title><place_in_publication>81, fig. 25g.  1880</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants moderate-sized to robust, often quite dense and compact; green, brownish green, golden brown to dark brown; capitulum flat-topped and not especially 5-radiate.  Stems green to dark brown; superficial cortex of 2 layers of enlarged, moderately differentiated cells.  Stem leaves triangular to triangular-lingulate, 0.9–1.1 mm; appressed to spreading; apex apiculate, acute or narrowly obtuse, appressed to spreading; hyaline cells nonseptate and efibrillose.  Branches straight to more typically curved, typically stout and blunt ended; strongly 5-ranked, leaves not much elongate at distal end.  Branch fascicles with 2 spreading and 2 pendent branches.  Branch stems green but often reddish at proximal end, with cortex enlarged with conspicuous retort cells.  Branch leaves ovate to ovate-lanceolate, 1.4–1.8 mm; straight to often subsecund; weakly undulate and slightly recurved; hyaline cells on convex surface with 1 pore per cell at apical end of cell, on concave surface with round wall thinnings in the cells ends and angles; chlorophyllous cells triangular to triangular-ovate in transverse section, very well-enclosed within concave surface.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Spores 25–28 µm; roughly papillous on both surfaces; proximal laesura more than 0.5 the length of the spore.</description><habitat>Abundant in poor fens and raised bogs, forming dense carpets at water level, especially on floating mats;</habitat><elevation> low to moderate elevations;</elevation><ca_distribution> Man.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.B.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.S.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Que.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Alaska</us_distribution><us_distribution> Conn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ind.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Maine</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mass.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mich.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Minn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.H.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.J.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Y.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Wis.</us_distribution><us_distribution> W.Va.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Europe.</global_distribution><discussion>Sporophytes are uncommon in Sphagnum pulchrum. With its distinctive broad and strongly 5-ranked branch leaves, It is one of our most easily recognized species.</discussion></treatment>
