<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">dicranaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Turner" date="1804">majus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Hibern. Spic.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>59. 1804,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dicranaceae;genus dicranum;species majus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in loose tufts, green to light green, glossy to somewhat dull. Stems 3–16
        cm, naked or with a few whitish rhizoids, rarely moderately tomentose, rhizoids
        (micronemata) in rows above each leaf. Leaves somewhat sparse, falcate-secund or
        erect-patent, flexuose or straight, little changed when dry, usually smooth, (6–)8–11.5(–15)
        × 1–2 mm, concave proximally, tubulose above, from a lanceolate to ovate-lanceolate base,
        gradually narrowed to a long, falcate-secund or straight, acute apex; margins serrate in the
        distal half, sometimes slightly serrulate above to almost entire; laminae 1-stratose or with
        few 2-stratose regions on or near the margins; costa percurrent to shortly excurrent,
        1/12–1/7 the width of the leaves at base, toothed distally or serrulate to nearly smooth on
        abaxial surface, with a double row of guide cells that is sometimes interrupted, two stereid
        bands extending to apex, adaxial epidermal layer of cells with some cells differentiated,
        the abaxial layer completely differentiated; cell walls between lamina cells not bulging;
        leaf cells smooth or abaxially prorate or toothed above; alar cells 2-stratose or
        multistratose, well-differentiated, not extending to costa; proximal laminal cells elongate,
        pitted, (42–)71–112(–140) × (5–)9–10(–15) µm; distal laminal cells shorter, linear to oval,
        pitted, (42–)47–61(–99) × (7–)10–11(–17) µm. Sexual condition pseudomonoicous; dwarf males
        among rhizoids of female plants; interior perichaetial leaves abruptly long-acuminate,
        convolute-sheathing. Seta 2.5–5 cm, aggregate, 2–5 per perichaetium, rarely solitary, yellow
        to light brown. Capsule 2–3.5 mm, arcuate, inclined to horizontal, smooth to faintly striate
        when dry, dark brown or yellowish brown; operculum 2–3 mm. Spores 14–19 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">nw, ne North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties ca. 12 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Dicranum majus is the only North American species of the genus with a double row of
        guide cells. It is a distinctive species with oceanic tendencies and in North America it
        commonly grows in northern coastal localities on both sides of the continent, occasionally
        occurring inland in very moist habitats.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves falcate-secund, 8–15 mm; margins serrate in the distal half; costa
                toothed distally on abaxial surface, with a double row of guide cells</description>
      <determination>6a. Dicranum majus var. majus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves erect-patent, 6–8 mm; margins slightly serrulate above to almost
                entire; costa serrulate to nearly smooth distally on abaxial surface, with an
                interrupted double row of guide cells</description>
      <determination>6b. Dicranum majus var. orthophyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
