<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">undulatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(2): 294.  1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species undulatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Blandow" date="unknown">bergeri</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species bergeri;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>R. R. Ireland (1971b) recorded Dicranum undulatum from Colorado, but W. Weber (pers. comm.) believes this is a misidentification for D. polysetum.  Dicranum undulatum is primarily a boreal species that is distinctive because of the yellowish green or yellowish brown, shiny, erect-appressed, lanceolate to oblong-lanceolate, undulate, keeled leaves, the leaf margins that are serrulate to serrate, and broadly recurved in the distal half, the leaf apices that are usually broadly acute, rarely narrowly acute, and the costae that are mostly subpercurrent or sometimes percurrent, smooth to serrulate above on abaxial surface.  When the leaf apices are narrow, ± acute, and the costa percurrent, as some D. undulatum plants are on rare occasion, the species when sterile can be confused with D. ontariense.  Dicranum undulatum has shiny leaves with twisted apices when dry compared to the more dull leaves that are variously contorted in D. ontariense.  When sporophytes are present the aggregate setae (2–5 per perichaetium) of D. ontariense will immediately distinguish it from D. undulatum which has solitary setae.  This species recently has been introduced on the University of California Berkeley Campus in a lawn-landscaping area; this is the only California locality where it has been found.  The plants are sterile but appear morphologically similar to those growing in native habitats in other parts of North America.  Dicranum undulatum of G. F. Weber &amp; C. Mohr (1803) is not a synonym of the taxon treated here.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
