<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>10.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Dicranum</genus_name>
    <species_name>drummondii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Müller Hal.</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Musc. Frond.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 356. 1848,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Dicranum</genus_name>
    <species_name>elatum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Lindberg</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Dicranum</genus_name>
    <species_name>robustum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Bruch &amp; Schimper</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants in loose tufts, yellowish green to yellowish brown below, shiny to dull.
        Stems 5–11 cm, densely tomentose below with reddish brown rhizoids. Leaves erect and
        compressed to somewhat flexuose, curled to flexuose at apices when dry, undulate or rugose,
        (7–)8–10(–12) × 1.5–2 mm, concave below, keeled above, from an oblong-ovate base to a
        long-acuminate apex; margins incurved to tubulose below, plane and strongly serrate above;
        laminae 1-stratose below, sometimes a few scattered 2-stratose regions above; costa
        percurrent to shortly excurrent, 1/10–1/6 the width of leaves at base, papillose to serrate
        above on abaxial surface, without lamellae, with a row of guide cells, two stereid bands
        above and below extending to apex, adaxial epidermal layer of cells with a few cells
        slightly larger than the stereids differentiated, the abaxial layer completely
        differentiated with cells slightly larger than the stereids; cell walls between lamina cells
        not bulging; leaf cells smooth or a few cells prorate on abaxial surface; alar cells
        2-stratose, differentiated, extending to costa; proximal laminal cells irregularly
        rectangular, often narrowed at ends, narrow and elongate on margins, pitted,
        (67–)82–98(–112) × (5–)6–8(–9) µm; distal laminal cells round, oblong, somewhat rectangular,
        with a few pits (9–)13–19(–30) × (3–)6–9(–12) µm. Sterile, no sex organs seen. [Sexual
        condition pseudomonoicous, male plants on leaves of female plants. Interior perichaetial
        leaves abruptly subulate, convolute-sheathing. Seta 3–5 cm, 2–3 per perichaetium, sometimes
        solitary, yellowish. Capsule 2.5–3.5 mm, arcuate, inclined to horizontal, striate when dry,
        yellowish brown; operculum 2.3–3 mm. Spores 14–18 µm.]</description>
  <habitat>As large clones in mesic mire</habitat>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Asia (China, Japan, Korea, Russia).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Dicranum drummondii, primarily an Eurasian species, was for years confused with the
        endemic North American species Dicranum ontariense W. L. Peterson (see discussion under 9.
        D. ontariense). It was only recently (August 2000) that W. B. Schofield, S. S. Talbot, and
        S. L. Talbot made the first and only collection of the species, which was sterile, from Attu
        Island in the Aleutian Islands. The species is best recognized by its robust size, stems
        5–11 cm, its leaves yellowish green to yellowish brown, undulate or rugose, erect and
        compressed, becoming flexuose at the tips when dry, concave below and keeled above, with an
        oblong-ovate base, becoming long-acuminate at apex, margins strongly toothed above, and
        costa percurrent to shortly excurrent, without lamellae. Microscopically, distinguishing
        characters are the leaves in the distal part with round, oblong, somewhat rectangular cells
        with few pits, cells smooth or prorate on abaxial surface, in cross section the lamina with
        a few scattered 2-stratose cells, cells walls between the lamina cells not bulging, and
        costa with a few cells differentiated on the adaxial epidermal surface.</discussion>
</treatment>
