<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Müller Hal." date="unknown">drummondii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Musc. Frond.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 356. 1848,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species drummondii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lindberg" date="unknown">elatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species elatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="unknown">robustum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species robustum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>10.</number>
  <discussion>Dicranum drummondii, primarily an Eurasian species, was for years confused with the
        endemic North American species Dicranum ontariense W. L. Peterson (see discussion under 9.
        D. ontariense). It was only recently (August 2000) that W. B. Schofield, S. S. Talbot, and
        S. L. Talbot made the first and only collection of the species, which was sterile, from Attu
        Island in the Aleutian Islands. The species is best recognized by its robust size, stems
        5–11 cm, its leaves yellowish green to yellowish brown, undulate or rugose, erect and
        compressed, becoming flexuose at the tips when dry, concave below and keeled above, with an
        oblong-ovate base, becoming long-acuminate at apex, margins strongly toothed above, and
        costa percurrent to shortly excurrent, without lamellae. Microscopically, distinguishing
        characters are the leaves in the distal part with round, oblong, somewhat rectangular cells
        with few pits, cells smooth or prorate on abaxial surface, in cross section the lamina with
        a few scattered 2-stratose cells, cells walls between the lamina cells not bulging, and
        costa with a few cells differentiated on the adaxial epidermal surface.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
