<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">condensatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp.. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>139.  1801, not plate 34,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species condensatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Renauld &amp; Cardot" date="unknown">sabuletorum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species sabuletorum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>11.</number>
  <discussion>Dicranum condensatum is a common species recognized in the field by its occurrence on sandy soil, by its light green to yellowish brown, dull plants in compact, dense tufts, its erect-spreading, oblong-lanceolate leaves, narrowing to a short-acuminate apex, keeled above, somewhat undulate or rugose, curled at tips when dry, and its solitary setae with an arcuate, inclined to horizontal capsule.  The papillose leaf cells with strongly bulging walls between the cells and the irregularly angled median and distal cells with nonpitted walls are distinctive microscopic characters.  Dicranum spurium is the species most commonly confused with D. condensatum.  Both species occur on sandy soil with their ranges overlapping.  The former occurs farther northward, where it is found in Newfoundland, while the latter occurs farther to the south, where its range extends to the tip of Florida.  Dicranum spurium has broader leaves, the broadest point near the middle rather than near the base like D. condensatum, and leaves that are tubulose above (most noticeable when wet) rather than keeled. Rarely, D. condensatum can be mistaken for 9. D. ontariense as discussed under that species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
