<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">dicranaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">spurium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>141.  1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dicranaceae; genus Dicranum;species spurium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in loose tufts, green to yellowish green or yellowish brown, dull.  Stems 2–11 cm, densely tomentose below with reddish brown rhizoids, inter-ruptedly foliate, the leaves crowded in some parts forming swollen, globose regions.  Leaves erect-spreading, arched and loosely imbricate with contorted apices when dry, ± undulate to rugose, (2.5–)5–6.5(–9) × 1–1.7 mm, concave below, tubulose above, acute, ovate at base, widest point at or somewhat below middle; margins serrulate to serrate in distal half, plane to involute; laminae 1-stratose or with 2-stratose regions near costa and on margins; costa percurrent to shortly excurrent, 1/8–1/4 the width of the leaves at base, serrulate or toothed above on abaxial surface, abaxial ridges absent, with a row of guide cells, two stereid bands extending to apex, adaxial epidermal layer of cells not differentiated, the abaxial layer differentiated; cell walls between lamina cells weakly to strongly bulging; leaf cells strongly papillose above on abaxial surface, sometimes a few papillae on adaxial surface; alar cells 2-stratose, distinctly differentiated, not extending to costa; proximal laminal cells elongate, pitted, (30–)49–68(–101) × (5–)10–11(–15) µm, abruptly shorter in distal half of leaf; distal laminal cells short, not or indistinctly pitted, cell walls irregularly thickened, (7–)11–12(–23) × (5–)7–13(–20) µm.  Sexual condition pseudomonoicous; dwarf males on rhizoids of female plants; interior perichaetial leaves abruptly short-acuminate, convolute-sheathing.  Seta 1–3 cm, solitary, reddish yellow or brown.  Capsule 1.5–2.5 mm, arcuate, inclined to horizontal, contracted below mouth and furrowed when dry, yellowish brown to brown; operculum 1.5–2.5 mm.  Spores 16–24 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature spring.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Sandy soil, decayed logs, acidic rock, humus over exposed bluffs or outcrops, in pine woods, sometimes bogs;</description>
  <description type="morphology">0–1400 m;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.S.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">P.E.I.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ark.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Conn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ga.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ill.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ky.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Maine</description>
  <description type="morphology">Md.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mass.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mich.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.H.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.J.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ohio</description>
  <description type="morphology">Okla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pa.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tenn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Vt.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Va.</description>
  <description type="morphology">W.Va.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe.</description>
  <number>12.</number>
  <discussion>Dicranum spurium is easily recognized by the turgid aspect of the plants with arched, imbricate leaves and with interruptedly foliate stems, i.e., some regions that appear swollen or globose as a result of several growth periods.  It is likely to be confused only with 11. D. condensatum (see discussion thereunder).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
