<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">dicranaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bridel" date="1818">groenlandicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Muscol. Recent., suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 68.  1818,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dicranaceae;genus dicranum;species groenlandicum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense tufts, light green, glossy.  Stems 4.5–10 cm, tomen-tose throughout with brown to red rhizoids.  Leaves erect-spreading, erect-appressed when dry, smooth, (2.5–)3–4(–6.5) × 0.3–0.5 mm, from an ovate-lanceolate base to a tubulose subula, narrowly obtuse at apex, rarely acute, sometimes apical leaves of stems julaceous; margins entire; laminae 1-stratose, occasional 2-stratose regions near costa in proximal part of leaf; costa subpercurrent to percurrent, 1/10–1/6 the width of the leaves at base, smooth, abaxial ridges absent, with a row of guide cells, two well developed and thick stereid bands (5–6 cells thick), adaxial epidermal layer of cells not differentiated, the abaxial layer usually with a few cells enlarged; cell walls between lamina cells slightly bulging; leaf cells smooth; alar cells 1- or 2-stratose, well-differentiated, not extending to costa; proximal laminal cells elongate-sinuose, strongly pitted, (36–)54–65(–98) × (2–)5–6(–9) µm; distal laminal cells (11–)17–26(–42) × (2–)5–6(–12) µm.  Sexual condition dioicous; male plants as large as females; interior perichaetial leaves abruptly short-acuminate, convolute-sheathing.  Seta 1.5–2 cm, solitary, yellow to reddish yellow.  Capsule 1.5–2 mm, nearly straight and erect to slightly arcuate, ± striate when dry, yellowish brown; operculum 1–1.7 mm.  Spores 14–19 µm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature in summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Arctic or alpine tundra, soil, humus or rocks, sometimes in bogs and fens;</description>
  <description type="elevation">10-3800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; Alta., B.C., Man., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.W.T., Nunavut, Ont., Que., Yukon; Alaska, Colo., N.Y.; Europe; Asia.</description>
  <number>20.</number>
  <discussion>Dicranum groenlandicum is sometimes not very distinct, often being difficult to separate from its nearest relative, 19. D. elongatum.  For distinctions see the discussion under that species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
