<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">montanum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>143.  1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species montanum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>25.</number>
  <discussion>Dicranum montanum is one of the smallest species of the genus in North America.  It can best be recognized by the small plants, often only 1–2 cm, the dull, yellowish green to dark green leaves that are strongly crisped when dry, the lanceolate, acuminate leaves that are subtubulose to keeled above, rough on the abaxial surface near the apex, and the straight, erect capsules.  Also aiding in its recognition is the occasional presence of small, delicate, clustered branchlets with linear leaves that are readily detachable (probably a means of asexual reproduction), which occur near the stem apices.  The detached leaves from the branchlets leave characteristic scars on the denuded portions.  Dicranum montanum can sometimes be mistaken for D. flagellare, its closest relative, especially when the latter species does not have its typical flagelliform branchlets in the leaf axils or when they have been overlooked.  Dicranum montanum has leaves with a keeled subula in the distal half, with a strongly papillose or toothed abaxial surface near the apex and distal leaf cells that are regularly quadrate.  Dicranum flagellare, in contrast, has leaves with a tubulose subula above, with the abaxial surface usually smooth, and mostly short-rectangular leaf cells.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
