<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">SPHAGNUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1106.  1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 487.  1754  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus SPHAGNUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek sphagnos, an unknown plant]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Species 285 (89 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The concept of species in Sphagnum is controversial.  We have followed P. Isoviita (1966) and K. I. Flatberg (1994) in the recognition of species.  H. A. Crum (1984) and others (R. E. Daniels and A. Eddy 1985; A. L. Andrews 1958, 1959) have adopted more conservative taxonomic concepts for species in the Northern Hemisphere.  Description of the spores above is from Cao T. and D. H. Vitt (1986); for additional discussion of the protonema see C. B. McQueen (1988).</discussion>
  <discussion>Microscopic features can be observed by using a concentrated aqueous or alcohol solution of Crystal Violet.  A 50% solution of alcohol and Methylene Blue or Safranin Red can be used, but these usually do not stain features such as minute pores, fibrils, wall thinnings, and surface sculpture on the chlorophyllous cells.  The number and kinds of branches should be determined, individual stem and branch leaves (from the middle of a spreading branch) should be examined from the distal 2 cm of the plant, and the superficial surface of stem cortical cells as well as cross sections of branch leaves and stems may need examination.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Crum, H. A. 1984. Sphagnaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Ser. 2, part 11.</reference>
    <reference>Daniels, R. E. and A. Eddy. 1985. Handbook of European Sphagna. Huntingdon.</reference>
    <reference>Queen, C. B. 1990. Field Guide to the Peat Mosses of Boreal North America. London.</reference>
    <reference>Crum, H. A. 1986. Sphagnaceae. In: G. S. Mogensen, ed. Illustrated moss flora of arctic North America and Greenland. 2. Meddel. Grønland, Biosci. 18: 1–61.</reference>
    <reference>Flatberg, K. I. 2002. The Norwegian Sphagna: A Field Colour Guide. Trondheim.</reference>
    <reference>Isoviita, P. 1966. Studies on Sphagnum L. 1. Nomenclatural revision of the European taxa. Ann. Bot. Fenn. 3: 199–264.</reference>
    <reference>Nyholm, E. 1954–1969. Illustrated Moss Flora of Fennoscandia II: Musci. Lund. Pp. 647–799.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer stem cortical cell walls reinforced with spiral fibrils</description>
      <determination>1a.   Sphagnum sect. Sphagnum, p. 48</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer stem cortical cell walls smooth.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer cortical cells of branches nearly all porose at distal end; branch leaves with denticulate margins and bordered with resorption furrow</description>
      <determination>1b.   Sphagnum sect. Rigida, p. 55</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer cortical cells of branches of two kinds, smaller aporose cells and larger retort-shaped cells with pore at apical end; branch leaf margins usually entire.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fascicles of 7 or more branches</description>
      <determination>1h.   Sphagnum sect. Polyclada, p. 85</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fascicles of 6 or fewer branches.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaf hyaline cells efibrillose, but see  46. S. splendens in sect. Cuspidata</description>
      <determination>1e.   Sphagnum sect. Isocladus, p. 60</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaf hyaline cells fibrillose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch and stem leaves isophyllous; branches in fascicles of 2–3, spreading and pendent branches similar, or plants may have single or no branches; hyaline cells of branch leaves usually with numerous pores along the commissures, giving a bead-like appearance; chlorophyllous cells of branch leaves in transverse section barrel-shaped, truncate-elliptic to trapezoidal, exposed equally on both surfaces or slightly broader on the convex surface</description>
      <determination>1g.   Sphagnum sect. Subsecunda (in part), p. 78</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch and stem leaves usually anisophyllous; 3–6 branches per fascicle, spreading branches clearly differentiated from pendent branches; hyaline cells of branch leaves with scattered pores along the commissures or free; chlorophyllous cells of branch leaves in transverse section triangular, truncate-trapezoidal to elliptical and may be more broadly exposed on either surface.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaf chlorophyllous cells triangular to trapezoidal, exposed much more broadly on concave or convex surface.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Chlorophyllous cells of branch leaves triangular to trapezoidal in transverse section, more broadly exposed on the convex surface; in plants with stellate capitula, the branches between the rays of the capitulum occur in pairs; stem leaves often hanging downward on the stem</description>
      <determination>1f.   Sphagnum sect. Cuspidata, p. 61</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Chlorophyllous cells of branch leaves triangular to trapezoidal in transverse section, more broadly exposed on the concave surface; in plants with stellate capitula, the branches between the rays of the capitulum single; stem leaves upright on the stem</description>
      <determination>1i.   Sphagnum sect. Acutifolia, p. 85</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaf chlorophyllous cells lenticular, truncate-elliptic to trapezoidal; exposed more or less equally on both surfaces or slightly more broadly on convex surface.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves with apex broad and fimbriate; branch leaves often squarrose from an enlarged clasping base; interior surface of chlorophyllous cells often finely papillose</description>
      <determination>1d.   Sphagnum sect. Squarrosa, p. 58</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves with apex obtuse and entire to erose; branch leaves straight, slightly subsecund, or slightly recurved; interior surface of chlorophyllous cells always smooth.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves with broad truncate toothed apex, hyaline cells with pores in cell ends and angles</description>
      <determination>1c.   Sphagnum sect. Insulosa, p. 57</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branch leaves with rounded, untoothed or weakly toothed apex, hyaline cells on convex surface with numerous pores along commissures or free</description>
      <determination>1g.   Sphagnum sect. Subsecunda (in part), p. 78</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
