<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>William A. Weber</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">dicranaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bridel" date="1826">OREAS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Univ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 380.  1826  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dicranaceae;genus OREAS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek Oread, mythological nymph of hills and mountains, alluding to alpine habitat]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in dense cushions, yellow-green distally, brown and compacted with red-brown radicles proximally.  Stems forked.  Leaves erect-spreading, crisped when dry, lance-acuminate, keeled, ending in a sharp, hyaline cell or short point; margins 2-stratose and narrowly revolute nearly to the apex, entire or somewhat irregular; costa prominent at base, smooth, ending near the leaf apex, entire to shortly excurrent; distal cells irregularly rounded-quadrate, smooth, thick-walled; basal cells narrowly rectangular, thick-walled, the alar cells not differentiated.  Sexual condition autoicous; perigonial buds minute, at base of perichaetium; perichaetial leaves similar to stem leaves, ending in a short, hyaline awn.  Seta straight or somewhat curved when dry, cygneous when moist, yellow.  Capsule mostly erect when dry, pendent when moist, short-necked, symmetric, subglobose but becoming broader at the mouth and somewhat contracted at the middle when dry, orange-brown, strongly ribbed; annulus persistent; operculum obliquely rostrate from a convex base; peristome teeth inserted slightly below the mouth, lance-acuminate, brown at base, entire or occasionally somewhat perforated, rarely cleft, yellowish brown above, pale at the slender tips, vertically striolate throughout.  Calyptra cucullate, smooth.  Spores warty-papillose, brown.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Europe, Asia.</description>
  <number>14.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Oreas much resembles Cynodontium, but has a cygneous seta (when moist) and symmetric capsules.  European specimens are more slender, with shorter leaves, but the differences are not significant.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Steere, W. C.  1958.  The discovery of Oreas martiana in arctic Alaska, a genus new to North America.  Bryologist 61: 119–124.</reference>
    <reference>Weber, W. A.  1960.  A second American record for Oreas martiana, from Colorado.  Bryologist 63: 241–244.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
