<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>15.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>PARALEUCOBRYUM</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>(Lindberg ex Limpricht) Loeske</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Allg. Bot. Z. Syst.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 162. 1907 ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[Greek para-, near, and genus Leucobryum, alluding to resemblance]</etymology>
  <author>Robert R. Ireland Jr.</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Dicranum</genus_name>
    <subgenus_name>Paraleucobrym</subgenus_name>
    <subgenus_authority>Lindberg ex Limpricht</subgenus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in G. L. Rabenhorst et al., Krypt.-Fl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 4(1): 373. 1886</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants in loose to dense tufts, whitish green, grayish green or yellowish green,
        glossy. Stems 1–4 cm, erect, simple or branched, rhizoids on stems below apex among leaves.
        Leaves subulate to narrowly lanceolate, gradually acuminate, subtubulose distally,
        erect-spreading to falcate-secund, especially at stem tips, little changed when dry, smooth;
        apices acute, sometimes deciduous; margins plane or incurved, serrate to serrulate distally
        to below leaf middle; laminae unistratose; costa single, percurrent, covering 1/2–2/3 of
        leaf base and all of subula, smooth or striate on abaxial surface, absent stereids, composed
        of 3–4 layers of large cells, hyaline, nonchlorophyllose cells intermingled with green,
        chlorophyllose cells, striations or ridges appearing as rows of teeth at high magnifications
        on abaxial surface of costa (P. longifolium); leaf cells pitted proximally, smooth, walls of
        medium thickness, median cells quadrate to rectangular, elongate proximally, alar cells
        inflated, extending to costa, 1-stratose, brown or sometimes hyaline. Specialized asexual
        propagation absent. Sexual condition dioicous; perigonia and perichaetia terminal;
        perigonial leaves ovate, concave, short-acuminate; perichaetial leaves with a broad base,
        abruptly narrowed to a long awn, inner ones sheathing. Seta solitary or rarely 2 per
        perichaetium, smooth, elongate, erect, straight to flexuose, twisted when dry, yellowish
        brown. Capsule erect to somewhat inclined, cylindric, straight, smooth, irregularly furrowed
        when dry, a few stomata at base, exothecial walls incrassate; annulus rudimentary; operculum
        rostrate, straight; peristome single, 16 lanceolate teeth, divided about halfway into 2
        segments, papillose above, vertically to obliquely striate below, brown to reddish brown.
        Spores 22–33 µm, spherical to ellipsoidal, minutely papillose. Calyptra cucullate, smooth,
        naked, covering most of capsule, fugacious.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 or 4 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Asia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Paraleucobryum is a rather peculiar member of the Dicranaceae because of its unique
        leaf structure. In the leaf cross section there is an adaxial and abaxial layer of
        hyalocysts and a median layer of chlorocysts. Sometimes a few chlorocysts are in the abaxial
        layer of cells in some species. Brothera and Atractylocarpus have a very similar leaf
        structure and are the reason that the three genera are often placed in the same subfamily,
        Paraleucobryoideae. Both B. H. Allen (1999) and P. Müller and J.-P. Frahm (1987) presented
        extensive discussion on the relationship of Paraleucobryum to other members of the
        Dicranaceae. They also discuss what may be heterospory or bimodal spores in P.
        longifolium.</discussion>
  <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES">
    <reference>Allen, B. H. 1999. The genus Paraleucobryum (Musci: Dicranaceae) in Maine.
            Evansia 16: 174–178.</reference>
    <reference>Barnes, C. 1958. The genus Paraleucobryum. Bryologist 61: 335–339.</reference>
    <reference>Ireland, R. R. 1994. Paraleucobryum. In: A. J. Sharp et al., eds. The moss flora
            of Mexico. Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 69: 147–148.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Costa with longitudinal striations, formed by rows of teeth evident at high
                magnifications, on abaxial surface (especially conspicuous in distal half); leaf
                margins serrulate near apex</statement>
      <determination>1. Paraleucobryum longifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Costa smooth on abaxial surface; leaf margins entire or rarely with a few
                teeth at apex</statement>
      <determination>2. Paraleucobryum enerve</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
