<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Paraleucobryum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Ehrhart ex Hedwig) Loeske" date="unknown">longifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hedwigia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>47: 171. 1908,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Paraleucobryum;species longifolium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ehrhart ex Hedwig" date="unknown">longifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>130. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species longifolium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Campylopus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">canadensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Campylopus;species canadensis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dicranum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kindberg" date="unknown">serratum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dicranum;species serratum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Paraleucobryum longifolium is best distinguished by its 4–8 mm, whitish green to
        grayish green, glossy leaves that are falcate-secund, particularly at stem tips, slenderly
        subulate with margins usually serrulate in distal half. The costa has conspicuous fine
        striations or ridges, formed by small teeth when viewed at high magnifications, that are
        especially noticeable in the distal half even at low magnifications with a dissecting
        microscope. The capsules are common, 1.5–3 mm, erect, cylindric, straight, smooth, with a
        1–2 mm long-rostrate operculum. This species and the next somewhat resemble a Dicranum
        because of the falcate-secund leaves. The species was reported from Alabama and Ohio by P.
        Müller and J.-P. Frahm (1987).</discussion>
  <discussion>Paraleucobryum sauteri (Bruch &amp; Schimper) Loeske has been considered a synonym
        by some bryologists (e.g., C. Barnes 1958; E. Lawton 1971). Gametophytically, it is
        distinguished by the costa (R. S. Williams 1913, as Dicranum sauteri Bruch &amp; Schimper;
        P. Müller and J.-P. Frahm 1987) that is less than 1/3 the width of the leaf base compared to
        the costa that is more than 1/2 the width of the leaf base in P. longifolium, which also
        means more rows of laminal cells in P. sauteri than in P. longifolium. Müller and Frahm
        further distinguished P. sauteri by its leaf cross section which has large median cells
        compared to the smaller adaxial and abaxial layers of cells. Paraleucobryum longifolium, in
        contrast, according to them, has small median cells in comparison to the larger adaxial and
        abaxial layers of cells. They also found that the peristome teeth of P. longifolium are
        divided only to the middle and inserted at the mouth, whereas in P. sauteri the teeth are
        divided nearly to the base and inserted below the mouth of the capsule. Williams also used a
        peristome difference to distinguish the two taxa. He found that in P. sauteri the peristome
        teeth are punctate or nearly smooth on the exterior surface, whereas they are obliquely
        striate in P. longifolium. Müller and Frahm reported specimens of P. sauteri only for
        western North America through the Rocky Mountains from British Columbia to Colorado, South
        Dakota, Arizona and New Mexico. I have found the costa width in P. longifolium, however, to
        be quite variable in plants in eastern North America but some of the western North American
        plants do have a narrow costa that fits the description of P. sauteri. I also could not
        confirm the cross section difference between the two taxa in the few North American
        specimens that could be referred to P. sauteri. I have decided not to recognize P. sauteri
        for this flora because I believe that a detailed study of the P. longifolium-P. sauteri
        complex is necessary, especially in regard to the plants from the western part of the
        continent.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
