<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>47.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name>
    <species_name>tenellum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Bridel) Bory</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Voy. Îles Afrique.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 107.  1804,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name>
    <species_name>cymbifolium</species_name>
    <variety_name>tenellum</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Bridel</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Musc. Recent.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(1): 24.  1798</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name>
    <species_name>molluscum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Bruch</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants small, slender and weak-stemmed; pale yellow to golden brown, rarely tinged with red; capitulum not especially distinct.  Stems pale green to pale brown; superficial cortex of 2–3 layers of enlarged thin-walled cells.  Stem leaves ovate-lingulate; 1–1.3 mm, apex broadly rounded; hyaline cells nonseptate, aporose and fibrillose in at least distal half of leaf.  Branches 2–3 spreading and 2 pendent leaves not much elongated at distal end.  Branch stems green; cortex enlarged, with conspicuously long-necked retort cells.  Branch leaves ovate, 1–1.5 mm; straight; not or weakly undulate or recurved when dry; margins entire; hyaline cells short and wide, convex surface with 1–3 small pores per cell and on concave surface with large round wall thinnings in the cell angles; chlorophyllous cells equilateral-triangular in transverse section, broadly exposed on convex surface and just reaching to well-enclosed on concave surface.  Sexual condition monoicous.  Spores 27–42 µm; both surfaces smooth, proximal surface with distinct bifurcated Y-mark sculpture surrounded by distinct circular border, distal surface with distinct raised border around margins; proximal laesura usually less than 0.4 spore radius.</description>
  <phenology>Capsules mature early to mid summer.</phenology>
  <habitat>Wet depressions in a variety of ombrotropic and weakly minerotrophic habitats;</habitat>
  <elevation>low to high elevations;</elevation>
  <global_distribution>Greenland</global_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Man.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.B.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.S.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.J.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Eurasia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Sporophytes are common in Sphagnum tenellum.  The delicate appearance created by the ovate and concave branch leaves as well as the large concave stem leaves make this a usually unmistakeable species.</discussion>
</treatment>
