<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Wilfred B. Schofield</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">dicranaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="unknown">RHABDOWEISIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 97.  1846  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family dicranaceae; genus RHABDOWEISIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek rhabdos, rod, presumably alluding to ribbed capsule, and genus Weissia, alluding to resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in short loose tufts, perennial, dull green to brownish.  Stems 0.2–3 cm, erect, forked by innovations, red-brown, without central strand, rhizoids smooth, at base of stem.  Leaves oblong-lanceolate to narrowly lanceolate, obtuse to acute, keeled, strongly divergent when moist, crisped to sinuose when dry, 2–4 mm; costa subpercurrent, formed of rectangular cells; margins usually recurved, mainly serrate to serrulate along distal margins, with 1-celled irregular teeth; laminal cells smooth, proximal cells hyaline to brownish, rectangular, thin-walled, absent chlorophyll; distal cells, quadrate to irregular, usually broader than long, chlorophyllose except for the marginal teeth.  Specialized asexual reproduction absent.  Sexual condition autoicous; perigonial leaves short-elliptic; perichaetial leaves not differing from the vegetative.  Seta solitary, erect, yellow, 2–6 mm, smooth.  Capsule exserted, erect, brown to yellow-brown, 0.5–1 mm, symmetric, ovoid to oblong-cylindric, when dry and empty contracted below mouth and deeply 8-furrowed,; annulus absent; stomata at base of urn, phaneropore; operculum obliquely subulate, 0.5–1 mm; peristome single, 16 teeth joined by a low basal membrane, inserted slightly below mouth, irregular and not forked, early deciduous.  Calyptra cucullate, smooth, covering 1/2 of capsule.  Spores nearly spherical to slightly angled, smooth, 16–20 µm, papillose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia</description>
  <description type="morphology">Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pacific Islands.</description>
  <number>16.</number>
  <discussion>Species 6 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Rhabdoweisia is known predominately from the Northern Hemisphere.  A strong case has been made to include this, as well as other genera, in the family Rhabdoweisiaceae Limpricht.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Lawton, E.  1961.  A revision of the genus Rhabdoweisia.  Bryologist 64: 140–156.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves long-ligulate, 2–4 mm, broadly acute to obtuse, irregularly dentate in distal part, distal cells hexagonal, 14–20 µm wide, thin-walled relative to the lumina</description>
      <determination>1.   Rhabdoweisia crenulata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear-lanceolate, 2–3.5 mm, gradually and narrowly acute, serrulate in distal part, distal cells mainly quadrate, often wider than long, 10–14 µm wide, somewhat incrassate</description>
      <determination>2.   Rhabdoweisia crispata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
