<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>23.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>BRUCHIACEAE</genus_name><genus_authority>Schimper</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><author>Richard H. Zander</author><description>Plants minute or merely small, gregarious to densely tufted.  Stems erect, simple or branching, with a central strand.  Leaves mostly lanceolate or subulate, straight or somewhat curved, base oblong to ovate; in several rows; margins plane, entire or serrulate distally; costa single, well developed, subpercurrent to shortly excurrent as a sometimes roughened or denticulate subula, in section poorly differentiated or with 1 row of guide cells and 2 (sub-)stereid bands, adaxial band much reduced; lamina cells smooth or abaxially papillose; basal cells broader, narrower towards the margins, those of basal angles not differentiated or forming a marginal border; distal cells short- to long-rectangular, walls firm.  Specialized asexual reproduction not known.  Sexual condition autoicous or paroicous [dioicous]; perigonia axillary or on short branches adjacent to perichaetia or basal on the plant; perichaetial leaves usually differentiated, longer and somewhat sheathing.  Seta short to elongate, usually yellow or brown; capsules immersed to exerted, cylindric or obovate with a distinct inflated-tapering to elongate neck, erect to curved; cleistocarpous, gymnostomous, or peristomate; annulus, when present, usually of 2–3 rows of larger cells, commonly revoluble; peristome, when present, single, of 16 simple, forked, or perforate teeth; operculum,when present, obliquely long-rostrate.  Calyptra cucullate or mitrate.  Spores often large, spheric to ovoid or weakly reniform, finely to coarsely papillose, spiculate, reticulate, or pitted.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Genera 4, species ca. 140 (2 genera, 16 species in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> cosmopolitan</global_distribution><global_distribution> greatest occurrence in temperate regions.</global_distribution><discussion>Species of Bruchiaceae commonly occur on soil, often as colonizers.  The family was well-characterized by W. R. Buck (1979), who recognized four genera and suggested a transitional position between Dicranaceae and Ditrichaceae.  The two genera represented in the flora area are quite different but share the salient well-developed capsule neck.</discussion><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Britton, E. G.  1913c.  Bruchiaceae.  In: N. L. Britton et al., eds.  1905+.  North American Flora....  47+ vols.  New York.  Vol. 15, pp. 47–54.</reference><reference>   Buck, W. R.  1979.  A re-evaluation of the Bruchiaceae with the description of a new genus.  Brittonia 31: 469–473.</reference></references><key><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Capsule cleistocarpic, immersed to short-exserted, neck conic to ovate</statement><determination>1.   Bruchia, p. 434</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Capsule stegocarpic, long-exserted, neck conic to long-cylindric</statement><determination>2.   Trematodon, p. 437</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
