<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Ceratodon</genus_name><species_name>heterophyllus</species_name><species_authority>Kindberg</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Ottawa Naturalist </publication_title><place_in_publication>5: 179.  1892,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Ceratodon</genus_name><species_name>purpureus</species_name><variety_name>obtusifolius</variety_name><variety_authority>Limpricht</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Ceratodon</genus_name><species_name>purpureus</species_name><variety_name>rotundifolius</variety_name><variety_authority>Berggren</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants in dense tufts or mats, green to dark green to brownish green.  Stems 0.3–1 cm.  Leaves loosely imbricate, somewhat contorted when dry, ovate to ovate-lanceolate, concave and often somewhat cucullate, (0.35–)0.5–0.9(–1.5) mm, margins plane to weakly recurved, often only at mid-leaf, and entire to, rarely, weakly toothed distally, apices obtuse; most costae ending before apex; medial laminal cells (9–)12–16(–22) µm, thin-walled to somewhat thickened.  Seta (0.9–)1.5(–2.5) cm, red.  Capsule ovate-cylindric to, occasionally, ovate, (0.9–)1–1.2(–1.5) mm, strongly sulcate when dry; peristome segments free at their nodes, finely papillose, dark red with pale borders to, rarely, completely pale.  Spores (18–)19–21(–22) µm.</description><phenology>Capsules mature early summer–late fall.</phenology><habitat>  Sandy, usually moist soil, Arctic habitats;</habitat><elevation> low elevations (0–200 m);</elevation><global_distribution> Greenland</global_distribution><ca_distribution> N.W.T.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Yukon</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Alaska</us_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia.</global_distribution><discussion>In Northwest Territories, Ceratodon heterophyllus is found only on Prince Patrick Island.</discussion><discussion>Ceratodon heterophyllus has also been treated as C. purpureus forma heterophyllus (Kindberg) Britton, and R. R. Ireland (1980) considered it to be a variety of C. purpureus, but J. S. Burley and N. M. Pritchard (1990) provided ample evidence that it is a distinct species.  The broadly ovate leaves of C. heterophyllus grade into some alpine variations of C. purpureus.</discussion><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCE"><reference>Ireland, R. R.  1980.  The taxonomic status of Ceratodon heterophyllus.  Bryologist 83: 234–237.</reference></references></treatment>
