<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Rodney D. Seppelt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="unknown">DISTICHIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 153.  1846  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus DISTICHIUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek distichos, in two rows, alluding to leaves]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants slender, elongate, in dense tomentose tufts, yellowish green to dark green.  Stems 1–6 cm, simple or branched; rhizoids from base to middle of stem forming a conspicuous tomentum.  Leaves distichous, linear subula spreading from erect, whitish ovate-lanceolate or oblong sheathing base,  margins plane to slightly incurved, becoming denticulate in subula particularly near the apex; costa excurrent, occupying most of subula, 1/4–1/3 width of leaf at base, subula roughened abaxially; lamina cells of sheathing base linear to oblong-linear, linear-flexuose or rectangular, becoming rectangular distally and quadrate to short-rectangular in subula.  Specialized asexual reproduction unknown.  Sexual condition autoicous, paroicous or synoicous; perigonia axillary, or on short branches proximal to perichaetium; perichaetial leaves not differentiated.  Seta yellow-brown to reddish, elongate, erect.  Capsule erect and symmetric or inclined and asymmetric, exserted, brown, cylindric to ovoid-cylindric, ± wrinkled when dry and empty; annulus of 2–3 rows of large, pale cells, deciduous; operculum conic, straight; peristome single, teeth16, variously split to near the base into 2(–3) minutely papillose filaments, teeth sometimes arranged in 8 groups of 2 teeth.  Calyptra cucullate.  Spores globose to ovoid, finely papillose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">worldwide.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Species 14 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Distichium capillaceum var. curvatum Flowers was described as a probable hybrid between D. capillaceum and D. inclinatum, characterized by capsule cylindric and strongly curved, and spores 20–23 µm.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsule erect, cylindric, straight to slightly arcuate, spores 15–25 µm</description>
      <determination>1.   Distichium capillaceum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsule inclined, ovoid to oblong-ovoid, spores more than 25 µm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Peristome with a yellowish to hyaline basal membrane uniting teeth into 8 separated groups each of 2 teeth</description>
      <determination>2.   Distichium hagenii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Peristome of 16, evenly spaced, irregularly divided or perforate teeth</description>
      <determination>3.   Distichium inclinatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
