<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Rodney D. Seppelt,Robert R. Ireland Jr.,Harold Robinson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hampe" date="unknown">DITRICHUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>50: 181.  1867,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus DITRICHUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek di-, two, and trichos, hair, alluding to peristome split longitudinally into two segments]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants in loose to dense tufts, green to yellowish green distally, yellow-brown to brown proximally.  Stems short or reaching 2 cm or more, simple or sometimes with a few branches; rhizoids at base, smoth.  Leaves rigid to flexuose or sometimes somewhat falcate when dry, erect-spreading when wet, lanceolate to subulate from a more or less sheathing base; margins entire throughout or denticulate near the apex; costa  percurrent or excurrent, occupying most of subula, 1/6–1/3 width of leaf base, 1 row of guide cells, 2 stereid bands, adaxial stereid band sometimes weak, rarely absent; medial lamina cells quadrate to short-rectangular, becoming longer and thinner-walled proximally toward margins, smooth or rarely papillose at both ends.  Specialized asexual reproduction occasionally by rhizoidal tubers.  Sexual condition monoicous or dioicous; perichaetial leaves usually with a longer and more or less sheathing base and shorter subulate than stem leaves.  Seta pale yellow to dark reddish brown, elongate, erect or flexuose.  Capsule mostly erect and symmetric, sometimes ± inclined and arcuate, exserted, ovoid to cylindric, smooth; annulus present, deciduous; operculum conic to short-rostrate; peristome single, teeth16, split into 2 filiform segments or sometimes irregularly perforate or split, with or without a short basal membrane, papillose to spiculose.  Calyptra cucullate.  Spores globose, very finely papillose, verrucose, or with somewhat vermicular ornamentation.</description>
  <description type="morphology">worldwide</description>
  <description type="morphology">including maritime Antarctic region.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 90 (11 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Ditrichum occurs from near sea level up to montane regions, on a wide range of soils, but is found occasionally on rock; some species are calciphilic.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants densely tufted, stems ± tomentose proximally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 1–4 cm; leaves to 3 mm, from an ovate-sheathing base sharply contracted to the subula; costa abaxially strongly convex; lamina cells near costa with weakly nodulose longitudinal walls; plants commonly fruiting</description>
      <determination>2.   Ditrichum flexicaule</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems to 7 cm or more; leaves from an elongate-ovate base tapering gradually to the long slender subula; costa abaxially weakly convex; basal laminal cells with weakly to strongly nodulose longitudinal walls; rarely found fruiting</description>
      <determination>3.   Ditrichum gracile</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants loosely to densely tufted or gregarious; stems, if tomentose, only so at extreme base.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">In cross section, distal leaf lamina partially 1-stratose with 2-stratose margins.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves erect-appressed to erect-patent when moist.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves oblong-lanceolate, widest proximally to middle, tapering to a blunt apex; lamina cells thin-walled, rectangular throughout, slightly shorter and narrower towards apex; seta to 2.5 cm, yellowish to orange-brown, erect; peristome teeth 200–220 µm, perforate, divided into 2 adhering filaments, finely papillose</description>
      <determination>5.   Ditrichum lineare</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves lanceolate to linear-lanceolate, gradually acuminate; lamina cells ± incrassate, subquadrate to short-rectangular distally, elongate-rectangular proximally; seta to 1.5 cm, reddish with age; peristome teeth 200–250 µm, the filaments finely and obliquely ridged and lightly papillose</description>
      <determination>8.   Ditrichum pusillum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves erect-spreading when moist.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems fastigiately branched from base, dichotomous distally; leaves linear-lanceolate, margins subserrulate distally, apex coarsely toothed; seta to 2.5 cm, pale yellow; capsule straight and erect or slightly curved, orange- to dark red-brown at maturity, elliptical, narrowed at mouth, 2–3 mm, flattened when dry; peristome teeth 600–800 µm, spiculose-papillose; autoicous</description>
      <determination>6.   Ditrichum montanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem branching distally from base; leaves lanceolate to linear-lanceolate, margins entire to serrulate distally, apex weakly toothed; seta shorter, 0.8–2 cm, red to orange-brown; capsule symmetric to slightly curved, 1–3 mm, not flattened when dry; peristome teeth 200–500 µm, papillose to spiculose; dioicous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems to 2 cm, often branched; leaves 1.5–4.5 mm, apex entire or serrulate, margins broadly recurved from base to leaf middle; leaf cross section 2-stratose on margins and sometimes near costa; seta 1.5–2 cm, red; capsule usually symmetric, straight and erect, rarely curved, 1.5–3 mm long, dark brown to reddish; peristome teeth 200–500 µm, twisted when dry</description>
      <determination>1.   Ditrichum ambiguum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems to 0.5 cm, seldom branched; leaves 1–3 mm, apex serrulate, margins plane or narrowly recurved from above leaf base to leaf middle; leaf cross section 2-stratose only at or near margins; seta 0.8–1.2 cm, orange-yellow, brownish or reddish; capsule usually asymmetric, erect, curved, 1–2 mm, yellow or light brown; peristome teeth 200 µm, nearly straight</description>
      <determination>11.   Ditrichum tortuloides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">In cross section, distal leaf lamina 2-stratose from costa to margins.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves 1.5–3 mm, from an ovate to oblong base gradually tapered to a channelled subula, erect-patent to subsecund; dioicous</description>
      <determination>4.   Ditrichum heteromallum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem leaves longer, 3–7 mm, long-subulate from an ovate to short-rectangular base, spreading, flexuose to subsecund; autoicous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves to 5 mm; seta to 2.5 cm, orange-yellow, becoming reddened at maturity; capsule ovoid-cylindric, ± asymmetric and slightly curved, pale brown, suberect, flattened when dry; peristome teeth to 1500 µm, densely spiculose-papillose; spores yellow-brown, 11–19 µm, vermicular papillose-verrucose</description>
      <determination>9.   Ditrichum rhynchostegium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 3–7 mm; seta 1–3 cm, yellow or becoming reddish brown at the base when mature; capsules subcylindric to cylindric, not flattened when dry; peristome teeth to 800 µm, finely papillose to spiculose-papillose; spores brown, 15–30 µm, coarsely roughened-papillose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves long-subulate from a short-ovoid sheathing base; seta to 2.5 cm, yellow, becoming reddened at the base with maturity; capsule suberect, subcylindric, 1–2.5 mm; peristome teeth pale brown to orange-brown, 300–800 µm, spiculose- papillose; spores 15–30 µm</description>
      <determination>7.   Ditrichum pallidum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves narrow filiform-subulate from an ovate-lanceolate sheathing base; seta 1–3 cm, yellow; capsule cylindric, 1.5–3 mm; peristome teeth pale yellow-brown, to 300 µm, irregularly perforate, finely papillose; spores 20–30 µm</description>
      <determination>10.   Ditrichum schimperi</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
