<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ditrichum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Schwägrichen) Hampe" date="unknown">flexicaule</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>50: 182.  1867,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ditrichum;species flexicaule;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cynodontium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">flexicaule</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond. Suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(1): 113, plate 29.  1811</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cynodontium;species flexicaule;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Ditrichum flexicaule in the broad sense (including D. gracile) is exceedingly variable in morphology, not only in North America (A. J. Grout 1928–1940, vol. 1, part 1; H. A. Crum and L. E. Anderson 1981) but throughout the world (R. D. Seppelt 1982; A. A. Frisvoll 1985).  While many workers have treated the variation and the described variant taxa as one highly polymorphic species (Crum and Anderson; M. F. V. Corley et al. 1981), others (Frisvoll; E. Nyholm 1986+, fasc. 1; I. Novotny 1996) have recognized two principal entities, D. flexicaule and D. crispatissimum (= D. crinale (Taylor) Kuntze).  We have followed this latter interpretation.  A comprehensive molecular analysis of the group would be highly desirable.  Crum and Anderson related all variation in habit and microscopic details to environmental conditions, particularly shade and moisture.  Frisvoll differentiated two taxa largely on the basis of gametophytic features.  Notwithstanding the considerable variability exhibited by these taxa, we also consider them distinct.  While often found infertile, D. flexicaule is more commonly found with sporophytes than is D. gracile.  Both are calciphiles.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
