<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>William R. Buck</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Wilson" date="unknown">ECCREMIDIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>London J. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 450.  1846  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus ECCREMIDIUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek ekkremes, hanging, and -idium, diminutive, alluding to pendulous capsule]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants scattered or in loose to compact turfs, mostly yellowish green, sometimes reddish.  Stems erect, to ca. 0.5 mm, sometimes seemingly absent; simple or branched by innovations; rhizoids at base, smooth.  Leaves imbricate to spreading when dry, lanceolate to ovate, acute to subulate; margins plane, entire or serrate; costa subpercurrent to excurrent, sometimes weak or absent toward insertion and in lowermost leaves,  medial laminal cells rhomboidal to short-rectangular, becoming longer toward the insertion, smooth.  Specialized asexual reproduction unknown.  Sexual condition autoicous or dioicous, cladocarpous; perichaetial leaves sometimes differentiated.  Seta short, curved at apex, rarely ± erect.  Capsule pendulous and laterally emergent, rarely erect and immersed, reddish at maturity, subglobose; annulus near midurn, of 1–2 rows of small cells, persistent; operculum obtuse to apiculate; peristome none.  Calyptra conic-mitrate, entire at base or crenate-lobed.  Spores globose to reniform, coarsely papillose to reticulate.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia</description>
  <description type="morphology">Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Australia.</description>
  <number>7.</number>
  <discussion>Species 6 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Crum, H. A.  1981.  Eccremidium, a genus of Ditrichaceae new to the Americas.  Bryologist 84: 527–532.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
