<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Müller Hal." date="unknown">erpodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Müller Hal." date="1875">venturiella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Ventenat) Müller Hal." date="1875">sinensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Griffin" date="1985">angusti-annulata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>57: 58.  1985,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family erpodiaceae;genus venturiella;species sinensis;variety angusti-annulata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants irregularly branched, in dense mats.  Leaves to 1.2 mm; laminal cells smooth, distal cells rhomboidal, 38–57 × 15–18 µm, proximal cells quadrate to oblate in several marginal rows.  Perichaetial leaves ovate, long-acuminate.  Seta short, 0.5 mm.  Capsule 1.5–1.8 mm; annulus narrow, 57–69 µm wide, in 4 rows of quadrate to octagonal cells.  Calyptra 0.6 mm.  Spores 21–30 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Dry areas on trunks and limbs of trees;</description>
  <description type="morphology">moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ark.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Okla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tex.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Dry areas on trunks and limbs of trees; moderate elevations; Ark., Okla., Tex.</text>
    <parsed>
      <habitat>Dry areas on trunks and limbs of trees;</habitat>
      <elevation>moderate elevations;</elevation>
      <distribution>Ark., Okla., Tex.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>1a.</number>
  <discussion>In the flora area, Venturiella sinensis is known only from from Stone County in Arkansas, Blaine, Cherokee, Comanche, Payne, and Washita counties in Oklahoma, and Culberson County in Texas.  G. J. Ikenberry et al. (1960) reported the species found on an elm tree near the campus of Oklahoma State University in Stillwater.</discussion>
  <discussion>Venturiella sinensis is the only Erpodiaceae in North America with a well developed peristome; the other species, Wildia solmsiellacea, occurs in Australia and New Caledonia.  D. G. Griffin and A. J. Sharp (1971) in a comparison of North American and Asian collections of V. sinensis recognized two varieties, based primarily on a difference in the width of the annuli (57–69 µm in North American specimens vs. 69–129 µm in Asian specimens).  In addition, the annular cells of North American plants are quadrate to octagonal while in the Asian plants the distal tiers of annular cells are usually ellipsoidal to rhomboidal.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
