<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eucladium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Bridel) Bruch &amp; Schimper" date="unknown">verticillatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Europ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 93.  1846,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eucladium;species verticillatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Weissia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">verticillata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. (Schrader)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1800(1): 283.  1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Weissia;species verticillata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Eucladium verticillatum is associated with yearround seepage, possibly the reason that, although the stem may be reduced, the leaves are seldom reduced as they frequently are in drought-tolerant species of the family.  The plants are typically a yellow-green, and there is usually a vivid contrast between the pellucid green laminal cells and the clear basal ones.  Stem hyalodermis cells are frequently attached to the costa base, and form decurrencies of long and thin-walled cells in the leaf angles when leaves are removed.  Gymnostomum and Molendoa are similar plants but differ by blunt apices and subpercurrent costae.  Both these genera possess a stem central strand, no hyalodermis, and occasional 2-stratose areas in the lamina.  Eucladium may be separated from these taxa and others that may be mistaken for it, such as Hymenostylium and Anoectangium by its highly differentiated bulging or lax, thin-walled basal cells.  Assurances in the literature to the contrary, many other taxa also possess serrulate or denticulate leaf-shoulder margins, especially Hymenostylium, while Eucladium may rarely lack such serrulations.  Specimens of Eucladium in which the lamina is highly reduced so that the leaves seem entirely costate are included without special rank in the range of variation of the species in North America.  The laminal papillae of Hymenostylium are clear, sharp, well-defined; those of Eucladium are low, amorphous or scablike on the lumen surface.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
