<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>2.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Trichostomum</genus_name>
    <species_name>planifolium</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Dixon) R. H. Zander</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Buffalo Soc. Nat. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>32: 92. 1993,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Weissia</genus_name>
    <species_name>planifolia</species_name>
    <species_authority>Dixon</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>55: 179, fig. 1. 1928</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Trichostomum</genus_name>
    <species_name>perligulatum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(H. A. Crum) R. H. Zander</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Weissia</genus_name>
    <species_name>perligulata</species_name>
    <species_authority>H. A. Crum</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Weissia</genus_name>
    <species_name>sweetii</species_name>
    <species_authority>E. B. Bartram</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Stem rounded-pentagonal in section. Leaves flattened, ovate to elliptical, distal
        margins plane or weakly erect or rarely broadly involute, entire, not bordered; apex rounded
        or rounded-acute, plane to weakly concave, keeled or cucullate; basal cells evenly
        differentiated across leaf base or as a U, only weakly running up margins if at all, not
        distinctly enlarged submarginally; distal laminal cells pluripapillose with low papillae;
        mucro short-conic, of 3–4 cells. Sexual condition autoicous. Peristome teeth absent to
        short-lanceolate.</description>
  <habitat>Soil, margins of boulders, rock crevices;</habitat>
  <elevation>moderate elevations;</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Colo.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia (China, Japan).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Trichostomum planifolium was synonymized with T. crispulum by A. Stoneburner (1985)
        and Stoneburner and R. Wyatt (1985), but is retained here because it is monoicous. The leaf
        margins are sometimes inflexed distally, as in Weissia, and it was synonymized with Weissia
        perligulata by L. R. Stark (1996), the type of which has weakly inflexed or laxly involute
        distal leaf margins. The costa of T. planifolium and the similar T. brachydontium is quite
        thick and protrudes strongly abaxially. The gametophyte of Trichostomum planifolium is
        essentially that of T. brachydontium. It differs from Weissia inoperculata in having a
        slightly shorter apiculus, in addition to the stegocarpic capsule. Some plants of the type
        of W. perligulata (= T. planifolium) have comparatively very wide leaves with costa ending
        below the broadly rounded apex, yet other plants have leaves with costae that are percurrent
        or shortly excurrent from an obtuse or rounded acute apex, and in all leaves the papillae
        are large and short-spiculose, though not as salient as those of specimens assigned to W.
        andersoniana (= W. ligulifolia); S. Flowers (1973) suspected that W. ligulifolia and W.
        perligulata are synonymous, but found sexual differences between them on the basis of a few
        specimens; here the former is distinguished by the strongly involute distal laminal margins
        and distal lamina ca. 12–18 cells across on one side of the costa just above mid leaf versus
        margins plane or weakly incurved to laxly inflexed, and lateral lamina 25–30 cells across
        for T. planifolium.</discussion>
</treatment>
