<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Sullivant" date="unknown">lescurii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray, Manual ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 611.  1856,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species lescurii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Warnstorf" date="unknown">orlandense</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species orlandense;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Warnstorf" date="unknown">plicatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species plicatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="H. A. Crum" date="unknown">wieboldtii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species wieboldtii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>56.</number>
  <discussion>Sporophytes are uncommon in Sphagnum lescurii, which may be the most phenotypically variable of all the North American Sphagnum species, and quite probably deserves some taxonomic splitting.  The tremendous phenotypic plasticity of this species, however, makes it quite difficult to sort out the genotypic component of variability, and thus most sphagnologists since Warnstorf have avoided the temptation of splitting and have instead treated this as one very variable species.  This is the approach maintained in this treatment.  We have also chosen not to use the earlier name S. denticulatum because its type is a phenotypic morphotype not clearly assignable to the current concept of either S. auriculatum or S. lescurii (K. I. Flatberg, pers. comm.).  Some of the American material assignable to S. lescurii is quite likely the same as the European species S. auriculatum, but much of our material is certainly not the same.  Until more definitive data are available, we have chosen to continue to use the name S. lescurii.  The large stem leaf will generally distinguish this from similar species of sect. Subsecunda. See also discussion under 55. S. inundatum and 61. S. platyphyllum.</discussion>
  <discussion>The names Sphagnum alabamae Warnstorf, S. aquatile Warnstorf, S. obesum (Wilson) Warnstorf, S. rufescens (Nees &amp; Hornschuch) Warnstorf, and S. turgidulum Warnstorf also have been applied to this taxon.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
