<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Patricia M. Eckel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Lindberg) Limpricht" date="unknown">TORTELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Laubm. Deutschl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 599. 1888,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae; genus TORTELLA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin tortus, twisted, and -ella, diminutive, alluding to peristome
        teeth]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Mollia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Lindberg" date="unknown">Tortella</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Musc. Scand.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21. 1879</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Mollia;subgenus Tortella;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small to medium-sized, in loose or dense tufts, mats or compact sods,
        fragile, dull green, yellowish to dark green distally, black, brown or tan proximally with
        prominent shining costae. Stems erect, often branched, in transverse section with
        hyalodermis, somewhat weak sclerodermis, central strand absent or present, rhizoids dense or
        few at the base, occasionally tomentose; axillary hairs long, 1-seriate, of 10–20 cells,
        hyaline. Stem leaves cirrhate-crispate to incurved when dry, spreading to recurved when
        moist, elongate-oblong to linear-lanceolate or linear-subulate, widest at or near the base;
        base hyaline, oblong, erect; margins plane to incurved distally, generally entire and
        minutely crenulate by projecting papillae, but often slightly or irregularly scalloped by
        indentations at points of laminal weakness, occasionally somewhat to strongly undulate,
        rarely with a border of elongate, clear, smooth cells in one series beyond midleaf,
        gradually tapering distally or more or less abruptly narrowed; apex acute or obtuse,
        cucullate or concave, with an apiculus, mucro or short subula; costa strong, percurrent to
        short-excurrent, adaxial and abaxial epidermal cells often present, often interrupted,
        adaxial and abaxial stereid bands and 1 layer of median guide cells present, hydroid strand
        occasionally present; proximal cells enlarged, laxly long-rectangular, thin-walled, hyaline,
        occasionally brown and rather thick-walled, smooth, abruptly differentiated from the green
        cells distally or gradual in transition, limit of the proximal region usually appears as a
        V, sometimes a U, often extending distally up each leaf margin as a short or elongated
        border; distal laminal cells medially and distally rounded-hexagonal, chlorophyllose,
        frequently obscured by numerous, dense, C-shaped papillae on both surfaces. Specialized
        asexual reproduction at the stem apex occasional, by deciduous or fragile propaguloid leaf
        tips, or by deterioration of fragile leaves along zones of laminal weakness. Sexual
        condition dioicous, occasionally autoicous; perigonia terminal, short-foliose to gemmate or
        as stalked buds in leaf axils of perichaetiate plants; perichaetia terminal, leaves not or
        little differentiated, or distinct and long-setaceous. Seta 1(–2) per perichaetium, yellow
        or reddish proximally with age, to 3 cm, erect, smooth. Capsule erect and symmetric or
        slightly inclined, yellow to reddish brown, darker red or brown at mouth, elliptic to
        cylindric, more or less wrinkled-plicate when dry and empty; annulus sometimes present, of
        1–4 rows of vesiculose cells, persistent; operculum conic or long-rostrate, half as long as
        the urn or longer, straight or inclined; peristome orange-red, single, with a low basal
        membrane, of 32 filiform rami joined at the base into 16 pairs, twisted counterclockwise or
        merely obliquely inclined, branched-spiculose, rarely nearly smooth. Calyptra cucullate,
        smooth. Spores 8–12(–20) µm, yellowish brown, moderately coarsely to finely papillose to
        nearly smooth.</description>
  <description type="morphology">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>7.</number>
  <discussion>Species 53 (7 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Trichostomum is similar to Tortella in leaf shape and margin flexion, but has distal
        laminal cells differentiated from the proximal cells in a line straight across the leaf base
        or in a low, poorly defined U shape, i.e., straight across but with some smooth, hyaline,
        elongated proximal cells extending up the leaf margins distal to the leaf shoulder. The
        proximal-cell line of differentiation usually forms a distinct V shape in Tortella. The
        peristomes of Trichostomum are erect, often short and frequently smooth, whereas those of
        Tortella are long and twisted generally 2–3 times (only slightly so in T. flavovirens) and
        densely spiculose in noncleistocarpous species (see R. H. Zander 1993). In much of the
        literature the peristomes of Tortella are described as papillose, when they are actually
        spiculose.</discussion>
  <discussion>Pleurochaete does not have the V-shaped area of differentiated hyaline proximal
        echlorophyllose cells as with Tortella, but has a median area of gradually differentiated
        proximal cells and a strong border of several rows of cells contrasting with both laminal
        and proximal cells in being abruptly longer, thinner-walled, smooth and without chlorophyll.
        Pleurochaete also has perichaetia, in addition to perigonia, borne laterally on short
        branches on the main axis of the plant.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species in Weissia are similar to Tortella by the incurving leaf margins (generally
        strongly and sharply incurved throughout the leaf length) with a tendency toward cucullation
        in the leaf apex. The proximal cells of some Weissia species may extend slightly up the
        margins, as in species of Trichostomum, and most especially, Weissia jamaicensis resembles a
        Tortella by a proximal region with a V shape. In the following treatment, great emphasis has
        been put on the cross section of the distal region of the leaf in delimiting taxa and for
        discussing relationships.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Crundwell, A. C. and E. Nyholm. 1962. Notes on the genus Tortella. I. T.
            inclinata, T. densa, T. flavovirens and T. glareicola. Trans. Brit. Bryol. Soc. 4:
            187–193.</reference>
    <reference>Eckel, P. M. 1998. Re-evaluation of Tortella (Musci, Pottiaceae) in conterminous
            U.S.A. and Canada with a treatment of the European species Tortella nitida. Bull.
            Buffalo Soc. Nat. Sci. 36: 117–191.</reference>
    <reference>Haring, I. M. 1938. Tortella. In: A. J. Grout. 1928–1940. Moss Flora of North
            America, North of Mexico. 3 vols. in 12 parts. Newfane, Vt. and New York. Vol. 1, pp.
            165–170.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves oblong-lanceolate or elliptical, apex broadly acute to obtuse,
                sometimes cucullate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Autoicous, nearly always fruiting; distal margins plane to erect, apex
                broadly acute; distal leaf cells about 6–7 µm; central strand present; cells on
                adaxial surface of the costa quadrate and papillose throughout most of its length;
                stems short; plants typically rosulate, densely foliose</description>
      <determination>1. Tortella humilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Dioicous, seldom fruiting; distal margins incurved to strongly or variably
                cucullate at the apex, apex obtuse; distal leaf cells 7–11(–14) µm; central strand
                present or absent; cells on adaxial surface of the costa quadrate and papillose
                throughout most of their length or mostly or entirely elongate and smooth; stems
                elongate; plants loosely foliose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem central strand present; costa with adaxial epidermis: areas on the
                adaxial surface of the costa with quadrate papillose cells; leaf apex variably
                somewhat cucullate, acute or obtuse with apical margins incurved; leaves flat in the
                leaf middle, keeled distally; fertile perichaetial leaves not much differentiated;
                mosses exclusively of coastal North Carolina south to Florida and west to
                Texas</description>
      <determination>2. Tortella flavovirens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stem central strand absent; costa without adaxial epidermis: adaxial surface
                of the costa with smooth, elongate cells throughout the leaf length; leaf apex
                distinctly cucullate, occasionally acute, leaves tubulose; fertile perichaetial
                leaves conspicuously differentiated, with subulate tips; mosses of the Great Lakes
                region and north.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf cells 11–12 µm or less, stems orange to greenish yellow-brown, leaves
                deep yellow or orange in KOH; leaves irregularly or uniformly twisted on the stem;
                leaf apices usually cucullate to narrowly acute, not deciduous; leaves in section
                usually keeled at the costa, margins incurved; rock crevices or unconsolidated
                alluvial sediments near water</description>
      <determination>6. Tortella inclinata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf cells averaging 14 µm; stems dark green to brown, leaves green in KOH;
                leaves erect, twisted only at the stem tips; leaf apices variable, usually acute to
                acuminate, never uniformly cucullate, frequently with a narrowed apical deciduous
                point; leaves in section broadly tubulose; limestone pavements with thin soil cover
                in the Great Lakes region</description>
      <determination>7. Tortella rigens (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves narrowly short to long- or linear-lanceolate, not cucullate or obtuse,
                apex narrowly acute, tapering to an acuminate point, sometimes apex very long, with
                a long, setaceous point.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves with distinctive apical propaguloid modifications, leaf apices
                regularly fallen.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 1–5 cm, coarsely tomentose; central strand absent; distal leaves to 7
                mm, densely crowded, rigid, with patches of elongated, nonpapillose cells on distal
                leaf margins of young leaves at the stem apex; leaf cells 10–12 µm; lamina proximal
                to subula 2-stratose; apical propagula falling in a single rigid unit; subulate limb
                2- to multistratose</description>
      <determination>5. Tortella fragilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 0.5 to 1.5 cm, scarcely or not tomentose; central strand present;
                distal leaves 1.5–2 mm, sparse, soft, leaf tips without differentiated marginal
                cells; leaf cells 14 µm; lamina 1-stratose throughout; propaguloid leaves and apical
                propagula articulated by periodic constrictions, falling in several pieces; leaves
                2-stratose only in patches or along costa distally</description>
      <determination>3. Tortella alpicola (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves without apical propaguloid modifications although some apices may be
                somewhat fragile.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with central strand, leaf cells ca. 14 µm</description>
      <determination>3. Tortella alpicola (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems without central strand, or this rare, leaf cells to 14 µm but often
                less.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves tubulose, margins broadly incurved; most distal laminal cells 14 µm;
                quadrate, papillose adaxial cells on the surface of the costa absent throughout the
                leaf length to a width of two or three cells in section; leaf apices deciduous;
                limestone pavements in the Great Lakes region</description>
      <determination>7. Tortella rigens (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves plane to canaliculate, margins plane to erect; distal laminal cells
                seldom attaining 12 µm, usually less; quadrate, papillose adaxial cells on the
                surface of the costa present in the median leaf region or higher; of general
                temperate to</description>
      <determination>4. Tortella tortuosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
