<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Jennings" date="unknown">humilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Mosses W. Pennsylvania,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>96. 1913,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tortella;species humilis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Barbula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">humilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>116, plate 25, figs. 1–4. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Barbula;species humilis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Barbula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">caespitosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Barbula;species caespitosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Schwägrichen) Limpricht" date="unknown">caespitosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tortella;species caespitosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Uniquely among species of the genus in the flora area, except for var. arctica of
        Tortella tortuosa, in T. humilis the proximal laminal cells of the leaf are typically
        gradually differentiated from the distal cells with a zone of cells intermediate in color,
        cell size, cell wall thickness and papillosity, the angle of hyaline marginal cell
        differentiation typically shallow across the leaf base, then extending up the margins in a U
        shape. This character is typical of the genus Trichostomum, with which Tortella is closely
        allied. Small (depauperate) plants of T. flavovirens may share this character. Typical basal
        cell differentiation in Tortella is abrupt, the angle of differentiated cells steep, the
        proximal echlorophyllose and distal chlorophyllose cell boundary sharp.</discussion>
  <discussion>In cross section, the costa of Tortella humilis diminishes in size toward the leaf
        tip: sectioning distally along the leaf, the epidermal layer first disappears, leaving up to
        two stereid cells in width exposed. In some instances at the extreme apex, even the stereid
        layer disappears leaving the guide cells exposed. The well-developed peristome—elongate and
        conspicuously twisted—will distinguish Tortella humilis from specimens of T. flavovirens and
        Trichostomum species, whose peristomes are either not or little twisted, or are rudimentary.
        Any specimen without fruit is unlikely to be Tortella humilis. H. A. Crum and L. E. Anderson
        (1981) well described and illustrated the rare species Trichostomum spirale from the Great
        Lakes region (Ontario, Wisconsin, Minnesota) that, like Tortella humilis, is a nearly
        stemless plant with gradually differentiated proximal cells and a similar leaf shape. It
        also has stalked perigonial buds and is autoicous. It may be distinguished by the peristome
        teeth said to be short, erect and smooth or marked with spiral lines rather than spiculose
        papillae, the latter characteristic of peristomes of the genus Tortella.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
