<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Jennings" date="unknown">humilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Mosses W. Pennsylvania,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>96. 1913,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae; genus Tortella;species humilis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Barbula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">humilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>116, plate 25, figs. 1–4. 1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Barbula;species humilis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Barbula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">caespitosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Barbula;species caespitosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Schwägrichen) Limpricht" date="unknown">caespitosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tortella;species caespitosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants usually dull and dark green to sordid yellow-green distally, brown to black
        proximally, typically compact and rosulate to more elongate and showing annual whorls. Stems
        almost absent or stems to 0.5(–0.7) cm, central strand distinct, densely radiculose with
        red-brown radicles or infrequently populations with elongate stems without tomentum. Stem
        leaves densely foliose in rosulate habits, abruptly larger distally, the whorl-bases
        consisting of small leaves, loosely and variously incurled and contorted, occasionally
        somewhat crisped when dry, widespreading to patent when moist, typically oblong or
        oblong-spathulate, most leaves flat at mid leaf, somewhat concave and weakly keeled near the
        apex, not cucullate; 1.5–3.5(–4) mm; base sub-clasping and often appearing narrower than the
        limb to somewhat broader and elliptic; margins flat to weakly and broadly undulate, erect or
        broadly incurved near the apex; apex typically obtuse to broadly or occasionally narrowly
        acute, usually stoutly mucronate; costa short-excurrent, adaxial surface papillose, adaxial
        epidermal cells typically quadrate to short-rectangular and similar to the laminal cells
        throughout, sometimes smooth and narrowly elongate cells (8:1) toward the apex due to
        exposure of the stereid band or, in the extreme apex, exposure of the guide cells; in cross
        section adaxial epidermis present, often interrupted in the extreme distal portion of the
        leaf, proximal laminal cells yellow-hyaline, elongate, laxly thin-walled, gradually distally
        papillose, marginal basal cells longer and larger than median cells, occasionally
        approximating a band of differentiated cells; proximal cells interior to the marginal
        gradually differentiated from the distal laminal cells; distal laminal cells small,
        typically 6–7(–9) µm wide. Specialized asexual reproduction none. Sexual condition
        autoicous; perigonia small, distinctive, stalked, flattened, usually single, rarely
        geminate, frequently yellow or orange, foliose buds of 2–6 leaves in axils of the distal
        leaves alongside and proximal to the perichaetium; inner perichaetial leaves little
        differentiated from stem leaves. Seta about (0.5–)0.7–1.7 cm; one per perichaetium, but
        often three to four per plant from different branches. Capsule 1.5–3 mm; annulus deciduous
        in fragments; operculum 1.2–1.5 mm; peristome teeth, to over 1 mm, spirally wound 2 or 3
        times.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature spring.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Thuja swamps and bogs, near streams, hard and softwood forests, dry, exposed or moist
        and shaded stations, bark at the base of trees, acid or basic substrates, rock crevices and
        surfaces, sandy or humic soil, organic debris, mortar and brick, concrete, maritime and
        inland forests;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.S.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ala.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ark.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Conn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Del.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Fla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ga.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ill.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ind.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Iowa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Kans.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ky.</description>
  <description type="morphology">La.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Md.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mich.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Minn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Miss.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nebr.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.J.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ohio</description>
  <description type="morphology">Okla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pa.</description>
  <description type="morphology">S.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tenn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tex.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Vt.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Va.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">W.Va.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wis.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico</description>
  <description type="morphology">West Indies</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia</description>
  <description type="morphology">Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pacific Islands.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Uniquely among species of the genus in the flora area, except for var. arctica of
        Tortella tortuosa, in T. humilis the proximal laminal cells of the leaf are typically
        gradually differentiated from the distal cells with a zone of cells intermediate in color,
        cell size, cell wall thickness and papillosity, the angle of hyaline marginal cell
        differentiation typically shallow across the leaf base, then extending up the margins in a U
        shape. This character is typical of the genus Trichostomum, with which Tortella is closely
        allied. Small (depauperate) plants of T. flavovirens may share this character. Typical basal
        cell differentiation in Tortella is abrupt, the angle of differentiated cells steep, the
        proximal echlorophyllose and distal chlorophyllose cell boundary sharp.</discussion>
  <discussion>In cross section, the costa of Tortella humilis diminishes in size toward the leaf
        tip: sectioning distally along the leaf, the epidermal layer first disappears, leaving up to
        two stereid cells in width exposed. In some instances at the extreme apex, even the stereid
        layer disappears leaving the guide cells exposed. The well-developed peristome—elongate and
        conspicuously twisted—will distinguish Tortella humilis from specimens of T. flavovirens and
        Trichostomum species, whose peristomes are either not or little twisted, or are rudimentary.
        Any specimen without fruit is unlikely to be Tortella humilis. H. A. Crum and L. E. Anderson
        (1981) well described and illustrated the rare species Trichostomum spirale from the Great
        Lakes region (Ontario, Wisconsin, Minnesota) that, like Tortella humilis, is a nearly
        stemless plant with gradually differentiated proximal cells and a similar leaf shape. It
        also has stalked perigonial buds and is autoicous. It may be distinguished by the peristome
        teeth said to be short, erect and smooth or marked with spiral lines rather than spiculose
        papillae, the latter characteristic of peristomes of the genus Tortella.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
