<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="(Schimper) Brotherus in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="1902">trichostomoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Lindberg) Limpricht" date="1888">tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(R. Hedwig) Limpricht" date="1888">inclinata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="unknown" date="unknown">inclinata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae;subfamily trichostomoideae;genus tortella;species inclinata;variety inclinata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Müller Hal. &amp; Kindberg" date="unknown">inclinatula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tortella;species inclinatula;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems stems yellow or green, rather pale, brown proximally, yellow in KOH, to 1 cm,
        not to few-branched, tomentum usually conspicuous. Leaves irregularly twisted and incurved
        when dry; majority of leaf apices obtuse, strongly cucullate, mucro of 1–3 cells; with cross
        section with adaxial and abaxial superficial walls the same width as the cross-walls; leaf
        cells 10–12 µm, papillae not elevated.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Spores mature spring (late May).</description>
  <description type="morphology">Exposed calcareous silt, sand or other loosely consolidated substrates where it
        functions as a pioneer species;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to high elevations (200–1900 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">frequently near bodies of inland fresh water</description>
  <description type="morphology">gravel bars</description>
  <description type="morphology">among pebbles on river banks</description>
  <description type="morphology">mud flats</description>
  <description type="morphology">sand dunes on the Great Lakes</description>
  <description type="morphology">also gravel pits near bogs and sandy clearings in mixed deciduous woods or
        spruce-pine groves</description>
  <description type="morphology">highway ditches</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alta.</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Yukon</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska</description>
  <description type="morphology">Iowa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mich.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Minn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ohio</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia</description>
  <description type="morphology">Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Spores mature spring (late May). Exposed calcareous silt, sand or other loosely consolidated substrates where it functions as a pioneer species, frequently near bodies of inland fresh water, gravel bars, among pebbles on river banks, mud flats, sand dunes on the Great Lakes, also gravel pits near bogs and sandy clearings in mixed deciduous woods or spruce-pine groves, highway ditches; low to high elevations (200-1900 m); Alta., B.C., N.W.T., Ont., Que., Yukon; Alaska, Iowa, Mich., Minn., Mont., Ohio; South America; Europe; Asia; Africa; Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Spores mature spring (late May).</phenology>
      <habitat>Exposed calcareous silt, sand or other loosely consolidated substrates where it functions as a pioneer species, frequently near bodies of inland fresh water, gravel bars, among pebbles on river banks, mud flats, sand dunes on the Great Lakes, also gravel pits near bogs and sandy clearings in mixed deciduous woods or spruce-pine groves, highway ditches;</habitat>
      <elevation>low to high elevations (200-1900 m);</elevation>
      <distribution>Alta., B.C., N.W.T., Ont., Que., Yukon; Alaska, Iowa, Mich., Minn., Mont., Ohio; South America; Europe; Asia; Africa; Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>6a.</number>
  <discussion>Variety inclinata, var. densa, and Tortella rigens are very similar in their
        tubulose and frequently cucullate leaves, and the groove of elongate, smooth cells on the
        adaxial surface of the costa extending throughout the leaf. In North America, var. inclinata
        appears to be restricted to calcareous silt, typically where streams flood (W. C. Steere
        1978). It also inhabits larger sediments, such as the coarse sands along the Great Lakes
        beaches and rivers. It characterizes areas in flood zones lower than those of var. densa,
        which also colonizes sandy soil, but in the crevices of rocks in hilly stations. Tortella
        humilis, which might possibly be confused with these varieties, has a distinct stem central
        strand. The strikingly differentiated perichaetial leaves of var. inclinata occur only in
        association with fertilized archegonia. In var. inclinata the setaceous perichaetial leaves
        may be conspicuous on dry stems where they rise more stiffly above the curled stem leaves—as
        is true of those of T. alpicola, T. fragilis and T. tortuosa. Such perichaetiate plants,
        though uncommon, are easy to confuse with sterile or fertile T. fragilis, but the setaceous
        leaves of that species have propaguloid modifications in the apex whether barren or
        fertile.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
