<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="(Schimper) Brotherus in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="1902">trichostomoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Lindberg) Limpricht" date="1888">tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(R. Hedwig) Limpricht" date="1888">inclinata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Lorentz &amp; Molendo) Limpricht" date="1888">densa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Laubm. Deutschl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 604. 1888,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae;subfamily trichostomoideae;genus tortella;species inclinata;variety densa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Barbula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">inclinata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Lorentz &amp; Molendo" date="unknown">densa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in P. G. Lorentz, Moosstudien,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>90. 1864</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Barbula;species inclinata;variety densa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tortella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">densa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tortella;species densa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems dull and often strongly orange-green, orange, or dull green distally and
        brownish black proximally, orange in KOH, to 2 cm, many-branched, tomentum hidden in leaf
        axils. Leaves when dry somewhat uniformly twisted on the stem (funaliform), erect
        proximally; leaf apices cucullate, acute, to narrowly acuminate, mucro of 5–7 cells; in
        cross section with thick abaxial and adaxial superficial walls, but thin cross-walls;
        papillae appearing pedestaled on thick walls, leaf cells 7–10 µm.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy soil of rocky uplands or hills, rock slides, soil at the base of sandstone outcrops, cliff crevices, ledges and bases in mesic to moist stations, associated with old post-glacial alluvium in drainage basins of lakes and rivers;</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate elevations (900-1600 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C., N.W.T.; Alaska, Mich., Vt., Wis.; Europe.</description>
  <number>6b.</number>
  <discussion>Variety densa is apparently associated with older, stable habitats, rather than
        colonizing relatively more recent ones, as does var. inclinata. The stems are reddish
        orange, the leaves are densely foliose, and in cross section they have thickened superficial
        cell walls on both sides of the leaf section, forming pedestals on which the papillae are
        developed. Most of the leaves are acuminate, rather than cucullate, perhaps because the
        stems are richly perichaetiate. As the two reports of Tortella inclinata from arctic North
        America are var. densa, var. inclinata is considered here to be absent from that region. The
        most striking characteristic of western North American specimens from rocky substrates is
        their tall, densely foliose, numerously branched stems in regimented tufts, unlike var.
        inclinata, with stems usually smaller and indistinct, little branched, and leaves more
        chaotically twisted around the stem and half buried in the debris. The western specimens
        have darker (fuscous to black proximally) or more highly colored (orange) aspect, stiffer
        leaves, many or most narrowly acute yet still inrolled such that a subcucullate aspect to
        the leaf apex could be identified, a relatively orderly ropelike disposition of the leaves
        on dry stems, and peculiar distinctly thickened superficial cell walls.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
