<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard H. Zander</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">WEISSIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>64.  1801  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus WEISSIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Friedrich Wilhelm Weiss, 1744–1826, lichenologist of Göttingen]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hampe" date="unknown">Astomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Astomum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">Hymenostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Hymenostomum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Weissia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Hampe) Müller Hal." date="unknown">Astomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Weissia;section Astomum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Weissia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Hampe) Kindberg" date="unknown">Astomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Weissia;subgenus Astomum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Weissia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(R. Brown) Andrews" date="unknown">Hymenostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Weissia;subgenus Hymenostomum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 97 (10 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>A world evaluation of Weissia and Trichostomum (R. H. Zander 1993) at the generic level suggested that species of the two genera might be shuffled into a more natural arrangement if taxa with identical or nearly identical gametophytes were grouped, with differences in sporophytes easily and simply explained by reduction.  It is insufficient, however, to simply split Weissia and Trichostomum into two genera, as was implemented by Zander, based on leaf margins sharply incurved or erect to nearly plane, respectively.  Weissia jamaicensis and T. crispulum have similar gametophytes but differ markedly in the leaves of the former being sharply incurved marginally and of the latter nearly plane to merely erect.  No major changes were made, however, for this treatment given the need for a full revision.  Certain Weissia species with erect leaf margins may have a somewhat cucullate leaf apex similar to that of T. crispulum, but the lamina of the latter is generally broader, 16–20 cells across on one side of the costa just above mid leaf (except in strongly reduced specimens with short-ovate leaves), while Weissia species with which it may be confused have laminae usually 10–15 cells across a lateral lamina.  The present species concepts are largely identical with those of A. Stoneburner (1985) with exceptions as noted.</discussion>
  <discussion>All species of Weissia with sharply inflexed distal leaf margins have a tendency to show adaxially bulging cells in leaf section, possibly because the inflexion crowds the cells.  This differential bulging of cell superfices is probably homoplastic to adaxially bulging distal laminal cells in other pottiaceous genera without sharply inflexed distal margins, such as Hyophila.  Thus, the close relationship of Weissia with Hyophila and relatives cladistically demonstrated by R. H. Zander (1993) is probably an artifact.  Regarding the hymenium that may be seen closing the newly deoperculate capsules of the eperistomate segregate genus Hymenostomum, such a membrane is present in all species of the genus, being the top of the spore sac, and it is simply more evident in the eperistomate species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Anderson, L. E. and B. E. Lemmon.  1972.  Cytological studies of natural intergeneric hybrids and their parental species in the moss genera Astomum and Weissia.  Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 59: 382–416.</reference>
    <reference>Stoneburner, A.  1985.  Variation and taxonomy of Weissia in the southwestern United States.  II.  Taxonomic treatment.  Bryologist 88: 293–314.</reference>
    <reference>Stoneburner, A. and R. Wyatt.  1985.  Variation and taxonomy of Weissia in the southwestern United States.  I.  Biometrical analyses.  Mitt. Thüring. Bot. Ges. 11: 175–185.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves cucullate, base usually abruptly broadened, with prominent shoulders; costa with adaxial stereid band almost as large as or larger than the abaxial</description>
      <determination>1.   Weissia jamaicensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves with channeled or plane apex, base weakly or gradually broadened, lacking distinct shoulders; costa with adaxial stereid band clearly smaller than the abaxial.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsule stegocarpic, operculum falling, peristome present, often rudimentary, or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal margins erect or almost plane, occasionally very broadly incurved, mucro strong and often cylindric, of 5–7(–10) cells</description>
      <determination>6.   Weissia brachycarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal margins distally incurved (occasionally involute or rolled), mucro weak or strong, triangular, of 1–5(–9) cells.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves long-elliptic or ligulate, base little wider than distal lamina, apex rounded- acute</description>
      <determination>4.   Weissia ligulifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves lanceolate to deltoid or ovate, base usually ovate or elliptic, apex acute to narrowly acute.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves short- to long-lanceolate or linear, distal laminal cells 6–13 µm wide, margins distally strongly and usually but not always sharply incurved or inrolled</description>
      <determination>2.   Weissia controversa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves deltoid to ovate, distal laminal cells 10–13 µm wide, distal margins usually loosely inrolled</description>
      <determination>3.   Weissia sharpii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsule cleistocarpic or at least indehiscent (operculum persistent), rarely fragments of peristome visible in transmitted light.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves short-lanceolate to elliptic, leaf mucro weak or strong, of 1–7 cells.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mucro usually weak, of 1–3 cells; capsule ovoid-elliptic, seta 0.1–0.2 cm; leaves sharply inrolled on margins distally</description>
      <determination>5.   Weissia occidentalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mucro strong, of (3–)4–6(–7) cells; capsule ovoid to short-cylindric, seta 0.2–</description>
      <determination>10.   Weissia inoperculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves long-lanceolate, leaf mucro commonly strong, of (1–)3–7(–14) cells.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal margins distally strongly and sharply incurved or inrolled; operculum persistent, peristome absent or rudimentary</description>
      <determination>7.   Weissia phascopsis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Laminal margins erect or almost plane, occasionally very broadly incurved; operculum not differentiated, peristome absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seta usually 0.08–0.15 cm, rhizautoicous, capsule with stomates</description>
      <determination>8.   Weissia ludoviciana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seta less than 0.05 cm, cladautoicous, capsule lacking stomates</description>
      <determination>9.   Weissia muhlenbergiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
