<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>59.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name>
    <species_name>orientale</species_name>
    <species_authority>L. I. Savicz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Mater. Otd. Sporov. Rast. Bot. Inst. Komarova Akad. Nauk
                S.S.S.R.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 206. 1951,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants pale yellow-brown, grey-green, to dark brown. Stems green to brownish;
        superficial cortex of 1 and often irregularly 2 layers of inflated, thin-walled cells. Stem
        leaves triangular-lingulate to lingulate; 0.7–0.8 mm; apex rounded and often erose, hyaline
        cells nonseptate or sometimes 1-septate, numerous small round pores more than 2 µm along the
        commissures and scattered across the cell on the convex surface, on the concave surface
        fewer similar-sized pores along the commissures. Branches short and slightly curved Branch
        fascicles with 2 spreading and 2 pendent branches. Branch leaves ovate, 1.1–1.3 mm,
        distinctly curved to secund; hyaline cells covered with numerous (more than 30 per cell)
        tiny pores (ca. 1 µm) on convex surface along the commissures and across the cell surface,
        sometimes forming several linear rows of free pores, on concave surface with fewer pores
        round to oval and slightly larger (more than 2 µm) restricted to commissures. Sexual
        condition probably dioicous. Capsule not seen. Spores not seen.</description>
  <habitat>Commonly in muskeg pond margins, low center polygons, wet meadows, and tundra pool
        margins, usually occurring in very wet or submerged habitats;</habitat>
  <elevation>low to moderate elevations;</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>Nunavut</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Asia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>The ecology of Sphagnum orientale is poorly known, due in part to taxonomic
        confusion with S. perfoliatum and in part to its very northern distribution. Like other
        species of sect. Subsecunda, however, it is clearly minerotrophic, probably weakly so.
        Associated vascular plants include Carex aquatilis Wahlenberg, C. bigelowii Torrey, C.
        fuliginosa Schkuhr, C. rotundata Wahlenberg, Eriophorum vaginatum Linnaeus, Vaccinium
        oxycoccus Linnaeus, and Betula glandulosa Michaux. Associated bryophytes include Sphagnum
        aongstroemii, S. fimbriatum subsp. concinnum, S. jensenii, S. obtusum, S. rubellum, S.
        talbotianum, S. squarrosum, and Cinclidium subrotundatum. Sporophytes are rare. Similar
        species with which it overlaps in range are S. subsecundum, S. perfoliatum and S.
        inexspectatum. Field separation from S. subsecundum and S. inexspectatum is difficult but
        the tiny branch leaf pores will separate it microsopically. Sphagnum perfoliatum is much
        larger and indeed looks much like some forms of S. lescurii or S.auriculatum, even to having
        curved, horn-like branches. Sphagnum perfoliatum is also typically quite richly colored and
        glossy in appearance.</discussion>
</treatment>
