<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="L. I. Savicz" date="unknown">orientale</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Mater. Otd. Sporov. Rast. Bot. Inst. Komarova Akad. Nauk
                S.S.S.R.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 206. 1951,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sphagnum;species orientale;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>59.</number>
  <discussion>The ecology of Sphagnum orientale is poorly known, due in part to taxonomic
        confusion with S. perfoliatum and in part to its very northern distribution. Like other
        species of sect. Subsecunda, however, it is clearly minerotrophic, probably weakly so.
        Associated vascular plants include Carex aquatilis Wahlenberg, C. bigelowii Torrey, C.
        fuliginosa Schkuhr, C. rotundata Wahlenberg, Eriophorum vaginatum Linnaeus, Vaccinium
        oxycoccus Linnaeus, and Betula glandulosa Michaux. Associated bryophytes include Sphagnum
        aongstroemii, S. fimbriatum subsp. concinnum, S. jensenii, S. obtusum, S. rubellum, S.
        talbotianum, S. squarrosum, and Cinclidium subrotundatum. Sporophytes are rare. Similar
        species with which it overlaps in range are S. subsecundum, S. perfoliatum and S.
        inexspectatum. Field separation from S. subsecundum and S. inexspectatum is difficult but
        the tiny branch leaf pores will separate it microsopically. Sphagnum perfoliatum is much
        larger and indeed looks much like some forms of S. lescurii or S.auriculatum, even to having
        curved, horn-like branches. Sphagnum perfoliatum is also typically quite richly colored and
        glossy in appearance.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
