<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>8.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Weissia</genus_name>
    <species_name>ludoviciana</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Sullivant) W. D. Reese &amp; B. A. E. Lemmon</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>68: 282.  1965,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Phascum</genus_name>
    <species_name>ludovicianum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Sullivant</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray, Manual ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 616.  1856</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Astomum</genus_name>
    <species_name>ludovicianum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Sullivant) Sullivant</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Leaves long-lanceolate, base long-elliptic or narrowly ovate, shoulders absent, distal laminal margins plane or erect, apex broadly channeled, acute, mucro very strong, of 7–10(–14) cells; costal adaxial stereid band smaller than the abaxial; distal laminal cells 8–10(–12) µm wide.  Sexual condition rhizautoicous.  Seta short, 0.08–0.015 cm not including the vaginula.  Capsule cleistocarpic, ovoid with a short-rostrate apiculus.</description>
  <phenology>Capsules mature fall–spring.</phenology>
  <habitat>Moist soil, fields, among grasses, roadside banks;</habitat>
  <elevation>low to moderate elevations;</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ala.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ark.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ky.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>La.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Miss.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>S.C.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>The gametophyte of Weissia ludoviciana is quite like that of W. brachycarpa.  If it has a hybrid origin, then the archegoniate parent is the latter species.  Weissia ludoviciana, W. muehlenbergiana, and W. phascopsis are similar in the short-seta, cleistocarpic capsules and long-lanceolate leaves, but differ most constantly in the traits given in the key.  Additional differences observed, which may prove inconstant on revision, are: W. ludoviciana is rhizautoicous, with antheridia in extremely small, serrate-leaved buds, on soil near base of the archegoniophore, the capsule has stomates and a weakly differentiated annulus of 3–4 rows of smaller cells, and the calyptra is ca. 1 mm; W. muehlenbergiana is cladautoicous, the capsule lacks stomates and an annulus is not distinguishable, and the calyptra is 0.5–0.6 mm; W. phascopsis is cladautoicous, the capsule has stomates and the annulus somewhat differentiated as a ridge, and the calyptra is 1.2–1.4 mm.  The hybrid Weissia ludoviciana × W. controversa was reported by W. D. Reese and B. E. Lemmon (1965).</discussion>
</treatment>
