<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="(Schimper) Brotherus in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="1902">trichostomoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">weissia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(H. A. Crum) H. A. Crum" date="1973">inoperculata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>67: 164. 1973,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae;subfamily trichostomoideae;genus weissia;species inoperculata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Hymenostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="H. A. Crum" date="unknown">inoperculatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14: 74, figs. 1–6. 1957</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Hymenostomum;species inoperculatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Leaves elliptic, base weakly or not differentiated in shape, shoulders absent,
        distal laminal margins plane to erect, rarely incurved, apex plane, acute to rounded-acute,
        mucro usually strong, of (3–)4–6(–7) cells; costal adaxial stereid band smaller than the
        abaxial; distal laminal cells 8–10(–13) µm wide. Sexual condition dioicous (perigoniate
        plants mixed with the archegoniate). Seta elongate, 0.2–0.3 cm. Capsule cleistocarpic,
        short-elliptic, operculum weakly differentiated, peristome absent.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature Feb.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Garden, soil;</description>
  <description type="morphology">moderate elevation;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <discussion>Weissia inoperculata is known only from the type specimen (Stanford University,
        Santa Clara County). It has a gametophyte much like that of Trichostomum brachydontium and
        may prove better placed in Trichostomum. The operculum is weakly marked off by a ring of
        several rows of small cells.</discussion>
  <discussion>Excluded Species:</discussion>
  <discussion>Weissia condensa (Voit) Lindberg</discussion>
  <discussion>This name replaces Weissia tortilis (Schwägrichen) Müller Hal., an illegitimate
        homonym according to M. F. V. Corley et al. (1981). Synonyms of this European species have
        been applied to specimens of W. controversa from the flora area include Hymenostomum tortile
        (Schwägrichen) Bruch &amp; Schimper; W. euteiches R. H. Zander, superfluous name; and W.
        tortilis (Schwägrichen) Müller Hal., illegitimate homonym. European specimens of W. condensa
        usually have cucullate leaf apices, thick costae to 100 µm wide basally, distal laminal
        cells 8–10 µm wide, and capsules usually eperistomate; the leaves commonly have rather stout
        and long mucros of (4–)7–10 cells. Weissia sharpii is similar but has large distal laminal
        cells, 10–13 µm wide (2–)1:1. The combination of a strong mucro, wide costa and generally
        eperistomate but stegocarpic capsule is not found in the flora area and thus this species is
        excluded. Although A. Stoneburner (1985) attributed an eperistomate condition to W.
        condensa, R. H. Zander (1994h) pointed out that W. condensa may occasionally have a very
        rudimentary peristome, one or two segments high, hidden below the capsule stomal rim (e.g.,
        Slovakia, Pilous 139, MO). The thickness of the capsule wall in numbers of cell layers was
        used by Zander to distinguish W. condensa from W. controversa in Mexico, but this is
        apparently not a good feature because all Weissia capsules examined in the present study are
        three to four cell layers thick although W. controversa occasionally has 2–3 layers, with
        the innermost layer difficult to demonstrate or possibly eroded or resorbed.</discussion>
  <discussion>Weissia flavescens. E. Britton (= Trichostomum brittonianum R. H.
        Zander)</discussion>
  <discussion>This species was reported from Florida by W. D. Reese (1991), but those sterile
        plants proved to be indistinguishable from Trichostomum crispulum.</discussion>
  <discussion>Weissia wimmeriana (Sendtner) Bruch &amp; Schimper</discussion>
  <discussion>This is a European species whose report from Minnesota, according to A. L. Andrews
        (1933) was based on material of Weissia controversa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
