<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard H. Zander,Patricia M. Eckel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schwägrichen" date="unknown">ANOECTANGIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond. Suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(1): 33.  1811,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus ANOECTANGIUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek anoiktos, opened, and angos, container, alluding to wide-mouthed capsule]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>10.</number>
  <discussion>Species 47 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Anoectangium is distinguishable from Molendoa, a morphologically similar genus also having very short perichaetia-bearing branches arranged laterally on the axis, by its often triangular stem section, constant lack of a ventral costal stereid band, the leaves keeled by a deep adaxial groove along the costa, and the nonglaucous color in nature.  Hymenostylium has similarly though not as deeply keeled leaves with elongate cells on the adaxial surface, but has terminal perichaetia, lacks a stem central strand, and medial laminal cells are commonly longitudinally elongated.  Amphidium species are similar in appearance but the sexual condition is autoicous (A. lapponicum) or papillae are simple and elliptical (A. mougeotii).  Species of Zygodon may be distinguished by the simple, isolated papillae, not obscuring the lumens.  Although the lack of an adaxial stereid band helps separate Anoectangium from robust specimens of Gymnostomum and Molendoa, variation in expression of this trait requires other traits for distinguishing small forms.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Gemmae abundant in leaf axils; leaves ligulate to short-elliptic or ovate, very short, 0.4–</description>
      <determination>3.   Anoectangium handelii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Gemmae absent; leaves lanceolate to linear or nearly ligulate, longer, usually 1–2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves distant on the stem, exposing it, short-lanceolate to nearly ligulate, not wasp-waisted; leaf apex narrowly to broadly acute, apiculus short-triangular; costa percurrent in distal leaves into a clear, sharp cell</description>
      <determination>1.   Anoectangium aestivum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves dense and hiding the stem, long-lanceolate to linear-elliptic, constricted above the leaf base; leaf apex narrowly acute to acuminate, apiculus narrowly triangular; costa regularly excurrent into a short or long, stout mucro of several cells</description>
      <determination>2.   Anoectangium stracheyanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
