<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Anoectangium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Schiffner" date="unknown">handelii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. K. K. Naturhist. Hofmus.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>27: 490, figs. 51–59.   1913,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Anoectangium;species handelii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Leaves dense, hiding the stem, ligulate to short-elliptic or ovate, 0.4–0.5(–0.6) mm; apex broadly acute to rarely rounded, apiculus absent or of one cell; margins often 2-stratose in patches; costa usually ending (1–)3–4 cells before apex.  Specialized asexual reproduction by ovate gemmae, sometimes uncommon, occasionally apiculate by a projection, of ca. 8 cells, born on rhizoids in leaf axils.  Sporophytes unknown.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Fissures in rock, calcareous and noncalcareous sandstone;</description>
  <description type="morphology">moderate to high elevations (900–1700 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Colo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nev.</description>
  <description type="morphology">s Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">sw</description>
  <description type="morphology">c Asia.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Anoectangium handelii is quite similar to Gymnostomum viridulum in habitat, size, general appearance, and production of axillary gemmae (a morphological phenocopy), but is immediately distinguished by its narrow adaxial costal groove.  Though apparently rare (California in Inyo County, Colorado in Boulder and Larimer counties, Nevada in Clark County), its small size and similarity to sterile Gymnostomum make A. handelii easy for collectors to pass over. C. C. Heyn and I. Hernnstadt (2004b) provided additional discussion of this curious species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Zander, R. H. and W. A. Weber.  2005.  Anoectangium handelii (Bryopsida, Pottiaceae) in the New World.  Bryologist 108: 47–49.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
