<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard H. Zander</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="(Herzog) Hilpert" date="1933">barbuloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Schimper" date="1876">GYROWEISIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Musc. Eur. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae;subfamily barbuloideae;genus GYROWEISIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek gyrus, circle, and genus Weissia, alluding to resemblance and well-developed, persistent annulus]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants gregarious or forming a thin turf, green distally, tan proximally.  Stems to 0.4[–3] cm, branching occasionally; rounded-pentagonal in transverse section, hyalodermis absent, sclerodermis present as substereids, central strand present or absent; rhizoids few; axillary hairs of ca. 5(–10) cells, the basal 1–2 brownish.  Leaves appressed-incurved when dry, weakly spreading reflexed when moist; narrowly ligulate or rectangular to long-ovate, adaxial surface nearly flat, 0.25–1.4 mm; base scarcely differentiated to ovate [sheathing]; distal margins plane to weakly recurved, entire, 1-stratose [2-stratose]; apex rounded to rounded acute or obtuse, sometimes apiculate by a sharp cell; costa ending ca. 4[–8] cells below apex [percurrent], adaxial outgrowths absent, adaxial cells elongate in 2–8 rows, abaxial cells elongate; transverse section of costa semicircular to ovate, adaxial epidermis usually present, adaxial stereid band absent or weak, exposed, guide cells 2 in 1 layer, hydroid strand absent, abaxial stereid band present, crescentiform or round in sectional shape, abaxial epidermis present or commonly absent; basal cells differentiated across leaf base in proximal 1/4–1/2 of leaf, little wider than distal cells or somewhat bulging [inflated], 3–5:1, walls of basal cells thin to evenly thickened; distal medial cells quadrate or shortly rectangular, ca. 8–11 µm wide, 1(–2):1, papillae absent or hollow, simple to indistinctly 2-fid, cell walls thin to evenly thickened, superficially flat to convex.  Specialized asexual reproduction when present by oval to spindle-shaped gemmae, of several cells, borne on basal rhizoids, green or brown.  Sexual condition dioicous [autoicous, occasionally heteroicous]; perigonia appear as buds at plant base or terminal, gemmate; perichaetia terminal, inner leaves often strongly sheathing seta, lanceolate, to 1.5 mm, laminal cells often rectangular to rhomboid.  Seta yellow-brown, ca. 1.5–3[–6] mm, twisted clockwise.  Capsule yellow-brown, ovate to short-cylindric, [neck differentiated,] 0.8–1 mm, exothecial cells shortly rectangular to rhomboid, thin-walled, annulus of 2–3 rows of highly vesiculose cells, revoluble and deciduous in pieces; operculum short-conic [narrowly rostrate], ca. 0.2–0.3[–0.6] mm, cells in straight rows; peristome teeth absent [16, rudimentary, short, spreading, ligulate or oblong and highly perforate, straight, articulations ca. 3–4, ca. 30–80 µm, lightly papillose to closely spiculose, basal membrane low].  Calyptra cucullate, ca. 0.7–1[–1.4] mm, smooth.  Spores ca. 9–11 µm, smooth to papillose, light brown.  KOH laminal color reaction yellow, rarely orange.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia (China, Middle East)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Africa.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 6 (1 in the flora): North America, Europe, Asia (China, Middle East), Africa.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 6 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Europe, Asia (China, Middle East), Africa.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>11.</number>
  <discussion>Species 6 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Gyroweisia species have ligulate leaves with subpercurrent costae and enlarged, hyaline basal cells, a vesiculose annulus, and peristome absent or rudimentary peristome.  Gyroweisia differs from the similar Gymnostomum by the occasional presence of a rudimentary peristome (outside the flora area), the large annulus, sterile plants distinctly smaller than the sporophyte-bearing gametophytes, basal leaf cells differentiated more strongly (often in the basal 1/4 to 1/2), and the more common presence of gemmae.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Andrews, A. L.  1922b.  The status of Gyroweisia in North America.  Bryologist 25: 97–100.</reference>
    <reference>Conard, H. S.  1945.  Gyroweisia reflexa in North America.  Bryologist 48: 28–29.</reference>
    <reference>Manierre, W. R.  1998.  Gyroweisia reflexa, a moss new for the United States.  Evansia 15: 30–31.</reference>
    <reference>Mogensen, G. S. and R. H. Zander.  1999.  Four moss species new to Greenland: Barbula amplexifolia, Didymodon brachyphyllus, D. michiganensis, and Gyroweisia tenuis (Pottiaceae, Musci).  Lindbergia 24: 77–83.</reference>
    <reference>Steere, W. C.  1939.  Gyroweisia tenuis in North America.  Bryologist 42: 16–23.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
