<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Gyroweisia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Schrader ex Hedwig) Schimper" date="unknown">tenuis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Musc. Eur. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 38.  1876,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Gyroweisia;species tenuis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Gymnostomum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Schrader ex Hedwig" date="unknown">tenue</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37, plate 4, figs. 1–4.  1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Gymnostomum;species tenue;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Gyroweisia tenuis is similar to and often confused with Gymnostomum aeruginosum but the latter has elongate leaves that are commonly acute (occasionally apiculate by a single cell), with quadrate to rectangular (but bulging) cells on the adaxial surface of the costa, gemmae are absent, the perichaetial leaves are little differentiated from the cauline or sheathing the seta only in lower 1/3 of leaf, the annulus is vesiculose but persistent, and the operculum is long-conic.  Specimens from the upper Great Lakes region are generally fruiting and have very short stems.  A comparatively long-stemmed specimen lacking sporophytes from Nebraska (Brown County, Churchill 12286, BC, DUKE, MO) has the characteristic narrowly rectangular cauline leaves and immature but strongly differentiated perichaetial leaves of Gyroweisia tenuis, and several-celled ovoid or spindle-shaped gemmae arising from axils of terminal leaves of sterile axes.  It is distinguished from Gymnostomum calcareum by the present of gemmae, and from Gymnostomum viridulum by the narrowly rectangular leaves.</discussion>
  <discussion>Excluded Species:</discussion>
  <discussion>Gyroweisia pusilla (Kindberg) Brotherus</discussion>
  <discussion>This entity was treated as a synonym of Gymnostomum calcareum by A. L. Andrews (1922b).</discussion>
  <discussion>Gyroweisia reflexa (Bridel) Schimper</discussion>
  <discussion>This is a peristomate species known for the flora area previously only from a single collection in Grey County, Owen Sound, Ontario (Moxley s.n., May 1924, CANM).  The specimen is indeed that, but H. A. Crum and L. E. Anderson (1981) questioned the report, suggesting a confusion of specimens by Moxley (as reviewed by W. R. Manierre 1998).  The region of the original station, now built over, has been examined by others, but no additional sites discovered.  The Michigan collection (MO) reported by Manierre is Tortula obtusifolia (Schwägrichen) Mathieu, which, though similar in the ligulate leaves and rudimentary peristome, differs significantly in the crowded, short-ovate leaves, and the single stereid band and enlarged adaxial superficial cells of the costa in section.  Although it would be difficult to demonstrate the absence of this species, given the circumstances it is now appropriate to consider it absent from the New World.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
