<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>12.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>BELLIBARBULA</genus_name><genus_authority>P. C. Chen</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Hedwigia </publication_title><place_in_publication>80: 222, plate 38.  1941  ,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Latin bellus, beautiful, and genus Barbula]</etymology><author>Patricia M. Eckel</author><description>Plants in dense turfs, dull yellow-green to red-brown distally, brown or red-brown proximally.  Stems small, erect, 0.6–3 cm; hyalodermis absent, sclerodermis thick, central strand present; axillary hairs short, 3–4 cells long, the basal 1(–2) cells yellow.  Leaves incurved and weakly contorted when dry, weakly spreading when moist, short ovate-lanceolate to triangular; base little differentiated or ovate; margins strongly recurved in basal 3/4 or nearly throughout, entire, lamina 1-stratose; apex narrow and bluntly acute, sometimes acuminate, occasionally with an apiculus; costa ending before the apex to percurrent, adaxial outgrowths absent, sinuose beyond leaf middle, rather thick, adaxial cells quadrate in 3–4 rows, papillose; transverse section circular or somewhat flattened, adaxial epidermis differentiated, adaxial stereid band moderately developed, guide cells 4–5 in 1 layer, hydroid strand lacking, abaxial stereid band present, abaxial epidermal cells present, semicircular or semi-elliptic; basal cells weakly differentiated medially near the insertion, quadrate to subrectangular, 1(–3):1, walls somewhat thin to evenly thickened; distal laminal cells irregularly hexagonal-quadrate to oval or elliptical, 1:1, 1-stratose, with small, sharp, simple to 2-fid papillae, 4–6 per lumen, thin- to somewhat thick-walled, in section superficially flat to subconvex on both surfaces.  Specialized asexual reproduction absent.  Sexual condition dioicous; perigonia at stem apex or as subterminal buds; [perichaetia terminal, distinctive, leaves convolute-sheathing, long-rectangular with an apiculus, to 2 mm.  Seta 4–6 mm.  Capsule stegocarpous, theca cylindric, annulus of highly vesiculose cells, revoluble; operculum short-conic; peristome lacking.  Calyptra cucullate.  Spores 15–18 µm.]  Laminal KOH color reaction red.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> e North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America (Bolivia)</global_distribution><global_distribution> Asia (China, the Himalayas, India).</global_distribution><discussion>Bellibarbula recurva has recently been removed from Bryoerythrophyllum.  As originally described by Chen, Bellibarbula was separated from other genera in the Barbuleae by the ovate-lanceolate leaves, undifferentiated or scarcely differentiated leaf bases, papillose distal laminal cells, eperistomate capsule and convolute-sheathing perichaetial leaves.  It is separable from Barbula by the color reaction to KOH of the distal laminal cells: yellow or orange in Barbula, red to brick-red in Bellibarbula.  The sinuose costa in the distal part of the leaf differentiates Bellibarbula from Bryoerythrophyllum.</discussion></treatment>
