<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard H. Zander</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">BARBULA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>115.  1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus BARBULA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin barba, beard, and -ula, diminutive, alluding to peristome]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>14.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 200 (6 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Barbula has been much reduced in size.  K. Saito (1975) presented cogent reasons for recognizing Didymodon as distinct.  Characters of importance in distinguishing Barbula  are: axillary hairs almost always entirely of hyaline cells; leaf adaxially usually deeply grooved along the costa; distal laminal cell papillae rough, knobby, obscuring the lumens, and protuberant along the distal laminal margins; costa usually excurrent as a sharp mucro or an apiculus of one or more clear cells; peristome is long and twisted, and as Saito (1975) pointed out, Barbula has gemmae generally larger than those of Didymodon.  The three sections are represented in the flora area: sect. Barbula, including B. unguiculata and B. orizabensis; sect. Convolutae Bruch &amp; Schimper (Streblotrichum P. Beauvois), including B. amplexifolia, B. convoluta, and B. indica; and sect. Hydrogonium (Müller Hal.) K. Saito [Hydrogonium (Müller Hal.) A. Jaeger], including B. bolleana.  For many taxa previously long-held in Barbula, see 16. Didymodon.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Steere, W. C.  1939b.  Barbula in North America north of Mexico.  Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 66: 93–119.</reference>
    <reference>Zander, R. H.  1994i.  Barbula.  In: A. J. Sharp et al., eds.  The moss flora of Mexico.  Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 69: 286–296.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves rather flaccid when wet, distal laminal cells 11–15 µm, often lax, quadrate to rectangular, not or weakly papillose</description>
      <determination>6.   Barbula bolleana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually firm when wet, distal laminal cells 7–12 µm, firm, quadrate, usually distinctly and strongly papillose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Abaxial costa surface cells doubly prorate (i.e., with both ends of rectangular superficial cells protruding) near apex, often with coarse mammillae in rows across the costa; leaf base widened but not sheathing</description>
      <determination>4.   Barbula indica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Abaxial costa surface cells with crowded, simple or occasionally 2-fid, hollow or solid papillae or smooth, seldom distinctly prorate near apex (and if so then papillae scattered); leaf base weakly sheathing (leaf base strongly sheathing only in B. amplexifolia).</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costa percurrent or ending before the apex; leaf apex entire or apiculate by a smooth or weakly papillose conical cell; specialized asexual reproduction when present by tubers on proximal rhizoids, or if by axillary gemmae then gemmae large and single in the axils; perigoniophores very short-stemmed</description>
      <determination>3.   Barbula convoluta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Costa short-excurrent as a mucro or if percurrent, then leaf acuminate; specialized asexual reproduction when present by multiple axillary gemmae; antheridiate plants long-stemmed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves triangular-lanceolate, margins plane or rarely recurved at mid leaf, leaf base long-oblong and sheathing; abaxial surface of costa smooth or rarely with prorulae; costal hydroids absent; gemmae usually present, on stalks in leaf axils</description>
      <determination>5.   Barbula amplexifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves long-ligulate or ovate-lanceolate, margins strongly but narrowly recurved or revolute in proximal half of leaf or to near apex, leaf base short-oblong, widened but not sheathing; abaxial surface of costa with simple papillae; costal hydroids present; gemmae absent or present.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex obtuse to broadly acute, margins recurved in proximal 1/2–2/3, rarely to near apex; gemmae always absent</description>
      <determination>1.   Barbula unguiculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf apex abruptly rounded to emarginate, margins recurved to near apex; gemmae spheric, on stalks in leaf axils</description>
      <determination>2.   Barbula orizabensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
