<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard H. Zander,Patricia M. Eckel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nees &amp; Hornschuch" date="unknown">GYMNOSTOMUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in C. G. D. Nees et al., Bryol. Germ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 112.  1823,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus GYMNOSTOMUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek gymnos, nude, and stoma, mouth, alluding to lack of peristome]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>15.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 22 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Gymnostomum is a calcicole of moist environments.  It differs from the similar Gyroweisia largely by the small annulus (though commonly differentiated as a circumstomal ring), basal leaf cells differentiated less strongly) and the perichaetial leaves only slightly larger or smaller than the cauline (not distinctly much larger).  Barbula convoluta is similar, but occurs in dry soil, fields, and rarely rock fissures, the adaxial surface of the leaf is keeled, and the costa has elongate adaxial cells.  The genus Gymnostomum needs revision as many species worldwide are of doubtful distinction or belong in other genera.  Those of the flora area are, however, well placed though closely related.  Hymenostylium differs in lacking a stem central strand in the area of the flora, leaves always lanceolate to ligulate, never short-elliptical or ovate, the leaf margins commonly recurved on only one side (often strongly so), the adaxial costal cells smooth, and the laminal papillae usually simple and scattered, less obscuring of the cell lumen than those of Gymnostomum.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Zander, R. H.  1994j.  Gymnostomum.  In: A. J. Sharp et al., eds.  The moss flora of Mexico.  Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 69: 246–247.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Exothecial cells flat or weakly convex, usually 20–25(–30) µm wide; perichaetia single on an axis, terminating the axis, perichaetial leaves ligulate to ovate-lanceolate, with laminal cells beyond the base quadrate and strongly papillose; cauline leaves long-rectangular or long-elliptical to broadly lanceolate, 0.5–1(–2) mm, distal adaxial costal epidermal cells quadrate to very short-rectangular; plants usually loosely cespitose, occasionally crowded, rarely forming a dense turf</description>
      <determination>1.   Gymnostomum aeruginosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Exothecial cells usually bulging, commonly 30–40 µm wide; perichaetia often multiple on an axis, terminating short or rather elongate lateral branches, perichaetial leaves narrowly lanceolate to triangular, with all or most cells elongate, rectangular to rhomboidal, smooth or weakly papillose; cauline leaves long-rectangular to short-elliptic, usually 0.3–0.6 mm, distal adaxial costal epidermal cells elongate, occasionally short-rectangular or quadrate in robust plants; plants often forming a dense turf.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Gemmae absent; leaves 0.4–0.6 mm; plants light green above, capsules elliptic, narrow-mouthed, with a distinct circumstomal collar; cauline leaves rectangular to elliptic, occasionally ovate</description>
      <determination>2.   Gymnostomum calcareum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Gemmae present in leaf axils; leaves 0.3–0.4(–0.6) mm; plants dark green above; capsules short-cylindric, wide-mouthed, lacking a circumstomal collar; leaves short-elliptic or ovate</description>
      <determination>3.   Gymnostomum viridulum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
