<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Didymodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. H. Zander" date="unknown">eckeliae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>48: 298, fig. 1.  2002,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Didymodon;species eckeliae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>12.</number>
  <discussion>Didymodon eckeliae is an uncommon species known from a few collections in southern and central California, and very recently in coastal British Columbia.  F. Puche has collected it in Spain (Alicante, Font Rojas).  It is closely related to D. vinealis, sharing the weakly differentiated leaf base, transverse section of the costa deeply convex, and the presence of a short, deep groove with the appearance of a long-elliptical window on the adaxial surface of the costa near the apex, but is immediately distinguished by distal leaf margins 2-stratose in a narrow band extending to the broadened base and often scalloped to weakly notched, at least in leaves of sterile plants.  Didymodon vinealis may occasionally have distal leaf margins 2-stratose in small patches, but never evenly so (though sometimes, apparently, completely 2-stratose in distal portion of leaf); D. nicholsonii has a much broader, long-ovate leaf outline.  Didymodon sinuosus (Mitten) Delongne of Europe is similar but its immature leaves have denticulate apices, and the distal marginal leaf cells are minutely crenulate (as in Trichostomum tenuirostre) and not 2-stratose.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
