<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Didymodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Culmann" date="unknown">nicholsonii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>34: 100, figs. 1–9.  1907 (as nicholsoni),</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae; genus Didymodon;species nicholsonii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Didymodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">vinealis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Culmann) R. H. Zander" date="unknown">nicholsonii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Didymodon;species vinealis;variety nicholsonii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants green to dark green, usually with a reddish cast.  Stems to 2 cm, central strand present.  Stem leaves appressed to weakly spreading when dry, spreading and not keeled when moist, monomorphic, long-ovate or occasionally ovate-lanceolate, rarely lanceolate, grooved adaxially along the costa, especially near leaf apex, to 3.5 mm, base scarcely differentiated to ovate or oblong in shape, margins narrowly recurved in proximal 3/4 of leaf, entire, apex acute to blunt, not fragile; costa percurrent or ending before the apex, not strongly spurred, not much widened or tapering, lacking an adaxial pad of cells, adaxial costal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, ca. 6 cells wide at mid leaf, guide cells in 1(–2) layers; basal laminal cells very weakly differentiated medially, walls thin to weakly thickened, quadrate to short-rectangular, not perforated; distal laminal cells 7–9 µm wide, 1:1, nearly smooth or papillae simple or 2-fid, 2–3 per lumen, lumens rounded-quadrate, walls thickened, weakly convex on both sides of lamina, 2-stratose in distal leaf half or occasionally only in patches or very rarely 1-stratose, cells of distal leaf margins 2-stratose or occasionally entire leaf 2-stratose distally.  Specialized asexual reproduction absent.  Seta ca. 1.2 cm.  Capsule 1.5–2.1 mm; peristome teeth 32, linear, twisted 1/2 times to once, to 1000 µm.  Spores 11–13 µm.  Distal laminal KOH reaction light to dark red-brown, occasionally deep red-orange.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Capsules mature spring–summer.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wet rocks, quartzite, wet silty sand, stream bank, canyon walls, streamside, chaparral;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to high elevations (50–1900 m);</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nev.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Utah</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia (Afghanistan).</description>
  <number>13.</number>
  <discussion>Didymodon nicholsonii intergrades somewhat with D. vinealis but the ovate-lanceolate leaves are distinctive as is the tendency to a partially or completely 2-stratose distal lamina.  It may be confused with D. rigidulus but has a broader leaf apex, the costa commonly ending before the apex, a deep apical groove over the costa, and 2-stratose distal marginal cells often in a narrow band.  The western species Grimmia cinclidontea Müller Hal. is similar and grows in similar habitats, but is autoicous, has smooth leaf cells and a homogeneous costal section.  S. Flowers’s (1973) illustration of D. rigidulus is actually of D. nicholsonii.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
