<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1h.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><section_name>Polyclada</section_name><section_authority>(C. E. O. Jensen) Horrell</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> J. Bot. </publication_title><place_in_publication>38: 119.  1900,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><unranked_epithet_name>Polyclada</unranked_epithet_name><unranked_epithet_authority>C. E. O. Jensen</unranked_epithet_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in Botaniske Forening København, Festskrift, </publication_title><place_in_publication>82.  1890</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Sphagnum</genus_name><unranked_epithet_name>Pycnoclada</unranked_epithet_name><unranked_epithet_authority>(Russow) H. Klinggräff</unranked_epithet_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants small to moderate-sized, with distinct capitulum; green, brown or variegated brown and red.  Stems green to red-brown, superficial cortex of 2–4 layers of efibrillose, non-ornamented, enlarged, short-rectangular cells.  Stem leaves smaller than branch leaves, triangular-lingulate, with rounded apex, border entire; hyaline cells efibrillose, non-ornamented, rhomboid, septate; resorbed on convex surface; concave surface intact except near apex.  Branches dimorphic, spreading branches stiff; pendent branches slender and delicate.  Branch fascicles with 3(–8) spreading and 3(–8) pendent branches.  Branch stems with distinct solitary retort cells, necks not or slightly rostrate.  Branch leaves ovate-lanceolate, apex involute, border entire; hyaline cells fibrillose and non-ornamented, convex surface with 4–6 small ringed ovate pores (approximately 1/4 the diameter of the cell), concave surface with 0–4 unringed pores per cell; chlorophyllous cells elliptic to truncate-elliptic in transverse section, qually exposed on both surfaces.  Sexual condition monoicous or dioicous.  Capsule with few pseudostomata.  Spores 15–24 µm; finely papillose on both surfaces; proximal laesura less than 0.5 the length of the spore.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia.</global_distribution></treatment>
