<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="(Herzog) Hilpert" date="1933">barbuloideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hedwig" date="1801">didymodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Mitten) H. A. Crum" date="1964">asperifolius</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryologist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>67: 163. 1964,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae;subfamily barbuloideae;genus didymodon;species asperifolius</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Barbula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Mitten" date="unknown">asperifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Proc. Linn. Soc., Bot., suppl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 34. 1859</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Barbula;species asperifolia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Didymodon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lorentz" date="unknown">rufus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Didymodon;species rufus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants orange-green or red-brown, occasionally blackish. Stems to 3 cm, central
        strand weak or absent. Stem leaves appressed-incurved when dry, usually strongly recurved
        and keeled when moist, monomorphic, triangular to lanceolate, adaxially grooved along costa,
        1.2–2.5 mm, base ovate, margins strongly and broadly recurved in proximal 1/2 or up to near
        apex, entire, apex narrowly to broadly acute, not fragile, commonly ending in a conical
        cell; costa percurrent or ending 1–4 cells before the apex, tapering, widened pad of cells
        absent, adaxial costal cells quadrate to short-rectangular, 4–6 cells wide at mid leaf,
        guide cells in 1 layer; basal laminal cells differentiated medially or across leaf,
        rectangular, walls usually thickened; distal laminal cells 13–15 µm wide, 1:1, papillae
        usually absent, rarely simple, weak and domelike, 1 per lumen, lumens rounded or angular,
        walls thickened, often irregular or very weakly trigonous, weakly to strongly convex on both
        sides, 1-stratose. Specialized asexual reproduction specialized structures absent. Seta
        0.4–0.6 cm. Capsule ca. 1 mm; peristome teeth 16, short-lanceolate to linear, irregularly
        cleft or perforate to near base, straight, to 50–300 µm. Spores 13–15 µm. Distal laminal KOH
        reaction red.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsule maturity undetermined.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Calcareous or acid rock, moist calcareous soil, peatland, streamside, alpine;</description>
  <description type="elevation">moderate to high elevations (500-3700 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">Greenland; Alta., B.C., Nfld. and Labr. (Labr.), N.W.T., Nunavut, Yukon; Alaska, Colo.; Europe; Asia.</description>
  <number>25.</number>
  <discussion>Didymodon asperifolius can sometimes be immediately recognized by a red-yellow
        translucency in leaves of dry plants, like oiled paper. The adaxial surface of the costa may
        have either quadrate or short-rectangular cells. The distal laminal cells are also rather
        large for the genus. The KOH reaction, as well as the natural color of the lamina are
        sometimes light orange, but usually quite red. Some plants may appear green but the laminal
        cell walls are red under high magnification.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
