<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Patricia M. Eckel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Herzog" date="unknown">RHEXOPHYLLUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Biblioth. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>87: 38.  1916  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus RHEXOPHYLLUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek rhexis, breaking, and phyllon, leaf, alluding to fissile distal leaf margins]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Thériot &amp; E. B. Bartram" date="unknown">Neocardotia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Neocardotia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants turf-forming, dull green to blackish green distally, reddish brown proximally.  Stems elongate, 2–4 cm; hyalodermis present, sclerodermis strong, central strand present; axillary hairs of ca. 10 cells, all hyaline, or proximal 1–3 cells yellow-brown.  Leaves appressed-incurved and loosely twisted-flexuose when dry, limb widely spreading to squarrose beyond an expanded base when moist; lanceolate, deeply and narrowly keeled distally; base rectangular, somewhat clasping, shortly decurrent; leaf margins recurved in proximal 1/4–1/2, coarsely, irregularly and sharply papillose-dentate to erose-dentate in distal 1/4–1/2, teeth multicellular, fragile margins tending to split in irregular horizontal lines, lamina 2-stratose in patches, sometimes only on the leaf margins; apex narrowly to broadly acute; costa excurrent as a sharp, denticulate mucro, adaxial outgrowths absent, adaxial cells elongate, short-rectangular to quadrate distally, 3–4 across costa at mid leaf; transverse section reniform, adaxial epidermis weakly differentiated or absent, two stereid bands present, guide cells 2–4 in 1 layer, hydroid strand variably present, abaxial stereid band reniform-semicircular in shape, abaxial epidermis strongly differentiated; basal cells nearly undifferentiated on the margins, gradually differentiated in the middle of the leaf base, oblong-rectangular, somewhat wider than distal cells, 3–5:1, walls thin; cells of limb subquadrate to rounded-hexagonal, 1:1, 2-stratose in patches, sometimes only on the leaf margins, papillae solid or hollow, crowded, multifid, walls thin, convex on both surfaces.  Specialized asexual reproduction lacking.  [Sexual condition dioicous; perichaetia terminal, interior leaves highly differentiated, long-lanceolate, convolute-sheathing.  Seta to 1 cm.  Capsule stegocarpous, theca ellipsoidal to cylindric; annulus of 2 rows of strongly vesiculose cells; operculum short-conic to conic-rostrate, somewhat inclined; peristome absent.  Calyptra cucullate.  Spores 11–18 µm.]  Laminal KOH color reaction red.</description>
  <description type="morphology">sw United States</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America.</description>
  <number>20.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>The significant character separating Rhexophyllum from the similar genus Leptodontium is the presence of a stem central strand.  There are apparently no close relatives although R. H. Zander’s (1993) phylogenetic study indicates that the genus shares an ancestor with Mironia, a similar Latin-American genus with species whose leaves are 2-stratose only along the margins of the distal lamina, and whose capsule is peristomate.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Zander, R. H.  1994o.  Rhexophyllum.  In: A. J. Sharp et al., eds.  The moss flora of Mexico.  Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 69: 260.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
