<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Patricia M. Eckel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bridel" date="unknown">HYMENOSTYLIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bryol. Univ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 81.  1827  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus HYMENOSTYLIUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hymen, membrane, and stylos, pillar, alluding to systylius capsule]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>22.</number>
  <discussion>Species 15 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Aside from the gymnostomous capsule, the most important character distinguishing Hymenostylium from other genera in the flora area is the absence of a stem central strand.  Gymnostomum, with a similar habitat, has a central strand.  Species in the peristomate genus Hennediella, for example, also may have systylius capsules but have central strands in addition to a laminal marginal border, while the costal adaxial stereid band is absent.  The genus Trichostomum has a stem central strand, as is characteristic of Barbula and Didymodon.  Leptodontium is similarly without a stem central strand, has a strong sclerodermis and hyalodermis, and reduced costa in cross section, but is distinct by the  well-developed peristome, toothed leaf margin and nonhygric habitat.  Eucladium, also without a central strand, lacks a sclerodermis, and its costa has both an ab- and adaxial epidermis and two stereid bands.  Hymenostylium  is frequently if perhaps not accurately described and illustrated as having no hyalodermis.  However, a large hyalodermis was often present in specimens from the flora area, this usually collapsed and perhaps overlooked.  According to R. H. Zander (1993), Hymenostylium is phylogenetically related to Leptodontium in the Leptodontieae, whereas Gymnostomum, a genus into which Hymenostylium is often placed, belongs with the Barbuleae.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Zander, R. H.  1994q.  Hymenostylium.  In: A. J. Sharp et al., eds.  The moss flora of Mexico.  Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 69: 250–252.</reference>
    <reference>Zander, R. H. and P. M. Eckel.  1982.  Hymenostylium recurvirostrum var. insigne and Barbula amplexifolia in British Columbia, Canada.  Canad. J. Bot. 60: 1596–1600.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
