<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>1a.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Tortula</genus_name>
    <species_name>cuneifolia</species_name>
    <variety_name>blissii</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>R. H. Zander</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Buffalo Soc. Nat. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>32: 223, plate 85, figs. 21–25.  1993,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Leaves short- to long-ovate, apex broadly acute, apiculate, margins plane, weakly bordered through-out or near apex with 2–4 rows of smaller, thicker-walled cells, occasionally short-rectangular; costa ending in an apiculus, lacking an adaxial pad of cells, distally narrow, (2–)4 cells across adaxial surface; distal laminal cells inflated hexagonal to short-rectangular, width 15–20 µm, 1(–2):1, smooth.  Sexual condition paroicous or autoicous.  Sporophytes exerted.  Seta length 0.4–0.5 cm.  Capsule stegocarpic, not systylius, cylindric, erect and nearly straight, urn 1.3–1.5 mm; peristome ca. 800 µm, teeth of 32 filaments twisted about 1/2 turn, basal membrane ca. 100 µm; operculum ca. 1.1 mm.  Spores 12–15 µm, spheric, finely papillose.</description>
  <phenology>Capsule maturity date unknown (the typical variety has capsules mature in spring).</phenology>
  <habitat>Apparently on soil;</habitat>
  <elevation>low elevations (0 m);</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>Nunavut.</ca_distribution>
  <discussion>Variety blissii is known only from the type collection, Nunavut, Cornwallis Island, Resolute Bay area.  It differs from the typical variety by blackish gametophyte, short-elliptic (not broadly obovate) leaves that are apiculate (never grading to short-awned), costa slightly wider, seta shorter and thicker, operculum larger.  The leaves of var. blissii are identical to those of muticous-leaved forms of the typical variety, but show a very strong color reaction to KOH: bright yellow upper lamina and deep brick-red basal cells, colors which are pale in European specimens.  The short, thick seta is apparently unique to this arctic variety; European specimens have setae 0.7–1.5 mm in length and ca. 0.15 mm in width.  As in European specimens, the capsule is variably macro- and microstomous, and the operculum is broadly to narrowly conic.  The type specimen was incorrectly reported (D. H. Vitt and R. H. Zander 1978) as representing a second known station for Tortula deciduidentata (as Crumia deciduidentata), which has a similar short, thick seta and smooth, weakly bordered leaves that are bright yellow in KOH except for brick-red basal cells, but which differs in the operculum pushed off by the elongating columella; capsule and spores larger; and leaves revolute proximally, with much-enlarged basal cells and costa narrower, sometimes excurrent and sharply truncate.</discussion>
</treatment>
