<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard H. Zander</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">pottiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Venturi" date="unknown">STEGONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rev. Bryol.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 96.  1883  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family pottiaceae; genus STEGONIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek stego, cover, alluding to concave, protecting leaves]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pottia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Venturi) Müller Hal." date="unknown">Stegonia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pottia;section Stegonia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants gregarious, bulbiform, white to whitish green distally, brown proximally.  Stems to 3 mm; hyalodermis absent, sclerodermis absent, central strand present; axillary hairs ca. 3–6 cells in length, proximal 2 cells firm-walled.  Leaves appressed when dry, appressed or loosely involute distally, weakly spreading when moist; nearly circular to very broadly ovate, sometimes elliptic, adaxial surface deeply concave, ca. 1.5–2 mm; base not differentiated, proximal margins not differentiated; distal margins broadly recurved to revolute, occasionally plane or weakly incurved, commonly serrulate near apex, occasionally entire, distal 1/4–1/3 of leaf usually hyaline, of rhomboid thick-walled cells; apex broadly acute or occasionally rounded; costa thin, excurrent as a flexuose hyaline awn or occasionally percurrent or subpercurrent, adaxial epidermal cells forming a bulging adaxial ridge, adaxial cells short-rectangular, bulliform (bulging, thin-walled), in ca. 3–4 rows, adaxial outgrowths rare, lamelliform, rounded or serrate and papillose; transverse section round, adaxial epidermis present, of bulliform cells, adaxial stereid band absent, guide cells 2 (often absent distally) in 1 layer, hydroid strand present, large (occasionally absent distally), abaxial stereid band present (occasionally substereid), round in section, abaxial epidermis absent distally, present proximally; proximal cells differentiated across leaf, rectangular, occasionally bulging, little differentiated or to 30 µm wide, to 4:1, walls of proximal cells often somewhat thicker than distal cells; distal medial cells rhomboid or hexagonal, grading to elongate rhomboid or hexagonal distally, often hyaline distally, 13–22 µm wide, 2–3:1, 1-stratose; papillae absent, cell walls usually thin medially and thick-walled near apex, especially on the abaxial superficial walls, convex on both sides.  Specialized asexual reproduction absent.  Sexual condition monoicous (paroicous or autoicous); perichaetia terminal, interior leaves little differentiated.  Seta 0.2–1.2 cm or very short (70–100 µm).  Capsule stegocarpous or cleistocarpous, theca exerted, ovate-cylindric and often slightly curved, to 1–2 mm; or immersed, ovate and very shortly apiculate, ca. 0.7 mm, annulus absent or of 2–3 rows of persistent, vesiculose cells; operculum absent or short-rostrate; peristome teeth absent, rudimentary or 16, cleft to near base, occasionally perforate, ligulate, straight, to 125 µm.  Calyptra cucullate.  Spores 20–45 µm.  KOH distal laminal color reaction yellow.</description>
  <description type="morphology">w North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico</description>
  <description type="morphology">Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia</description>
  <description type="morphology">Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Antarctic.</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <discussion>Species 3 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The capsules of Stegonia exhibit a reduction series (R. H. Zander 1993): one species is peristomate, another cleistocarpous, while the third, of northern Africa, is stegocarpous but eperistomate.  Both species in the flora area have perichaetial leaves with a leaf apex of hyaline, elongate, rectangular cells (this variable in S. latifolia) similar to that of the arctic Hilpertia velenovskyi, but smaller, proximal leaves similar to those of Tortula acaulon.</discussion>
  <discussion>1 Seta (2–)4–12 mm; capsule stegocarpous, exerted, ovate-cylindric, to 1–2 mm 1.   Stegonia latifolia</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seta 0.07–0.1 mm; capsule cleistocarpous, immersed, ovate, ca. 0.7 mm</description>
      <determination>2.   Stegonia hyalinotricha</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
