<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">sphagnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sphagnum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. E. Andrus" date="unknown">bergianum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sida</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>22: 964, figs. 14–20.  2006,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family sphagnaceae; genus Sphagnum;species bergianum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants moderate-sized to robust, capitulum more or less flat-topped and large; dark brown overall with a golden center to the capitulum and a distinctive deep red tinge in the field which becomes a pinkish purple sheen upon drying.  Stems dark brown; superficial cortical cells aporose.  Stem leaves broadly triangular-lingulate, 1.15–1.25 × 0.8 mm, apex slightly to broadly obtuse, border moderately broadened at base; hyaline cells mostly 1-septate with a few to many 2-septate in the mid region, shape rhomboid.  Branches more or less 5-ranked.  Branch fascicles  with 2 spreading and 1 hanging branch.  Branch leaves 1.2–1.3 × 0.65–0.75 mm, broadly ovate, apex involute; hyaline cells on convex surface with numerous round to elliptic pores along the commissures, these grading from small pores at the apex to large pores at the base; concave surface aporose except for a few large pores in the lower side regions.  Sexual condition dioicous.  Spores  26–30 µm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Hummocks in fens;</description>
  <description type="morphology">low to moderate elevations;</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska.</description>
  <number>70.</number>
  <discussion>Sphagnum bergianum forms dense hummocks in medium to rich fen habitats and is associated with such species as Sphagnum warnstorfii, S. subfulvum, S. subsecundum, S. platyphyllum and S. fuscum.</discussion>
  <discussion>Sphagnum bergianum is quite distinct in the field from its very dark brown color tinged with a deep red as well as its 5-ranked branch leaves.  Sphagnum subnitens is colored a light brown and red combination, and has unranked branch leaves.  Sphagnum subfulvum has a golden brown color that can be tinged with purple but also has unranked branch leaves.  Sphagnum flavicomans is a similar-sized brown species of sect. Acutifolia that overlaps S. bergianum in Newfoundland but it is golden brown, lacks the red tinge and has a longer and narrower branch and stem leaves.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
