<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard H. Zander</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Paris" date="unknown">HENNEDIELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Actes Soc. Linn. Bordeaux, sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 9: 232. 1895 ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus HENNEDIELLA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Roger Hennedy, 1809–1877, Scottish phycologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown bis" date="unknown">Hennedia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. &amp; Proc. New Zealand Inst.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>25: 285. 1893,</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>not Hennedya Harvey 1855</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Hennedia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants growing in loose turf or cushions, green distally, reddish brown proximally.
        Stems ca. 0.5–1 cm; hyalodermis absent or weakly developed, not collapsed, sclerodermis
        absent or substereid, central strand present; axillary hairs of ca. 5 cells, proximal 1–2
        cells occasionally somewhat thick-walled. Stem leaves appressed or incurved when dry,
        spreading when moist; ovate to long-lanceolate, occasionally ligulate or spathulate, adaxial
        surface plane or broadly channeled across leaf, (0.5–)3–4(–7) mm; base not differentiated in
        shape or ovate and somewhat sheathing, proximal margins commonly bordered; distal margins
        plane, dentate distally or less commonly entire, bordered (sometimes intramarginally) by
        short-rectangular to elongate cells, usually less papillose, occasionally thick-walled,
        rarely 2–3-stratose; apex acute or rarely obtuse; costa percurrent or short-excurrent as
        flat, denticulate mucro, rarely ending 3–4 cells before apex, adaxial cells quadrate to
        short-rectangular, in 4–5 rows; transverse section round to elliptic, adaxial epidermis
        present, adaxial stereid band absent, guide cells 2–4 per layer in (1-)2 layers, hydroid
        strand present, usually large, abaxial stereid band present, of substereid cells, elliptic
        or round in section, abaxial epidermis present (occasionally only lateral) or absent;
        proximal cells differentiated across leaf, rectangular, 18–30 µm wide, (2–)4–6:1, walls of
        proximal cells thin; distal medial cells relatively large, quadrate to hexagonal or
        short-rectangular, ca. 18–24 µm wide, 1–2:1, often marginally elongate and multistratose;
        papillae hollow, simple to 2-fid, usually 6–8 or more per lumen, cell walls thin to evenly
        thickened, flat to weakly convex. Specialized asexual reproduction absent. Sexual condition
        autoicous, cladautoicous or dioicous. Perichaetia terminal, leaves somewhat larger than the
        cauline leaves. Seta 0.05–2.5 cm. Capsule stegocarpous, theca ovate to cylindric,
        occasionally microstomous, 0.8–3.5 mm, annulus of 2–4 rows of vesiculose cells; operculum
        conic to rostrate, often narrowly so, occasionally systilius; peristome teeth absent,
        rudimentary or of 32 long, filamentous teeth, twisted counterclockwise, teeth when well
        developed to 1.5 mm. Calyptra cucullate, occasionally flaring proximally and not split.
        Spores 8–30 µm. KOH distal laminal color reaction red.</description>
  <description type="morphology">nearly worldwide</description>
  <description type="morphology">most diverse in austral temperate areas.</description>
  <number>37.</number>
  <discussion>Species 20 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Hennediella was recently recognized as much larger than previously thought (T. L.
        Blockeel 1991; R. H. Zander 1989, 1993). The bordered, dentate, plane leaves with flat
        laminal cells, red in KOH, are distinctive. The sporophyte varies among the species from
        well developed to much reduced. The operculum is often long, (0.6–)1.2–1.8 mm. The genus is
        found in soil and on rock, commonly in wet areas.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Blockeel, T. L. 1990. The genus Hennediella Par.: A note on the affinities of
            Tortula brevis Whitehouse &amp; Newton and T. stanfordensis W. C. Steere. J. Bryol. 16:
            187–192.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves broadly lanceolate to ovate, tubulose and stiff, distal margins
                1-stratose, monoicous, commonly fruiting</description>
      <determination>1. Hennediella heimii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves broadly elliptic to obovate, flat and lax, distal margins 2-stratose,
                dioicous, sporophytes unknown in area of the flora</description>
      <determination>2. Hennediella stanfordensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
