<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Patricia M. Eckel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Thériot &amp; P. de la Varde" date="unknown">LUISIERELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Soc. Bot. France</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>83: 73, fig. 1.  1936  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus LUISIERELLA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Alphonse Luisier, 1872–1957, French bryologist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>40.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Luisierella is characterized by plants blackish, minute, with ligulate leaves tubulose when dry, laminal cells adaxially mammillose, abaxially plane, adaxial costal surface with bulging rounded cells, and adaxial stereid band absent.  The abruptly thin-walled hyaline basal cells extending up the leaf margin in a V shape is distinctive; it is this latter character that quickly distinguishes this genus from similar genera: Gyroweisia, Hyophila, and Plaubelia.  Luisierella bears little relation to the genus Tortella, which is also characterized by differentiated basal cells that extend higher on the leaf margin than along the costa.  Luisierella has been suggested to be ancestrally related to the genus Quaesticula R. H. Zander (R. H. Zander 1993) through reduction of gametophyte characters and elaboration of reproductive ones.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Crum, H. A. and L. E. Anderson.  1961.  Luisierella barbula in Georgia.  Bryologist 64: 315–320.</reference>
    <reference>Deguchi, H.  1987.  Luisierella (Pottiaceae, Musci), a moss genus with a disjunctive distribution in Neotropics and Japan.  J. Jap. Bot. 62: 7–15.</reference>
    <reference>Steere, W. C.  1945.  Luisierella, a genus of mosses new to North America.  Bryologist 48: 83–85.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
