<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Virginia S. Bryan</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">EPHEMERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family EPHEMERACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
    
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants leafy ephemerals, less than 3 mm, solitary, scattered, or gregarious on
        sparse or abundant protonemata with upright, aerial, determinate branches, green,
        pale-yellow, or brown. Stem virtually absent or to 1 mm (to 3.7 mm in Micromitrium
        synoicum), rhizoids absent or few. Leaves rarely more than 12, the proximal small, broadly
        triangular to ovate, ecostate, apex acuminate, the distal becoming larger, linear,
        lanceolate, or ligulate, with or without shoulders, margins distal to the middle entire,
        serrulate, serrate, or spinose, apex acuminate; costate or ecostate; laminal cells lax and
        transparent, long-rhomboidal to rectangular, in some species becoming denser distally,
        smooth, papillose by projecting distal ends, or spinose. Specialized asexual reproduction by
        fragments and rarely by thick-walled elongate, swollen protonematal segments, commonly
        brown, and persisting on or in the soil. Sexual condition autoicous, dioicous, or synoicous.
        Perigonia arising from the protonemata, from rhizoids, or just proximal to the perichaetium;
        small, bud-like with ecostate leaves of lax areolation, broadly triangular to broadly ovate.
        Perichaetium consisting of the 1–3 most distal leaves on the stem, typically the largest and
        best developed. Vaginula conspicuous. Sporophytes 1–3 per perichaetium with immersed to
        emerging capsules. Seta virtually absent or very short. Capsule globose or ovoid, without or
        with an apiculus, cleistocarpous or opening along an indistinct or distinct ring of cells
        near the equator; exothecium of 1–2 layers of lax and thin-walled cells; stomates absent or
        superficial with two guard cells. Calyptra persistent, mitrate, and minute, or fugacious,
        mitrate or cucullate, and irregularly lobed or torn at the base, covering up to 2/3 of the
        capsule. Spores appearing reniform, globose, or variously angled, 20–120 µm, ranging from
        barely papillose to coarsely warty, the elaboration often correlating with degree of
        maturity, usually bearing small remnants of a hyaline membrane, orange, red, brown, or
        black.</description>
  <description type="morphology">nearly worldwide in temperate and tropical regions.</description>
  <number>31.</number>
  <discussion>Genera 2, species ca. 35 (2 genera, 8 species in the
        flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The Ephemeraceae are usually found in sunny or partly shaded areas, on moist or
        drying disturbed soil, where there is little competition from more persistent mosses and
        larger plants. They are visible for the most part as patches of greenish, alga-like
        protonemata with minute leafy plants and are best seen in the field when the protonemal mass
        is most abundant and green, with leafy plants that are green and approaching
        maturity.</discussion>
  <discussion>The distinguishing characters of the leaves are derived from the largest, usually
        the most distal, leaves. The middle and proximal leaves vary in shape, marginal cells, and
        costal development. For example, the distal leaves bear the well-developed costa, but the
        proximal leaves are usually ecostate, and the middle leaves vary from ecostate to weakly or
        markedly costate. In the nominally ecostate species the proximal and middle leaves are
        ecostate, but the largest leaves, while in a strict sense ecostate, may have in the costal
        position thicker walled cells or a few undifferentiated cells in a double layer. As seen in
        cross-section, the double-layered cells are not organized as a costa and do not differ from
        other laminal cells, except that they may have very slightly thicker walls. In surface view
        the double layer is barely distinguishable.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bryan, V. S. and L. E. Anderson. 1957. The Ephemeraceae in North America.
            Bryologist 60: 67–102.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Calyptra minute, tightly adherent at or near the apex of the capsule,
                persistent; capsule cleistocarpous or with a ring of differentiated cells at or just
                distal to the equator, ± globose, without a well-developed, multicellular apiculus;
                costa commonly absent, but occasionally suggested by a few median cells with thick
                walls or in a short and indistinct double layer distal to the leaf middle; laminal
                cells lax, hyaline, smooth</description>
      <determination>1. Micromitrium, p. 647</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Calyptra covering most of the distal half of the capsule, fugacious; capsule
                cleistocarpous, ovoid, and distinctly apiculate; costa well-developed, except mostly
                absent in Ephemerum serratum; laminal cells of the leaves lax in the proximal half
                and in the distal half firmer, smaller, and usually papillose</description>
      <determination>2. Ephemerum, p. 650</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
