<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Micromitrium</genus_name><species_name>wrightii</species_name><species_authority>(Müller Hal.) Crosby</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Bryologist </publication_title><place_in_publication>71: 116.  1968,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Ephemerum</genus_name><species_name>wrightii</species_name><species_authority>Müller Hal.</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Linnaea </publication_title><place_in_publication>43: 351.  1882</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Nanomitrium</genus_name><species_name>wrightii</species_name><species_authority>(Müller Hal.) V. S. Bryan &amp; L. E. Anderson</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants scattered in abundant pro-tonemata, green.  Stems virtually absent.  Leaves erect, linear-lanceolate, rarely with narrow, toothed shoulders, gradually and slenderly acuminate, 1–2 × 0.15–0.26 mm, margins plane, entire or with short single or double teeth distally.  Sexual condition synoicous or dioicous.  Capsule cleistocarpous or rarely dehiscing by a ring of differentiated cells distal to the equator, yellow- to orange-brown, globose or slightly flattened, slightly apiculate; exothecial cells in 2 layers, stomates numerous and confined to proximal half.  Spores fewer than 100, various shapes, proximal face not concave, 50–84 × 40–66 µm, red-brown or dark brown.</description><phenology>Capsules mature year around.</phenology><habitat>  Soil in shaded ravines, drying mud, clay in dry sloughs;</habitat><elevation> low elevations (0–100 m);</elevation><us_distribution> La.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies (Cuba).</global_distribution><discussion>Although the leaves of Micromitrium wrightii are most accurately described as ecostate, the largest leaves may have suggestions of a costa.  Some have merely thick-walled cells in the median part of the leaf, and others may have ± 3 median, undifferentiated cells in a double layer.</discussion><discussion>Micromitrium wrightii is known from five or fewer localities.</discussion></treatment>
