<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schimper" date="unknown">ephemeraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hampe" date="1837">ephemerum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hedwig) Hampe" date="1837">serratum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20: 285.  1837,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ephemeraceae;genus ephemerum;species serratum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Phascum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hedwig" date="unknown">serratum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>23.  1801</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Phascum;species serratum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ephemerum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">serratum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Lindberg) Grout" date="unknown">minutissimum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ephemerum;species serratum;variety minutissimum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants less than 2 mm, gregarious in persistent matted protonemata.  Leaves linear-lanceolate to ovate-lanceolate, sometimes narrowed from distinct shoulders, 1–2.4 × 0.17–0.3 mm; margins usually coarsely and irregularly serrate distal to the proximal third, often with spines, but varying to scarcely serrate; apex tapering gradually to a sharply pointed acumen, absent papillae; costa usually absent, but sometimes suggested by a few thick-walled cells or an obscure double layer of undifferentiated cells, smooth; areolation lax proximally and somewhat firm distally; median laminal cells in vertical rows, smooth; distal laminal cells smooth.  Capsule with columella resorbed before meiosis; stomates only at the base.  Spores spherical or reniform, 55–106 × 27–75 µm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Capsules mature year around, mostly in autumn.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Basic habitats more often than other species of the family, meadows, pastures, drying and dried soil;</description>
  <description type="elevation">low to moderate elevations (5-1200 m);</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.B., N.W.T., N.S., Ont., Que., Sask.; Ala., Calif., Conn., Fla., Ind., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Miss., Mo., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Oreg., Pa., S.C., Tenn., Tex., Va., W.Va., Wis.; South America (Brazil); Europe (Sardinia); Asia (China); Africa (South Africa); Pacific Islands (New Zealand).</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>The leaf margins in Ephemerum serratum vary markedly, from barely serrate to long spinose.  In general, plants from eastern North America tend to be more strongly serrate than plants from California and Oregon, although barely serrate plants from the east as well as distinctly serrate plants from the west have been seen.  Mature capsules frequently persist with only the remnants of leaves remaining, the distal portions of the leaves apparently eroded away.  Rarely, thick-walled, elongate, brown structures occur on the protonemata and they may serve as diaspores.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
