<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>4.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Syrrhopodon</genus_name>
    <species_name>ligulatus</species_name>
    <species_authority>Montagne</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syll. Gen. Sp. Crypt.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>47.  1856,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Calymperes</genus_name>
    <species_name>crispum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Austin) Austin</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Syrrhopodon</genus_name>
    <species_name>crispus</species_name>
    <species_authority>Austin</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants gregarious to caespitose, dark green to brownish green, to 0.5 cm.  Leaves monomorphic, 2 mm, crispate when dry; distal lamina not reflexed at shoulders, often folded-falcate when wet, ligulate, apex rounded or retuse; margins bordered at shoulders and irregularly distally with hyaline cells, entire or irregularly dentate at shoulders, entire distally except for projecting papillose cells; medial cells obscure due to papillosity, 5.5–6.5 µm, with bulging simple or multifid papillae ad- and abaxially; cancellinae rounded distally.  Gemmae clavate, smooth to slightly papillose, sparse, subterminal on adaxial surface of leaf apex.</description>
  <habitat>Not producing sporophytes in flora area.  Fissures of tree bark, sandstone, humid forests along rivers and in swamp forests;</habitat>
  <elevation>low elevations (0 m);</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>La.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Miss.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>West Indies</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>South America.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Syrrhopodon ligulatus is not often collected because of its small size and obscure habitat, which is mostly on bark fissures.  The short-ligulate bluntly tipped leaves, crispate when dry, and with restricted hyaline border, make this species easy to recognize.</discussion>
</treatment>
