<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>4.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Calymperes</genus_name>
    <species_name>tenerum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Müller Hal.</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 174.  1872,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Calymperes</genus_name>
    <species_name>nashii</species_name>
    <species_authority>R. S. Williams</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Calymperes</genus_name>
    <species_name>tenerum</species_name>
    <subspecies_name>edamense</subspecies_name>
    <subspecies_authority>Fleischer</subspecies_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants gregarious or tufted, pale green to brownish, straight or curved at tips when dry, to 5 mm or more but mostly much shorter.  Leaves dimorphic; vegetative 1–3 mm; distal lamina oblong to broadly linear-lanceolate; margins 1-stratose or slightly thickened distally, entire; costa in cross section showing ad- and abaxial bands of stereid cells; medial cells distinct, 7–8 µm, slightly bulging adaxially, smooth or minutely papillose abaxially; teniolae absent; cancellinae ending in broad angles distally, adaxial cells smooth distally; gemmiferous leaves with apex of costa excurrent, bearing gemmae in pale golfball-like spheres all around on costa apex.</description>
  <habitat>Not producing sporophytes in flora area.  Tree trunks and logs in hammock vegetation;</habitat>
  <elevation>low elevations (0 m);</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>West Indies (Grand Bahama, Haiti, Puerto Rico)</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>South America (s Brazil)</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Asia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Africa</global_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Indian Ocean Islands</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Pacific Islands</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Australia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Calymperes tenerum is very rare in the flora area, where it is known only from a few specimens from southern peninsular Florida.  Its absence of teniolae, narrow cancellinae, and gemmae in golfball-like spheres make it distinctive.  This species has a very wide distribution in the tropical parts of the world and is very common in the paleotropics; it is extremely scarce in the Neotropics, suggesting that it is an introduction there.</discussion>
</treatment>
