<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>1.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Octoblepharum</genus_name>
    <species_name>albidum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hedwig</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Musc. Frond.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>50. 1801,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants glossy, glaucous-green to white, often with pink tinge; densely cespitose;
        axillary hairs 3 per axil, 5-celled. Leaves spreading-recurved, fleshy, fragile when dry,
        4–5 mm, apiculate, older leaves sometimes with rhizoids on tips. Specialized asexual
        reproduction rare, by gemmae. Seta yellow, 2–5 mm. Capsule brownish, 1–1.5 mm,
        ovoid-cylindric, slightly asymmetric, with stomata at base; operculum 0.8 mm; peristome of 8
        blunt triangular pairs of teeth, teeth smooth or faintly striate, 200 µm tall, each composed
        of one interior and one exterior layer of intact, empty, cell-like plates; prostome present.
        Calyptra 1.5–1.9 mm. Spores finely papillose, 17–24 µm.</description>
  <phenology>Capsules mature throughout the year but most common Sep–Apr.</phenology>
  <habitat>Hammocks and open forests, primarily on stems and bases of Quercus virginiana and
        Sabal palmetto, and rotted logs, occasionally terrestrial on soil and humus;</habitat>
  <elevation>low elevations (0–30 m);</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>La.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>pantropical.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Octoblepharum albidum is a weedy and conspicuous moss that is distributed worldwide
        in the tropics. It grows especially on palms, often forming deep soft cushions. The flat,
        glossy, ligulate, spreading-recurved leaves distinguish it easily in the field from the
        superficially similar Leucobryum, which has erect or spreading, pointed, subtubulose
        leaves.</discussion>
</treatment>
