<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>14.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Mirabilis</genus_name><species_name>linearis</species_name><species_authority>(Pursh) Heimerl</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Annuaire Conserv. Jard. Bot. Gen ève</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5: 186. 1901</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Allionia</genus_name><species_name>linearis</species_name><species_authority>Pursh</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 728. 1814</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Mirabilis</genus_name><species_name>hirsuta</species_name><species_authority>(Pursh) MacMillan</species_authority><variety_name>linearis</variety_name><variety_authority>(Pursh) B. Boivin</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Oxybaphus</genus_name><species_name>linearis</species_name><species_authority>(Pursh) B. L. Robinson</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems decumbent, ascending, or erect, sparsely leafy with few stems to very leafy and bushy branched, leafy primarily in proximal 1/5 to throughout, 1–1.3 dm, basally minutely puberulent in 2 lines, sparsely or densely spreading-hirsute, or rarely glabrate or glabrous; distally minutely puberulent in 2 lines, sparsely or densely spreading-hirsute, or rarely glabrate or glabrous, usually glandular-puberulent or pubescent in inflorescence. Leaves strongly ascending to spreading at 5–80°; petiole 0–1.5 cm; blade green to blue-gray and glaucous, linear to linear-lanceolate, rarely lanceolate, 3–11.5 × 0.1–1(–1.8) cm, thin to fleshy, thick, and succulent, base long attenuate or narrowly acute, apex acutely tapered to rounded, surfaces glabrous, glandular-pubescent, or hirsute. Inflorescences axillary and terminal, when axillary, consisting of single involucres or short branches, when terminal with ± well-defined central axis and shorter side branches, or narrowly to widely forked without main axis; peduncle 3–10 mm, usually spreading glandular-puberulent or pilose, crosswalls of hairs pale or dark; involucres pale green, sometimes tinged with purple, narrowly to widely bell-shaped, 3–6 mm in flower, 4–10(–15) mm in fruit, spreading viscid-pubescent to hirsute, 40–70% connate, lobes ovate. Flowers 3 per involucre; perianth white to purple-pink, 0.7–1.1 cm. Fruits olive brown or dark olive brown, narrowly obovate and tapering at both ends to obovoid, 3.1–5.5 mm, pubescent with spreading crinkled hairs in tufts or ± evenly distributed, hairs 0.1–0.5 mm; ribs sometimes slightly paler, slightly elevated above surface (usually less than 0.5 times as wide as high), low rounded to round-angled, 0.5–1 times width of sulci, 0.3–1 times as wide as high, smooth throughout or sometimes rugose on sides, occasionally interrupted and tuberculate near apex; sulci with small or rarely large tubercles, or low and inconspicuous or occasionally high and prominently cross-rugose.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems hirsute, at least basally</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems minutely puberulent, glabrate, or glabrous basally.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades linear, grayish or bluish green; perianth white to deep rose-pink</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades linear-lanceolate to lanceolate, green; peri anth pink to deep purple-pink</statement>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
