<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Adanson" date="unknown">portulacaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="1814">phemeranthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Holzinger) Kiger" date="2001">rugospermus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 320. 2001</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family portulacaceae;genus phemeranthus;species rugospermus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Talinum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Holzinger" date="unknown">rugospermum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Asa Gray Bull.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 117, fig. 1a–c. 1899</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Talinum;species rugospermum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants to 2.5 dm; roots elongate, fleshily woody. Stems ± erect, simple or sometimes branching. Leaves sessile; blade terete, to 6 cm. Inflorescences cymose, much overtopping leaves; peduncle scapelike, to 15 cm. Flowers: sepals deciduous, ovate, 4 mm; petals pink to magenta, ovate to obovate, sometimes mucronulate, 6.5–8 mm; stamens 12–28; stigmas 3, spreading widely, linear, 1/2–1/3 as long as styles. Capsules subglobose, 4 mm. Seeds without arcuate ridges, 1.2 mm, corrugate-rugulose overall. 2n = 24.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May-Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sand or sandy soils, dunes, mounds, flats, banks, ridges, edges of igneous or metamorphic rock outcrops, along or near watercourses;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., La., Minn., Nebr., Tex., Wis.</description>
  <number>11.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Rough-seeded fameflower</other_name>
  <discussion>Within the overall area of its distribution, Phemeranthus rugospermus is nowhere abundant, its occurrence being everywhere spotty and localized. According to T. S. Cochrane (1993), the disjunctions probably reflect a history of long-distance dispersal from a center in the partially unglaciated Kansas and Nebraska sandhills, the present-day gaps resulting from a paucity of suitable habitats between that area and the others where it is now found. Even so, its discovery in Missouri, Arkansas, and/or Oklahoma would not be surprising.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cochrane, T. S. 1993. Status and distribution of Talinum rugospermum Holzinger (Portulacaceae). Nat. Areas J. 13: 33–41.</reference>
    <reference>MacRoberts, M. H. and B. R. MacRoberts. 1997. Talinum rugospermum Holzinger new to Louisiana with notes on terete-leaved Talinum in Louisiana. Phytologia 82: 86–93.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
