<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert W. Kiger</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Adanson" date="unknown">PORTULACACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">TALINOPSIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(5): 14. 1852</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family PORTULACACEAE;genus TALINOPSIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[From generic name Talinum , and Greek opsis , resembling]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs. Roots tuberous. Stems branching, suffrutescent, glabrous except at nodes; young branches slender, nodes dilated, tufted-pubescent. Leaves opposite, sometimes in axillary fascicles, sessile; blade subterete, fleshy, margins entire. Inflorescences lateral, cymose, few-flowered, axes angled; peduncle short. Flowers sessile; sepals persistent, distinct; petals fugacious, 5, distinct; stamens 20–25, distinct, anther 2-locular, oblong; gynoecium 3-carpellate, ovary superior, placentation free-central, style 1, stigmas 3, dilated. Fruits capsular, longitudinally dehiscent from apex; valves persistent; exocarp and endocarp evidently differentiated and separating; exocarp 3-valved, valves recurving; endocarp 6-valved, valves erect. Seeds many, uncinate to arcuate, small, estrophiolate; seed coat granulate, pellicle absent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>A cladistic analysis of chloroplast ndhF sequence data (W. L. Applequist and R. S. Wallace 2001) indicated that Talinopsis is closely related to representatives of Anacampseros Linnaeus and Grahamia Gillies ex Hooker &amp; Arnott (as originally suggested by A. Gray), in a clade not far removed from Talinum but fairly distant from the one that includes Phemeranthus mengesii and presumably the other species of that genus (except perhaps P. aurantiacus, which see).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Wilson, P. 1932c. Talinopsis. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 21, p. 290.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
