<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard W. Spellenberg</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">NYCTAGINACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Choisy" date="unknown">NYCTAGINIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13(2): 429. 1849</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family NYCTAGINACEAE;genus NYCTAGINIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek nyct , night, in reference to noctural flowering]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, viscid-pubescent, from tuberous taproots. Stems erect to spreading, unarmed, without glutinous bands on internodes. Leaves long petiolate, unequal in each pair, thick and fleshy, base ± asymmetric. Inflorescences axillary and terminal, long pedunculate, capitate; bracts 6–20, forming involucre, subtending cluster of more than 3 flowers; outer bracts ovate or lanceolate, apex acuminate or narrowly acute; inner bracts persistent, not accrescent, distinct, narrower than outer, herbaceous. Flowers bisexual, chasmogamous and/or cleistogamous; cleistogamous perianth small green dome atop developing turbinate base; chasmogamous perianth radially symmetric, orange-red, or all yellow, funnelform, constricted beyond ovary, abruptly expanded to 5-lobed limb; stamens 5–8, slightly exserted; styles exserted slightly beyond stamens; stigmas capitate. Fruits radially symmetric, turbinate, constricted beyond base, apex umbonate, stiffly coriaceous; ribs 10 low, rounded, each swollen at junction of distal, umbonate portion, glabrous, smooth, without glands.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
