<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard W. Spellenberg</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">NYCTAGINACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">ALLIONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Nat. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10, 2: 890. 1759</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family NYCTAGINACEAE;genus ALLIONIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For C. Allioni, 1725–1804, Italian botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Loefling" date="unknown">Wedelia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Wedelia;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name>name rejected</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cockerell" date="unknown">Wedeliella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Wedeliella;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>9.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The two species of Allionia are very similar, differing primarily in the nature and
    number of teeth on the fruit. In many floras for areas south of the United States only a single
    species, Allionia incarnata, is recognized. When sympatric, the two species are distinguishable
    by vegetative and perianth features, but throughout their ranges, the two species cannot be
    consistently distinguished by the same characteristics. Nevertheless, as noted by B. L. Turner
    (1994), plants with intergradient fruits are uncommon. Both species may produce fruits with
    lateral ribs that are curved and winglike, without teeth; this condition is frequent in A.
    incarnata in North America and occasional in A. choisyi in South America.</discussion>
  <discussion>The three bilaterally symmetric flowers in the Allionia inflorescence bloom
    synchronously and are sufficiently closely situated that the entire inflorescence resembles a
    single radially symmetric flower. The fruit is among the most complex in the family. The convex
    side, oriented toward the center of the cluster of three flowers, exudes copious mucilage when
    wetted. The viscid glands on the concave surface remain sticky for decades in the
    herbarium.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Turner, B. L. 1994. Revisionary study of the genus Allionia
      (Nyctaginaceae). Phytologia 77: 45–55.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits deeply convex adaxially; lateral ribs developed as curved wings with 0–4
        irregular or reg ular triangular teeth; viscid glands on concave side on stalks usually
        equaling or shorterthan diameter of glandular head</description>
      <determination>1. Allionia incarnataglandular head</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
