<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">nyctaginaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Jussieu" date="1789">abronia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. Watson" date="1879">nana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14: 294. 1879</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family nyctaginaceae;genus abronia;species nana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, acaulescent or nearly so, usually cespitose. Leaves: petiole 1–5 cm; blade elliptic to lanceolate, shortly ovate, or oblong-ovate, (0.4–)0.5–2.5 × (0.2–)0.4–1.2 cm, less than 3 times as long as wide, margins entire or ± repand and undulate, surfaces glabrous or glandular-pubescent. Inflorescences: bracts lanceolate to ovate, 4–9 × 2–7 mm, scarious, glandular-puberulent, often minutely so; flowers 15–25. Perianth: tube pale pink, 8–30 mm, limb white to pink, 6–10 mm diam. Fruits obovate to obcordate in profile, 6–10 × 5–7 mm, scarious, apex low and broadly conic; wings 5, without dilations, without cavities.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States.</description>
  <number>17.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Abronia nana is a highly variable species. Perhaps contraction of the range of A. nana during the Pleistocene left isolated populations that have since diverged. This is especially apparent on the southern edge of the range of the species. In northeastern Arizona, densely tufted plants with very small blades are similar to short-leaved plants of A. bigelovii from north-central New Mexico.</discussion>
  <discussion>Based on the fruits, the taxon described as Abronia nana var. harrisii S. L. Welsh is A. elliptica.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic-lanceolate to elliptic-ovate; inflorescence bracts ovate to oblong-lanceolate,or vestigial</description>
      <determination>17a. Abronia nana ### var. nana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades shortly ovate to oblong-ovate; inflo-rescence bracts lanceolate</description>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
