<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>GALENIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 359. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5, 169. 1754</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Claudius Galenius, a.d. 130–200, Roman physician and writer on medicine]</etymology><author>Nancy J. Vivrette</author><description>Subshrubs [herbs or shrubs], perennial. Roots fibrous. Stems ± prostrate, semiwoody at base, with vesicular, peltate, hairlike scales. Leaves cauline, alternate [opposite], sessile; stipules absent; blade flat, margins entire; earlier leaves larger within 1 growing season. Inflorescences axillary, flowers solitary, sessile; bracts absent. Flowers bisexual, inconspicuous, 2–3 mm diam.; calyx tubular; calyx lobes [4 or]5, white, pink, or yellow, linear, oblong, or lanceolate-oblong; petals and petaloid staminodia absent; nectary glands absent; stamens 10, paired, pairs alternating with calyx lobes; pistil 2–5-carpellate; ovary superior, 2–5-loculed, angled; placentation apical-axile; ovule 1 per locule, with long funicles; styles 2–5; stigmas 2–5. Fruits capsules, 3–5-angled, leathery, apex 3–5-lobed, truncate, dehiscence loculicidal at apex of angles. Seeds 2–5, black, ribbed, triangular to compressed and reniform, 1 mm, shiny, tuberculate; arils absent.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 27 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>s Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution>Australia.</global_distribution><discussion>The two species of Galenia introduced in the flora belong to subgenus Kolleria (C. Presl) Frenzl as emended by R. S. Adamson (1956; 21 spp.). Kolleria is characterized by alternate, obovate leaves over 5 mm wide, four or five perianth segments, and four or five styles.</discussion><discussion>The key below is adapted from A. Prescott (1984).</discussion><references>
    <reference>Adamson, R. S. 1956. The South African species of Aizoaceae III. Galenia L. J. S. African Bot. 22: 87–127.</reference>
    <reference> Prescott, A. 1984. Galenia. In: R. Robertson et al., eds. 1981+. Flora of Australia. 23+ vols. Canberra. Vol. 4, pp. 50–52.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves and stems gray-green; younger stems with sparse, closely appressed scales, 0.5 mm;calyx lobes white to pink adaxially; styles 5</statement>
      <determination>1. Galenia pubescens</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves and stems gray-white; younger stems with abundant, loosely appressed scales, 1.5mm; calyx lobes white to yellow adaxially; styles usually 4</statement>
      <determination>2. Galenia secunda</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
