<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>CARPOBROTUS</genus_name><genus_authority>N. E. Brown</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gard. Chron., ser.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3, 78: 433. 1925</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Fig-marigold</common_name><etymology>[Greek karpos , fruit, and brota , edible things]</etymology><author>Nancy J. Vivrette</author><description>Subshrubs, succulent, glabrous. Roots fibrous. Stems trailing, mat-forming, 5–30 dm; rooting at nodes; inflorescence branches ascending. Leaves cauline, opposite, slightly connate basally, sessile, those of each pair equal; stipules absent; blade straight or curved, rounded-triangular to sharply 3-angled in cross section, thick, fleshy, margins entire or dentate. Inflorescences terminal or axillary, flowers solitary; bracts absent or 2, leaflike; pedicel [absent or 1–]10–60[–100] mm, erect. Flowers showy, tubular, 3–10[–15] cm diam.; calyx lobes 4–5, unequal, 2 larger ± opposite, sometimes leaflike, 2–3 inner, smaller, with expanded membranous margins; petals (including petaloid staminodia) to 250, distinct, magenta, pink, yellow, cream, or white; nectary absent; stamens to 600, erect; pistil 8–12[–25]-carpellate; ovary inferior, 8–12[–25]-loculed; placentation parietal; style absent; stigmas 8–12[–25], radiate, linear, plumose. Fruits berries, fleshy, edible, indehiscent; valves absent. Seeds to 1000, brown, obovoid, compressed, shiny, slightly tuberculate; arils absent.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 13 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>s Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution>also introduced in Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>South America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution>Australia.</global_distribution><discussion>Species of Carpobrotus naturalize vegetatively and from seed.</discussion><references>
    <reference>Blake, S. T. 1969. A revision of Carpobrotus and Sarcozona in Australia, genera allied to Mesembryanthemum (Aizoaceae). Contr. Queensland Herb. 7: 1–65.</reference>
    <reference> Brown, N. E. 1928. Mesembryanthemum and allied genera. J. Bot. 66: 322–327.</reference>
    <reference> Wisura, W. and H. F. Glen. 1993. The South African species of Carpobrotus (Mesembryanthema–Aizoaceae). Contr. Bolus Herb. 15: 76–107.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Flowers 3–5 cm diam.; petals rose-magenta; leaves 4–7 cm, rounded-triangular in cross</statement>
      <determination>1. Carpobrotus chilensis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Flowers 8–10 cm diam.; petals yellow, aging pink; leaves 6–10 cm, sharply triangular incross section, outer angle serrate near tip</statement>
      <determination>2. Carpobrotus edulis</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
