<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>6.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>GISEKIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Mant. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 554, 562 (as Gisechia). 1771</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Paul Dietrich Giseke, 1741–1796, German professor, botanist, and pupil of Linnaeus]</etymology><description>Herbs, annual. Leaves opposite or appearing whorled. Inflorescences axillary, compound dichasia, appearing umbelliform. Flowers: sepals 5; stamens 5; carpels 5, free; ovaries 5, each 1-loculed; style and stigma 1 per carpel; stigma terminal. Fruits: group of thin-walled, lenticular achenes. Seed 1 per carpel.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 5 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Eurasia</global_distribution><global_distribution>Africa.</global_distribution><discussion>Described as “debatably phytolaccaceous” by G. K. Rogers (1985), Gisekia has been referred also to Aizoaceae, Molluginaceae, and even Portulacaceae—and, perhaps the best solution, to its own family, Gisekiaceae.</discussion><discussion>The generic name is sometimes misspelled as “Giesekia.”</discussion><references>
    <reference>Bogle, A. L. 1970b. The genera of Molluginaceae and Aizoaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 51: 431–462.</reference>
    <reference> Gilbert, M. G. 1993. A review of Gisekia (Gisekiaceae). Kew Bull. 48: 343–356.</reference>
    <reference> Godfrey, R. K. 1961. Gisekia pharnacioides, a new weed. Rhodora 63: 226–228.</reference>
    <reference> Narayana, L. L. and P. S. Narayana. 1989. The bearing of amino acids on the status and systematic position of Gisekia Linnaeus. J. Econ. Tax. Bot. 13: 699–704.</reference>
    <reference> Narayana, P. S. and L. L. Narayana. 1988. Systematic position of Gisekia Linnaeus—a numerical assessment. Feddes Repert. 99: 189–193.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
