<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>PERESKIA</genus_name><genus_authority>Miller</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gard. Dict. Abr. ed.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4, vol. 3. 1754</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Nicolas Claude Fabri de Peiresc, 1580–1637, French scholar]</etymology><author>Michael W. Hawkes</author><description>Stems straight or zig-zag. Spines 1–12 per areole. Flowers from areoles of new growth, fragrant or not; outer tepals often greenish, colored near margins; inner tepals white, yellow, orange-red, red, pink to purplish; stamens 50–100 in small-flowered species, to 300 in large-flowered species; filaments colorless near base, in some species pigmented distally, color either matching inner tepals or contrasting with them; styles shorter to longer than stamens; stigma lobes 3–20. x = 11.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 17 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>tropical and subtropical regions in the New World</global_distribution><global_distribution>primarily South America.</global_distribution><discussion>Whether the populations of Pereskia in the flora area are reproducing sexually or maintaining themselves solely by vegetative means remains unclear. The population biology of both species and their long-term persistence in the flora need to be monitored.</discussion><references>
    <reference>Leuenberger, B. E. 1986. Pereskia (Cactaceae). Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 41: 1–141.</reference>
    <reference> Leuenberger, B. E. 1992. Leaf-bearing cacti (genus Pereskia) in cultivation. Cact. Succ. J. (Los Angeles) 64: 247–263.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants clambering shrubs or vines; first spines formed in each areole recurved and clawlike, secondary spines straight; fruits not angled, less than 40 × 15–25 mm, never proliferating;flowers fragrant</statement>
      <determination>1. Pereskia aculeata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants erect shrubs or trees; all spines straight; fruits angled, 50–100 × 30–70 mm, oftenproliferating; flowers not fragrant</statement>
      <determination>2. Pereskia grandifolia</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
