<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>9.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Opuntia</genus_name><species_name>chlorotica</species_name><species_authority>Engelma nn &amp; J. M. Bigelow</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3: 291. 1856</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Pancake pricklypear</common_name><description>Trees or shrubs, erect, 2–2.5 m, with spiny, well-defined trunk to 30 cm diam. Stem segments not disarticulating, blue-green, flattened, obovate to circular, 13–21 × 11.5–19 cm, nearly smooth, glabrous; areoles 7–10 per diagonal row across midstem segment, subcircular to elliptic, with basal ridge, 3–6 × 2.5–4 mm; wool tan, aging grayish white. Spines absent or usually in distal areoles to evenly distributed over entire stem segment, yellow, aging red-brown to blackish, straight or weakly curved, ± acicular, deflexed, or some erect in marginal areoles; larger spines 0–7 per areole, terete or basally flattened, 25–45 mm, usually accompanied by few straight to wavy bristle-spines. Glochids crowded in narrow crescent along adaxial margins, longer toward base of areole margins, subapical tuft absent or poorly developed, yellow, aging reddish brown, to 14 mm. Flowers: inner tepals yellow (sometimes with reddish blush near base), abaxially reddish streaked along midveins, broadly spatulate-apiculate, 18–30 mm; filaments white to yellow; anthers; style and stigma lobes white, yellowish, or pale green. Fruits red, barrel-shaped, 30–60 × 18–40 mm, fleshy (often mummifying), glabrous, spineless; umbilicus 6–9 mm deep; areoles 40–68. Seeds yellowish, 3.5–4 × 3–3.5 mm, 1.5–1.8 mm thick, reniform to subcircular, flattened, often warped; girdle protruding 0.1–0.5 mm. 2n = 22.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>desert grasslands</habitat><habitat>woodlands</habitat><habitat>chaparral</habitat><habitat>desert flats</habitat><habitat>rocky ledges</habitat><habitat>hills</habitat><habitat>canyons</habitat><elevation>600–2400 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Utah</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Baja California).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Baja California Sur).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Sonora).</global_distribution><discussion>Opuntia chlorotica hybridizes with O. santa-rita in southeastern Arizona and with the hexaploid O. phaeacantha forming the tetraploid O. ×curvispina in areas of Arizona, California, and Nevada.</discussion></treatment>
