<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard W. Spellenberg</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">NYCTAGINACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">BOERHAVIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 3. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 4. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family NYCTAGINACEAE;genus BOERHAVIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Hermann Boerhaave, 1668–1738, physician and botanist of Leiden]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, sometimes suffrutescent at base, slender, often glandular, glabrous, or pubescent, from slender and soft or stout, ± woody, and ropelike or fusiform taproot. Stems procumbent, decumbent, ascending, or erect, unarmed, with or without glutinous bands on internodes. Leaves petiolate, pairs unequal in size in each pair; blade thin or thick and slightly fleshy, base symmetric to asymmetric. Inflorescences terminal and axillary, pedunculate or not clearly pedunculate because of repeated branching from distal axils, diffuse, and then usually widely cymose, paniculate, or thyrsiform, terminal portions cymose, racemose, spicate, subumbellate, umbellate, subcapitate, or capitate, rarely borne singly; bracts ± persistent and not accrescent, or deciduous, 1–3 beneath each flower, distinct, lanceolate, minute, thin, translucent. Flowers bisexual, chasmogamous; perianth radially symmetric or slightly bilaterally symmetric, campanulate or widely funnelform, constricted beyond ovaries, tube abruptly expanded to (4–)5-lobed limb; stamens 2–8, included or exserted; styles at or extending beyond anthers; stigmas peltate. Fruits fusiform, clavate, oblong-clavate, obovoid, or obpyramidal, stiffly coriaceous; ribs (3–)5, rounded, angular, or winglike, smooth, glabrous or glandular-pubescent; sulci smooth or rugose, epidermal surface smooth, papillate, or minutely pubescent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">warm-temperate and tropical regions worldwide.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Spiderling</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 40 (16 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Numerous authors, particularly those of the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, “corrected” to Boerhaavia Linneaus’ intentional Latinization (Boerhavia) of Boerhaave’s name. Boerhavia sometimes includes Anulocaulis, Commicarpus, and Cyphomeris (F. R. Fosberg 1978). At the species level, there is variation that is often difficult to treat taxonomically, especially among annuals of the Sonoran Desert and the pantropical B. diffusa–B. coccinea complex. Many species probably are highly autogamous (R. Spellenberg 2000). P. C. Standley’s publications on the family in North America (1909, 1911, 1918) have been the basis for much of the subsequent floristic efforts, with all authors taking a more conservative approach. Nevertheless, careful examination of Boerhavia fruits indicates that some of the entities that Standley proposed represent distinct taxa. For most species in the flora, identification requires mature fruits. In this treatment, the range of ratios of length to width (l/w) of individual fruits of a species is given as a means to relate shape. Fruits from a number of Boerhavia species exude mucilage when wet (J. M. Willson and R. Spellenberg 1977).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits glandular-pubescent or minutely pubescent; plants perennial.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly distributed throughout plant; inflorescences axillary or terminal; branches spreading-villous or hispid to minutely and finely pubescent; flowers usually more than 5 per cluster;fruits narrowly obovate and tapering at both ends or clavate, apex</description>
      <determination>2. Boerhavia coccinea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves mostly concentrated in basal 1 / 2of plant; inflorescences mostly terminal; branches glabrate or glabrous; flowers usually borne singly or up to 5 per cluster, occasionally more; fruits oblong-clavate or obpyramidal, apex round, broadly conic, or truncate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths wine red or brick red, 2–4.5 mm; stamens well exserted; flowers usually borne singly on slender pedicels; fru its oblong-clavate, minutely pubescent, some-times with minute gland-tipped hairs</description>
      <determination>3. Boerhavia gracillima ### (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths purplish red to reddish pink or nearly white, 1–1.5 mm; stamens included or barely exserted; flowers usually in tight clust ers of 2–5 at ends of branches;fruits obpyramidal, conspicuously stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>1. Boerhavia diffusa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits glabrous (rarely with some minute pubescence in sulci); plants annual or perennial.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; fruit ribs rounded or bluntly ro und-angled.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts at base of perianths soon deciduous after anthesis; perianths wine red tobrick red; sulci of fruit usually smooth</description>
      <determination>3. Boerhavia gracillima ### (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts at base of perianths persistent; perianths red-pink, pink-lavender, pin k, or white; sulci of fruit smooth or papillate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear to lanceolate, rarely ovate; perianths 4–7 mm; stamens usually</description>
      <determination>6. Boerhavia linearifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ovate to round; perianths 2.5–10 mm; stamens 3–8; surface ofsulci minutely papillate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths 5–10 mm; stamens (4–)5–8; edges of fruit ribs rounded, notoverhanging sulci</description>
      <determination>4. Boerhavia anisophylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths 2.5–3 mm; stamens 3–5; edges of fruit ribs sharp, slightly over-hanging sulci</description>
      <determination>5. Boerhavia ci liata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants annual; fruit ribs obtusely to acutely angled, ribs sometimes winglike, rarely bluntly round-angled.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches of inflorescence densely glandular-villous, rarely minutely pubescent or glabrous, without sticky bands on distal internodes; bracts at base of perianth 1.5–4 mm, ovate (occasionally lance-acuminate in B. wrightii ), persistent; fruits 4- or 5-ribbed, ribs never winglike.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits 4(–5)-ribbed; inflorescences racemose or spicate, axis 10–35 mm</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits5-ribbed; inflorescences subcapitate or capitate, axis 0–2.5 mm</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches of inflorescence usually glabrous, sometimes minutely pubescent but not glandular, often with sticky bands on distal internodes; bracts at base of p erianth 0.4–1.8 mm, usually lanceolate or narrower, deciduous; fruits (3–)5-ribbed, ribs sometimes winglike.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Terminal portions of inflorescences spicate or racemose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits broadly obovoid (l/w: usually 1.7–2.1), usually overlapping in inflorescence; sulci and ribs slightly rugose; sulci usually about 0.5 times as wide as base of ribs; stemsusually glandular and spreading-pilose basally</description>
      <determination>14. Boerhavia spicata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits narrowly obovoid or obpyramidal (l/w: usua lly 2.1–3.1), overlapping in inflorescence or remote; sulci and ribs slightly rugose to smooth; sulci 0.1–1 times as wide as base of ribs; stems puberulent, often sparsely pilose, rarely glandular basally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Epidermal surface of sulci papillose; sulci 0.5–1 times as wide as base of ribs; sidesof ribs strongly rugose</description>
      <determination>15. Boerhavia torreyana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Epidermal surface of sulci glabrous; sulci 0.1–0.3 times as wide as base of ribs; sidesof ribs smooth or slightly rugose</description>
      <determination>16. Boerhavia coulteri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Termin al portions of inflorescences subracemose, subumbellate, umbellate, or capitate, or flowers borne singly.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits 3–4(–5)-ribbed, ribs acute or winglike.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences capitate clusters on short peduncles among leaves and terminal onbranches; fr uit tapering to stipelike base distal to pedicels</description>
      <determination>11. Boerhavia pterocarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences repeatedly forked, ending in umbels or single flowers, usually wellbeyond leaves; fruit tapering to pedicels, without stipelike base</description>
      <determination>9. Boerhavia triquetra</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits (3–)5-ribbed, ribs winglike or not.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sulci of fruits smooth or very slightly rugose; fruits with 5 winglike ribs</description>
      <determination>10. Boerhavia megaptera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sulci of fruits slightly to prominently rugose; fruits with (4–)5 angular ribs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Terminal flower clusters usually precise umbels, all pedicels attaching at 1 node;occasionally terminal inflorescences 1-flowered; fruits 2–3.2 mm</description>
      <determination>8. Boerhavia intermedia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Terminal flower clusters irregularly umbellate or subracemose, at least some pedicels attaching well below others; terminal inflorescences rarely 1-flowered;fruits 2.7–4 mm</description>
      <determination>7. Boerhavia erecta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
