<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>34.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Opuntia</genus_name><species_name>polyacan</species_name><species_authority>tha Haworth</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Suppl. Pl. Succ.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>82. 1819</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Starvation pricklypear</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Cactus</genus_name><species_name>ferox</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 296. 1818,</place_in_publication><other_info>not Willdenow 1813</other_info></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Tunas</genus_name><species_name>polyacantha</species_name><species_authority>(Haworth) Nieuwland &amp; Lunell</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs, low, 10–25 cm, with ± prostrate branches. Stem segments not easily detached, green, elliptic to narrowly to broadly obovate to circular, 4–27 × 2–18 cm, low tuberculate; areoles 4–14 per diagonal row across midstem segment, subcircular, 3–6 mm; wool tan to brown. Spines at all or only distal areoles of stem segment, terete to flattened, stout to acicular to bristlelike, straight to curling, of 1 or 2 kinds; if 1 kind: 0–18 per areole, spreading and curling in various directions, sometimes straight, erect, ascending to deflexed, yellow to dark brown to black, turning gray, pink-gray to gray-brown, longest (35–)40–90(–185) mm; if ± 2 kinds: major spines (0–)1–5, reflexed to porrect, yellow-brown to brown to gray, longest 20–150 mm; minor spines (0–)5–11, deflexed, white to white-gray, longest 4–16 mm. Glochids inconspicuous, in narrow, tidy crescent at adaxial edge of areole or in broad, brushy crescent and tuft, yellow to reddish, aging brown, to 10 mm. Flowers: inner tepals yellow to magenta throughout, 25–40 mm; filaments white, yellow, or red to magenta (flowers may superficially appear bicolored); anthers yellow; style white to pale pink; stigma lobes green. Fruits tan to brown, ± cylindric, 15–45 × 12–25 mm, dry at maturity, glabrous, sometimes burlike; areoles 10–33, each or only distal areoles bearing 3–16 spines, 4–20 mm. Seeds tan to gray, flattened, warped, oblong to subcircular, 3–7 × 2–4 mm; girdle protruding 1–2 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 5 (5 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w United States</global_distribution><global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution><discussion>Populations of Opuntia polyacantha with spines few or absent (especially var. hystricina) were the basis for several names including O. juniperina, O. utahensis, and O. rhodantha.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Areoles 4–6 per diagonal row across midstem segment; stem segments 4–7 × 2–3(–5) cm, elliptic to very narrowly obovate; Texas, New Mexico,</statement>
      <determination>34b. Opuntia polyacantha ### var. arenaria</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Areoles 6–14 per diagonal row across midstem segment; stem segments 6–27 × 5–18 cm, obovate to circular or, if elliptic, longer than 9 cm; widespread in w United States and Canada.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spines of 2 kinds: majo r spines 1–3 per areole, usually deflexed on terminal stem segment, but sometimes ascending at stem segment apex; minor spines 1–3 per areole, deflexed, white, subtending major spines.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Longest spines 2–4 cm; areoles 6–13 mm apart; stem segments 6–12 cm;Great Plains, n and e Great Basin Desert)</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Longest spines 4.5–12 cm; areoles 12–30 mm apart; stem segments 10–27 cm; Arizona and Utah border</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Spines of 1 kind, grading in length, from ascending to deflexed, 7–18 per areole, longest spines of terminal stem segment porrect to ascending, shorter spines deflexed to porrect.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spines usually dark brown, those of proximal stem segments like those of terminal stem segm ents, porrect to ascending, straight and stiff; fruit areoles 11–21, spiny but not burlike</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spines usually pale, those of proximal stem segments not like those of terminals stem segments, more numerous, longe r and more reflexed, straight or flexuous and/or hairlike or threadlike; fruit areoles 20–33, spiny, forming dense bur</statement>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
