<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Bruce D. Parfitt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Eaton" date="unknown">Cactoideae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Dict. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4, 43. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Cactaceae;subfamily Cactoideae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>37c.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">Cacteae</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 111, species ca. 1500 (28 genera, 121 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Subfamily Cactoideae is the most diverse group of the Cactaceae, in terms of size, architecture, habitat, and habit. The vast majority of North American species are xerophytic, with columnar to spheric or barrel-shaped stems. A few are geophytic, that is, stems are mostly deep-seated in the soil substrate, often with the plant consisting mostly of an enlarged taproot and the visible parts of the stems appearing nearly flush with the soil surface or nearly buried during drought, becoming taller and slightly more conspicuous only during the growing season. Fewer species still, are epiphytic, and those only in the tropical and subtropical regions of North America and South America.</discussion>
  <discussion>In the following treatments, most authors have attempted to recognize varieties wherever current evidence is compelling. Where evidence is equivocal, our tendency has been to include greater variability within varieties and, hence, fewer formal trinomials. Unfortunately, in the absence of strong supporting evidence, herbarium specimens of cacti are usually inadequate for the purpose of making taxonomic decisions. As a consequence, some populations of conservation interest here have been placed into synonmy before critical studies have been conducted to determine quantitatively and objectively how distinct each population is, or which deserve varietal status. Authors do not intend to imply that other varieties should not eventually be recognized. More systematic work, including DNA research and field research of all variants, is needed as a prelude to reassessing the status of currently listed and proposed populations. Such populations need to be protected during the entire phase of analysis and reassessment.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
