<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>ACANTHOCEREUS</genus_name><genus_authority>(Engelmann ex A. Berger) Britton &amp; Rose</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>12: 432. 1909</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek akantha , thorn, and Cereus , a genus of cacti]</etymology><author>Bruce D. Parfitt</author><author>Arthur C. Gibson</author><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Cereus</genus_name><genus_authority>Miller</genus_authority><subsection_name>canthocereus</subsection_name><subsection_authority>Engelmann ex A. Berger</subsection_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Rep. (Annual) Missouri Bot. Gard. </publication_title><place_in_publication>16: 77. 1905</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs, erect to arching, clambering, or climbing, often sparingly branched, sometimes forming impenetrable thickets. Roots diffuse, adventitious where arching stems touch soil. Stems segmented or unsegmented, green, greatly elongate, angled, 30–400[–700] × (4–)6–10 cm; ribs 3–5[–7], narrowly triangular to winglike, very prominent, 3–5 cm deep, less than 1 cm thick, rib crests undulate; areoles widely spaced, located next to sinuses, 2–5 cm apart along ribs, circular to oval, short woolly. Spines [0–]4–10 per areole, diffusely spreading, brown or reddish [white, yellowish, or black], aging gray, ± straight, acicular to subulate, terete or somewhat flattened, longest spines 10–40[–70] mm, hard; radial spines [0–]6–8 per areole, 5–25 mm; central spines [0–]1–2[–4] per areole, 0–40 mm. Flowers nocturnal, lateral to terminal on stems 1 or more years old, at adaxial edge of areoles, funnelform, [11–]14–20[–25] cm; outer tepals green or purple tinged, lanceolate-linear, 3–5 × 1 cm; inner tepals white, broadly linear to narrowly oblanceolate, 5–15 × 1–4 cm, margins entire or minutely denticulate; ovary minutely scaly, spiny [spineless], with short wool; stigma lobes 10–15, white, to 12 mm. Fruits indehiscent or irregularly dehiscent longitudinally, red to red-purple, spheric, ovoid, ellipsoid, oblong, or pyriform, 30–80[–120] mm, fleshy or juicy [tough in A. columbianus], scaly, spiny [or spineless]; scales deciduous; pulp red; floral remnant persistent. Seeds black, broadly obovoid, to 4.8 mm, smooth and shiny; testa cells flat. x = 11.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 6 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>se United States</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution>n and e South America.</global_distribution><discussion>Acanthocereus needs critical taxonomic study. E. F. Anderson (2001) followed W. Barthlott and D. R. Hunt (1993) in recognizing six species; other accounts have recognized up to twelve species or as few as two (A. tetragonus and A. occidentalis Britton &amp; Rose).</discussion><references>
    <reference>Hunt, D. R. 1991. Acanthocereus. Bradleya 9: 82–83.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
