<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Engelmann in F. A.Wislizenus" date="1848">echinocereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Engelmann) F. Seitz" date="1870">stramineus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="unknown" date="unknown">stramineus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cactaceae;genus echinocereus;species stramineus;variety stramineus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants branched, forming clumps or compact mounds of 20–100(–500) branches, clumps
        15–60(–100) cm, either dense or lax. Stems erect, long ovoid, less than 30 × 4.5–11 cm; ribs
        10–16; crests slightly undulate; areoles 12–20(–25) mm apart. Spines 9–14(–16) per areole,
        straight, straw colored, ± translucent, often glassy white tinted with yellow, darkest
        spines sometimes tan or brown; radial spines 7–14 per areole, 15–40 mm; central spines
        2–4(–5) per areole, abaxial central spine strongly projecting, all central spines terete or
        somewhat flattened, 57–100 mm. Flowers 8–12 × 10–12.5(–15) cm; flower tube 25–35 × 15–35 mm;
        flower tube hairs 1–1.5 mm; inner tepals rose-pink to magenta, darkest proximally and/or
        centrally, 55–60(–80) × 12–25 mm, tips white to greenish, relatively thin and delicate;
        anthers yellow; nectar chamber ± 5–8 mm. Fruits bright pinkish brown, with characteristic
        reticulate pattern of slightly darker or greener color between flattened tubercles, usually
        35–40(–50) mm, pulp white to pale pink (varying on same plant). 2n = 44.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Mar-Jul; fruiting mostly Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Chihuahuan desert scrub, rocky slopes, rarely flats, igneous and sedimentary substrates;</description>
  <description type="elevation">500-1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex., Tex.; Mexico (Chihuahua, Coahuila, Nuevo León).</description>
  <number>2a.</number>
  <discussion>The densely branched stems of Echinocereus stramineus form hemispheric mounds
        bristling with unusually long, yellow-tinted spines, thus appearing like a heap of straw;
        old clumps of these cacti are unique visual dominants on many rocky slopes in the Chihuahuan
        Desert. The delicious ripe fruits of this species are much larger than those of E.
        enneacanthus, and may be the largest fruits in the genus. Rare white-flowered individuals
        occur.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
