<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Engelmann in F. A.Wislizenus" date="1848">echinocereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Parry ex Engelmann) Lemaire" date="1868">engelmannii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cactées,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>56. 1868</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cactaceae;genus echinocereus;species engelmannii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Parry ex Engelmann" date="unknown">engelmannii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. J. Sci. Arts, ser.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 14: 338. 1852 (as engelmanni)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cereus;species engelmannii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Echinocereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">engelmannii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="L. D. Benson" date="unknown">armatus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Echinocereus;species engelmannii;variety armatus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Echinocereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">engelmannii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Engelmann &amp; Bigelow) Rümpler" date="unknown">chrysocentrus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Echinocereus;species engelmannii;variety chrysocentrus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Echinocereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">engelmannii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="L. D. Benson" date="unknown">howei</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Echinocereus;species engelmannii;variety howei;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 3–60-branched, ultimately forming somewhat open clumps. Stems mostly erect,
        cylindric or somewhat tapering distally, (5–)14–45(–70) × 3–9 cm; ribs 10–13, crests
        slightly undulate; areoles 6–10(–15) mm apart. Spines (8–)15–20 per areole, usually straight
        (curved and twisted in desert mountains and peninsular ranges of California), individual
        spines with broad zones of different colors: whitish or grayish, dull golden-yellow, or
        reddish brown to nearly black; radial spines 6–14 per areole, 8–20(–50) mm; central spines
        (2–)4–6(–9) per areole, divergent-porrect, 12–70 mm, abaxial central spine often fading
        whitish, flat to sharply angled (terete or nearly so in north-central Arizona). Flowers 6–9
        × 5–9 cm; flower tube 13–30 × 10–30 mm; flower tube hairs 1 mm; inner tepals bright
        rose-pink to magenta, often varying from paler to darker in same population, proximally
        darker, 37–75 × (8–)14–25 mm, tips relatively thin, delicate; anthers yellow; nectar chamber
        4–6 mm. Fruits red or orangish, 25–45 mm, pulp whitish be-coming infused with pink or red
        from the skin. 2n = 44.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Mar-Apr; fruiting May-Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sonoran and Mojave deserts, chaparral, pinyon-juniper woodlands;</description>
  <description type="elevation">200-2400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., Calif., Nev., Utah; Mexico (Baja California, Sonora).</description>
  <number>9.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Engelmann’s hedgehog cactus</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">strawberry hedgehog cactus</other_name>
  <discussion>The characteristics distinguishing Echinocereus engelmannii from E. fasciculatus to
        the east are poorly documented, and W. Blum et al. (1998) combined the two as separate
        subspecies of E. engelmannii. Historically, E. engelmannii has been characterized as having
        the abaxial central spine in each areole particularly long, pale, and strongly compressed
        dorsiventrally (sharply angled, hence daggerlike), contrasting with the other spines. In
        practice that trait is not always diagnostic. Plants called Echinocereus engelmannii var.
        acicularis L. D. Benson are essentially morphologically and geographically intermediate
        between those referred to E. fasciculatus and E. engelmannii var.
        chrysocentrus.</discussion>
  <discussion>The history of confusion with Echinocereus nicholii has resulted in
        misidentification of yellow-spined individuals of E. engelmannii.</discussion>
  <discussion>Spine color polymorphism, common within Echinocereus engelmannii, provided the
        original basis for varieties chrysocentrus and purpureus. The well-marked, identifiable
        extremes often occur in populations that include individuals easily assigned to other named
        varieties, or not assignable to any. L. D. Benson (1969, 1982) and subsequent authors (e.g.,
        N. P. Taylor 1985; W. Blum et al. 1998) have attempted to recognize infraspecific taxa
        within E. engelmannii. However, one of those is clearly a distinct species (E. nicholii),
        while the remainder are either too poorly defined or too poorly known to treat fully here.
        At higher elevations beyond the western edge of the desert, E. engelmannii var. munzii
        (Parish) P. Pierce &amp; Fosberg has been distinguished by its curving, twisting, gray
        spines, somewhat resembling spines of westernmost plants of E. triglochidiatus var.
        mojavensis. Plants of the western Sonoran Desert margin in the Mexican boundary region in
        California are the typical E. engelmannii var. engelmannii. Similar plants from the
        opposite, eastern, side of the Sonoran Desert, in Arizona, have been called E. engelmannii
        var. acicularis L. D. Benson. In the intervening Colorado River Valley is spinier E.
        engelmannii var. chrysocentrus (Engelmann &amp; J. M. Bigelow) Rümpler. In E. engelmannii
        var. acicularis at the lowest altitudes, central spines are usually four, in which cases
        taxonomic segregation from E. engelmannii var. chrysocentrus seems arbitrary. At higher
        altitudes, plants of E. engelmannii var. acicularis with only one or two central spines per
        areole are frequent, and the abaxial central spine may be terete instead of angular and
        daggerlike as in E. engelmannii var. chrysocentrus. The most formidably spiny extremes of
        the species were segregated as E. engelmannii vars. howei and armatus; however, other
        individuals in the original populations (type localities) are readily assigned to E.
        engelmannii var. chrysocentrus. W. Blum et al. (1998) placed all of the above varieties
        under E. engelmannii subsp. engelmannii.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants smaller in all parts and with fewer central spines from north-central Arizona
        are Echinocereus engelmannii subsp. decumbens (Clover &amp; Jotter) W. Blum &amp; Mich.
        Lange. L. D. Benson (1969) referred those to var. variegatus (Engelmann &amp; J. M. Bigelow)
        Rümpler, but the type locality of var. variegatus is in a different region. The status of E.
        engelmannii var. purpureus L. D. Benson remains uncertain; its similarity to unidentified
        diploid material found in northern Arizona suggests that it could be a separate species, but
        more variable than its original diagnosis allowed.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
