<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Engelmann in F. A.Wislizenus" date="1848">echinocereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Engelmann in F. A. Wislizenus" date="1848">coccineus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in F. A. Wislizenus, Mem. Tour N. Mexico,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>93. 1848</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cactaceae;genus echinocereus;species coccineus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Echinocereus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Engelmann" date="unknown">coccineus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="(Engelmann ex S. Watson) W. Blum" date="unknown">aggregatus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mich. Lange &amp; Rutow</publication_title>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Echinocereus;species coccineus;subspecies aggregatus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Echinoce</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">triglochidiatus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Engelmann) L. D. Benson" date="unknown">melanacanthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Echinoce;species triglochidiatus;variety melanacanthus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants commonly 20–100(–500)-branched, loosely aggregated into clumps or tightly
        packed into rounded mounds, to 100 cm diam. Stems erect, cylindric (or spheric), 5–40 × 4–15
        cm; ribs (5–)6–14, crests slightly (or conspicuously) undulate; areoles 10–20(–42) mm apart.
        Spines (1–)5–16(–22) per areole, mostly straight except on unusually long-spined
        individuals, ashy white to gray, brown, yellowish, reddish, or black, often dark tipped;
        radial spines (1–)4–13(–18) per areole, appressed to slightly projecting, (3–)5–40(–49) mm;
        central spines 0–6 per areole, spreading to projecting outward, terete (to angular),
        (5–)10–80 mm. Flowers unisexual, (2.5–)3.8–8(–9) × (1.5–)3–7 cm; flower tube (12–)15–40 ×
        8–30 mm; flower tube hairs usually 1–2 mm; inner tepals crimson or scarlet, less often
        orange-red (very rarely rose-pink), with or without whitish or yellowish (or pink) proximal
        portion, usually 14–40 × 5–16 mm, tips thick and rigid; anthers usually pink or purple
        (rarely yellow); nectar chamber 4–10 mm (longer if measurement includes tube formed by
        connate stamen bases). Fruits greenish or yellowish to pinkish, bright red or brownish
        tinged, 20–40(–72) mm or less, pulp white. 2n = 44.</description>
  <description type="phenology">mar</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">apr</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="habitat">chihuahuan desert</description>
  <description type="habitat">desert scrub</description>
  <description type="habitat">desert grasslands</description>
  <description type="habitat">pinyon-juniper and oak woodlands</description>
  <description type="habitat">great plains grasslands</description>
  <description type="habitat">montane forest</description>
  <description type="habitat">bajadas</description>
  <description type="habitat">rocky slopes</description>
  <description type="habitat">and cliffs</description>
  <description type="habitat">igneous, metamorphic, and limestone substrates</description>
  <description type="elevation">150–2700(–3000) m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Colo.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Chihuahua).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Coahuila).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico (Sonora).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering late Mar-Jun; fruiting 2-3 months after flowering. Chihuahuan Desert, desert scrub, desert grasslands, pinyon-juniper and oak woodlands, Great Plains grasslands, montane forest, bajadas, rocky slopes, and cliffs, igneous, metamorphic, and limestone substrates; 150-2700(-3000) m; Ariz., Colo., N.Mex., Tex.; Mexico (Chihuahua, Coahuila, Sonora).</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering late Mar-Jun; fruiting 2-3 months after flowering.</phenology>
      <habitat>Chihuahuan Desert, desert scrub, desert grasslands, pinyon-juniper and oak woodlands, Great Plains grasslands, montane forest, bajadas, rocky slopes, and cliffs, igneous, metamorphic, and limestone substrates;</habitat>
      <elevation>150-2700(-3000) m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Ariz., Colo., N.Mex., Tex.; Mexico (Chihuahua, Coahuila, Sonora).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>14.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Claret-cup cactus</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">scarlet hedgehog cactus</other_name>
  <discussion>Tetraploids belonging to Echinocereus coccineus constituted the greater part of L.
        D. Benson’s concept (1969, 1969b, 1969c, 1982) of E. triglochidiatus var. melanacanthus (see
        also discussion under 12. E. triglochidiatus). Where sympatric, the diploids and tetraploids
        are usually different in appearance, except in southeastern Arizona and extreme southwestern
        New Mexico (see discussion under 13. E. arizonicus), and in northern Arizona.</discussion>
  <discussion>The common, tetraploid, claret-cup cacti of southeastern Arizona mountain ranges
        have bisexual flowers, and they have been named Echinocereus santaritensis W. Blum &amp;
        Rutow. Similar plants from southwestern New Mexico are the basis for E. coccineus subsp.
        aggregatus [also called E. aggregatus (Engelmann ex S. Watson) Rydberg].</discussion>
  <discussion>Populations of Echinocereus coccineus form an intergrading series from densely
        spine-covered typical coccineus in Colorado and northern New Mexico to sparsely spined
        plants in west-central Texas. Populations in the mildest climates have strikingly large
        stems, but shrink when transplanted (D. Weniger 1970). Populations intermediate between
        those extremes in the El Paso region sometimes are segregated as E. coccineus subsp.
        rosei.</discussion>
  <discussion>Populations in northwestern Arizona with unusually small, narrow flowers
        Echinocereus toroweapensis (P. C. Fisher) Fuersch appear identical to E. canyonensis Clover
        &amp; Jotter (M. A. Baker, pers. comm.). A type specimen for E. toroweapensis was apparently
        never preserved, so the name may be invalid.</discussion>
  <discussion>Populations in the granitic region of central Texas (chromosome number unknown),
        probably belonging in Echinocereus coccineus, have been called E. coccineus subsp. roemeri
        (Muehlenpfordt) W. Blum, Mich. Lange &amp; Rutow. Spines are more numerous than in the
        surrounding populations on limestone.</discussion>
  <discussion>Echinocereus coccineus var. gurneyi (L. D. Benson) D. Ferguson was based on a
        short-spined plant, apparently introgressed from E. dasyacanthus, and so it pertains to E.
        ×roetteri Rümpler in the broad sense. It is not a true geographic race of E.
        coccineus.</discussion>
  <discussion>Echinocereus santaritensis and the diploid called E. nigrihorridispinus (see
        discussion under 13. E. arizonicus) are ecologically and reproductively segregated but
        difficult to distinguish morphologically, especially when sterile. Spines of E.
        santaritensis tend to be thinner but only extremes are identifiable by spine thickness
        alone. Arizona reports of E. triglochidiatus var. neomexicanus were based on robust
        individuals from both of those taxa, whereas slender-spined specimens were identified mostly
        as E. triglochidiatus var. melanacanthus. Arizona reports of E. polyacanthus were based on
        either the hairy salverform flowers of E. santaritensis or the robust plants of E.
        nigrihorridispinus.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
