<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Michael W. Hawkes</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Haworth" date="1812">EPIPHYLLUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Pl. Succ.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>197. 1812</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cactaceae;genus EPIPHYLLUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek epi , upon, and phyllon , a leaf, referring to flowers borne on leaves, actually phylloclades, leaflike stems]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, epiphytic or rarely epipetric, erect to pendent, many branched. Roots diffuse or adventitious along stems. Stems segmented, green, segments leaflike, narrowly elongate-oblanceolate, terete or 3-angled in narrow proximal portion, broadly flattened and bladelike distally, with prominent midvein-like axis, [30–]50–120+[–500] × [1.5–]4–5[–12+] cm, glabrous; ribs 2 or, on proximal portion and on juvenile stems, 3, rib margins (crests) crenate-undulate to shallow lobed [serrate to pinnatifid in other species]; areoles only in sinuses along rib margins (ca. 2–7 cm apart along rib), circular, woolly, stiff spines absent, sometimes fine, hairlike bristles present; areolar glands absent; cortex and pith mucilaginous. Spines usually absent from adult stems, present and slender on terete and juvenile stems. Flowers nocturnal [diurnal in 2 species], lateral on stem in marginal areoles, with long tube, salverform to funnelform, 8–38 cm; flower tube straight or strongly curved to 90°; outer tepals greenish [to yellow, white, or dull red] often tinged with red, 3–10 cm, margins entire; inner tepals white [to yellow], 3–10 cm, margins entire; ovary scaly, spineless, spiny, or with bristles or hairlike spines; scales small; stigma lobes 8–21, white, extending beyond stamens, ca. 10 mm. Fruits dehiscent along 1 side when mature, light green, red, or purple, smooth [to ridged or angular], ellipsoid to ovoid, [20–]40–100 × 20–50 mm, fleshy, spineless, spiny, or with bristles or hairlike spines; pulp white or slightly pinkish; floral remnant persistent. Seeds black, reniform, 2–3 × 1–2.5 mm; testa cells shiny or dull when minutely pitted. x = 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical regions of s Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n and c South America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 19 (1 in the flora): introduced; tropical regions of s Mexico, West Indies, Central America, n and c South America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 19 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; tropical regions of s Mexico, West Indies, Central America, n and c South America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>13.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Climbing cactus</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 19 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The spineless, leaflike stems of this epiphytic genus make it easy to overlook as a member of Cactaceae. The usually white, nocturnal flowers with long, thin flower tubes, copious nectar, and strong fragrance suggest hawkmoth pollinators for most species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kimnach, M. 1964. Epiphyllum phyllanthus. Cact. Succ. J. (Los Angeles) 36: 105–115.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
