<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Arthur C. Gibson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Britton &amp; Rose" date="1909">BERGEROCACTUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 435. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cactaceae;genus BERGEROCACTUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Alwin Berger, 1871–1931, German cactologist and horticulturist at La Mortola, Italy, and Cactus , an old genus name]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, ascending to erect, spreading, or reclining, usually much branched near base, forming thickets. Roots diffuse. Stems somewhat segmented, green, long cylindric, 30–150 × 3–5(–6) cm, glabrous; ribs (12–)14–18, rounded; tubercles low, indistinct; areoles to 10 mm apart on rib crests, circular, felty; areolar glands absent; cortex and pith mucilaginous. Spines 30–45 per areole, straw colored, aging brown, acicular, terete; radial spines 613 mm; central spines 1–3 per areole, to 60 mm, longest spines bend downward. Flowers diurnal, lateral to terminal on stems, from adaxial edge of areole, never on first-year shoots, funnelform, 3.5–5 cm; flower tube 15–20 mm; tepals 12–20 mm; outer tepals yellow with green or reddish midstripes and tips, oblanceolate; inner tepals yellow, oblanceolate to oblong; ovary subglobose, spines usually absent; scales deltate to ovate or awl-shaped, 1–4 mm, margins entire, with tannish hairs in axils, spiny or spineless; stigma lobes 911, pale yellow, 4–5 mm. Fruits dehiscent by extruding ribbon of pulp with seeds through apical pore, green with reddish tubercles, spheric, 25–30 mm, juicy, becoming dry after dehiscence, densely spiny like stems; pulp red; floral remnant persistent. Seeds black, obovoid, 2–3 mm, glossy; testa cells ± flat to slightly concave. x = 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States, nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>15.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Snakecactus</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Moran, R. V. 1965. Revisión de Bergerocactus. Cact. Suc. Mex. 10: 5159.</reference>
    <reference>Moran, R. V. 1966. The fruit of Bergerocactus. Natl. Cact. Succ. J. 21: 3031.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
