<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">nyctaginaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">boerhavia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. Gray" date="1853">purpurascens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. J. Sci. Arts, ser.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 15: 321. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family nyctaginaceae;genus boerhavia;species purpurascens</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual; taproot tapered, soft or ± woody. Stems erect or ascending, unbranched when small to branched ca. 1–5 times throughout, 10–60 dm, minutely puberulent to glandular-pubescent basally, usually glandular-pubescent, sometimes minutely puberulent or glabrous distally. Leaves mostly in basal 1/2; larger leaves with petiole 2–22 mm, blade oval, ovate, oblong, or lanceolate, 12–37 × 5–20 mm (distal leaves smaller, proportionately narrower), adaxial surface glabrate, sparsely puberulent, sometimes glandular-pubescent, abaxial surface not noticeably to prominently paler than adaxial, glabrate or occasionally glandular-pubescent, both surfaces usually punctate with dark cells, base round to obtuse, margins sinuate to sinuate-crisped, apex acute, obtuse, or round. Inflorescences terminal, branched ca. 1–4 times unequally, without sticky internodal bands; branches strongly ascending, terminating in compact, capitate or subcapitate flower clusters, axis 0–2.5 mm. Flowers: pedicel 0.8–2.5 mm; bracts at base of perianth persistent, 1–3, ovate to obovate, 2.5–4 mm, apex apiculate; perianth whitish to pale pink, funnelform beyond constriction, 2.5–4 mm; stamens 3–4(–5), well exserted. Fruits 3–9 per cluster, straw colored to grayish tan, broadly obovoid, 2.3–3 × 1.3–1.7 mm (l/w: 1.6–2.1), apex round or broadly obtuse, glabrous; ribs 5, acute, smooth; sulci 2–2.5 times as wide as base of ribs, not or shallowly rugose, lightly papillate.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy soils in open arid grasslands, among open shrubs or oaks, pinyon pines, juniper [thornscrub];</description>
  <description type="elevation">[200-]1300-1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex.; Mexico (Chihuahua, Sonora).</description>
  <number>13.</number>
  <discussion>The inclusion of Boerhavia purpurascens in recent Texas floras is based upon misidentified Mirabilis species (C. F. Reed 1969).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
