<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(K. Schumann) Britton &amp; Rose" date="1923">ancistrocactus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Salm-Dyck) Britton &amp; Rose" date="1923">scheeri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cact.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 4. 1923</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cactaceae;genus ancistrocactus;species scheeri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Echinocactus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Salm-Dyck" date="unknown">scheeri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cact. Hort. Dyck.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1849, 155. 1849</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Echinocactus;species scheeri;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ancistrocactus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Rose) Britton &amp; Rose" date="unknown">megarhizus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ancistrocactus;species megarhizus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sclerocactus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Salm-Dyck) N. P. Taylor" date="unknown">scheeri</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sclerocactus;species scheeri;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants unbranched (unless injured) until very old age, then few branched from
        ground level, precociously conspicuous. Roots long, fleshy, tuberlike taproots with bulbous
        swellings, sometimes having bulbous secondary roots, frequently horizontally oriented. Stem
        cylindric to club-shaped and stipitate, or spheric, to 17 × 8 cm. Spines: radial spines
        13–28 per areole, translucent yellowish, tips red-brown, longest spines 6–28 × 0.15–0.55 mm;
        central spines 3–4 per areole; abaxial central spine 1 per areole, hooked (very rarely
        straight), ± terete or adaxially flattened, generally whitish or light brown, sometimes
        adaxially dark striped with brown to black, 12–38 mm; adaxial central spines (2–)3 per
        areole, erect, straight, dorsiventrally compressed, abaxially tan to whitish, adaxially
        brown to dark reddish brown, 19–50 mm. Flowers: inner tepals consistently bright green to
        yellowish (rarely pink to pale reddish). Fruits 19–35 mm. 2n = 22.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Nov-Mar.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Tamaulipan thorn scrub, plains and low hills, sandy, loamy, silty, or gravelly soils [rarely on shale];</description>
  <description type="elevation">20-500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.; Mexico (Nuevo León, Tamaulipas).</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Root cactus</other_name>
  <discussion>The roots of Ancistrocactus scheeri are diagnostic at all ages; frequently they are
        horizontally oriented, sausage-shaped or otherwise strongly tuberlike, but always separated
        from the stem by a fragile constriction, in contrast to the short, succulent, vertical
        taproots of A. brevihamatus. When separated from the tuberlike roots, stems of A. scheeri in
        horticulture will develop their peculiar succulent root systems, even in the artificial
        environment of a container.</discussion>
  <discussion>Seedlings and immature plants of A. scheeri often have narrowly cylindric stems and
        numerous tightly appressed, pectinately arranged, short radial spines. With age, the stems
        broaden distally and new spines are longer, coarser, and less tightly
        appressed.</discussion>
  <discussion>Adult plants of Ancistrocactus scheeri and A. brevihamatus are relatively similar
        above ground. The stems of immature A. brevihamatus, however, are not obscured by spines and
        are often flush with the soil surface, whereas those of A. scheeri are nearly hidden by
        spines and fully exposed above the soil.</discussion>
  <discussion>Ribs on the stems of Ancistrocactus scheeri seem straighter and better defined than
        ribs of A. brevihamatus, even prior to sexual maturity.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
