<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Allan D. Zimmerman,Bruce D. Parfitt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Britton &amp; Rose" date="1922">HAMATOCACTUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cact.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 104, figs. 110–114. 1922</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cactaceae;genus HAMATOCACTUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin hamatus, hooked, in reference to the hooked central spines, and Cactus , an old genus name]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants erect, unbranched or branched in basal portion, not deep-seated in substrate. Roots diffuse. Stems unsegmented, bright deep green, hemispheric when young, becoming spheric or ovoid to cylindric, 3.6–12(–20) × 4.5–12 cm, glabrous; ribs 13, spiraling or vertical, slender, crests sinuate, sharp, not interrupted or undulate, narrow; areoles circular or, on older parts of stem, elliptic to ovate, adaxially elongated into short areolar grooves; areolar glands golden, darker with age, cylindric or peglike; cortex and pith firm, not mucilaginous. Spines 11–20 per areole, not obscuring stems, yellowish, whitish, or reddish brown, acicular (rarely central spine flattened), longest spines 12–38 mm; radial spines 10–19 per areole, straight or slightly curved toward stem, longest spines 11–32 mm; central spines 1 per areole, porrect, hooked, terete (rarely flattened). Flowers diurnal, near stem apex, at adaxial edge of areoles or at axillary ends of short areolar grooves, widely funnelform, 3.7–7 × 4–7 cm; outer tepals finely fringed; inner tepals yellow (to ivory) with red bases, 20–25 × 6–9 mm, margins entire, toothed, or lacerate; ovary scaly, hairless, spineless; stigma lobes 5–11, pale yellow to orangish, 3–7 mm. Fruits indehiscent or eventually dehiscent by vertical slits, bright red, spheric or nearly so, ca. 10 × 8–13 mm, fleshy, with 15 or fewer whitish, broad fringed, naked, spineless scales; floral remnant persistent. Seeds black, obovoid, usually 1–1.4 × 0.8–1 mm, minutely papillate; testa cells weakly convex, nearly flat toward proximal end of seed. x = 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">arid regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico.</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Twisted-rib cactus</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Hamatocactus has been submerged in Ferocactus or Thelocactus by various authors and grouped with Glandulicactus by others.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
