<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Allan D. Zimmerman,Bruce D. Parfitt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">Cactaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subfamily" authority="Eaton" date="unknown">Cactoideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Engelmann) Lemaire" date="unknown">CORYPHANTHA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cactées,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>32. 1868</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Cactaceae;subfamily Cactoideae;genus CORYPHANTHA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek coryph, head/helmet/crown, and Greek anthos , flower, refe rring to the apical location of flowers in contrast with the ring of lateral flowers in the related genus Mammillaria ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Haworth" date="unknown">Mammillaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="Engelmann" date="unknown">Coryphantha</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 264. 1856 (as Mamillaria)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Mammillaria;subgenus Coryphantha;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Lemaire" date="unknown">Aulacothelae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Aulacothelae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="W. Earle" date="unknown">Cochiseia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cochiseia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Buxbaum" date="unknown">Cumarinia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cumarinia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Britton &amp; Rose" date="unknown">Escobaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Escobaria;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Hester" date="unknown">Escobesseya</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Escobesseya;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Backeberg" date="unknown">Lepidocoryphantha</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lepidocoryphantha;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Britton &amp; Rose" date="unknown">Neobesseya</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Neobesseya;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>28.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pincushion cactus</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 60–70 (20 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Coryphantha may be polyphyletic, or paraphyletic, with respect to Mammillaria, from which it differs primarily by the presence of an adaxial areolar groove on tubercles of sexually mature coryphanthas. Most species of Coryphantha produce a more or less apical tuft of flowers from the current growth; most mammillarias bloom in a ring from older areoles at least 1 cm from the stem apex. Coryphantha recurvata is an exception with a ring of flowers as in most species of Mammillaria. Some species in each genus display intermediate floral positions. In both genera, pitted seeds characterize putatively primitive species.</discussion>
  <discussion>The coryphanthas with pitted seeds often are segregated as Escobaria (species numbered 8–20 here). That segregate, recognized by the International Cactaceae Systematics Group (ICSG) but not here, lacks the glands found in the areoles of typical Coryphantha. Such glands are ephemeral. The glands, occuring singly or in small groups usually at either end of each areolar groove, are spheroid or mushroom-shaped (then deeply nestled among short trichomes so appear to be hemispheric), smooth, colorful (red, green, purplish, orange, or yellow), and about 1 mm in diameter. Fallen glands leave circular gray scars.</discussion>
  <discussion>Several species of Coryphantha closely resemble, and may be confused with, Neolloydia conoidea. Both genera have naked ovaries and grooved tubercles; however, Neolloydia has seeds like those of Ariocarpus or Lophophora. The tiny fruits of N. conoidea usually are overlooked, often leading to misidentifications. In immature plants of several genera that tend to be “ribbed” (e.g., Echinomastus), and in the adults of neotenous species, stems are tuberculate; however, the areolar extensions in those plants are shorter and/or wider than those of Coryphantha, and the tubercles usually are basally confluent, unlike the (linear) grooves and distinct tubercles of Coryphantha and Neolloydia.</discussion>
  <discussion>As many as fourteen species of coryphanthas may occur sympatrically, with no natural hybrids dectected. Flowers may be few and ephemeral; however, identifications based on vegetative traits may be difficult because of polymorphism and age-related heteromorphic growth within populations, geographic variation within species, and parallel evolution among ecological counterparts in relatively distant lineages.</discussion>
  <discussion>Calcium oxatate crystal aggregates (druses) in the stem parenchyma of Coryphantha are spheric, oblong, or lens-shaped masses like grains of sand. Most druses are only 0.1–0.4 mm diam., seen best with a compound microscope and polarizing filters, but five species (species 16–20) have unusually large druses (0.5–1 mm diam.) conspicuous to the naked eye. With practice, the thick pale-looking skin associated with a several-layered and/or druse-containing stem can be recognized.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species with specialized mucilage cells in the pith and cortex of stems are wet with tangibly and visibly viscous slime when cut open. Mucilage usually can be seen and felt in healthy living tubercles. Fresh sections feel watery or mealy in species lacking specialized mucilage cells.</discussion>
  <discussion>A medullary vascular system (when present) is a diffuse network of fine threadlike strands of wood inside the pith at the center of the stem, within the woody vascular cylinder. Such whitish vascular strands are seen by holding a light source behind a translucently thin stem section.</discussion>
  <discussion>Stem diameter includes the tubercles, unless otherwise stated; lesser stem diameter excludes the tubercles and is used only to define the relative size of the pith. Tubercle diameter is the maximum measurement of the cross section at midpoint between the base and apex of a tubercle. Spine thickness is measured midspine.</discussion>
  <discussion>Flower length may be misinterpreted on flowers deeply hidden in the axils of the subtending tubercles. Accurate measurements of diameter require fully opened flowers (in some species the flower may not be fully open if the angle between the inner tepals and floral tube is less than 45º). Fruits with fully formed seeds may not be mature with respect to taxonomically important characters of fruit size and color. Ripe fruits are those that abscise easily from the plant with a gentle tug (although fruits of Coryphantha robustispina sometimes require a hard pull). A pitted seed testa is easily viewed with a hand lens. A weakly raised-reticulate seed testa is distinguishable from a smooth testa only with a lens (10× or greater magnification). A reticulate color pattern alone does not imply that the anticlinal cell walls actually protrude.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Taylor, N. P. 1983. Die Arten der Gattung Escobaria Britton et Rose: [1]–5. Kakt. And. Sukk. 34: 76–79, 120–123, 136–140, 154–158, 184–188.</reference>
    <reference>Zimmerman, A. D. 1985. Systematics of the Genus Coryphantha (Cactaceae). Ph.D. dissertation. University of Texas.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines peglike, not sharply pointed, proximally compressed laterally; radial spines 5 mmor less; stems 1–2.7 × 0.6–1.7(–2.5) cm</description>
      <determination>15. Coryphantha minima</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines needlelike, sharp pointed, terete or compressed dorsiventrally or laterally; radial spines mostly 6–35(–50) mm (rarely as short as 4 or 5 mm in C. chaffeyi, C. duncanii, C. missouriensis, C. robertii, C. sneedii, C. tuberculosa ); stems 2.5–27 × (1–)1.5–15 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">In sexually mature plants areolar groove extending 1 / 2 – 3 / 4of distance from spine cluster to axil of tubercle; stem cortex mucilaginous; inner tepals rose-pink to magenta</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">In sexually mature plants areolar groove connecting spine clusters and axils of tubercles; stem cortex usually not mucilaginous; inner tepals yellowish, whitish, greenish, pink, or purple.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seeds smooth or weakly raised-reticulate, brown when dry, red or yellow when fresh; outer tepals entire, denticulate, or minutely fringed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inner tepals pink to deep rose-purple with white proximal zone; seeds 1–1.5mm</description>
      <determination>3. Coryphantha ramillosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inner tepals yellow, turning pinkish or reddish only in wilted or day-old flowers, proximally red, yellow, or greenish yellow; seeds 1.7–3 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercles (10–)15–30(–40) m m; fruits (35–)42(–52) mm; longest central spines, when present, 23–34 mm, hooked or straight to strongly curved</description>
      <next_statement_id>5. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercles 6–15 mm; fruits 9–28 mm; longest central spines 9–25 mm, only straight or curved throughout their lengths.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers distant from stem apex, forming ring around stem; Arizonaand Mexico</description>
      <determination>4. Coryphantha recurvata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers apical or nearly so, only fruits sometimes displaced away from stem apex by growth of new tubercles after flowering; Texas and Mexico.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers lacking red in centers.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigma lobes white or cream; inner tepals pale yellow; pith occupying 1 / 2of lesser stem diam.; medullary vascular systemconspicuous; near Laredo, Texas</description>
      <determination>2. Coryphantha nickelsiae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigma lobes whitish orgreenish yellow; inner tepals bright yellow; pith occupying 1 / 4 – 1 / 3of lesser stem diam.; medullaryvascular system absent; mostly w of Pecos River, Texas</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers red centered, or at least with filaments partly r ed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines 16–34 per areole; tubercles firm; mostly w of Pecos</description>
      <determination>6. Coryphantha echinus ### (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines 9 – 16( –18) per areole; tubercles soft or flaccid; e of</description>
      <determination>7. Coryphantha sulcata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seeds pitted, black or brown when dry, black, brown, red, or yellow when fresh; outer tepals fringed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral remnant on fruit deciduous; spines 6–20 per areole; stems deep-seated in substrate, often nearly subterranean except in growing season [segregate genus Neobesseya ]</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spine-bearing areoles with long, white wool, making areoles appear unusually large, obscuring basal portions of spines; restricted distribution, se Arizona near Mexicanboundary</description>
      <determination>13. Coryphantha robbinsorum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spine-bearing areoles with short, white wool, 1–3 mm, shorter with age making areoles appear normal size, not obscuring spine bases; widespread from c Arizonanorthward and eastward</description>
      <determination>14. Coryphantha missouriensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral remnant on fruit persistent; spines (10–)15–76(–95) per areole; stems usually not deep-seated, more than 1 / 2above ground (sometimes deep-seated and flat-topped in winter in C. hesteriand C. vivipara )[segregate genus Escobaria ]</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Central spines erect, appressed and therefore inconspicuous ag ainst adaxial radial spines (i.e., abaxial or “inner” central spines absent).</description>
      <next_statement_id>13. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines (21–)31–44(–55) per areole; stigma lobes dark green to bright yellow;seeds black; fruit bright red</description>
      <determination>12. Coryphantha duncanii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines (12–)15–20(–25) per areole ; stigma lobes white (to pink or purple); seeds brown; fruit green to dull reddish.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Central spines, when present, 9.5–13(–15) mm; roots fleshy, enlarged taproots, basally 1 / 3 – 1 / 2of stem diam.; fruits (3.5–)5–8(–10) × 3–6 mm, quickly drying; seeds darkbrown, spheric; above-ground portion of stem 1–6.5</description>
      <determination>16. Coryphantha hesteri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Central spines 9–25 mm; roots ± diffuse, less than 1 / 4of stem diam.; fruits 12–28 × 7–20 mm, juicy; seeds bright reddish brown, comma-shaped or nearly obovoid; above-ground portion of stem 2.5–20 cm; druses 0.7–1mm diam.</description>
      <determination>19. Coryphantha vivipara ### (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Central spines radiating in every direction and not confined to adaxial parts of spine clusters, or principal central spine in ea ch areole porrect and conspicuous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ripe fruit green or maroon to dull reddish pink (sometimes blood red or crimson in C. sneedii ); stigma lobes pink, purple, or white; druses large, 0.5–1 mm diam., lenticular, present in older parts of the pith and cor tex; widespread, w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches 0–250; inner tepals generally white, cream, pale tan, greenish white, or pale rose-pink; fruits either red color phase or green color phase;se New Mexico, w Texas</description>
      <determination>20. Coryphantha sneedii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches 0–30 ; inner tepals pale rose-pink to intense pink, pale dull creamy yellow, or pale greenish tan to pale yellow-orange, or pale apricot; fruits green, dull pink, or brownish red; widespread, California to Texas northward.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigma lobes widely spreading; s C alifornia</description>
      <determination>18. Coryphantha alversonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigma lobes spreading, ascending, or recurved; California eastward.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inner tepals ascending or recurved only at tips, pale dull creamy yellow or pale greenish tan to pale yellow-orange or pale apricot,usual ly with distinct darker midstripes</description>
      <determination>17. Coryphantha chlorantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inner tepals usually spreading, recurved, pale rose-pink to reddish pink or magenta throughout or with vaguely to sharply defineddarker midstripes</description>
      <determination>19. Coryphantha vivipara ### (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1 5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ripe fruit red; stigma lobes green or white (rarely red); druses, when present, nearly microscopic, not lenticular; New Mexico, Texas.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigma lobes white; anthers pale yellow, nearly white; sterile distal part offlower tube 5–8.5(–11) mm, longer than stamen-bearing part 8. Coryphantha tuberculosa</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigma lobes green to bright yellow (rarely red); anthers bright yellow; sterile distal part of flower tube 0–2 mm, much shorter than the stamen-bearing part.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched, resulting in irregular masses of mostly immature stems that proliferate before reaching sexual maturity, clumps 10–30(–100) cm diam.; below 500 m elevation, eof Pecos River.</description>
      <determination>9. Coryphantha robertii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually unbranched (rarely w ith 2–5 branches); 800–2500 m elevation, w of Pecos River.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines (35–)40–55(–81) per areole, white with reddish or yellowish tips</description>
      <determination>10. Coryphantha chaffeyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spines 26–42 per areole, white with dark tips</description>
      <determination>11. Coryphantha dasyacantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
