<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1a.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Neolloydia</genus_name><species_name>conoidea</species_name><species_authority>(de Candolle) Br itton &amp; Rose</species_authority><variety_name>conoidea</variety_name></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Texas cone cactus</common_name><description>Stems: tubercles ascending but not overlapping sufficiently to be called imbricate; axils copiously woolly at stem apex during flowering; hairs pure white, to 6 mm. Spines: radial spines appressed, whitish, often with dark tips (rarely all white or all brown), translucent or opaque, 0.3 mm diam. beyond bulbous basal portion; central spines black or dark brown, 6–25(–30) × 0.5–1 mm diam.; abaxial longest central spine porrect or angled slightly toward base of plant, 17–24 mm; adaxial 1–3 central spines angled toward apex of plant, 9–17 mm. Flowers: outer tepals whitish with greenish midvein; inner tepals bright rose-pink, almost magenta, without darker midstripes; anthers 1 mm; style 7–11 × 1 mm. Fruits persistent, pale yellowish olive, proximal part hidden by hairs, off white with very slight pink tint. Seeds black, pyriform, 1.4–1.6 mm. 2n = 22.</description><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>nov</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><habitat>chihuahuan desert scrub</habitat><habitat>edge of tamaulipan thorn scrub</habitat><habitat>stony grasslands</habitat><habitat>usually on limestone</habitat><elevation>[500–]800–1400[–2300] m;</elevation><us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Coahuila).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Durango).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Nuevo León).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (San Luis Potosí).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Tamaulipas).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico (Zacatecas).</global_distribution><discussion>Neolloydia conoidea has the grooved tubercles and general appearance of many species of Coryphantha, but has flowers, fruits, and seeds most like those of Ariocarpus.</discussion><discussion>Neolloydia gautii L. D. Benson, known only from the type specimen, was alleged to be from Texas (L. D. Benson 1982). The controversial specimen, a greenhouse-grown plant with a J. N. Rose garden number, represents the common Mexican species Turbinicarpus beguinii (N. P. Taylor) Mosco &amp; Zanovello (in the broad sense).</discussion></treatment>
