<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>12.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Mammillaria</genus_name><species_name>heyderi</species_name><species_authority>Muehlenpfordt</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Allg. Gartenzeitung</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>16: 20. 1848</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><past_name>Mamillaria</past_name><common_name>Little nipple cactus</common_name><description>Plants unbranched, protruding relatively little above soil. Roots obconic taproots; secondary roots diffuse. Stems top-shaped, flat-topped (aerial part sometimes hemispheric in old age or in dense subtropical vegetation), protruding above ground 0–2 × (4–)7.5–15 cm, firm; tubercles 9–15(–20) × 3–7 mm; axils with short wool, bristles absent; cortex and pith not mucilaginous; latex abundant in healthy tissue throughout cortex of stem, tubercles, and sometimes flower receptacle, sticky, white. Spines (8–)10–18(–27) per areole, usually brownish, darker at tip, glabrous; radial spines (8–)10–22(–26) per areole, white to white-and-brown or brown, needlelike, 6–15(–16) mm, stiff, abaxial spines longest; central spines (0–)1(–4) per areole, porrect or ascending, not hooked, (0.5–)2–8 × 0.15–0.45 mm; subcentral spines 0. Flowers 1.9–3.8 × 1.5–3 cm; outermost tepal margins entire; inner tepals white, greenish or cream to pale pink, with tan, pink, greenish, or brownish midstripes, 11–19 × 2–2.5 mm; stigma lobes externally green, internally green or red (or pink), 2.5–3 mm. Fruits brilliant red: scarlet, carmine, or crimson, obovoid to clavate, 10–35(–40) × 5–8 mm, juicy only in fruit walls; floral remnant weakly persistent. Seeds reddish brown, sometimes yellowish when fresh, 1–1.2 mm, deeply pitted; testa thin, relatively flexible; anticlinal cell walls sinuate, interstices narrower than pit diameters; pits cavernous or deeply concave. 2n = 22.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>sw United States</global_distribution><global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution><discussion>Green fruits of Mammillaria heyderi with fully mature, viable seeds precede the ripe (elongate) fruits by six months to a year.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Central spines 0.15–0.35 mm diam.; radial spines (7–)13–17(–26) per areole, abaxial radial spines 6–11(–16) mm; e of El Paso, Texas, New Mexico,</statement>
      <determination>12a. Mammillaria heyderi ### var. heyderi</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Central spines 0.35–0.45 mm diam.; radial spines 10–14 p er areole, abaxial radial spines 9–15 mm; El Paso, Texas, w to Arizona</statement>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
