<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>28.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Chenopodium</genus_name>
        <species_name>ficifolium</species_name>
        <species_authority>Smith</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Fl. Brit.</publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>1: 276. 1800</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Stems erect, simple, 1.8–5.5 dm, glabrous to sparsely farinose. Leaves nonaromatic;
        petiole 0.3–4.5 cm, usually shorter than leaves; blade distinctly 3-lobed, narrowly ovate to
        elongate, (1.4–)2.7–6.2 × (0.5–)1.2–2.5 cm, base cuneate, margins toothed or nearly entire,
        with pair of basal lobes, apex obtuse to subacute, sparsely farinose. Inflorescences
        glomerules in terminal and lateral spikes and panicles, 11 cm; glomerules irregularly
        globose, in different stages of development, 1.7–1.9 mm diam.; bracts absent or leaflike.
        Flowers: perianth segments 5, connate at base into 0.3 mm tube; lobes ovate, 0.5–0.9 ×
        0.5–0.8 mm, apex acute, farinose, keeled, covering fruit at maturity; stamens 5; stigmas 2,
        0.3 mm. Utricles depressed-ovoid; pericarp nonadherent, smooth. Seeds lenticular, 0.9–1 mm
        diam.; seed coat black, honeycomb-pitted. 2n = 18.</description>
    <phenology_fruiting>fruiting early summer–fall</phenology_fruiting>
    <habitat>disturbed nitrogen-rich habitats</habitat>
    <elevation>0–200 m;</elevation>
    <introduced>introduced;</introduced>
    <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Mo.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Pa.</us_distribution>
    <global_distribution>native s</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution>se Asia</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution>occasionally introduced in other parts of the world.</global_distribution>
    <discussion>Chenopodium ficifolium has often been called C. serotinum Linnaeus. P. Aellen
        (1929b) and P. Uotila (1979b) have shown that the type of C. serotinum is a sterile Atriplex
        specimen (most probably A. tatarica Linnaeus) based on its Kranz-type leaf structure.
        Chenopodium blomianum Aellen [= C. ficifolium subsp. blomianum (Aellen) Aellen] was
        described from Sweden based on alien plants of presumably East Asian origin (P. Aellen
        1928). According to Aellen, that subspecies occurs in southern and southeastern Asia and
        differs from C. ficifolium subsp. ficifolium in having leaves with spreading basal lobes
        almost perpendicular to the central lobe and seeds with shallow elongate depressions. All
        North American plants of C. ficifolium belong to subsp. ficifolium. In Europe C. ficifolium
        occasionally hybridizes with other species, including C. album (producing C. ×zahnii Murr)
        and C. suecicum (producing C. ×gruellii Aellen). No study has been made of such hybrids in
        North America.</discussion>
</treatment>
