<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ventenat" date="unknown">chenopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">chenopodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">album</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 219. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family chenopodiaceae;genus chenopodium;species album</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems erect to sprawling, simple to much-branched, 1–30 dm, sparsely to densely
        farinose. Leaves nonaromatic; petiole 1–2.5 cm, shorter than blades or occasionally longer;
        blade ovate-lanceolate to rhombic-lanceolate or broadly oblong, 1–5.5(–12) × 0.5–3.8(–8) cm,
        base narrowly to broadly cuneate, margins sinuous-dentate to shallowly serrate or entire,
        apex acute to subobtuse, farinose abaxially. Inflorescences glomerules or occasionally
        1-flowered peduncles in terminal and lateral compound spikes, 2–19 cm; glomerules
        subglobose, 3–4 mm diam.; bracts absent. Flowers: perianth segments 5, distinct nearly to
        base; lobes ovate, ca. 1 × 1.1 mm, apex obtuse, keeled, farinose, largely covering fruit at
        maturity; stamens 5; stigmas 2, 0.2–0.3 mm. Utricles depressed-ovoid; pericarp nonadherent,
        occasionally adherent, smooth to papillate. Seeds lenticular, margins round, 0.9–1.6 mm
        diam.; seed coat black, smooth, indistinctly granulate and/or radially grooved, or with
        faint reticulate-rugose ridges. 2n = 54.</description>
  <description type="phenology" scope="fruiting">fruiting late summer–fall</description>
  <description type="habitat">disturbed soils in open habitats</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–1400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta.</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Man.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.B.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nfld. and Labr.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.S.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont.</description>
  <description type="distribution">P.E.I.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Que.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Sask.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Yukon</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alaska</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ark.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Colo.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Conn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Del.</description>
  <description type="distribution">D.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Idaho</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ill.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ind.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Iowa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Kans.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ky.</description>
  <description type="distribution">La.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Maine</description>
  <description type="distribution">Md.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mass.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mich.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Minn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Miss.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mo.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mont.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nebr.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nev.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.H.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.J.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Dak.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ohio</description>
  <description type="distribution">Okla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pa.</description>
  <description type="distribution">R.I.</description>
  <description type="distribution">S.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">S.Dak.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tenn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Utah</description>
  <description type="distribution">Vt.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Va.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wash.</description>
  <description type="distribution">W.Va.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wis.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wyo</description>
  <description type="distribution">probably mostly native in Europe.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Fruiting late summer-fall. Disturbed soils in open habitats; 0-1400 m; introduced; Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., N.S., Nunavut, Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask., Yukon; Ala., Alaska, Ariz., Ark., Calif., Colo., Conn., Del., D.C., Fla., Ga., Idaho, Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Miss., Mo., Mont., Nebr., Nev., N.H., N.J., N.Mex., N.Y., N.C., N.Dak., Ohio, Okla., Oreg., Pa., R.I., S.C., S.Dak., Tenn., Tex., Utah, Vt., Va., Wash., W.Va., Wis., Wyo; probably mostly native in Europe.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Fruiting late summer-fall.</phenology>
      <habitat>Disturbed soils in open habitats;</habitat>
      <elevation>0-1400 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>introduced; Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., N.S., Nunavut, Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask., Yukon; Ala., Alaska, Ariz., Ark., Calif., Colo., Conn., Del., D.C., Fla., Ga., Idaho, Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Miss., Mo., Mont., Nebr., Nev., N.H., N.J., N.Mex., N.Y., N.C., N.Dak., Ohio, Okla., Oreg., Pa., R.I., S.C., S.Dak., Tenn., Tex., Utah, Vt., Va., Wash., W.Va., Wis., Wyo; probably mostly native in Europe.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>32.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Lamb’s-quarters</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">pigweed</other_name>
  <discussion>Chenopodium album, one of the worst weeds and most widespread synanthropic plants on
        the Earth, in its broad circumscription is also among the most polymorphic plant species. It
        is a loosely arranged aggregate of still insufficiently understood races. Hundreds of
        segregate microspecies and infraspecific entities (including nomenclatural combinations) of
        the C. album aggregate have been described and/or recognized by various authors. Some
        authors have recognized numerous segregate intergrading species, while others have developed
        elaborate infraspecific hierarchies with numerous subspecies, varieties, forms, and even
        numerous subforms (e.g., B. Jüttersonke and K. Arlt 1989), or have combined both approaches.
        Neither approach has brought satisfactory and uncontroversial results.</discussion>
  <discussion>It is evident that most recent evolutionary processes within the group were greatly
        affected by anthropic factors, including extensive recent invasions, hybridization between
        previously geographically isolated taxa, poly-ploidy, intensive selective processes and
        mutagenesis in synanthropic habitats, gene drift, and so forth. All of these modern factors
        further complicated the taxonomic situation. Consequently, no infraspecific taxa are
        formally recognized in the present treatment. We attempt, however, to outline below the most
        common or noteworthy groups currently placed in Chenopodium album sensu lato. Although we
        list such groups under binomials, they should be considered here as informal groupings
        rather than accepted species.</discussion>
  <discussion>It should be also kept in mind that many enigmatic and deviant forms of the
        Chenopodium album aggregate are in fact hybrids with other (occasionally several) species,
        and between infraspecific entities. C. album hybridizes with C. suecicum (producing C.
        ×fursajevii Aellen &amp; Iljin), C. opulifolium (producing C. ×preissmannii Murr), C.
        strictum [producing C. ×pseudostriatum (Zschacke) Murr], C. ficifolium (producing C.
        ×jedlickae Dvorák or C. ×zahnii Murr), C. berlandieri (producing C. ×variabile Aellen), and
        some other species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium album sensu stricto: plants usually erect, ± farinose, at maturity
        becoming yellowish green with reddish tint; not profusely branched, branches in proximal 1/2
        mostly arching, in distal part straight and upright; proximal and middle cauline leaf blades
        ovate to weakly 3-lobed, margins dentate, teeth usually small and densely arranged;
        inflorescences normally condensed, spicate; seeds variable (especially in hybrids and
        deviate forms) but most often 1–1.25 mm diam., seed coat smooth or nearly so.</discussion>
  <discussion>The typical form of Chenopodium album is widespread in North America, but occurs
        sporadically and less commonly than the following form.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium lanceolatum Muhlenberg ex Willdenow: plants usually robust, erect to
        ascending, sparsely to moderately farinose, at maturity usually dark green; profusely
        branched, especially in inflorescence, branches arcuate and spreading; proximal and middle
        cauline leaf blades elliptic or elongate to narrowly lanceolate, base cuneate to narrowly
        cuneate, margins entire or with few teeth (usually in proximal 1/2); inflorescences normally
        much-branched, loosely paniculate, often nodding; seeds variable in size.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium lanceolatum is probably the most widespread and variable group of
        presumably hybridogenous forms in North America. I. J. Bassett and C. Crompton (1982)
        considered C. lanceolatum to be a form of C. album. It appears that the difference between
        these two taxa is based on habitat—C. album grows in cultivated ground and has an erect
        growth habit whereas C. lanceolatum grows in vacant lots, roadsides, etc., and has a more
        sprawling habit.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium pedunculare Bertoloni: plants similar to C. lanceolatum, but less
        robust, usually with ascending branches, sparsely to moderately farinose, at maturity dark
        green to yellowish; profusely branched, especially in inflorescence; proximal and middle
        cauline leaf blades ovate to broadly lanceolate (distal ones lanceolate), base rounded to
        cuneate, margins normally entire or with few teeth at base; inflorescences much-branched,
        loosely paniculate, nodding; seeds large, ca. 1.5 mm diam., seed coat smooth to irregularly
        and indistinctly grooved.</discussion>
  <discussion>Forms similar to the European ones occur in North America, but their exact
        distribution and taxonomic status are uncertain. The taxonomy of Chenopodium pedunculare was
        discussed in detail by F. Dvo ák (1984).</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium suecicum Murr, and similar taxa including C. pseudopulifolium (J. B.
        Scholz) Murr: plants usually erect, sparsely to moderately farinose, or becoming glabrous,
        at maturity usually light green to dark green; branched in middle portion of stem and in
        inflorescence, branches straight to arcuate; proximal and middle cauline leaf blades
        elliptic or elongate to narrowly lanceolate, base cuneate to narrowly cuneate, margins
        variously 3-lobed and/or dentate, teeth few, usually large (especially in proximal 1/2);
        inflorescences much-branched, loosely paniculate; seeds variable, but predominantly ca. 1 mm
        diam., seed coat with indistinct elongate depressions and radial grooves, occasionally
        nearly smooth.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium suecicum was repeatedly reported from North America, mostly by European
        authors, and indeed, similar forms occur in the New World. However, their taxonomy is far
        from clear, and because of that they are treated here collectively, as an informal group of
        C. album. Some forms are transitional toward C. lanceolatum. Numerous forms of “C. syecucyn”
        were identified in North America as C. album sensu stricto or C. missouriense. The name C.
        paganum auct. was also widely misapplied.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium jenissejense Iljin: plants usually with erect or ascending (rarely
        prostrate) main stem, sparsely farinose to almost glabrous, deep olive green, at maturity
        becoming yellowish or reddish; not profusely branched, proximal branches arcuate to almost
        prostrate; proximal and middle cauline leaf blades ovate-deltoid, 3-lobed to indistinctly
        3-lobed, margins of lobes entire or nearly so, teeth (if present) small and obtuse;
        inflorescences normally compact, spicate; perianth segments spreading at maturity, not
        covering fruit; seeds 1–1.4 mm diam., seed coat indistinctly pitted with weak radial
        grooves.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium jenissejense is a characteristic nonweedy alluvial taxon of sandy and
        gravelly river shores of northern Eurasia (northeastern European Russia, Siberia), related
        to C. acerifolium (see below). Several specimens collected in Alaska are probably referable
        to C. jenissejense; the available scarce material is not sufficient to confirm
        this.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium acerifolium Andrzejowsky: similar in morphology to C. jenissejense, this
        is a characteristic, predominantly nonweedy alluvial species confined to sandy habitats of
        eastern Europe and western Siberia. It has been reported as introduced in Colorado (W. A.
        Weber and R. C. Wittmann 1992); this record was probably based on misidentification of C.
        berlandieri (var. sinuatum?).</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium giganteum D. Don, C. centrorubrum (Makino) Nakai, C. probstii Aellen,
        and other similar forms: plants usually exceptionally robust, to 20–30 (occasionally more)
        dm, erect, ± densely farinose (mealy pubescence of young leaves usually reddish or
        yellowish), at maturity becoming yellowish green, yellow to deep beet red; variously (but
        usually not profusely) branched; proximal and middle cauline leaf blades large (to 15 cm),
        ovate to distinctly 3-lobed, margins dentate to ± entire; terminal inflorescences normally
        condensed, spicate (in some forms lax but large), lateral inflorescences usually weakly
        developed; seeds variable but most often ca 1.2 mm diam. or larger, seed coat smooth or
        nearly so.</discussion>
  <discussion>These taxa are probably all native to southern and southeastern Asia, where they
        were occasionally cultivated as ancient leaf vegetables and pseudocereals. In Japan and
        eastern China they were usually known as Chenopodium centrorubrum (Makino) Nakai, and in
        India and western China as C. giganteum D. Don. Other forms, such as C. amaranticolor Coste
        &amp; Reynier, are of uncertain origin. Chenopodium probstii Aellen was described from
        Europe as an alien species supposedly introduced from Australia, but then its North American
        origin was suggested. Probably the forms discussed evolved independently in different parts
        of Eurasia and, consequently, represent different taxa of the C. album aggregate. Despite
        several painstaking efforts (e.g., P. Aellen 1929c; F. Dvo ák 1992), their taxonomy still
        remains confused and is in need of further experimental studies.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium album var. stevensii Aellen: plants with thick leaves and reduced size
        are possibly a phenotypic response to dry northern prairie habitats. It has been reported
        from southern Manitoba and northern parts of the upper Midwest.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chenopodium missouriense Aellen: a confusing taxon because of its mixed
        typification. It appears to be a native form of C. album that flowers in mid September
        regardless of when it germinated. The inflorescences are somewhat reminiscent of C.
        standleyanum. It occurs in the United States in the central lowlands and part of the
        Appalachian plateau and is designated a weed (D. T. Patterson et al. 1989).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
