<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Noel H. Holmgren</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Chenopodiaceae Ventenat" date="unknown">CHENOPODIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Grayia Hooker &amp; Arnott" date="unknown">GRAYIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Beechey Voy.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>387. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CHENOPODIACEAE;genus GRAYIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Asa Gray, 1810–1888, botany professor at Harvard, for many years the pre-eminent American botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, dioecious or monoecious, spinescent; herbage scurfy-puberulent when young, mostly with branched hairs, becoming glabrate. Stems erect, much branched, woody throughout, not jointed, forming a rounded bush; younger branches ribbed, rigid; lateral branches becoming spinescent. Leaves alternate, succulent or coriaceous; blade with midveins prominent, spatulate to oblanceolate, sometimes narrowly so, base gradually tapering to petiole, margins entire, apex rounded to obtuse. Inflorescences terminal, spikelike clusters. Flowers unisexual; staminate in 2–5-flowered clusters in bract axils, perianth 4(–5)-parted, equaling or slightly longer than stamens, stamens 4–5; pistillate in 1–few-flowered clusters per glomerule, each closely invested by 2 wholly united bracts, perianth absent; stigma 2-lobed. Fruiting structure: bracts forming flattened, samaralike fruiting structure around utricle, margins thickened, spongy within; pericarp free. Seeds vertical, compressed-lenticular, seed coat brown, tuberculate; embryo annular; perisperm copious. x = 18.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <number>13.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hopsage</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
