<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Chenopodiaceae Ventenat" date="unknown">CHENOPODIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Corispermum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Mosyakin" date="unknown">hookeri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 349. 1995</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CHENOPODIACEAE;genus Corispermum;species hookeri;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants branched from base, 10–40(–60) cm, sparsely covered with dendroid and almost stellate hairs. Leaf blades narrowly lanceolate or linear-lanceolate, plane, 2–5 × (0.1–)0.2–0.5(–0.6) cm. Inflorescences usually dense, ovoid, ovate-clavate, or ovate-cylindric, rarely interrupted near base. Bracts ovate or ovate-lanceolate, 0.5–1.5(–2) × 0.3–1 cm. Perianth segment 1. Fruits usually deep olive green, brown, or rarely to almost black, usually without spots and/or warts, or occasionally spotted, strongly convex abaxially, prominently concave to almost plane adaxially, usually broadest beyond middle, (3.2–)3.5–4.5(–5) × 2.2–3.3(–3.5) mm; wing (when present) semitranslucent, to 0.2 mm wide, margins entire, apex rounded or indistinctly triangular.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The inflorescence bracts of Corispermum hookeri are conspicuously imbricate (usually strongly overlapping). Corispermum hookeri seems to be closely related to the narrow-winged taxa, C. villosum and C. ochotense, and to C. pallasii sensu stricto. The names C. orientale and C. hyssopifolium have been commonly misapplied to this species.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences dense throughout, rarely interrupted. Fruits oblong-obovate to obovate</description>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences dense only at apex, interrupted. Fruits elongate to oblong-obovate</description>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
