<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>20.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>ATRIPLEX</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 1052. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5, 472. 1754</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Orach</common_name><common_name>saltbush</common_name><etymology>[ancient Latin name]</etymology><author>Stanley L. Welsh</author><description>Herbs or shrubs, annual or perennial, monoecious or dioecious, often with bladderlike hairs that collapse to form silvery or scurfy (mealy) vesture, less often with elongate trichomes. Leaves persistent or tardily deciduous, alternate, partially opposite, or opposite, sessile or petiolate; blade entire, serrate, or lobed, with venation either of Kranz-type or normal dicotyledonous type, axillary buds inconspicuous or lacking. Inflorescences axillary or terminal; flowers borne in axillary clusters or glomerules, or in terminal spikes or spicate panicles. Staminate flowers with 3–5-parted calyx, ebracteate; stamens 3–5. Pistillate flowers lacking perianth, pistil naked, or in few species with (1–)3–5-lobed perianth, commonly enclosed within pair of foliaceous bracteoles; stigmas 2. Fruiting bracteoles enlarged in fruit, of various shapes and variously connate or not, thickened, and appendaged; pericarp free, tightly enclosed in the fruiting bracteoles. Seeds flattened, mainly vertical; radicle inferior, lateral, or superior. x = 9.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 250 (62 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>worldwide</global_distribution><global_distribution>mainly in subarctic</global_distribution><global_distribution>temperate</global_distribution><global_distribution>and subtropical regions.</global_distribution><discussion>Many species of Atriplex are halophytic, others occupy soils low in dissolved particulates.</discussion><discussion>Prior to the 1900s, the genus Suckleya was treated within Atriplex, but its obcompressed fruiting bracteoles are quite unlike anything in Atriplex, and the plants were recognized as a distinct genus.</discussion><references>
    <reference>Bassett, I. J., C. W. Crompton, J. McNeill, and P. M. Taschereau. 1983. The Genus Atriplex (Chenopodiaceae) in Canada. Ottawa. [Agricu. Canada Monogr. 31.] Brown, G. D. 1956. Taxonomy of American Atriplex. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 55: 199–210.</reference>
    <reference> Hall, H. M. and F. E. Clements. 1923. The phylogenetic method in taxonomy: The North American species of Artemisia, Chrysothamnus, and Atriplex. Publ. Carnegie Inst. Wash. 326. Hanson, C. A. 1962. Perennial Atriplex of Utah and the Northern Deserts. M.S. thesis. Brigham Young University. McNeill, J., I. J. Bassett, C. W. Crompton, and P. M. Taschereau. 1983. Taxonomic and nomenclatural notes on Atriplex L. (Chenopodiaceae). Taxon 32: 549–556.</reference>
    <reference> Taschereau, P. M. 1972. Taxonomy and distribution of Atriplex species in Nova Scotia. Canad. J. Bot. 50: 1571–1594.</reference>
    <reference> Turesson, G. 1925. Studies in the genus Atriplex. Acta Univ. Lund, n. s. 21: 1–15.</reference>
    <reference> Welsh, S. L. 1995. Names and types of perennial Atriplex Linnaeus (Chenopodiaceae) in North America selectively exclusive of Mexico. Great Basin Naturalist 55: 322–334.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants perennial shrubs [20c.Atriplexsubg. Pterochiton , in part] Key 4</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants annual or perennial herbs.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves usually green on both surfaces, glabrous or sparingly powdery or finely s curfy Key 1</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves white to gray, densely and finely scurfy, especially adaxially.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants perennial Key 2</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants annual Key 3</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pistillate flowers of 2 kinds: some with calyx 3–5-lobed and seed horizontal, others lacking perianth, enclosedin pair of bracteoles, seed vertical; fruiting bracteoles samaralike, strongly compressed, oval to orbicular or ovate; plants widespread in North America [20a.1.Atriplex</statement>
      <determination>1. Atriplex hortensis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pistillate flowers all alike or, if dimorphic, both kinds lacking perianth, enclosed within bracteoles, and seed vertical; fruiting bracteoles variously compressed (orbicular in A. heterosperma ).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles ± thickened with spongy tissue, especially toward base [20a.2.Atriplexsect. Teutliopsis ]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lower leaves linear or ovate-lanceolate, sometimes toothed and/or with proximalmost lobe largest, but then not triangular, or if so leaves thick textured.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves linear to lanceolate or oblong, thin, green or slightly scurfy when young; seeds ovoid, not wider than long; coastal e Canada and ne United States, wdisjunctly to Pennsylvania, Ohio, and Indiana</statement>
      <determination>2. Atriplex littoralis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves ovate-lanceolate or linear, or triangular or triangular-hastate, typically thickened and ± scurfy, even in age; seeds ellipsoid, wider than long; broad distribution from coastal e Canada and United States, and c and w United</statement>
      <determination>8. Atriplex d ioica ### (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lower leaves (sometimes all or most) triangular and thin textured.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles, some or all, short stipitate, margin irregularly denticulate to laciniate, lateral angles of faces usually developed into 1–3 teeth;Cape Breton coast,</statement>
      <determination>10. Atriplex glabriuscula (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles all sessile, margin entire or slightly toothed, lateral angles shortly pointed but not definitely toothed; ge ography below.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence with leafy bracts to the tip, glomerules loose, irregularly spaced; bracteoles thick spongy, margin united to middle; seeds 2.5+ mm wide, usually not distinctly dimorphic, dark brown to black, irregularly biconvex; radicle m edian, ± antrorse; coastal e United States, from New Jersey n to Maine and Nova Scotia and n to Newfoundland and Labrador, and w</statement>
      <determination>10. Atriplex glabriuscula (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence with leafy bracts only at base, glomerules tight, contiguous or irregularly spaced; bracteoles thin to slightly thickened and spongy, margin united only at base; seeds mostly less than 2.5 mm wide, usually distinctly dimorphic, mostly small and glossy black,but also some larger, and dull brown, flattened and disc-shaped; radicle subbasal, obliquely antrorse to spreading; plant a weedy introduction of broad distribution in</statement>
      <determination>9. Atriplex prostrata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles not thickened (except A. joaquiniana ).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants mostly less than 1.2 dm; proximal leaves lanceolate to rhombic-ovate, bases cuneate to attenuate; bracteoles rhombic-ovate, thin herbaceous or membranaceous, entire, free to ba se; seeds black, lustrous, biconvex, 1.2–2.5 mm wide, with subbasal, spreading radicle; plants in the sublittoral zone on coasts of Newfoundland</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants mostly more t han 1.2 dm; proximal leaves, bracteoles, and seeds not simultaneously as above; distribution various.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles ovate to elliptic or orbiculate-cordate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles ovate to widely triangular, surfaces often 2-tuberculate, margin toothed;leaves usually thickened, ± scurfy, even at maturity</statement>
      <determination>8. Atriplex dioica ### (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles orbiculate-ovate, surfaces smooth, margin entire; leaves usually thin, green on both sides, not or scarcely scurfy.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves broadly t riangular-hastate; widely distributed from Quebec, w to Brit-ish Columbia and s to California, Nevada, Utah, and Colorado</statement>
      <determination>7. Atriplex heterosperma</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mostly lanceolate to narrowly hastate; s British Columbia, adjacent</statement>
      <determination>4. Atriplex oblongifolia (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles never orbiculate-cordate, frequently toothed, usually with lateral angles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles (2–)2.5–3(–4.5) mm; leaf blades deltoid to rhombic-ovate or oblong-ovate, coarsely toothed; saline soils in Sacramento Valley and east San Francisco</statement>
      <determination>6. Atriplex joaquiniana</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>11. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles mainly 4–10+ mm; leaf blades hastate or entire, lanceolate to oblong; coastal salt marshes or ruderal weedy species of broad distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>12. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Largest bracteoles strap-shaped or ovate-lanceolate; halophytes of w and nwcoastal areas of North America</statement>
      <determination>5. Atriplex gmelinii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Largest bracteoles ovate, ovate-triangular, or rhombic; e coastal North America (disjunctly westward) or widespread ruderal weeds.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Radicle of brown seeds basal and spreading; e coastal salt marshes and</statement>
      <determination>10. Atriplex glabriuscula (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Radicle of brown seeds subbasal to median and antrorse; widespread ruderal weeds.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles rhombic, margin united almost to middle, lateral angles definite; terminal inflorescen ce with densely compressed, ± uniform-sized bracteoles; distal leaves green on both sides</statement>
      <determination>3. Atriplex patula</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles ovate or triangular-ovate, margin free to base, lateral angles lacking; terminal inflorescence with loosely spaced, larger and smallerbracteoles; distal leaves whitish abaxially</statement>
      <determination>4. Atriplex oblongifolia (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants dioecious; leaves sessile, mostly opposite [20b.3i. Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect. Californicae , for the most part]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 2–5 mm, subequal to internodes; fruiting bracteoles 2–3 mm; coastal or nearcoastal s Texas and adjacent Mexico</statement>
      <determination>46. Atriplex matamorensis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 8–25 mm, often surpassing internodes; fruiting bracteoles 4–8 mm; coastal Santa</statement>
      <determination>45. Atriplex watsonii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants monoecious; leaves various, but if sessile and mo stly opposite, of different distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves sessile, blade 5–20 × 1.5–5 mm; fruiting bracteoles 3 mm, rhombic-ovate, acute, sessile, scarcely united, entire; coastal and insular Marin County, California s to Baja</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves subsessile to long petiolate, blade and fruiting bracteoles mostly more tha n 3 mm, but if shorter, not from coastal California.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles (5–)6–12 mm, fibrous and spongy or merely spongy-thickened.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles obovoid-globular, summit closed by 2 erect, appressed, entire or 3-toothed valves; plants known from cultivation in Wyoming and Texas</statement>
      <determination>15. Atriplex holocarpa</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles variously shaped, bearing 1 or 2 appendages; different distrib utions.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles 5–7 mm, broadly ovate in profile, entire or dentate, usually with wartlike projections on faces; sea beaches and coastal strand, occasionally inland, from Humboldt County, California, south to Baja Cali-fornia, Mexico [20b.</statement>
      <determination>3h. Atriplex ### sect. Obione ### subsect. Leucophyllae ]</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles 6–12 mm, broadly turbinate or hemispheric, flattened at summit,bordered by a narrow horizontal wing or acutely angled; plants escaped from cultivation in San Joaquin Valley and San Diego County,</statement>
      <determination>16. Atriplex lindleyi</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles mainly 3–6 mm, not fibrous or spongy thickened.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Seeds dimorphic: black, 1.5–1.7 mm, or brown, 2 mm; bracteoles fleshy; plants low growing, many stemmed; leaf margin irregularlydentate; introduced, sw British Columbia and Washington, to s California, s Arizona, s Nevada, sw Utah, s Arizona, s</statement>
      <determination>17. Atriplex semibaccata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Seeds monomorphic, either black or brown; bracts not fleshy; plants not low growing; leaf margin entire to dentate; various or other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>8. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Petioles to 1 / 2as long as blades, or some blades typically more than 2.5 cm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruit ing bracteoles 3 mm and as wide at apex, bluntly deltoid to circular, swollen, hard, smooth, denticulate at apex, faces unappendaged; Australian species [20a.5.Atriplexsect. Semibaccata, in part, Atriplex muelleriBentham, see 17.A. semibaccata ]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles (3–)5–7 mm, 2–4 mm broad, cuneate-orbicular, margin sharply dentate, faces with appendages or unappendaged; indigenous plants from nc to s California, w ands Nevada, Arizona, New Mexico, w and n</statement>
      <determination>25. Atriplex argentea (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Petioles short (much less than 1 / 2as long as blades) or lacking, blades of various lengths.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves sinuate-dentate; fruiting bracteoles rhombic, widest and 2- to 4-toothed beyond middle; plants known from s California, e to s Utah [20a.5. Atriplex</statement>
      <determination>18. Atriplex suberecta (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves vari ously toothed or entire; fruiting bracteoles variously shaped and toothed; various or other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles 2–4 mm wide, orbicular, subsessile to short stipitate, strongly compressed, united except at thin margin, margin dentate, terminal teeth often prominent, faces smooth; Mojave and Colorado deserts,</statement>
      <determination>42. Atriplex elegans (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles, at least some, more than 4 mm, rhombic or obovate to cuneate-orbicul ate, orbiculate, or obovate, margin deeply and acutely dentate, faces variously toothed or appendaged, the terminal teeth not conspicuous; various or other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Faces of cuneate-orbiculate fruiting bracteoles with 2 dentate crests or covered with irregular, conic-acute, corky tubercles; sandy seashores, s</statement>
      <determination>37. Atriplex pentandra (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Faces of obovate or orbiculate fruiting bracteoles without dentate crests or co rky tubercles, usually smooth; saline or alkaline substrates in California, Nevada, Arizona, and Utah.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>13. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles 2–3 mm, obovate, united 1 / 2of length, free margin deeply and sharply dentate, faces smooth or sometimes tuberculate; Santa Barbara and Los Angeles to w San Bernardino</statement>
      <determination>40. Atriplex coulteri</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles often larger, suborbiculate, or orbiculate, united except at thin margin, margin dentate, terminal teeth often prominent, faces often smooth; interior California, Nevada, Arizona, and Utah.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate flowers in terminal spikes, pistillate ones in axillary clusters; Sacramento and San Joaquin valleys, California</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate flowers in axillary clusters, or staminate and pistillate mixed, usually in axillary clusters; e of Sierra Nevada, in s California, e to Rio Grande Valley of s Texas, and s to Mexico</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades all or most of them dentate or sinuate-dentate, leaves all alternate, or opposite only at proximalmost 1–3 nodes.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles widest at middle, entire below middle, 2–4-toothed beyond middle;</statement>
      <determination>18. Atriplex suberecta (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles mostly widest below middle, variously toothed, tuberculate, or entire; various or other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades orbiculate or suborbiculate, flabellate to broadly obtuse at base; fruit flask-shaped in outline; Milk River Valley, Upper Missouri, south to Colorado[an Atriplexlook-alike, Suckleya suckleyana(Torrey ex A. Gray)Rydberg]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mainly ovate to lanceolate, acute to obtuse basally; various distribution [20a.3.Atriplexsect. Sclerocalymma ]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants erect; leaves with Kranz anatomy; seeds 2–2.5 mm wide; common, widespread weedyspecies mainly in saline substrates, widely distributed in United</statement>
      <determination>12. Atriplex rosea</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants decumbent; leaves with or without Kranz anatomy; seeds 3.5–4 mm wide (1.5–2 mm in A. tatarica ); rare coastal halophytes of sandy beaches bordering Gulf of St. Lawrence, Canada, and along Atlantic coast to Alabama.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Seeds 1.5–2 mm; leaves without Kranz anatomy; staminate glomerules arranged in terminal panicles or spikes to several cm; plants robust, stems usually 2–15 dm, leaves often more than 5 cm; rare ballast waifs, introduced from Europe, from Massachusetts to Pennsylvania, and disjunctly incoastal Alabama</statement>
      <determination>13. Atriplex tatarica</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Seeds 3.5–4 mm; lea ves with Kranz anatomy; staminate glomerules in distal axils and in short dense terminal spikes to 1 cm; plants small, stems less</statement>
      <determination>14. Atriplex laciniata (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades not all d entate, some, or all, of them entire, leaves commonly opposite or subopposite at proximalmost nodes.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perianth of staminate flowers cup-shaped, lobes fleshy-crested on back, pink; bracteole margin united to apex; high plains and steppes, se Alberta and sSaskatchewan, e Montana, w North Dakota, South Dakota, Wyoming, and nw Colorado [</statement>
      <determination>20b.2. Atriplex</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perianth of stam inate flowers not cup-shaped, lobes ovate, rounded on back, green in center, becoming membranous near margins; bracteole margin united at base or to middle; various or other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles 3–7 mm wide, enclosing 2–5 flowers, these with perianth of 5 hyaline scales 1–1.2 mm; leaves without Kranz anatomy; mainly on Mancos Shale and Morrison formations, Four Corners vicinity, Colorado, Utah, New Mexico</statement>
      <determination>21. Atriplex pleiantha</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles of various sizes, not enclosing more than 1 flower; leaves mainly with Kranz anatomy (except A. covillei ); of various or other distribut ion.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles on stipes 2–6 mm, body 5–6 mm thick, globose, with hornlike ap-pendages on both faces; se Utah</statement>
      <determination>24. Atriplex saccaria (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles variously sessile or, if stipitate, not otherwise as above.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bract eoles samaralike, orbicular, often over 10 mm, margin 2–4 times as wide as body; staminate flowers in deciduous terminal panicles; local ine Utah, and wc Colorado</statement>
      <determination>23. Atriplex graciliflora</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles commonly less than 10 mm (mostly much less; 5–20 mm in A. phyllostegia ), margin usually little if at all wider than body; staminate flowers in panicles or some or all in axillary glomerules; various or other distribu tion.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles orbicular, finely and regularly radiately dentate to base, strongly compressed; deserts in se California and e to sw Utah, s Nevada, s Arizona, s New Mexico, w Texas, and in Sonora and Chihuahua [20b.3g.Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect.</statement>
      <determination>42. Atriplex elegans (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles not orbicular, or if so, never radiately dentate to base and not at once strongly c ompressed; other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades oval to ovate or ovate-lanceolate, hastate or not; w Nevada and Great Valley of California.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves oval to ovate, seldom if ever with long-attenuate, hastate lobes; plants with Kranz anatomy; w Nevada [20b .4.Atriplexsubg. Obionesect.</statement>
      <determination>47. Atriplex phyllostegia</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves ovate-lanceolate, mainly with acute to long-attenuate hastate lobes; plants without Kranz anatomy; w Nevada and c and s California [20b.5. Atriplex</statement>
      <determination>48. Atriplex covillei</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades variously shaped, if as abov e, mainly of other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles 4–7 mm wide, variably and irregularly 3–7-cleft, typically constricted near middle and with terminal lobes 1.5–2.8 mm, doubly cristate on faces or smooth; Kleberg, LaSalle, Starr, and Webb counties, s coastalTexas [20b.3c.</statement>
      <determination>27. Atriplex klebergorum</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles less than 4–6 mm wide, or if that wide, then differing o therwise or of other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles deltoid to ovate or hastate-ovate to ovate-oblong, broadest at or near base, often about twice as long as broad, small, sparingly dentate or tuberculate, or entire or smooth, acute; leaves small, sessile, b lade typically entire, ovate to linear.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>15. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>15. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves and/or branches opposite, at least proximalmost [20b.3f. Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect. Pusillae , in part]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants tending to sprawl, with leaves and foliose bracts tending torecurve</statement>
      <determination>31. Atriplex parishii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants erect or ascending, with leaves and foliose bracts straight or nearly so.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>17. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>17. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Proximal leaves with rounded base, with both leaves and foliosebracts somewhat thickened and stiffly ascending; fruiting bracteoles 2.5–3.5 mm, ovate to rhombic; Kern Lake, s San</statement>
      <determination>33. Atriplex tularensis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Proximal leaves acute to obtuse at base, with both leav es and foliose bracteoles rather thin and merely ascending; fruiting bracteoles 2.5–4 mm, broadly deltate to suborbiculate in profile; San Joaquin Valley, Kern and Fresno counties, California</statement>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves and branches all alternate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>18. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>18. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles 1.5–2 × 1–1.5 mm, ovate-oblong, fused to near summit, tridentate apically, occasionally with marginal or less commonly with facial appendages; se Utah [20b.3c. Atriplex</statement>
      <determination>26. Atriplex powellii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles not at once as above; various or other distribution [20b.3f.Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect. Pusillae , for the most part]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>19. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>19. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades of at least some proximalmost leaves cordate atbase; nc and c California</statement>
      <determination>32. Atriplex cordulata (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades ro unded to acute or at most subcordate at base; various distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Branches copiously villous, at least around inflorescence</statement>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <statement>Branches merely scurfy.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Faces of bracteoles tuberculate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2 2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2 2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades mainly 0.4–2.5 × 0.1–0.3 cm, linear to narrowly lanceolate; fruiting bracteoles ovate to cuneate; Utah, Wyoming, and Colorado [20b.3e.Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect.</statement>
      <determination>9. Atriplex wolfii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades 0.2–0.4 × 0.1–0.3 cm, ovate to ovate-lanceolate; fruiting bracteoles ovate-oblong; Glenn, Merced, and Tulare counties, California</statement>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <statement>Faces of bracteoles smooth.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles 2–3 mm, subhastate, denticulate, or crenulate; stems mainly not suffused with red; cvalley of California southward</statement>
      <determination>31. Atriplex parishii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles 1–2 mm, ovate, entire; stems suffusedwith red; ne California, se Oregon, Nevada</statement>
      <determination>30. Atriplex pusilla</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles broadest near or above middle, usually rounded or truncate at apex, or if not so, leaves dentate; leaves usually large and often some petiolate (but see also A. coronata ).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>24. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>24. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades, most of them, deltoid to deltoid-ovate or broadly ovate, broadest at or near base (lanceolate to elliptic in A. coronata ), usually entire.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades often cordate at base; fruiting bracteoles of 2 kinds on each plant; s Wyoming, e Utah, n Arizona, nw New Mexico, and w Texas [20b.3b.Atriplex</statement>
      <determination>24. Atriplex saccaria (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades never cordate at base or, in some, sessile distal ones sometimes cordate-clasping; fruiting bracteoles all similar on same plant.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles pandurifor m (fiddle-shaped) in outline (with 2 lateral rounded lobes lateral to terminal tooth), faces often obscured by cristate or unaligned appendages; leaf blades conspicuously 3-veined; Alberta, Saskatchewan, se Oregon, sw Idaho, Oregon, Utah, nw New Mexico, Co lorado, Wyoming, South Dakota, Montana [20b.3c.Atriplexsubg.Obionesubsect. Argenteae,in part]</statement>
      <determination>26. Atriplex powellii (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles not panduriform; leaf blades not conspicuously 3-veined.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles broadly rhombic, toothed beyond middle; Sacramento and San Joaquin valleys, California [20.b.3f. Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect. Pusillae,in part]</statement>
      <determination>32. Atriplex cordulata (in pa rt)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles of various shapes and teeth various; various or other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles dentate only at truncate apex, small; s British Columbia, Alberta, and sw Saskatchewan, s to California, Nevada, Utah, Colo-</statement>
      <determination>28. Atriplex truncata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles dentate well below apex, often to base, large; other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades closely repand-dentate; nc to s California, w and s Nevada, Arizona, New Mexico, w and n Texas, and w Oklahoma</statement>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades entire or remotely and irregularly dentate; other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>30. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>30. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades mostly oblong, oblong-ovate, or elliptic to lanceolate, not subhastate or angled at base; Sacramento and San Joaquin valleys, e and s CoastRanges, California [20b.3f.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades variously shaped, at least some typically subhastate or angled at base, or if acute to obtuse at base (as in some A. argenteavarieties) of different distribution; s British Columbia e to sw Manitoba, and s to e Washington, e Idaho, Nevada, se California, Utah, ne Arizona, nw New Mexico, n Texas [20b.3c. Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect.Argenteae,in part]</statement>
      <determination>25. Atriplex argentea (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades neither deltoid nor ovate, usual ly broadest at or beyond middle, in few species leaves broadest at base and conspicuously dentate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>31. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>31. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades linear, concolorous; bracteoles truncate apically; sw Wyoming, ne and c</statement>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades usually broader than linear, or if linear, abaxial surface much paler than adaxial and bracteoles not truncat e; other distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades entire.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteole faces, at least some, conspicuously tuberculate or cristate [20b.3g.Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect. Arenariae ]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles (3.5–)4.5–7 × 3.5–5.6 mm, typically longer than broad, faces with or without appendages; plants coastal from New England s along</statement>
      <determination>38. Atriplex mucronata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting bracteoles 2.5–4.5 × 2.6–5mm, typically as wide or wider than long, and with faces appendaged; plants coastal from North Carolina s along Atlantic and w along Gulf to coastal or near coastal w Texas</statement>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteole facestypically smooth, sometimes inconspicuously tuberculate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate glomerules all axillary</statement>
      <determination>39. Atriplex pacifica</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate glomerules mainly in terminal spikes</statement>
      <determination>37. Atriplex pentandra (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3 2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades dentate, or if entire staminate glomerules mainly in terminal spikes.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate glomerules axillary, or in very short, simple, terminal spikes [20b.3g.Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect. Arenariae ]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteole faces not appendaged; s California</statement>
      <determination>35. Atriplex serenana (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>37. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteole faces tuberculate, muricate, or cristate; coastal se and s United</statement>
      <determination>37. ### Atriplex pentandra (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate glomerules in elongate, usually paniculate spikes.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles 4–6 mm; leaf blades sinuate-dentate; Gulf of St. Lawrence, Prince Edward Island, Nova Scotia, and Quebec [20a.3.Atriplexsect.</statement>
      <determination>14. Atriplex laciniata (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>38. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles 2–3.5 mm; leaf blades various, but if as above, of different distribution [20b.3g. Atriplexsubg. Obionesubsect. Arenariae ]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves lanceolate to oblong, elliptic, or oval, subconcolorous; bracteole faces almost always conspicuously tuberculate; California and w Ne-vada</statement>
      <determination>35. Atriplex serenana ( in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>39. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves linear to lanceolate or oblong, white abaxially, green adaxially; bracteole faces usually unappendaged; s Arizona, s New Mexico andalong Rio Grande, in Texas and Mexico</statement>
      <determination>36. Atriplex wrightii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves sinuate-dentate to dentate or laciniate (at least some), or strongly undulate-crisped and appearing lobed; herbage silvery white.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades deeply, sharply dentate or laciniate; fruiting bracteoles orbiculate, entire tocrenate, sessile, surfaces lacking processes; sw Utah, s Nevada, s California</statement>
      <determination>54. Atriplex hymenelytra</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades sinuate, sinuate-dentate, or hastate; fruiting bracteoles stipitate, 6–15 mm, macelike, surfaces often with elongate, radiating, hornlike, or flattened processes; se</statement>
      <determination>49. Atriplex acanthocarpa</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves entire or merely hastately lobed, or if sinuate-dentate or denticulate, herbage green or gray.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles conspicuously longitudinally 4-winged, or with tubercles aligned in 4 parallel rows.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants low, seldom more than 4 dm; subshrubs of playas in GreatBasin and Range,or w Great Plains</statement>
      <determination>51. Atriplex gardneri (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants low or tall; broad or various distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mainly 2–3 mm wide and often over 2 cm, narrowly linear-elliptic, often rather acute apically; plants with very slender branchlets; s Arizona and s</statement>
      <determination>62. Atriplex linearis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mostly 3–10+ mm wide, or if occasionally less then often less than 2 cm or of different distribution, or leaves spatulate, thickened,and obtuse apically; plants with branchlets not especially slender; various distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mainly 0.3–0.8 cm wide; bract tip lacking lateral teeth; shrubs mainly 8–20 dm; widespread in w North America, from s Canada, southward in</statement>
      <determination>61. Atriplex canescens</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves often more than 8 mm wide; bract tip with or without lateral teeth;shrubs mainly 2–8 dm; se Utah and n Arizona</statement>
      <determination>53. Atriplex garrettii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Br acteoles lacking lateral wings (tubercles sometimes aligned in 4 rows).</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants definitely spiny, branches terminating in thorns; bracteoles foliose, entire, united only at base, surfaces lacking appendages.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles (4–)6–15 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>9. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves ovate tooval or elliptic, not hastate; body of bracteoles not constricted below free terminal valves; e Montana and sw North Dakota to</statement>
      <determination>56. Atriplex confertifolia</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves elongate -deltoid and commonly somewhat hastate; body of bracteoles constricted below terminal valves; w San Joaquin Valley and w</statement>
      <determination>57. Atriplex spinifera</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <statement>Bracteoles 2–4(–6) mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves short petiolate to sessile, cordate basally, blade 0.5–1.5 cm; herbagesilvery white; low shrubs</statement>
      <determination>60. Atriplex parryi</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves petiolate, truncate or cuneate basally, typically some subhastate; herbage grayish or greenish; shrubs to 20+ dm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <statement>Twigssharply angled, glabrous to sparingly puberulent; sw Utah, Ne-vada, s Arizona, s California</statement>
      <determination>59. Atriplex torreyi (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants not definitely spiny, or if somewhat so bracteoles at least 1 / 3united, surfaces appendaged or not.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>12. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades typically some subhastate (except A. polycarpa , with many, tiny, commonly clustered leav es); shrubs to 30 dm; Utah sw to Mexico.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Branchlets conspicuously and sharply angled; sw Utah, s Nevada, s Ari-zona, and s California</statement>
      <determination>59. A ### triplex torreyi (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <statement>Branchlets terete or nearly so; extending to Mexico.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>14. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 10–50 × 50 mm; sw Utah, Arizona, Nevada, California,</statement>
      <determination>58. Atriplex lentiformis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>14. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 3–15 (longer only on juvenile shoots) × 2–4 mm; s Nevada, sw</statement>
      <determination>55. Atriplex polycarpa</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>12. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades attenuate to rounded basally, seldom some subhastate; shrubs mainly less than 20 dm; various distribution.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves 2–4+ mm wide; bracteoles with appendages on basal 1 / 3; staminate flowers inspikes; plants prostrate; w Colorado, ne New Mexico, and e Utah</statement>
      <determination>52. Atriplex corrugata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>15. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves often more than 4 mm wide; bracteoles with appendages various; staminate flowers mainly in panicles; plants not or seldom prostrate; distribution various or other.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>16. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>16. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves dentate to denticulate or less commonly some or all entire; bracteoles somewhat rhomboid to orbicular; introduced, native to Australia, known in s California ands Arizona [20a.6 Atriplexsect. Dialysex ]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves elliptic to oblong, often shortly hastate, and sometimes remotely denticulate; bracteoles somewhat rhomboid to semicircular in profile, biconvex, thickened and hard all overor with short papery valves; introduced in coastals California</statement>
      <determination>20. Atriplex amnicola</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves rhomboid to orbicular, sinuate-dentate; fruiting bracteoles rhomboid to orbicular, papery all over or with thickened base; s Calif ornia, s Arizona</statement>
      <next_statement_id>16. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>16. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves not simultaneously of above size and proportion; fruiting bracteoles various but not as above; w Great Plains and Intermountain region [20c. Atriplexsubg. Pterochiton , in part]</statement>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves oblong-ovate to orbicular, more than 1 cm wide, proximalmost alternate; stems stiffly erect; staminate glomerules very numerous; se Utah south-ward through e Arizona, New Mexico, w Texas</statement>
      <determination>50. Atriplex obov ata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves linear to oblong, mainly less than 1 cm wide, or if wider, proximalmost opposite; stems prostrate to ascending, or less commonly erect; staminate glomerules numerous; Great Plains w to Great Basin and Colorado River dr ainage</statement>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
