<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ventenat" date="unknown">chenopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="C. A. Meyer ex Bongard" date="1838">gmelinii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Acad. Imp. Sci. St. Pétersbourg, Sér.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6, Sci. Math. 2: 160. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family chenopodiaceae;genus atriplex;species gmelinii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, monoecious, erect or ascending, branched from base or rarely simple, 0.5–8(–100) dm; proximal branches mostly elongated and often prostrate. Leaves alternate, except the proximal-most; petiole 0.5–1.5(–2) cm; blade green on both sides, ovate to oblong or lanceolate to oblong, deltoid-oblong, or linear, 9–100 × 1–50 mm, base mostly rounded to tapering or more rarely broadly cuneate from a hastate base, margin entire or repand denticulate, apex acute or acuminate or more rarely obtuse, glabrous or nearly so. Flowers glomerate in rather loose, spiciform inflorescences, and in axillary clusters; staminate ones 4–5-merous. Fruiting bracteoles darkening at maturity, sessile or stipitate, ovate or oblong to orbiculate, longest ones strap-shaped or ovate-lanceolate, mainly 4–10 mm, distinct nearly to base, margin entire or with (1 or) 2 or more teeth, apex acuminate to acute, often bulging on both sides of the impressed midnerve, at first mealy, finally glabrate. Seeds dimorphic: some small, black (lacking? in var. alaskensis), convex, 1.5–2 mm wide, lustrous, others pale brown, flat, 1.5–3.5 mm wide; radicle inferior or subascending. 2n = 54.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <number>5.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Gmelin’s orach</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Brown seeds 1.7–3 mm wide; fruiting bracteoles mostly less than 10 mm; leaf blades mainly oblong to lance-oblong or linear, less commonlyhastate-lanceolate</description>
      <determination>5a. Atriplex gmelinii ### var. gmelini i</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Brown seeds 2.8–3.5 mm wide; fruiting bracteoles often more than 10 mm; leaf blades oblong to lanceolate or hastate-lanceolate or -ovate</description>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
