<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Chenopodiaceae Ventenat" date="unknown">CHENOPODIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">dioica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Monthly Mag. &amp; Crit. Rev.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2(2): 119. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CHENOPODIACEAE;genus Atriplex;species dioica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">patula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Nuttall) S. Watson" date="unknown">subspicata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atriplex;species patula;variety subspicata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Nuttall) Rydberg" date="unknown">subspicata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atriplex;species subspicata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, monoecious, typically erect and often branching, 3–15 dm; stems green or
        striped, angular. Leaves opposite or subopposite at least proximally; petiole 1–3 cm; blade
        strongly 3-veined from near base, lanceolate to linear-lanceolate or often triangular-ovate
        or lance-ovate, 30–125 × 25–60(–80) mm, thickened, basal or subbasal lobes spreading to
        mainly antrorse, obtuse, blade otherwise entire to sparingly dentate, typically scurfy.
        Flowers in terminal or terminal on lateral branches, in spiciform spikes, 2–9 cm, naked
        except at base. Fruiting bracteoles green, blackening in age, sessile, veined or veins
        obscure, broadly triangular to ovate, 3–10 mm, thick, usually longer than wide, base
        truncate to obtuse, margin united at base, apex acute lateral angles entire or with short,
        sharp teeth, faces smooth or with 2 tubercles, with an inflated inner spongy layer. Seeds
        ellipsoid, wider than long, dimorphic: brown, 1.5–3 mm wide, flattened at base, or black,
        1–2 mm wide, shiny; radicle inferior. 2n = 36, 54.</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="phenology">aug</description>
  <description type="phenology">fall</description>
  <description type="phenology">sep</description>
  <description type="phenology">oct</description>
  <description type="phenology">nov</description>
  <description type="habitat">sea beaches</description>
  <description type="habitat">other saline habitats</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–1500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta.</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Man.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.S.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Que.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Sask.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Yukon</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Colo.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Idaho</description>
  <description type="distribution">Iowa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Kans.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Maine</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mass.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Minn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mont.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nebr.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nev.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.H.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.J.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Dak.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Okla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="distribution">R.I.</description>
  <description type="distribution">S.Dak.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Utah</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wash.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wyo.</description>
  <number>8</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Thickleaf orach</other_name>
  <discussion>The distribution of the species is evidently bipartite, with an eastern coastal
        series extending northward mainly from New Jersey to Newfoundland and along the St. Lawrence
        seaway, and perhaps extending to James Bay of Hudson Bay. The western grouping lies mainly
        west of the 95th meridian of longitude, where it has been collected since early historical
        times to the present in saline marshes or other saline sites from the Yukon Territory and
        Northwest Territories, southward to southern California, northern Arizona, northern New
        Mexico, and Oklahoma.</discussion>
  <discussion>Rafinesque gave the following information: “Stem upright angular branched, leaves
        petiolate, deltoid, acute, thick, scaly, the proximal opposite toothed, the distal
        alternate, hastated, entire: flowers dioical glomerate, male spiked naked, female unequal,
        sepals deltoid, warty-crested.”</discussion>
  <discussion>The name Atriplex dioica Rafinesque antedates Chenopodium subspicatum Nuttall by
        half a year, being published in December 1817. Hence, it is the correct name for the widely
        ranging species, which has passed most recently under the name A. subspicata. Nuttall’s
        description of the habitat of Chenopodium subspicatum is: “In saline soils around Mandan
        Village, Missouri,” a designation of habitat that applies to this day.</discussion>
  <discussion>The species forms a mirror-image set of specimens with the remarkably similar
        Atriplex prostrata, from which it may be distinguished in most cases by the thickened,
        merely ovate to lanceolate leaf blades, and less commonly but in some localities exclusively
        triangular-hastate to lanceolate, mostly scurfy and prominently 3-veined leaf blades. In
        some specimens, including the types of both Chenopodium subspicatum and Atriplex carnosa,
        the blades bear a hastate lobe at or above the base and sometimes match triangular-hastate
        profile of A. prostrata. The leaves of A. prostrata are typically thin-textured, green, not
        scurfy, and the veins of the blade are obscure. I. J. Bassett et al. (1983) disallowed
        within A. dioica (as A. subspicata) any but those with lanceolate blades, including those
        with the proximalmost leaves with a pair of subbasal hastate lobes. However, there are
        numerous specimens in which the blades are thickened and transitional in that regard to the
        triangular-hastate profile as in A. prostrata. Certainly those specimens with triangular or
        triangular-hastate leaves taken prior to the introduction of A. prostrata sometime late in
        the nineteenth or early twentieth century, clearly belong to the indigenous A. dioica.
        Whether there are intermediates between diploid (2n = 18) A. prostrata and tetraploid or
        hexaploid (2n = 36, 54) A. dioica is not known. There does not seem to be any consistent
        feature or combination of features by which all specimens can be assigned to one or the
        other of the two taxa. It seems probable, however, that A. prostrata is a late introduction
        from Europe, and that it, along with the related A. heterosperma, is now invading habitats
        previously occupied exclusively by the indigenous A. dioica.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
