<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Chenopodiaceae Ventenat" date="unknown">CHENOPODIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="W. A. Weber" date="unknown">Obione</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="S. L. Welsh" date="unknown">Pleianthae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>102: 418. 2001</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CHENOPODIACEAE;genus Atriplex;subgenus Obione;section Pleianthae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Proatriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atriplex;subgenus Proatriplex;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(W. A. Weber) Stutz &amp; G. L. Chu" date="unknown">Proatriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>section Proatriplex;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, monoecious. Leaves with normal (non-Kranz) anatomy. Staminate flowers
    with calyx lobes not crested. Pistillate flowers 2–5, typically with a 5-lobed perianth.
    Bracteoles triangular-ovate, united to middle or beyond, faces lacking tubercles. Seeds: radicle
    lateral, declined (the tip at opposite end from styles).</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <number>20b.1.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>The similarity of the single taxon in this section, Atriplex pleiantha, with other
    species of Atriplex in the Colorado Plateau is illusory. Great weight has been given to the
    presence of apparently primitive inflorescences within the flowering bracteoles, but that
    feature is probably derived, not primitive. The linear, pale perianth segments subtending the
    3–5 flowers are not unlike those in A. phyllostegia and A. suckleyi, both of which also lack
    Kranz anatomy in their leaves. Rather than representing primitive features, the presence of the
    perianth and, in the case of A. pleiantha, multiple flowers, these striking and seductively
    attractive features appear to represent independently derived occurrences within the highly
    variable genus Atriplex. If any of the taxa with included perianth are to be segregated within
    separate genera, then each should be so treated. However, such an approach might overshadow the
    true relationships to other species within the vast and complex genus. The radicle placement in
    seeds of sect. Pleianthae is inferior (lateral, with the tip of the radicle at a point
    diametrically opposed to the styles), possibly indicating a relationship divergent from the
    other species with perianth scales subtending the ovary in pistillate flowers. Because of the
    radicle position, the section is possibly best placed within subg. Atriplex. However, the
    radicle position might also be a derived condition in Atriplex in the broad sense, at least in
    some cases. If so, the relationship could well lie with other members now treated within the
    subg. Obione, the current but tentative placement of the section herein.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Stutz, H. C., G. Chu, and S. C. Sanderson. 1990. Evolutionary
      studies of Atriplex: Phylogenetic relationships of Atriplex pleiantha. Amer. J. Bot. 77:
      364–369.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
