<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>20b.3b.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Atriplex</genus_name>
        <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
        <subgenus_name>Obione</subgenus_name>
        <section_name>Obione</section_name>
        <subsection_name>Saccariae</subsection_name>
        <subsection_authority>(Standley) S. L. Welsh</subsection_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>102: 419. 2001</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Atriplex</genus_name>
        <unranked_epithet_name>Saccariae</unranked_epithet_name>
        <unranked_epithet_authority>Standley</unranked_epithet_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>in N. L. Britton et al., N. Amer. Fl. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>21: 45. 1916</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Leaves usually short petiolate; blade mostly cordate or ovate, entire. Staminate
        flowers in spicate or paniculate glomerules, the inflorescence soon deciduous. Fruiting
        bracteoles typically (but not always) dimorphic, some large, stipitate and faces mostly
        tuberculate, others small, cuneate and unappendaged, or lacking, united at base. Seeds:
        radicle superior.</description>
    <number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa>
    <global_distribution>w North America.</global_distribution>
    <discussion>The taxa of subsect. Saccariae are morphologically similar to members of subsect.
        Argenteae, differing in the usually dimorphic fruiting bracteoles, the smaller sessile
        bracteoles mainly lacking surficial appendages, but with radiating appendages on the larger
        stipitate bracteoles, or with appendages radiating from the globular surface on the mainly
        stipitate, monomorphic bracteoles. The alliance of this complex with the Atriplex argentea
        assemblage is suggested by intermediacy of even the main diagnostic features. It seems
        probable that the sessile, smooth-faced bracteole might have been derived from some A.
        argentea-type ancestor. Certainly, the two complexes are closely allied both taxonomically
        and geographically.</discussion>
</treatment>
