<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Chenopodiaceae Ventenat" date="unknown">CHENOPODIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. Watson" date="unknown">saccaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Eastwood) S. L. Welsh" date="unknown">saccaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CHENOPODIACEAE;genus Atriplex;species saccaria;variety saccaria;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Eastwood" date="unknown">caput-medusae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atriplex;species caput-medusae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">saccaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="unknown" date="unknown">caput-medusae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atriplex;species saccaria;variety caput-medusae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, erect, mainly 0.5–5 dm. Leaves all petiolate or distal ones subsessile,
        blade cordate-ovate or subreniform to oval or ovate, 10–30 × 10–25 mm, base cordate or some
        only broadly truncate or less commonly rather abruptly cuneate, margin entire or rarely
        slightly hastate. Staminate flowers in glomerules in distal axils and in terminal, deciduous
        panicles. Fruiting bracteoles dimorphic, those with subglobose body bearing flattened or
        cristate processes borne on stipes to 10+ mm, and those mainly lacking processes, cuneate in
        outline, and sessile.</description>
  <description type="habitat">mat-atriplex, shadscale, greasewood</description>
  <description type="habitat">and pinyon-juniper communities</description>
  <description type="habitat">on fine-textured saline substrates (often semibarren) of the bridger, duchesne river,
        mancos shale</description>
  <description type="habitat">dakota, morrison, entrada, and chinle formations</description>
  <description type="habitat">and on fine-textured alluvium</description>
  <description type="elevation">1100–2200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Colo.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Utah</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wyo.</description>
  <number>24a.</number>
  <discussion>The main center of diversity of the Atriplex saccaria complex is in the Four Corners
        region. Both leaf and bracteoles profiles are almost as variable within var. saccaria as for
        the species as a whole. Bracteoles vary from mainly cuneate and mostly lacking processes to
        almost all or indeed all of them stipitate and with either flattened or hornlike appendages.
        The main, but still tenuous, feature used to hold this assemblage together is leaf shape,
        which varies around a cordate profile, with extreme on the cordate side being clearly
        reniform, but with variations to oval, ovate, elliptic, and triangular also being present.
        The triangular ones are rather common in juvenile plants. Sometimes the most extreme
        bracteole condition, wherein the stipes are greatly elongate and the surfaces are completely
        covered with large, flattened processes (simulating var. cornuta), occurs on plants with the
        most exorbitant cordate-reniform leaves, but these extreme forms occur within populations
        that also bear partially subdued processes or none at all.</discussion>
  <discussion>There are specimens from along the San Juan River with decidedly triangular juvenile
        leaf blades, which otherwise produce bracteoles as within A. saccaria. They fit the original
        description of Atriplex caput-medusae. Miss Eastwood’s description of the fruiting bracts
        also clearly indicates an affinity with A. saccaria. Every degree of transition is present
        between plants with triangular leaves and those that are definitely cordate or reniform.
        There seems to be no substantial reason for recognition of additional taxa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
