<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>26.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Atriplex</genus_name><species_name>powellii</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>9: 114. 1874</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Powell’s orach</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Obione</genus_name><species_name>powellii</species_name><species_authority>(S. Watson) Ulbrich</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, dioecious or sometimes sparingly monoecious. Stems slender to stout, mainly 1–5(–7) dm, branching almost throughout; herbage pubescent with scurfy and arachnoid hairs. Leaves alternate, proximalmost on petioles (3–)5–30 mm, becoming subsessile or short petiolate distally; blade 3-veined, ovate to rhombic or orbiculate to elliptic, 0.4–5 × 0.2–3 cm, base rounded to cuneate, margin entire, apex acute to obtuse. Staminate flowers with calyx 4–5-lobed. Fruiting bracteoles sessile, ovate to oblong or broadly cuneate or pan-duriform, 1.5–5.5 × 1.5–5 mm, thick, united to apex, apex truncate to cuspidate or tridentate, surfaces with thickened processes or rarely smooth. Seeds greenish, yellowish, or brown, 0.9–2 mm; radicle superior. 2n = 18.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w North America.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves mostly conspicuously 3-veined, proximalmost with petioles 0.5–2.5(–3.5) cm, distalmost bracteate leaves typically short petiolate; fruiting bracteoles easi ly discerned at bract bases; plants mostly dioecious; from Alberta and Saskatchewan s to Utah and New Mexico</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves inconspicuously, if at all, 3-veined, proximalmost with petioles 0.5–1.5(–2) cm, distalmost bracteate leaves typically sessile; fruiting bracteoles apparent only by removing the subtending bract; plants evidently monoecious; localdistribution in se Utah</statement>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
