<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ventenat" date="unknown">chenopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Gaertner) S. L. Welsh" date="2001">obione</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="S. L. Welsh" date="2001">Covilleiae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>102: 425. 2001</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family chenopodiaceae;genus atriplex;subgenus obione;section Covilleiae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, monoecious or subdioecious, glabrate. Leaves without Kranz anatomy,
        alternate, petiolate; blade sharply triangular-hastate or less commonly some of them entire,
        with overall shape ovate to lanceolate or elliptic. Staminate flowers in axillary glomerules
        or in naked terminal spikes. Fruiting bracteoles sessile or stipitate, mostly 3-lobed,
        lateral lobes rounded, united only at base, the enclosed pistillate flower with calyx of
        (1–)3(–5) segments. Seeds: radicle superior.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: w United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>w United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>20b.5.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>The pattern of venation in this section is very similar to that of the closely
        comparable Atriplex phyllostegia, even though the veins lack the associated C4 arrangement
        of chlorenchyma cells surrounding the veins. The plants differ otherwise as noted in the
        descriptions. Placement of this species within the segregate genus Endolepis by various
        workers is based on two morphologic characteristics considered to be of fundamental
        importance, i.e., the lack of Kranz leaf anatomy and the presence of sepals subtending the
        ovary within the fruiting bracteoles. Sepals of staminate flowers lack the distinctive
        crests seen in A. [Endolepis] suckleyi, a feature on which the genus Endolepis was based.
        The placement of A. covillei within Endolepis, while convenient, does not take into account
        the overall similarity of this species to the evidently related A. phyllostegia. Neither
        does it take into account the potential for recurrence of sepals subtending the ovaries as
        possibly derived features.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
