<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ventenat" date="unknown">chenopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Pursh) Nuttall" date="1818">canescens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 197. 1818</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family chenopodiaceae;genus atriplex;species canescens</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Calligonum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Pursh" date="unknown">canescens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Amer Sept.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 370. 1814</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Calligonum;species canescens;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Atriplex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. Watson" date="unknown">nuttallii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Atriplex;species nuttallii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, dioecious or rarely monoecious, mainly 8–20 dm, as wide or wider, not
    especially armed. Leaves persistent, alternate, sessile or nearly so, blade linear to
    oblanceolate, oblong, or obovate, mainly 10–40 × 3–8 mm, margin entire, apex retuse to obtuse.
    Staminate flowers yellow (rarely brown), in clusters 2–3 mm wide, borne in panicles 3–15 cm.
    Pistillate flowers borne in panicles 5–40 cm. Fruiting bracteoles 8–25 mm, as wide, on stipes
    1–8 mm, with 4 prominent wings extending the bract length, united throughout, wings dentate to
    entire, apex toothed, surface of wings and body smooth or reticulate. Seeds 1.5–2.5 mm wide. 2n
    = 18, 36+.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <number>61.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Four-wing saltbu sh</other_name>
  <discussion>This species forms hybrids with Atriplex confertifolia and A. gardneri varieties (see var. bonnevillensis).  Materials from the vicinity of the type locality of the species in South Dakota are low subherbaceous plants that differ from our shrubby tall material.  However, the type area is presently covered with water from a dam on the Missouri River, and it is not possible to exclude the possibility of A. canescens as it has been interpreted for the past century to have existed at that site during the Lewis and Clark Expedition, if that is indeed where the lectotype was collected.</discussion>
  <discussion>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora)</discussion>
  <discussion>Nuttall’s new combination Atriplex canescens was based on Calligonum canescens Pursh.
    Watson based his new name A. nuttallii directly on A. canescens Nuttall, i.e., including the
    citation of Nuttall’s “Genera, 1. 197,” and on its basionym, C. canescens. The name A. nuttallii
    is thus a nomenclatural synonym of A. canescens and was thus illegitimate at its inception. It
    cannot be resurrected by even the most sophisticated arguments. A sheet of Atriplex canescens,
    noted as “a shrub,” taken by Nuttall on the 1810 Missouri River expedition is extant in the
    Lambert herbarium (PH). It bears several, obviously shrubby, staminate flowering branches, but
    the only pistillate branch is very immature. The name A. gardneri, also cited provisionally by
    Watson within the concept of A. nuttallii, clearly has priority over other names for that widely
    distributed species complex. Attempts at leptotypification of the name nuttallii by J. McNeill
    et al. (1983) and H. C. Stutz and S. C. Sanderson (1998) are both superfluous, the name being
    illegitimate.</discussion>
  <discussion>C. A. Hanson (1962) noted the similarity between the occasional wingless fruiting
    bracteoles of Atriplex canescens and A. gardneri var. falcata. He noted further that the bracts
    of both species lack lateral teeth subtending the terminal ones, have terminal teeth united half
    their length, and have indurate bracts. Whether such similarity indicates relationship or mere
    coincidence is open to question. However, A. canescens is known to form hybrids with most, if
    not all, portions of the gardneri complex and with other woody species whose range it overlaps
    as well.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Stutz, H. C. and S. C. Sanderson. 1979. The role of polyploidy in the evolution of
      Atriplex canescens. In: J. R. Goodin and D. K. Northington, eds. 1929. Arid Plant Resources….
      Lubbock. Pp. 615–621.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting bracteoles merely dentate to entire, commonly 8–25 mm wide; plants of
        broad or other distribution.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracteoles mainl y less than 12 mm wide; plants not layering in sand dunes,
        widespread</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracteoles mainly 15– mm wide; plants layering in sand dunes, cw Utah</description>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting bracteoles dentate to laciniate, mainly 5–10 mm wide; plants of s
        California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting bracteoles mainly 4–8 mm wide, dentate or laciniate; shrubs mainly 3–10
        dm</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting bracteoles mainly 8–11 mm wide, la-ciniate; shrubs mainly 10–20
        dm</description>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
