<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>23.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>SARCOCORNIA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Sarcocornia A. J. Scott</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>B ot. J. Linn. Soc.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>75: 366. 1978</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Samphire</common_name>
  <common_name>glasswort</common_name>
  <common_name>saltwort</common_name>
  <etymology>[Greek sarco , fleshy, and Latin cornis , horned, in reference to the appearance of the
    plants]</etymology>
  <author>Peter W. Ball</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Salicornia</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Perennes</section_name>
    <section_authority>Duval-Jouve ex Moss</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Bot. </publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>49: 178. 1911</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Shrubs, glabrous. Stems apparently jointed and fleshy when young, becoming woody and
    not jointed, not armed; some stems terminated by an inflorescences, others entirely vegetative.
    Leaves opposite, united at base, petiolate, decurrent forming fleshy joints (sterile segments)
    fleshy on stem, fleshy; eventually deciduous; blade fleshy triangular projections at tips of
    joints, edges with narrow scarious margins. Inflorescences terminal and lateral, spikelike,
    apparently jointed, each joint (fertile segment) consisting of 2 opposite, axillary,
    3(–5)-flowered cymes embedded in and adnate to fleshy tissue of distal internode; flowers in
    each cyme arranged in transverse rows, central flower separating lateral flowers, slightly
    larger; flowers in each cyme partially separated by flaps of tissue which persist on stem when
    flowers have fallen. Flowers bisexual or unisexual, ± radially symmetric; perianth segments
    persistent in fruit, 3–4, united except at tip, fleshy; stamens 1–2; styles 2–3. Fruits
    utriclelike, ellipsoid; pericarp membranous. Seeds vertical, ellipsoid; seed coat light brown,
    membranous, pubescent; hairs strongly curved or hooked and slender, or conic, straight or
    slightly curved; perisperm absent. x = 9.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 15 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>w Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mediterranean region</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>s</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Africa</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Australasia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Sarcocornia is taxonomically difficult and has never been the subject of a taxonomic
    revision for the Northern Hemisphere. Although it is possible to identify dry specimens to some
    extent, by comparison, it is impossible to obtain from dried specimens data that can be used in
    a taxonomic revision. Characters that may be taxonomically useful are lost on drying, especially
    flower and inflorescence characters and those derived from the fleshy vegetative segments. Habit
    appears to be useful, but few specimen labels note the habit of the living plant, and the parts
    collected rarely allow for a reliable determination of habit. Some species, such as S. perennis
    are prostrate, with the woody stems readily rooting in the substrate. Others such as S. pacifica
    are procumbent to erect shrubs in which the woody stems usually do not root. This apparently
    obvious habit difference is sometimes confounded by external factors, erect species becoming
    procumbent due to water movement, trampling, or burial by silt or sand deposits. Conversely,
    prostrate rooting species can be disturbed by erosion and appear to be procumbent plants of a
    nonrooting species.</discussion>
  <discussion>One of the most useful characters, the indumentum on the testa of the seeds, is rarely
    present in dried specimens because of the lateness of the plants’ flowering season. Plants
    collected in August and September rarely have even immature seeds present, so most herbarium
    specimens do not display this character.</discussion>
  <discussion>The consequence of these problems is that most accounts of Sarcocornia in North
    America recognize only one species, frequently using the name Salicornia virginica Linnaeus for
    the collective entity. The type specimens of S. virginica were collected by John Clayton,
    presumably from Virginia, which are immature annuals and not flowering. The name S. virginica
    cannot be applied to a species in this genus.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Seeds smooth except for conic, straight papillae on edge; papillae 0.6–0.9 mm;
        anthers</statement>
      <determination>3. Sarcocorn ia utahensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Seeds covered with slender, hooked or strongly curved hairs; hairs mostly 1–2 mm;
        anthers 0.7–1 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants with creeping, rooting, woody stems; erect stems simple or sparingly
        branched,</statement>
      <determination>1. Sarcocornia perennis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants with erect or procumbent woody stems, sometimes creeping and rooting at
        base; stems sparingly to much-branched, 10–50 cm; longest terminal spikes onplant
        with</statement>
      <determination>2. Sarcocornia pacifica</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
