<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Matthew H. Hils,John W. Thieret,James D. Morefield</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Chenopodiaceae Ventenat" date="unknown">CHENOPODIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Sarcobatus Nees" date="unknown">SARCOBATUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in M. P. zu Wied, Reise Nord-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 510. 1839</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CHENOPODIACEAE;genus SARCOBATUS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek sarco , flesh, and batos , bramble, alluding to the leaves and
    thorns]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey" date="unknown">Fremontia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Fremontia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, deciduous, monoecious, glabrous or pubescent. Stems erect, much-branched, not
    jointed, dimorphic, not fleshy; long shoots solitary, axillary, elongate, bearing leaves and
    axillary thorns; short shoots clustered, budlike, usually subtending thorns or lateral branches,
    bearing leaves; thorns 1(–2) per node. Leaves mostly alternate on long shoots (sometimes
    opposite proximally) or clustered (“tufted”) on short shoots, sessile, succulent; blade linear,
    nearly terete to somewhat flattened, margins entire, apex obtuse (mucronate). Inflorescences:
    pistillate flowers solitary or paired in axils of foliage leaves; staminate inflorescences
    distal to pistillate, terminal, pedunculate, cylindric spike of 10–40 spirally arranged flowers.
    Flowers unisexual, ebracteolate; pistillate sessile (sometimes short-pedunculate in fruit);
    “perianth” accrescent, adnate, cuplike, margins subentire to shallowly lobed, flaring to form
    wing in fruit; stigmas 2; staminate flowers: perianth absent; anthers caducous, (1–)2–4(–5),
    almost sessile, arising from spike axis and around stalk of persistent, overtopping and
    concealing, eccentrically peltate, rhombic, scarious scale. Fruiting structures: fruits achenes,
    proximal portion below wing turbinate, enlarging less than distal portion; distal portion above
    wing conic; wing sometimes red-tinged, veiny, broad, margins shallowly to deeply lobed,
    undulate, crenulate to erose. Seeds vertical, flattened, orbiculate; seed coat transparent,
    membranous; perisperm absent. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">including nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>24.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Sarcobatus was considered monotypic until F. V. Coville published a second species,
    from western Nevada. The following features have been used (with variable success) to separate
    the taxa: stature, bark color, leaf length and vestiture, fruit dimensions and vestiture, length
    of staminate spikes, and number of pistillate flowers per flowering branch. Sarcobatus baileyi
    has been treated as a species by some, as S. vermiculatus var. baileyi (Coville) Jepson by
    others, as an unnamed form, and as a taxon not worthy of recognition. Further study may resolve
    its status; we prefer to maintain the specific rank originally assigned to it.</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of Sarcobatus are divaricating shrubs, with elongate lateral branches and
    thorns extending from the main stems at more-or-less right angles, resulting in a tangle of
    branches and thorns in mature individuals. In addition to elongate lateral branches, they also
    have short budlike shoots, often clustered into a “cushionlike” structure, that subtend these
    elongate lateral branches or thorns (i.e., in the position of leaf scars). One key difference
    between the species is the abundance and behavior of these short shoots and how they produce
    additional lateral leafy and flowering branches.</discussion>
  <discussion>The two species of Sarcobatus can grow together and may intergrade. Many equivocal
    specimens can be identified as either somewhat depauperate S. vermiculatus or somewhat robust S.
    baileyi, both apparently resulting from intermediate soil-moisture conditions or possibly as a
    response to infestation by fungi or arthropods. Other specimens are problematical, combining in
    various degrees the features allegedly defining the two taxa. Assigning such specimens to either
    of the taxa requires a certain amount of arbitrariness; some specimens we cannot determine with
    certainty. Collectors should record notes on habit, height, and foliage color; photographs of
    the plants may be helpful. Occasional individuals may be F1 hybrids, being intermediate in
    morphology, having malformed leaves and inflorescences, and appearing to be
    sterile.</discussion>
  <discussion>We have seen a few equivocal specimens of Sarcobatus that look disfigured and show
    numerous, large, dense, short shoots with numerous leaves, giving the appearance of
    witches’-broom disease. These short shoots, although resembling those of S. baileyi, are unlike
    those of either species because they are much larger and possess many more leaves than occur on
    typical short shoots. In addition, the long shoots on these anomalous specimens are like those
    characteristic of S. vermiculatus.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Baillon, H. E. 1887. Développement de la fleur femelle du
      Sarcobatus. Bull. Mens. Soc. Linn. Paris 1: 649.</reference>
    <reference>Behnke, H.-D. 1997. Sarcobataceae—a new
      family of Caryophyllales. Taxon 46: 495–507.</reference>
    <reference>Carlquist, S. 2000b. Wood and stem anatomy of Sarcobatus (Caryophyllales):
      Systematic and ecological implications. Taxon 49: 27–34.</reference>
    <reference>Sanderson, S. C., H. C. Stutz, M. Stutz, and R. C. Roos. 1999. Chromosome races
      in Sarcobatus (Sarcobataceae, Caryophyllales). Great Basin Naturalist 59: 301–314.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually glabrous, or slightly pubescent, bright green to yellowish
        green in life, (0.3–)1.5–4(–5) cm; leaves mostly solitary on elongate shoots of current sea
        son; pistillate flowers and staminate spikes on long lateral branches with 3–9 readily
        visible internodes; staminate spikes at maturity usually 11–40 mm; widespread in w North
        America</description>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bl ades usually pubescent, dull green to grayish green in life, (0.5–)1–1.6
        cm; leaves mostly clustered on cushionlike base on older wood; pistillate flowers and
        staminate spikes on short branches with 1–3 barely discernible internodes; staminate spikes
        at ma turity usu-ally to 10 mm; Nevada</description>
      <determination>2. Sarcobatus baileyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
