<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Ventenat" date="unknown">chenopodiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Forsskål ex J. F. Gmelin" date="unknown">suaeda</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Iljin" date="1936">Limbogermen</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sovetsk. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 47. 1936</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family chenopodiaceae;genus suaeda;section Limbogermen</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, subshrubs, or facultative annuals, glabrous or with scattered trichomes to sparsely hirtellous, puberulent, tomentulose, or villous. Leaves sessile or short-petiolate, cross section with dark-green ring of chlorenchyma just inside epidermis (best seen at 10× or greater magnification). Inflorescences glomes, each glome in axis of one leaflike bract or bractless; bracteoles subtending glomes often with scattered marginal hairs. Flowers bisexual or, sometimes, pistillate; perianth actinomorphic, globose to oblong; perianth segments connate proximally or to middle, abaxially rounded, sometimes distally hooded, without appendages, succulent, apex acute to obtuse; ovary lanceoloid to ovoid or often ± vase-shaped with distal necklike extension; stigmas (2–)3, arising from pit at apex of ovary or from pit on distal necklike extension of ovary, subsessile or on short style, filiform to lanceolate, pilose-papillate. Seeds horizontal or vertical, not distinctly dimorphic, sometimes variable in size and color, lenticular; seed coat black or brown, shiny, usually finely reticulate (seen at 40× magnification), sometimes smooth.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <number>25c.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 10 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts m ostly equaling proximal leaves; inflorescences distributed throughout plant; stems knobby.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or vestiture sparse; leaves usually not glaucous; ovary without obviousdistal necklike extension</description>
      <determination>8. Suaeda californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems sometimes glabrous or vestiture usually dense; leaves glaucous; ovary with distalnecklike extension</description>
      <determination>9. Suaeda taxifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts mostly shorter than proximal leaves; inflorescences mostly on distal branches; stems sm ooth or knobby.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf scars on stems ± smooth; inflorescence branches mostly thinner than vegetativebranches; widespread, including Texas 10. S uaeda nigra</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf scars on stems ± knobby; inflorescence branches as thick as vegetat ive branches; Texas.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems decumbent to erect, densely tomentulose; leaf apices acuminate to apiculate</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems prostrate to decumbent, glabrous; leaf apices rounded</description>
      <determination>12. Suaeda conferta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
