<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Kenneth R. Robertson,Steven E. Clemants</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">AMARANTHACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family AMARANTHACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, rarely subshrubs, annual or perennial; trichomes simple (branched in Tidestromia). Stems without nodal spines (Amaranthus spinosus sometimes with paired nodal spines). Leaves alternate or opposite, exstipulate, usually petiolate; blade margins entire (entire or serrulate in Iresine; entire, crispate, or erose in Amaranthus). Inflorescences cymules arranged in spikes, panicles, thyrses, heads, glomerules, clusters, or racemes; each flower subtended by 1 bract and 2 bracteoles (latter sometimes 1 or absent in Amaranthus). Flowers bisexual or unisexual (plants then monoecious or dioecious), hypogynous, generally small or minute; tepals mostly (1–)4–5 or absent, distinct or connate into cups or tubes, scarious, chartaceous, membranaceous, or indurate; stamens 2–5, filaments basally connate into cups or tubes, rarely distinct, alternating with pseudostaminodes (appendages on staminal tubes) or not, anthers 2-locular with 1 line of dehiscence or 4-locular with 2 lines of dehiscence; ovary superior, 1-locular; ovules 1 or, rarely, 2–many; style 1 or absent; stigmas 1–3(–5). Fruits utricles, dry, dehiscent or not. Seeds black, reddish brown, or brown, lenticular, subglobose or globose (rarely cylindric), usually small; embryo peripheral, surrounding mealy perisperm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide</description>
  <description type="distribution">most abundant in tropics</description>
  <description type="distribution">subtropics</description>
  <description type="distribution">and warm-temperate regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">evidently absent from alpine and arctic regions.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Genera ca. 65, species ca. 900 (12 genera, 80 species in the flora): nearly worldwide, most abundant in tropics, subtropics, and warm-temperate regions, evidently absent from alpine and arctic regions.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Genera ca. 65, species ca. 900 (12 genera, 80 species in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>nearly worldwide, most abundant in tropics, subtropics, and warm-temperate regions, evidently absent from alpine and arctic regions.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>39.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Amaranth Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 65, species ca. 900 (12 genera, 80 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Centers of diversity for Amaranthaceae are southwestern North America, Central America, South America, and Africa south of the Sahara Desert. Generic limits are not well defined in some groups; fewer than 60 or more than 70 genera could be recognized.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some species occur in severe habitats such as sandy, calcareous, gypseous, saline, or serpentine soils in deserts, semideserts, and seashores. Some species are weedy, including the major agricultural weeds in Amaranthus. Some species are cultivated as ornamentals, particularly Amaranthus caudatus (love-lies-bleeding), A. hypochondriacus (prince’s-feather), A. tricolor (Joseph’s-coat), Celosia cristata (cockscomb), and Gomphrena globosa (globe-amaranth). Native Americans domesticated white-seeded grain amaranths (A. caudatus, A. cruentus, and A. hypochondriacus) for use as cereal grains. Some species of Amaranthus and Celosia are potherbs.</discussion>
  <discussion>Amaranthaceae are usually divided into subfamilies Amaranthoideae (anthers 4-locular with two lines of dehiscence) and Gomphrenoideae Schinz (anthers 2-locular with one line of dehiscence). Amaranthaceae and Chenopodiaceae have long been recognized as allied families that share a number of features: generally small flowers, one perianth whorl, a syncarpous gynoecium with a superior ovary and often only one ovule, basal or free-central placentation, pollen characteristics, centrospermous embryo development, betalain pigments, and P-type form (c) sieve-element plastids.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Carolin, R. C. 1983. The trichomes of the Chenopodiaceae and Amaranthaceae. Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 103: 451–466.</reference>
    <reference>Eliasson, U. H. 1988. Floral morphology and taxonomic relations among the genera of Amaranthaceae in the New World and the Hawaiian Islands. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 96: 235–283.</reference>
    <reference>Robertson, K. R. 1981. The genera of Amaranthaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 62: 267–314.</reference>
    <reference>Standley, P. C. 1915. The North American tribes and genera of Amaranthaceae. J. Wash. Acad. Sci. 5: 391–396.</reference>
    <reference>Standley, P. C. 1917b. Amaranthaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora…. 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 21, pp. 95–169.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal leaves alternate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers unisexual (plants monoecious or dioecious); utricles 1-seeded.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Shrubs</description>
      <determination>11. ### Iresine (in part), p. 454</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual, rarely perennial</description>
      <determination>3. Amaranthus , p. 410</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2 .</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers bisexual; utricles 2+-seeded.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades mostly lanceolate, ovate, or deltate; pseudostaminodes absent</description>
      <determination>1. Celosia , p. 407</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades linear; pseudostaminodes alternating with filaments on staminal tubes</description>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">D istal leaves opposite.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers unisexual (plants dioecious); inflorescences terminal, diffuse, open panicles</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers bisexual; inflorescences terminal and/or axillary glomerules, heads, or spikes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences s essile glomerules or condensed spikes, axillary.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences several-flowered, axillary spikes; pseudostaminodes present</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences 1–20-flowered, axillary glomerules; pseudostaminodes present or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Indumentum of branched or barbed trichomes, densely covering plant (rarelyglabrous); pseudostaminoides present</description>
      <determination>7. Tidestromia , p. 439</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Indumentum of simple trichomes; pseudostaminoides absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals connate proximally, tips 1-veined; filamenttubes inserted distally on perianth tubes; basal rosette leaves usually absent at anthesis</description>
      <next_statement_id>9. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals distinct, 3-veined; filament tubes ± free from tepals; basal rosetteleaves present at anthesis</description>
      <determination>6. Gossypianthus , p. 438</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences pedunculate heads or spikes, terminal and sometimes axillary near stem tips.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences simple or compound spikes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences mostly compound, interrupted spikes; tepals connate intoindurate tubes with lateral crests or s pines, lanate</description>
      <determination>8. Froelichia , p. 443</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences simple spikes or few-branched panicles, flowers progressively farther apart below; tepals basally connate into indurate tubes,without ornamentation, ± glabrous</description>
      <determination>4. Achyranthes , p. 435</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflore scences globose or cylindric heads or spikes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences not immediately subtended by leaves</description>
      <determination>9. ### Alternanthera (in part), p. 447</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences immediately subtended by 2 or more leaves.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves fleshy, sessile; blade linear to narrowly obovate, glabrous exceptin axils</description>
      <determination>12. Blutaparon , p. 456</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not fleshy, petiolate or sessile; blade ovate to obovate,pilose at least abaxially</description>
      <determination>10. Gomphrena , p. 451</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
