<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">AMARANTHACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Amaranthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="J. D. Sauer" date="unknown">acanthochiton</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 44. 1955</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family AMARANTHACEAE;genus Amaranthus;species acanthochiton;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Acanthochiton</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey" date="unknown">wrightii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in L. Sitgreaves, Rep. Exped. Zuni Colorado Rivers,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>170, plate 13. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Acanthochiton;species wrightii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>9.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Gree nstripe</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">greenstripe amaranth</other_name>
  <discussion>Amaranthus acanthochiton is very different morphologically from other taxa of dioecious amaranths. In its vegetative and floral morphology, it is similar to the monoecious A. fimbriatus, especially in branching habit, narrow linear to linear-lanceolate leaf blade, and broadly spatulate to almost fan-shaped tepals of the pistillate flowers. These species are also similar phytogeographically, occurring within the southwestern part of the United States and neighboring northern Mexico. The “dioecious amaranths” are an artificial and polyphyletic group consisting of at least two (or three) independently evolved lineages roughly corresponding to the sections of subg. Acnida outlined by S. L. Mosyakin and K. R. Robertson (1996).</discussion>
  <discussion>Amaranthus acanthochiton is critically imperiled in Utah and imperiled in Arizona; its Global Heritage Status Rank is G5 as defined by The Nature Conservancy. Seeds and young leaves of A. acanthochiton were used by Native Americans (Hopi) as food: the seeds cooked as a kind of porridge, and the leaves cooked and eaten as greens or with meat (D. E. Moerman 1998).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
