<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">amaranthaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">amaranthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">tricolor</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 989. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family amaranthaceae;genus amaranthus;species tricolor</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual, glabrous. Stems erect, often branched, 0.8–1.5 m. Leaves: petiole 1/2 as long as blade; blade ovate, elliptic, rhombic, or lanceolate, mostly 4–12 × 1.4–6 cm, base tapering, margins entire, usually undulate, apex acuminate and short-mucronate; distal leaf blades green, red, scarlet, maroon, purple, yellow, and cream (unique to A. tricolor). Inflorescences axillary glomerules. Bracts of pistillate flowers ovate to lanceolate, 5–6 mm. Pistillate flowers: tepals 3, narrowly ovate to lanceolate, 5–6 mm, apex aristate; style branches spreading; stigmas 2–3. Staminate flowers intermixed with pistillate; tepals 3; stamens 3. Utricles ovoid, 2–2.5 mm, rugose, dehiscence regularly circumscissile. Seeds black or brownish black, subglobose, 1 mm diam., shiny.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer-fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Locally escaped from cultivation, disturbed areas;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; La., Mich., Mo.; native in tropical Asia.</description>
  <number>34.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Joseph’s coat</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">summer poinsettia</other_name>
  <discussion>Amaranthus tricolor is widely cultivated as a garden plant for its showy, often variegated, distal leaves of striking colors—red, scarlet, maroon, purple, yellow, cream, and green. Other cultivated varieties with green leaves are sometimes cultivated as a potherb. Escaped plants sometimes occur near places of cultivation; we have no evidence of widespread establishment.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
