<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ross A. McCauley</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">AMARANTHACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Moench" date="unknown">FROELICHIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Methodus,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>50. 1794</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family AMARANTHACEAE;genus FROELICHIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Joseph Aloys von Froelich, 1766–1841, German physician and botanist who published on Sonchus , Hieracium , and Gentiana ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Cottonweed</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">snake-cotton</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 16 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Froelichia is most abundant in the Sonoran and Chihuahuan deserts, the plains of southern Texas and Florida in North America, and the grasslands of South America, particularly eastern Paraguay and southern Brazil. Two species (F. lanigera Andersson, F. nudicaulis Hooker f.) are endemic to the Galápagos Islands.</discussion>
  <discussion>Froelichia is divided into sect. Hoplotheca (Nuttall) Moquin-Tandon, with stigmas interpreted as being capitate (the capitate form is derived from a bifid structure), and sect. Dilopha Moquin-Tandon, with penicillate stigmas. Section Dilopha is restricted to South America; sect. Hoplotheca to North America and South America.</discussion>
  <discussion>Evolutionarily there are two principle clades occuring across North America. One clade comprises the perennial Froelichia interrupta comprised of three varieties occuring south through most of Mexico to Nicaragua. Morphologically the group is distinguished by plants with relatively sparsely flowered inflorescences with the flowers arranged in a 3-ranked spriral. The pseudostaminodes are short and exhibit a blunt apex. The second clade occurs to the north and comprises a mix of annual and perennial species, including the taxa described here and F. “xantusii” R. A. McCauley, which is endemic to southern Baja California.</discussion>
  <discussion>Froelichia is probably best known as a roadside weed because it thrives in occasionally disturbed environments with little competition. It is also a common member of coastal pine areas, particularly along the Gulf Coast. The plants are pioneers in disturbed sandy soils, can become agricultural pests in rare instances, and form large patches in fallow fields or pastures. Introduction of Froelichia has occurred throughout much of the United States (F. gracilis); F. floridana is naturalized in Queensland, Australia, most likely from contaminated seed in the mid-1950s.</discussion>
  <discussion>Confusion in the identity of Froelichia species has been due in large part to the over-reliance on variable characters, principally the nature of the lateral wings on the mature perianth. Recent revisionary work (R. A. McCauley 2002) has served to identify more stable characters for identification and has led to recircumscriptions of the geographic ranges of the species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kolli, S. 1967. Biochemical and Floral Anatomical Studies in the Genus Froelichia (Amaranthaceae). Ph.D. thesis. Catholic University of America. McCauley, R. A. 2002. Systematics of the genus Froelichia in North America (Amaranthaceae subfamily Gomphrenoideae). Ph.D. thesis. Ohio University.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; taproots woody.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades (at least the distal ones) ovate-orbiculate or short-lanceolate, pubescence grayish white; pubescence of mature flowers sparse, dull; fruiting perianth with narrow or broad, entire or crenulate lateral wings; face of perianth tube on each side with orwithout 1 basal tubercle or spine; flowers 3–4.6 mm; s Texas</description>
      <determination>1. Froelichia texana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades lanceolate, pubescence bright white; pu bescence of tepals of mature flowers dense, bright white; fruiting perianth with irregularly dentate lateral wings; faces of perianth tube on each side with 1 or more basal tubercles or spines; flowers (3.5–)4–</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.5 mm; s</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.5 mm; s</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Arizona, s New Mexico, w Texas</description>
      <determination>2. Froelichia arizonica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants annual or short-lived perennial; taproots semiwoody.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched from base (rarely with only 1 slender stalk in depauperate specimens); floral spikes 3-ranked; bracteoles glabrous, not pubescent distally; stem pubescence grayish white; fruiting perianth slightly oblique apically, with irregularly and deeplycut (“spiny”) lateral wings; flowers 2.4–3.8 mm</description>
      <determination>3. Froelichia gracilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with 1 or more erect to decumbent branches from ground level; floral spikes 5-ra nked; bracteoles sparsely or densely pubescent distally; stem pubescence grayish white to brownish; fruiting perianth symmetric, with irregularly dentate to crenulate lateral wings; flowers 3.5–6 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4. ###</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pseudostaminodes blunt, brown tinted (often observedas darkened flower tips), usually not recurved; bracteoles sparsely hairy distally; flowers 3.5–5.4 mm; sc</description>
      <determination>4. Froelichia drummondii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4. ###</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pseudostaminodes acute, greenish white or pinkish, usually recurved; bracteoleswith small tufts of pubescenc e distally; flowers 4–6 mm; widespread</description>
      <determination>5. Froelichia floridana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
