<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">AMARANTHACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Froelichia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="J. M. Coulter &amp; Fisher" date="unknown">texana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 350. 1892</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family AMARANTHACEAE;genus Froelichia;species texana;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Froelichia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Moquin-Tandon" date="unknown">interrupta</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Uline &amp; W. L. Bray" date="unknown">cordata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Froelichia;species interrupta;variety cordata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Texas snake-cotton</other_name>
  <discussion>Froelichia texana has been a relatively obscure taxon and has either been included within a broadly defined F. floridana or within F. interrupta (Linnaeus) Moquin-Tandon, a wide-ranging and morphologically variable species extending from northern Mexico to Peru. Similarities in overall growth form and the lack of divisions on the lateral wings of the mature perianth led to the long inclusion of this species within F. interrupta, although more detailed analysis points to a closer phylogenetic relationship between F. texana and F. floridana.</discussion>
  <discussion>Froelichia interrupta has been reported to occur within the range of the flora; however, most of those records are, in fact, F. texana or misidentified F. arizonica. While I have seen no records definitively placing F. interrupta in the flora, I suspect it could occur as I have observed F. interrupta growing at higher elevations in northern Sonora. A suspected specimen of F. interrupta would key to F. texana, but differ by having a 3-ranked inflorescence and the fruiting perianth would always lack a basal tubercle or spine.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
