<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">nyctaginaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">mirabilis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(L’Heritier ex Willdenow) Heimerl in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="unknown">Oxybaphus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl, Nat.
                Pflanzenfam.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>31[III,1b]: 24. 1889</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family nyctaginaceae;genus mirabilis;section Oxybaphus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="L’Heritier ex Willdenow" date="unknown">Oxybaphus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(1): 170, 185. 1797</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>section Oxybaphus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from cylindric, cordlike or thick and woody roots. Stems erect to
        decumbent, sparsely to densely leafy primarily in proximal 2/3 or throughout. Leaves: basal
        leaves petiolate, blade proportionately broader; distal leaves sessile or subsessile, blade
        narrower, margins entire to crisped. Inflorescences axillary and terminal in open or
        congested, few or repeatedly branched cymes (single in axils, especially in cleistogamous
        phases); involucres usually notably accrescent, becoming tan, translucent, prominently
        net-veined, broadly bell-shaped to saucer-shaped, with (1–)3 flowers inserted at base.
        Flowers: perianth broadly funnelform, abruptly flared from narrow tubes, deeply 5-lobed;
        stamens 3–5. Fruits with 5 low ribs, obovoid or narrowly obovate and tapering at both ends,
        base prominently constricted, apex rounded to nipplelike, surface of fruit slightly rugose
        to prominently tuberculate on ribs and/or sulci (or ribs and/or sulci without tubercles),
        glabrous or pubescent, mucilaginous when wetted.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <number>7e.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">Eu-Oxybaphus</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 25 (10 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Mirabilis sect. Oxybaphus is most diverse in the warm, semiarid regions of North
        America. Of all the subgroups (i.e., genera in P. C. Standley 1918) within a broadly
        constructed Mirabilis, sect. Oxybaphus has been the last to be maintained at the generic
        level by some authors of regional floras. The markedly accrescent involucres of most species
        make members of the section easily recognized. Standley (1931), in making transfers from
        Allionia and Oxybaphus to Mirabilis, noted that characteristics supposedly distinctive
        between segregate genera are not so in South America. C. F. Reed (1969) also used this
        justification for an inclusive Mirabilis in a treatment of Texas species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Taxonomy at the species level within the section is unusually problematic. In the
        introduction to his treatment for Mirabilis, L. H. Shinners (1951b) expressed biological and
        nomen-clatural problems that plague satisfactory classification. R. W. Cruden (1973) showed
        cleistogamic and chasmogamic flowers in M. nyctaginea, and self-compatibility in chasmogamic
        flowers, and R. Spellenberg (1998) mentioned other biological attributes that probably
        contribute to difficulties. The floral mechanism that Cruden described for M. nyctaginea
        (stamens and style curling together as the flowers close in late morning) is found in all
        species and ensures self-pollination. Cleistogamic flowers are found in many other species.
        Chasmogamic flowers are attractive in some species and are visited by various strong-flying
        pollinators, among them bees and hummingbirds. B. L. Turner (1993b) used the argument of
        cleistogamy and hybridization, combined with phenotypic plasticity, to support his concept
        of a widespread and variable M. albida. Ultimately, some species complexes in the section
        may be treated more satisfactorily with a number of broadly distributed and variable
        species, each consisting of a number of infraspecific taxa.</discussion>
  <discussion>Each species in this section intergrades in some respect with one or more others.
        Populations of these intergradient types are often highly uniform within. Here, insofar as
        practicable, species are recognized on combinations of characters that occur within some
        reasonably extensive geographic region and/or are found in populations that occur in certain
        rather well-defined ecological situations. Areas of difficult variation are the mountains of
        the south-western United States and the eastern base of the Rocky Mountains.</discussion>
  <discussion>Measurements for leaves in the following descriptions are for leaves from mid-stem
        area. Leaves located toward the base are commonly proportionately broader and on longer
        petioles; those near and in the inflorescence are proportionately narrower and have much
        shorter petioles or are sessile.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
