<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Lewisia</genus_name><species_name>leeana</species_name><species_authority>(Porter) B. L. Robinson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in A. Gray et al., Syn. Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 269. 1897</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><past_name>leana</past_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Calandrinia</genus_name><species_name>leeana</species_name><species_authority>Porter</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bot. Bull. (Hanover) </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 49. 1876 (as leana)</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lewisia</genus_name><species_name>eastwoodiana</species_name><species_authority>Purdy</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Oreobroma</genus_name><species_name>leeanum</species_name><species_authority>(Porter) Howell</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Taproots gradually ramified distally. Stems spreading or suberect, 8–20 cm. Leaves: basal leaves evergreen, sessile, blade linear, ± terete, 1.5–6 cm, margins entire, apex obtuse; cauline leaves alternate, intergrading with bracts, blade narrowly lanceolate, 5 mm, margins entire, apex acute. Inflorescences paniculate cymes, 50–70(–100)-flowered; bracts several, alternate proximally, 2 at each flowering node distally, ovate to narrowly lanceolate, 2–5 mm, margins glandular-toothed, apex acute. Flowers pedicellate, not disarticulate in fruit; sepals 2, suborbiculate, 1–4 mm, herbaceous at anthesis, margins glandular-toothed, apex truncate; petals 5–8, magenta, lavender, or white with or without magenta veins, obovate, 5–7 mm; stamens 4–8; stigmas 2; pedicel 3–15 mm. Capsules 4–5 mm. Seeds 1–2, 2–2.5 mm, shiny, smooth. 2n = 14.</description><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>open north- or northwest-facing granitic or serpentine slopes or cliffs</habitat><elevation>1300–3400 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><discussion>Lewisia leeana is known only from northwestern California and southwesternmost Oregon, and a disjunct population in Fresno County, California. As discussed by B. Mathew (1989b), Lewisia ×whiteae Purdy (California) is a natural, constantly recurring hybrid between L. leeana and L. cotyledon. In their narrowly spatulate leaves, the hybrids resemble L. columbiana out of range (cf. L. T. Dempster 1993); the flowers are reportedly more deeply colored.</discussion></treatment>
