<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>12.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Lewisia</genus_name><species_name>oppositifolia</species_name><species_authority>(S. Watson) B. L. Robinson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in A. Gray et al., Syn. Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 268. 1897</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Calandrinia</genus_name><species_name>oppositifolia</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts </publication_title><place_in_publication>20: 355. 1885</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Oreobroma</genus_name><species_name>oppositifolium</species_name><species_authority>(S. Watson) Howell</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Taproots gradually ramified distally. Stems erect, basal nodes underground, 10–20(–25) cm. Leaves: basal leaves withering at or soon after anthesis, abruptly narrowed into broad petiole, blade linear-spatulate to linear-oblanceolate, flattened, 4–11 cm, margins entire, apex obtuse to subacute; cauline leaves opposite, in 1–3 pairs near stem base, smaller than and similar to basal leaves. Inflorescences racemose to subumbellate cymes, (1–)2–5(–6)-flowered; bracts alternate proximally, 1–many at each flowering node distally, lanceolate, 4–8 mm, margins entire or toothed at apex, apex acute to acuminate. Flowers pedicellate, not disarticulate in fruit; sepals 2, suborbiculate, 4–8(–10) mm, herbaceous at anthesis, margins coarsely toothed but not glandular, apex obtuse to rounded; petals 8–11, pink fading to white, oblanceolate to obovate, 9–15 mm; stamens 8–18; stigmas 3–5; pedicel 20–75 mm. Capsules 5–6 mm. Seeds 5–15, 1–1.8 mm, shiny, smooth.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><habitat>decomposed serpentine substrates</habitat><elevation>300–1300 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><discussion>Lewisia oppositifolia is known only from Del Norte County, California, and Josephine County, Oregon.</discussion><discussion>The floral symmetry of Lewisia oppositifolia may be somewhat elliptical, the outer two petals alternating with the sepals and the remaining petals imbricate and opposite the sepals, giving the flowers a pinched appearance, a feature also reported for L. nevadensis. The more diminutive, higher-elevation plants of L. oppositifolia possibly represent a distinct taxon that has been informally recognized as “Lewisia richeyi” (B. Mathew 1989b).</discussion></treatment>
