<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Lauren Raz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">DIOSCOREACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family DIOSCOREACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>228.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Yam Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera (3–)7(–more than 20), species ca. 650 (1 genus, 6 species in the flora; 4 species introduced):</discussion>
  <discussion>Circumscription of the Dioscoreaceae remains controversial. A strict interpretation of the family, adhering to the original taxonomic concept of R. Brown, would include only Dioscorea Linnaeus (ca. 600 species), Tamus Linnaeus (5 species, Mediterranean), and Rajania Linnaeus (25 species, West Indies); recent systematic studies by L. R. Caddick et al. (2000) portray Dioscorea as subsuming the latter two genera. In its broad sense (I. H. Burkill 1960; L. R. Caddick et al. 2000; R. Knuth 1924), the family includes the bisexual genera Avetra H. Perrier (1 species, Madagascar), Trichopus Gaertner (1 species, Indo-Malaysia), and Stenomeris Planchon (2 species, Malaysia), each of which has also been recognized at the family level (R. M. T. Dahlgren et al. 1985; J. Hutchinson 1973; A. L. Takhtajan 1997). Tacca J. R. Forster &amp; G. Forster (10 species, Malaysia; Taccaceae) is closely allied with Avetra and Trichopus, (L. R. Caddick et al. 2000) and the broadest interpretation of the Dioscoreaceae (adopted here) includes Tacca as well. Only Dioscorea is represented in the flora.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Shehbaz, I. A. and B. G. Schubert. 1989. The Dioscoreaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 70: 57–95.  </reference>
    <reference>Ayensu, E. S. 1972. Dioscoreales. In: C. R. Metcalfe, ed. 1960+. Anatomy of the Monocotyledons. 8+ vols. Oxford. Vol. 6.  </reference>
    <reference>Bouman, F. 1995. Seed structure and systematics in Dioscoreales. In: P. J. Rudall et al., eds. 1995. Monocotyledons: Systematics and Evolution. 2 vols. Kew. Vol. 1, pp. 139–156.  </reference>
    <reference>Burkill, I. H. 1960. The organography and evolution of the Dioscoreaceae, the family of yams. J. Linn. Soc., Bot. 56: 319–407.  </reference>
    <reference>Caddick, L. R. et al. 1998. Microsporogenesis and pollen morphology in Dioscoreales and allied taxa. Grana 37: 321–336.  </reference>
    <reference>Caddick, L. R. et al. 2000. Yams and their allies: Systematics of Dioscoreales. In: K. L. Wilson and D. A. Morrison, eds. 2000. Monocots: Systematics and Evolution. Melbourne. Pp. 475–487.  </reference>
    <reference>Coursey, D. G. 1967. Yams: An Account of the Nature, Origins, Cultivation and Utilisation of the Useful Members of the Dioscoreaceae. London.  </reference>
    <reference>Huber, H. 1998. Dioscoreaceae. In: K. Kubitzky et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 4+ vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 3, pp. 216–235.  </reference>
    <reference>Knuth, R. 1924. Dioscoreaceae. In: H. G. A. Engler, ed. 1900–1953. Das Pflanzenreich…. 107 vols. Berlin. Vol. 87 [IV,43], pp. 1–387.  </reference>
    <reference>Queva, C. 1894. Recherches sur l’Anatomie de l’Appareil Vegetatif des Taccacées &amp; Dioscorées. Lille.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
