<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">DIOSCOREACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">DIOSCOREA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1032. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 456. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family DIOSCOREACEAE;genus DIOSCOREA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Dioscorides, ca. 40–90, Greek physician, author of De Materia Medica ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Yam</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">ñame</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 600 (6 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The most comprehensive treatment to date (R. Knuth 1924) divides Dioscorea into 60+ sections. The native North American species are assigned to sect. Macropoda Uline: stems twining counter-clockwise, staminate flowers aggregated into more or less sessile cymes and with six fertile stamens, tepals united only at the base, and capsules as broad as or broader than long, reflexed at maturity, with seeds winged all around. This section also includes disjunct species from the Balkan Peninsula, the Himalayas, temperate East Asia, and the Caucasus Mountains.</discussion>
  <discussion>The taxonomy of Dioscorea is notoriously problematic. Many of the species are poorly known, and in the absence of comparative studies there has been an unchecked proliferation of names in the genus. That Dioscorea exhibits considerable diversity across its expansive geographic range is not contested, but a great many of the names in current use are very narrowly applied and lack any corroboration from field, laboratory, or herbarium studies. At present there is also no phylogenetic framework from which to interpret the variation that has been documented. Segregate genera have been erected, only to be subsumed again. A robust classification will ultimately emerge from rigorous systematic investigation, now in progress at research institutions around the world (L. R. Caddick et al. 2000; H. Huber 1998; P. Wilkin 1999; C. C. Xifreda 2000).</discussion>
  <discussion>Dioscorea species are cultivated circumtropically, especially in West Africa and the West Indies, for their starchy tubers (yams), the cultivars having been derived from about ten species, including three of the four taxa naturalized in the flora. The rhizomes/tubers of many noncomestible species accumulate varying concentrations of steroidal saponins (F. W. Martin 1969), and Dioscorea species of Mexican, South African, and Asian origin have been utilized extensively in the industrial synthesis of cortisone and human sex hormones. Much lower saponin yields are obtained from the native North American species than from the species harvested commercially elsewhere. Saponin content varies as a function of plant age and time of harvest, as well as phylogenetic position (L. Degras 1993). The rhizomes of D. villosa are included in some Native American pharmacopeias and are used to ease the pain of childbirth (H. H. Smith 1928). An alcohol extract of the “root” was widely administered in nineteenth- century eclectic medicine as a remedy for colic (H. H. Bartlett 1910).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bartlett, H. H. 1910. The source of the drug Dioscorea, with a consideration of the Dioscoreae found in the United States. U.S.D.A. Bur. Pl. Industr. Bull. 189: 1–29.</reference>
    <reference>Degras, L. 1993. The Yam: A Tropical Root Crop. London, New York, and Wageningen. Martin, F. W. 1969. The species of Dioscorea containing sapogenin. Econ. Bot. 23: 373–379.</reference>
    <reference>Wilkin, P. 1999. A revision of the compound-leaved yams of Africa. Kew Bull. 54: 19–39.</reference>
    <reference>Xifreda, C. C. 2000. Evaluation of pollen and vegetative characters in the systematics of South American species of Dioscorea (Dioscoreaceae). In: K. L. Wilson and D. A. Morrison, eds. 2000. Monocots: Systematics and Evolution. Melbourne. Pp. 488–496.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants rhizomatous; bulbils never produced in leaf axils; leaf margins entire or repand; petiole base never clasping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes brownish, nodes not articulate; staminate inflorescences solitary in leaf axils; perianth of both staminate and pistillate flowers greenish white; stamens erect; thecae</description>
      <determination>1.  Dioscorea villosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes yellow, nodes articulate, each bearing 1 dark, contrasting, ± deltate scale leaf or the dark vertical scar remaining once leaf falls; staminate inflorescences (1–)2–5 in leaf axils; perianth of both staminate and pistillate flowers orangish yellow; stamens</description>
      <determination>2.  Dioscorea floridana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants tuberous; bulbils produced in leaf axils; leaf margins lobed or entire; petiole base sometimes clasping.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins 3–5-lobed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blade hastate-cordate, margins 3-lobed, apex acute or mucronate; petiole base</description>
      <determination>3.  Dioscorea polystachya</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blade reniform, margins irregularly 3–5-lobed, apex conspicuously caudate;</description>
      <determination>6.  Dioscorea sansibarensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf margins entire.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems broadly winged, 4-angular; distal leaves decussate, blade base sagittate; seeds</description>
      <determination>4.  Dioscorea alata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems terete, usually unwinged; leaves alternate throughout, blade base orbicular;</description>
      <determination>5.  Dioscorea bulbifera</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
