<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">orchidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">vanilla</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Reichenbach f." date="1865">phaeantha</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>48: 274. 1865</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orchidaceae;genus vanilla;species phaeantha</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots usually 1 per node, aerial portions 1–2 mm diam. Stems occasionally branched, leafy, thick, 8–12 mm diam., smooth. Leaves persistent; blade oblong-elliptic, flat, equal to or shorter than internodes, to 15 × 2.5–5 cm, fleshy-leathery, tapering to acute apex. Inflorescences axillary, 12-flowered racemes, short-pedunculate, ± to 8 cm excluding peduncle; floral bracts foliaceous, ovate, cucullate, to 2.5 × 1.5 cm, fleshy. Flowers: sepals and petals spreading, green, fleshy, rigid; sepals narrowly oblanceolate, 7–9 × 1.3–2 cm, margins straight, apex obtuse to acute, spreading; petals obliquely narrowly oblanceolate, abaxially keeled, thinner than sepals, 6.5–8 ×1–1.5 cm, apex acute to subacuminate; lip adnate to column for 3 cm, white becoming yellow-cream toward apex, lamina gulletlike, cuneate, obovate, clawed, obscurely 3-lobed distally, to 7.5–9 × 3.5–4 cm when spread, lateral lobes arching over column, margins involute, apex rounded, middle lobe broadly subquadrangular, margins undulate, apex retuse; disc with multiple longitudinal ribs, central tuft of retrorse scales, thickened broad rib extending from tuft to apex; column curved distal to middle, white, slender, 6.5 cm, adaxially bearded; pollinia yellow; pedicellate ovary 4–8 cm. Berries cylindric, 8–10 × 1 cm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Apr--Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cypress swamps, hammocks;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--20 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.; West Indies (Trinidad).</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Leafy vanilla</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">oblong-leaved vanilla</other_name>
  <discussion>Vanilla phaeantha is known in the flora area only from Collier County, Florida (P. M. Brown 2002).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
