<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Katharine B. Gregg,Paul M. Catling</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">orchidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Richard ex Lindley" date="1840">CLEISTES</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Sp. Orchid. Pl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>409. 1840</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orchidaceae;genus CLEISTES</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek kleistos , closed, alluding to lip and petals that diverge only near apex, forming tube for most of their length, the flower thus appearing closed]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, terrestrial. Roots 1–2 mm wide, sometimes with wider nodular tuberoids, frequently rather brittle. Leaves 1–3 on vegetative plants, 1(–2) centrally on flowering stems, sessile; blade oblong-lanceolate or elliptic-oblong. Inflorescences terminal,1–3-flowered; floral bracts leaflike. Flowers resupinate, erect, sessile; sepals olive-green, brown, or maroon, linear-lanceolate, apex acuminate; petals rose-pink to white, spatulate or oblanceolate, usually forming tube with lip; lip rose-pink to white, with rose or purple veins, oblanceolate, 3-lobed, middle lobe medially winged or tuberculate, central keel grooved from base to 3/4 its length; column free, white, apex lacerate, truncate; anther terminal, hinged; pollinia 2, without viscidium, soft, mealy; pollen grains in tetrads. Fruits capsules, erect, cylindric.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">2 in Central America.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Spreading pogonia</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 25 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Authors of some neotropical floras have questioned the separation of Cleistes from Pogonia; most recent North American authors have followed O. Ames (1905–1922) in recognizing Cleistes, and we prefer to do the same until a detailed study suggests otherwise. The two North American species can reproduce asexually by root shoots.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ames, O. 1905–1922. Orchidaceae: Illustrations and Studies of the Family Orchidaceae Issuing from the Ames Botanical Laboratory…. 7 vols. Boston and New York. Vol. 7.  </reference>
    <reference>Catling, P. M. and K. B. Gregg. 1992. Systematics of the genus Cleistes in North America. Lindleyana 7: 57–73.  </reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1946b. Some orchids of the Manual range. Rhodora 48: 161–162, 184–197, plates 1045–1048.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Column 13–19 mm; lip 21–33(–38) mm</description>
      <determination>1.  Cleistes bifaria</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Column 21–25(–29) mm; lip (26–)34–55 mm</description>
      <determination>2.  Cleistes divaricata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
