<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Loyal A. Mehrhoff,Michael A. Homoya</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ORCHIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">ISOTRIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Med. Repos., hexade</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 5: 357. 1808</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ORCHIDACEAE;genus ISOTRIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek iso , equal, and tri , 3; probably referring to 3 sepals of equal size and shape]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, terrestrial, winter dormant. Roots long, slender, hairy with mycorrhizae. Stems simple, hollow, fleshy, smooth, glaucous. Leaves (2–)5(–6), appearing whorled. Inflorescences terminal; bracts absent. Flowers 1–2, resupinate, erect, yellowish green to white, yellow, and purple, subsessile to pedicellate; sepals of same color, linear-oblanceolate to lanceolate, of equal size; petals oblanceolate, elliptic-obovate, or elliptic-lanceolate, enclosing column; lip apically 3-lobed, lateral lobes triangular, margins involute; callus forming fleshy medial crest; column white, apex denticulate; anther operculate; pollinia 2, hinged, soft, mealy; rostellum obscure; pollen in tetrads, granular; ovary green, slender. Fruits capsules, commonly persistent through following growing season, erect, ellipsoid-cylindric, dehiscent in fall. Seeds 1.2 × 0.2 mm. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e North America.</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Whorled pogonia orchid</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Ames, O. 1905–1922. Orchidaceae: Illustrations and Studies of the Family Orchidaceae Issuing from the Ames Botanical Laboratory…. 7 vols. Boston and New York. Vol. 7.  </reference>
    <reference>Homoya, M. A. 1977. The Distribution and Ecology of the Genus Isotria in Illinois. Master’s thesis. Southern Illinois University.  </reference>
    <reference>Mehrhoff, L. A. 1983. Pollination in the genus Isotria (Orchidaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 70: 1444–1453.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals green to light green, less than 30 mm; lip light yellowish green to pale greenish white, streaked with green; pedicel of mature capsule 5–17(–20) mm ; stem and leaves pale grayish</description>
      <determination>1.  Isotria medeoloides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals purplish brown, greater than 30 mm; lip yellowish green to white, streaked with purple; pedicel of mature capsule 20–55 mm ; stem purplish to brownish green; leaves green</description>
      <determination>2.  Isotria verticillata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
