<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>James D. Ackerman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">orchidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">PRESCOTTIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. J. Hooker, Exotic Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: plate 115. 1824</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orchidaceae;genus PRESCOTTIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For John Prescott (d. 1837), a British botanist resident in Russia who traveled widely in northern Asia]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, terrestrial. Roots fasciculate, fibrous or thick and fleshy, villous. Stems: rhizomes sometimes branched. Leaves basal, petiolate or sessile, not articulate, membranous. Inflorescences terminal, many-flowered spikes; peduncles partially covered by sheathing bracts. Flowers not resupinate, sessile; sepals spreading or reflexed, rarely distinct, basally connate forming short cup, thin; petals adnate to column and sepal cup, narrow, thin; lip distalmost in flower, attached to column foot, clawed, often basally auriculate distal to claw, deeply concave, often enclosing column, very fleshy; column and foot adnate to sepal cup when present, minute, column blunt; anther abaxial, erect; pollinia 4, slightly flattened, soft, mealy; caudicles absent; stigmas entire. Fruits capsules, ovoid to ellipsoid.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 24 (1 in the flora): tropical and subtropical regions, North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 24 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>tropical and subtropical regions, North America, Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>9.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">Prescotia</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 24 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Originally the name was spelled as “Prescotia.” Since then and until recently, most authors, with the exception of W. Voth (1976) and J. D. Ackerman (1989), spelled it with two ts. “Prescotia” should be treated as an orthographic error (J. D. Ackerman 1995), and the spelling with two ts should prevail</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
