<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>10.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>CYCLOPOGON</genus_name><genus_authority>C. Presl</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Reliq. Haenk.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 93, plate 13. 1827</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek cyclo , circular, and pogon , beard, perhaps in reference to pubescent bases of sepals of the type species]</etymology><author>James D. Ackerman</author><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Beadlea</genus_name><genus_authority>Small</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, terrestrial, sympodial. Roots fasciculate, fleshy, villous. Stems simple, rhizomatous. Leaves few to many, basal, petiolate; blade not articulate, convolute, mostly ovate to elliptic, soft. Inflorescences terminal, many-flowered spikes or racemes, erect; scapes bracteate. Flowers resupinate, horizontal, greenish or yellowish green, small; sepals subparallel, distinct or connate at base, forming obscure mentum with base of column or sepaline nectar tube; petals connivent with dorsal sepal; lip clawed, sagittate to cordate, constricted proximal to apex; lateral margins appressed to sides of column; column erect; pollinia 2, clavate-oblong, mealy; stylar canal entrance central; stigma lobes 2, distinct or approximate; rostellum longer than wide; viscidium relatively large, disc-shaped; ovary sessile or subsessile. Fruits capsules.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 70 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>tropical and subtropical regions</global_distribution><global_distribution>s North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution>South America.</global_distribution><discussion>All species of Cyclopogon except the holotype were placed in the genus Beadlea (L. A. Garay 1980[1982]) because their perianth base was not united into a tube. That characteristic was rejected as a valid generic distinction but the taxon was recognized as Cyclopogon sect. Beadlea (P. Burns-Balogh 1982; P. Burns-Balogh and H. Robinson 1983). The perianth tube character is a matter of degree and not one of presence or absence (D. L. Szlachetko 1993).</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Midvein and margins of petals darkened distally; lip broadest proximal to apical constriction; leaf blades purplish abaxially, dark purplish green adaxially; petioles spreading to</statement>
      <determination>1.  Cyclopogon cranichoides</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Midvein and margins of petals unmarked distally; lip broadest distal to apical constriction or distal and proximal parts of lip equal in width; leaf blades green; petioles erect, 3–10 cm</statement>
      <determination>2.  Cyclopogon elatus</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
