<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>13.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>ELTROPLECTRIS</genus_name><genus_authority>Rafinesque</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Tellur.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 51. 1837</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek eleutheros , free, and plectron , spur, referring to free spur of sepal]</etymology><author>James D. Ackerman</author><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Centrogenium</genus_name><genus_authority>Schlechter</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Stenorrhynchos</genus_name><genus_authority>Richard ex Sprengel</genus_authority><section_name>Eltroplectris</section_name><section_authority>(Rafinesque) Burns-Balogh</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, terrestrial, sympodial. Roots fasciculate, fleshy, densely villous. Stems erect, rhizomatous. Leaves 1–2, basal; blade not articulate, long-petiolate. Inflorescences terminal, few- to many-flowered racemes, erect; peduncle slender, bracteate. Flowers resupinate; sepals spreading, distinct; lateral sepals longer than dorsal, attached along column foot forming spur; petals appressed to dorsal sepal, basally decurrent on column; lip arcuately recurved, clawed, shorter than sepals, membranous; column erect, short, slender; column foot partially adnate to ovary, elongate; anther persistent; pollinia 2, clavate, mealy; stigmas distinct; rostellum subulate to linear, pointed, rigid; viscidium oblong. Fruits capsules, ellipsoid-cyclindric.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 12 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>subtropical and tropical regions</global_distribution><global_distribution>North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies.</global_distribution><discussion>Eltroplectris has been treated as Stenorrhynchos Richard ex Sprengel sect. Eltroplectris (P. Burns-Balogh 1982); others have treated Eltroplectris as distinct (e.g., L. A. Garay 1980[1982]; D. L. Szlachetko 1995).</discussion><references>
    <reference>  Burns-Balogh, P. 1982. Generic redefinition in subtribe Spiranthinae (Orchidaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 69: 1119–1132.  Szlachetko, D. L. 1995. Systema orchidalium. Fragm. Florist. Geobot., suppl. 3: 1–152.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
