<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Trillium</genus_name><species_name>persistens</species_name><species_authority>W. H. Duncan</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>73: 244. 1971</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Rhizomes horizontal to erect, short, praemorse. Scapes 1–2, round in cross section, 2–3 dm, slender, glabrous. Bracts horizontal to drooping distally, sessile; blade 3–5-veined, ovate-lanceolate to lanceolate, 3–8.5+ × 1.5–3.5 cm, adaxial surface faintly glossy, rarely with ± 2 mm, winged, petiolelike base, apex acuminate. Flower opening above bracts; sepals spreading, green, elliptic to narrowly ovate, 11–22 × 5–6 mm, thin-textured, margins entire, apex acute; petals erect proximally, spreading distally, white, fading to deep pink with inverted V-shaped basal portion remaining white, veins not engraved, linear-elliptic to occasionally linear, 2–3.5 × 0.5–1 cm, thin-textured, margins undulate at least in distal portion, apex acute; stamens prominent, erect to divergent, straight, 9–14 mm; filaments ± equaling anthers; anthers straight, yellow or white, dehiscence introrse; connective barely longer than anther sacs; ovary white or greenish white, obovate, very sharply 6-angled, 2.5–6 mm; style 2–6 mm; stigmas erect, slightly divergent at tip, delicate, not lobed, shortly connate basally, uniformly thin; pedicel erect or slightly leaning, 1–3 cm, 1/4–1/2 bract length at anthesis. Fruits baccate, greenish white, 6-angled, pulpy, not juicy.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><habitat>humus soils in mixed deciduous-pine woodlands</habitat><habitat>along stream flats and at edges of rhododendron thickets</habitat><habitat>occasionally in open vaccinium-filled clearings</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>50 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution>S.C.</us_distribution><discussion>Listed as a U.S. endangered species, Trillium persistens has appeared as such on a postage stamp. The species is very rare and known only from an approximately four-square-mile area at the head of Tallulah Gorge in Georgia and South Carolina.</discussion></treatment>
