<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Charles J. Sheviak,Paul Martin Brown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">orchidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Richard" date="unknown">SPIRANTHES</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>De Orchid. Eur.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20, 28, 36. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orchidaceae;genus SPIRANTHES</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek speira , coil, and anthos , flower, in allusion to the spirally arranged inflorescence]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, terrestrial. Roots fleshy, fasciculate, slender to tuberous. Stems with foliaceous sheaths. Leaves basal or occasionally cauline. Inflorescences terminal spikes, flowers inserted in lax to dense, ± evident spiral, pubescent to glabrous, often glandular. Flowers resupinate, often somewhat apically recurved, white, cream, or yellow (pink in S. sinensis); perianth parts distinct or sepals basally connate, connivent; lip lanceolate to ovate or pandurate, rarely linear, fleshy to somewhat membranaceous, base with pair of calli, apex usually ± crisped; mentum or spur absent; column short, cylindric; anther cordate, apex acute or obtuse; pollinia clavate with slender viscidium; ovary sessile, cylindric.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>19.</number>
  <discussion>Species 45 (23 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Two extra-limital species of Spiranthes have been reported from the flora. The Central American S. graminea Lindley was reported from southern Arizona (C. A. Luer 1975), based on plants subsequently described as S. delitescens Sheviak. The Asiatic S. sinensis Persoon was reported from Florida (J. Beckner 1996) based on plants of S. vernalis with unusual orange markings on the lips.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Catling, P. M. 1980b. Systematics of Spiranthes L. C. Richard in Northeastern North America. Ph.D. thesis. University of Toronto.  </reference>
    <reference>Catling, P. M. 1981. Taxonomy of autumn-flowering Spiranthes species of southern Nova Scotia. Canad. J. Bot. 59: 1253–1270.  </reference>
    <reference>Catling, P. M. 1982. Breeding systems of northeastern North American Spiranthes (Orchidaceae). Canad. J. Bot. 60: 3017–3039.  </reference>
    <reference>Catling, P. M. and J. R. Brown. 1983. Morphometrics and ecological isolation in sympatric Spiranthes (Orchidaceae) in southwestern Ontario. Canad. J. Bot. 61: 2747–2759.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip pandurate, subapical constriction deep, apex broadly dilated, glabrous adaxially; veins typically 3, lateral veins with branches wide-spreading toward margins; rachis glabrous or</description>
      <determination>19.  Spiranthes romanzoffiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip linear to lanceolate, ovate, oblong, or elliptic, at most only slightly constricted or scarcely to not at all differentiated from petals, glabrous to pubescent or papillate adaxially; veins various; rachis glabrous or densely pubescent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Viscidium oval (2–2.5 times as long as wide); lip bright yellow or orange-yellow with</description>
      <determination>18.  Spiranthes lucida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Viscidium lanceolate to linear (3–12 times as long as wide), or absent; lip white or if yellowish or orange, sepals and petals creamy or ivory to yellowish, not pure white, or lip without greenish veins, or perianth green, or lip scarcely to not at all differentiated from petals; sepals basally connate to distinct throughout.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis densely pubescent with all or many trichomes tapered, either pointed and not glandular or obscurely glandular; terminal glands equaling or narrower than stipes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis with obscurely glandular trichomes, glands equaling or narrower than</description>
      <determination>22.  Spiranthes delitescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis with all or many trichomes pointed, wholly not glandular; veins of lip</description>
      <determination>1.  Spiranthes vernalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis glabrous or densely pubescent with conspicuously glandular trichomes; terminal glands markedly broader than stipes, non-glandular trichomes of uniform thickness, blunt or truncate, not tapered or pointed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip with conspicuous, terminally widened, green (rarely cream-colored) diverging veins extending to near tip; lip glabrous on adaxial distal surface; leaves</description>
      <determination>17.  Spiranthes praecox</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip without conspicuously widened veins, veins sometimes greenish, either straight or divergent, not also widened; lip either pubescent or glabrous on adaxial distal surface; leaves linear to ovate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Root solitary (rarely divided near tip), vertical, turbinate (4–12 mm wide, ratio of length/width about 5); rachis entirely glabrous; flowers gaping from</description>
      <determination>9.  Spiranthes tuberosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Roots few to numerous, horizontal to strongly descending, slender to tuberously thickened, elongate (mostly 2–8 mm wide, rarely to 15 mm, ratio of length/width more than 5); rachis conspicuously or minutely and sparsely pubescent or glabrous; flowers gaping only from 2 / 3 – 3 / 4 their lengths from base, tubular portion more than 3 mm; lip white, creamy, yellow, or green in center, or often wholly green if undifferentiated from petals (i.e., flowers peloric).</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals spatulate to obovate, suborbiculate, or ovate-elliptic, conspicuously shorter than sepals.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip with margins fleshy, ± inflexed at apex, apex acute; petals creamy</description>
      <determination>15.  Spiranthes casei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip truncate to broadly rounded at apex, apical margin thin, delicately crisped; petals whitish to yellow-green with longitudinal cen-</description>
      <determination>16.  Spiranthes parksii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals slender, linear, linear-lanceolate, linear-oblong, slenderly elliptic, or linear-oblanceolate, slightly shorter to longer than sepals.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals basally connate for more than 0.4 mm; rachis glabrous or sparsely (rarely densely) pubescent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip broadest near middle, narrowed to base from between center and basal 1 / 3 ; perianth parts with basal 1 / 4 (or more) thick, fleshy, bright green, the remainder yellowish; lip variably orange centrally; sepals 4–6 mm; rachis glabrous, often farinose</description>
      <determination>21.  Spiranthes infernalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip broadest near base, narrowed from below basal 1 / 4 ; perianth parts uniformly white to yellowish, membranaceous (except sometimes lip centrally fleshy, more deeply colored); sepals 4.6–15 mm; rachis glabrous or sparsely to densely pubescent, not farinose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis glabrous or sparsely pubescent, longest trichomes 0.18 mm, glands often sessile; lip lanceolate to lance-ovate, distal surface adaxially with dense cushion of peg-shaped trichomes; flowers creamy to markedly yellowish, slenderly tubular, apex of lip recurved less than to scarcely more</description>
      <determination>20.  Spiranthes porrifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis sparsely (rarely densely) pubescent, longest trichomes 0.2–0.4 mm, glands obviously stalked; lip ovate to ovate-oblong, distal surface adaxially without dense cushion of peg-shaped trichomes; flowers white to ivory, strongly gaping with lip prominently diverging from se-</description>
      <determination>23.  Spiranthes diluvialis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals not basally connate or connate for less than 0.3 mm; rachis sparsely to densely pubescent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences with 5 or more flowers per cycle of spiral; spiral usually open and obvious.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lateral sepals widely diverging from base, 8–10 mm; lip dilated at base, oblong toward apex, yellow centrally; flowers gaping from near middle; leaves fugaceous or persisting through anthesis; inflorescence secund to twisted usually no more than 180º; fall–</description>
      <determination>3.  Spiranthes longilabris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lateral sepals somewhat spreading to appressed, not widely diverging, 3.8–10 mm; lip ovate to oblong-quadrangular, basal dilation not distinct from oblong apex, white or creamy centrally; flowers gaping from near middle to merely apically; leaves persistent to fugaceous; spiral of inflorescence usually with few–several cycles of 360º, sometimes secund; spring–fall blooming.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip with distal margin laciniate-dentate; leaves usually linear with length/width ratio greater than 30 (rarely broader on stout, leafy plants nearly to more than 1 m),</description>
      <determination>2.  Spiranthes laciniata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip with distal margin undulate to crisped, sometimes ragged, not laciniate-dentate; leaves lanceolate to ovate to obovate (linear in S. torta ), with length/width ratio less than 30, often fugaceous and absent at flowering.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers comparatively large, stout, perianth 5–12 mm, white to yellowish, lip often darker centrally, not green nor greenish yellow, ovary often equaling perianth in freshly opened flowers; leaves ascending, relatively slender, not ovate nor obovate, present at flowering; rachis conspicuously and densely glandularly capitate-pubescent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip distally truncate, 5–7.5 mm; flowers yellowish, cream, or ivory, arcuate-</description>
      <determination>15.  Spiranthes casei (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip distally acute to rounded, not truncate, usually more than 7.5 mm (in shorter flowers ovary often much shorter than perianth); flowers white to</description>
      <determination>14.  Spiranthes cernua (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers comparatively small, slender, perianth usually less than 5.5 mm (if longer, lip green centrally and leaves ascending, slender, often fugaceous), ovary less than 1 / 2 length of perianth in freshly opened flowers; leaves strictly basal, spreading and ovate to obovate or oblanceolate, or ascending and slender, and often on base of stem in S . torta , often absent at flowering; rachis glabrous or sparsely to densely, minutely pubescent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis densely pubescent; flowers cream to pale yellow, lip yellow centrally</description>
      <determination>4.  Spiranthes brevilabris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rachis glabrous or sparsely and minutely pubescent; flowers yellowish to white, lip yellowish or green centrally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers creamy yellow to pale greenish yellow, lip yellow centrally</description>
      <determination>5.  Spiranthes floridana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers white, lip green centrally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ascending, linear, often absent at flowering; lateral sepals</description>
      <determination>8.  Spiranthes torta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves spreading, ovate to obovate, oblanceolate, or elliptic, present or absent at flowering; lateral sepals slightly spreading to appressed (not arching downward); various locales.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves oblanceolate, withering at anthesis; sepals spatulate,</description>
      <determination>7.  Spiranthes eatonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves obovate, spreading, present or absent at anthesis; lateral sepals acuminate, white throughout; summer/fall-</description>
      <determination>6.  Spiranthes lacera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences with 3 or 4 flowers per cycle of spiral, spiral usually tight and obscure, then with 3 or 4 secondary vertical ranks evident.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals 6 mm; proximal portion of stem with recurved-spreading leaves</description>
      <determination>10.  Spiranthes ovalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals 7.5 mm or longer; leaves wholly basal, or proximal portion of stem with ascending to recurved-spreading blades, or leaves absent at flowering.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip only slightly or not at all differentiated from petals (flowers peloric); often buds failing to open, setting seed agamospermically; column normal or abnormally</description>
      <determination>14.  Spiranthes cernua (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip clearly differentiated from petals; buds opening into normal flowers; column normal; leaves present or absent at flowering.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip with variably evident median constriction, apical 1 / 3 of lip usually about 1 / 2 as wide as basal 1 / 3 ; veins of lip often with laterally diverging branches; flowers</description>
      <determination>23.  Spiranthes diluvialis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip without conspicuous median constriction, apical 1 / 3 of lip 2 / 3 or more as wide as basal 1 / 3 ; veins of lip with branches parallel.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal calli relatively short and conic, as wide as high, mostly to 1 mm; lateral sepals distinct, spreading, often over top of flower; leaves absent at flowering (rarely persisting in Northern and High Plains, and New Mexico)</description>
      <determination>11. Spiranthes magnicamporum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal calli 1–2 mm; lateral sepals ± appressed, very rarely spreading over top of flower; leaves present at flowering (commonly absent in prairie populations).</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal margin of lateral sepals obviously separated from adjacent margin of dorsal sepal, separation abrupt from base, commonly by about 1 mm; lip strongly curving from claw (resulting angle 20–60º), base cu-</description>
      <determination>12.  Spiranthes ochroleuca</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Distal margin of lateral sepals touching, or nearly touching, adjacent margin of dorsal sepal, or only gradually separated with distance from base; lip not strongly curving from claw (angle less than 30º), base cordate to truncate; perianth white to creamy or ivory, center of lip ivory to pale yellowish or rarely greenish.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants to 50 cm; leaves comparatively slender, ascending to spreading (flaccidly so because of membranaceous blades with thickened midrib); petioles of basal leaves less than 6 mm wide; leaves wholly basal or lower sheaths with ascending-spreading blades; perianth usually 8–11 mm; lip membranaceous to fleshy, less than</description>
      <determination>14.  Spiranthes cernua (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants to 100 cm or more; leaves broad, ascending to spreading (rigidly so because of aerenchymatous thickening of blade); petioles of basal leaves 7 mm or more wide; blades spreading-recurved on proximal cauline sheaths, frequently also on distal, leaves then extending to inflorescence; perianth (4–)10–18 mm (shorter in young</description>
      <determination>13.  Spiranthes odorata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
