<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">LILIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Trillium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">pusillum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 215. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family LILIACEAE;genus Trillium;species pusillum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Trillium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Pursh" date="unknown">pumilum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Trillium;species pumilum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>9.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Dwarf trillium</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">least trillium</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Trillium pusillum comprises widely disjunct, regional populations, each varying somewhat from the others and variable within itself as well. Some of these populations have been named as varieties or separate species. In the wild, the plants that have been recognized as var. ozarkanum generally grow taller than others and are said to have bracts with five major veins instead of three. Plants attributed to var. texanum, on the other hand, are generally smaller in all parts, with narrower petals, and often revert to a single bract when not flowering. Only var. virginianum is easily distinguished at sight by its “sessile” flower. This variety has received extensive study. P. R. Cabe (1995), in a morphological study including statistical analysis, found variation within and between populations. He felt that his results were inconclusive, and also that some of the variation might be environmentally induced. The variation that he found did not correlate with a geographic pattern, and he suggested treating all Virginia populations as var. virginianum, or simply T. pusillum. In a later study, P. R. Cabe and C. R. Werth (1995), using isozyme evidence, obtained like results, and suggested treating all Virginia populations as a single variety pending further investigation. Until there has been such study, of the Virginia plants as well as the rest of the T. pusillum complex, I choose to retain the fairly distinctive and more or less traditionally known var. virginianum, and include all other populations in a broadly circumscribed var. pusillum.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cabe, P. R. 1995. The Trillium pusillum Michaux (Liliaceae) complex in Virginia. I. Morphological investigations. Castanea 60: 1–14.  </reference>
    <reference>Cabe, P. R. and C. R. Werth. 1995. The Trillium pusillum Michaux (Liliaceae) complex in Virginia. II. Isozyme evidence. Castanea 60: 15–29.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flower pedicillate; pedicel usually 0.5–2 cm</description>
      <determination>9a.  Trillium pusillum var. pusillum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flower sessile or subsessile; pedicel, if present, 0.1–</description>
      <determination>9b.  Trillium pusillum var. virginianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
