<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>8.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Spiranthes</genus_name><species_name>torta</species_name><species_authority>(Thunberg) Garay &amp; H. R. Sweet</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in R. A. Howard, Fl. Less. Antill.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 77. 1974</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Ophrys</genus_name><species_name>torta</species_name><species_authority>Thunberg</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Mus. Nat. Acad. Upsal. </publication_title><place_in_publication>9: 136. 1791</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Ibidium</genus_name><species_name>tortile</species_name><species_authority>(Swartz) House</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Spiranthes</genus_name><species_name>tortilis</species_name><species_authority>(Swartz) Richard</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 7–50 cm. Roots few, spreading to descending, slender to somewhat tuberous, mostly to 1 cm diam. Leaves fugacious, 2 or 3, basal, reduced to bracts on stem, ascending, narrowly oblanceolate, 5–20 × 0.5 cm. Spikes secund to loosely spiraled, 8–10 flowers per cycle of spiral; rachis sparsely pubescent, some trichomes capitate, glands obviously stalked. Flowers nodding, white; sepals elliptic, 5 × 1 mm; lateral sepals distinct to base, curving slightly downward, oblique; petals green at base, oblique, elliptic, 5 × 1.5 mm; lip green with white apex, ovate, 4 × 2 mm; veins parallel; basal calli very short, stout, to 0.3 mm; viscidium linear-lanceolate; ovary mostly 3 mm. Seeds monoembryonic.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>dry pinelands</habitat><elevation>0–10 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies (Bahamas)</global_distribution><global_distribution>Bermuda</global_distribution><global_distribution>Central America.</global_distribution><discussion>Spiranthes torta is restricted to the rocky pinelands in southern Florida and is easily recognized by its nodding flowers and downward-pointing lateral sepals. It could only be confused with S. tuberosa, typically a much shorter plant with pure white flowers.</discussion><discussion>Spiranthes amesiana Schlechter is often included as a synonym of S. torta; recent studies indicate that it may be a distinct species. It is said to differ from S. torta in its denser inflorescence, spade-shaped lip with a crenulate-ciliate margin, and densely pubescent basal calli. Within the area covered by the flora, it is restricted to extreme southern Florida; it also has been collected in the Bahamas and Nicaragua.</discussion></treatment>
