<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ORCHIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="unknown" date="unknown">CRANICHIDEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">SPIRANTHINAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Spiranthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Richard" date="unknown">cernua</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>De Orchid. Eur.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ORCHIDACEAE;tribe CRANICHIDEAE;subtribe SPIRANTHINAE;genus Spiranthes;species cernua;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ophrys</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">cernua</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 946. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ophrys;species cernua;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ibidium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) House" date="unknown">cernuum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ibidium;species cernuum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>14.</number>
  <discussion>Spiranthes cernua is a facultatively agamospermic polyploid compilospecies in which unidirectional gene flow from related diploids generates a wide range of novel forms and races. Chromosomal segregation has given rise to some forms that very nearly approximate the diploid donor, and meiotic irregularities produce peloria and other abnormal conditions. Apomixis then permits reproduction in pure lines, some of which are so distinctive as to appear to be species. Determination of this and related species is consequently often challenging.</discussion>
  <discussion>Adventitious embryony in this species commonly gives rise to polyembryonic seeds and seeds exhibiting irregularities such as embryos erupting through or developing outside the testa and naked embryos lacking testae. Often a capsule contains a mixture of polyembryonic and monoembryonic seeds. Rarely all or most seed is monoembryonic, yet irregularities can still be seen.</discussion>
  <discussion>Polyembryony is also characteristic of Spiranthes casei and S. parksii, species that are probably derivatives of S. cernua. For the most part, at least, related diploids and all other species are strictly sexual and characterized by wholly monoembryonic seed. Some indication of apomixis and polyembryony in S. magnicamporum, S. ochroleuca, and S. odorata in the northeastern portion of the range of the complex has been reported (P. M. Catling 1981, 1982), but the difficulty in distinguishing between diploid donors and tetraploid chromosomal segregates makes interpretation difficult (C. J. Sheviak 1982, 1991). In particular, the range of S. odorata northward along the Atlantic Coast is uncertain. Plants that appear typical of S. odorata in all respects but with polyembryonic seed occur from Virginia northward and quickly replace monoembryonic plants toward the north. Such plants from as far south as Virginia, however, have proven to be tetraploids and furthermore to assume morphology typical of S. cernua when grown away from the Coast.</discussion>
  <discussion>Gene flow from Spiranthes magnicamporum generates cytogenetically based peloria, a common element in portions of the prairie region. Most commonly differentiation of the lip is suppressed, but in some forms the petals are elaborated and approach the lip in form. Additionally, buds may fail to open and a functional column may be lacking, yet seed is produced apomictically. See the discussion under 16. S. parksii.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Sheviak, C. J. 1982. Biosystematic study of the Spiranthes cernua complex. Bull. New York State Mus. Sci. Serv. 448.  Sheviak, C. J. 1991. Morphological variation in the compilospecies Spiranthes cernua (L.) L. C. Rich.: Ecologically-limited effects of gene flow. Lindleyana 6: 228–234. </reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
