<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">orchidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Richard" date="unknown">spiranthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Sheviak" date="1990">delitescens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>92: 215, figs. 1, 2. 1990</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orchidaceae;genus spiranthes;species delitescens</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 20–48 cm. Roots few–several, descending, slenderly tuberous, to 5 mm diam. Leaves persisting through anthesis, basal, on proximal 1/2 of stem, ascending to spreading, linear-lanceolate to oblanceolate, to 18 × 1.5 cm (rarely wider). Spikes loosely to tightly spiraled, 3 flowers per cycle of spiral; rachis rather densely pubescent, trichomes without glands pointed, glandular obviously stalked, glands equaling or narrower than stipes. Flowers curving through horizontal, white, somewhat gaping and open with wide-spreading lateral sepals; sepals usually connate at base, 6.5–8(–9.9) mm; lateral sepals curving outward throughout lengths, usually directed somewhat downward; petals linear to linear-oblanceolate, apex obtuse; lip creamy or very pale yellow centrally, oblong, with variably evident median constriction, 5.8–7.9 × 3.2–4.9 mm, apex broadly expanded with extensive transverse pleats, distal surface mostly glabrous adaxially; basal calli prominent, stout; veins few, branches mostly wide-spreading; viscidia linear to linear-lanceolate; ovary 3–6 mm. Seeds monoembryonic. 2n = 74.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jul--Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cienegas, wet riparian meadows, stream banks;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1400--1500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <number>22.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Spiranthes delitescens is an amphiploid product of hybridization of species in the n = 15 and n = 22 lineages. Although its origin is unknown, on morphologic grounds C. J. Sheviak (1990) proposed S. vernalis and S. porrifolia as possible parents.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Sheviak, C. J. 1990. A new Spiranthes (Orchidaceae) from the cienegas of southernmost Arizona. Rhodora 92: 213–231.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
