<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>18.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Platanthera</genus_name><species_name>flava</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) Lindley</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. Sp. Orchid. Pl.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>293. 1835</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Orchis</genus_name><species_name>flava</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 942. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Habenaria</genus_name><species_name>flava</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) R. Brown</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Perularia</genus_name><species_name>scutellata</species_name><species_authority>(Nuttall) Small</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 13–65 cm. Leaves (1–)2–3(–4), spreading to ascending, gradually to rather abruptly reduced to bracts distally; blade lanceolate to elliptic-oblong, 5–35 × 1–7 cm. Spikes lax to dense. Flowers resupinate, inconspicuous, yellowish green; lateral sepals porrect to reflexed; petals oblong-orbiculate to ovate, apex somewhat crenulate; lip descending to commonly reflexed, 2–6 × 1.8–5 mm, base auriculate, with prominent central tubercle, distal margin entire to slightly crenulate; spur cylindric to strongly clavate, 4–8(–11) mm, apex rarely 2-lobed; rostellum lobes mostly parallel to slightly diverging, directed downward, minute, obscure; pollinia remaining enclosed in anther sacs; viscidia mostly quad-rangular, oblong-quadrangular, orbiculate, or broadly asymmetric, commonly canaliculate to nearly cylindric and difficult to assess; ovary rather slender to stout, mostly 8–10 × 2 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>e North America.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip (excluding auricles) subquadrangular, suborbiculate, or broadly ovate, often emarginate; inflorescences usually rather lax, slender (this enhanced by floral bracts mostly shorter than</statement>
      <determination>18a.  Platanthera flava var. flava</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip (excluding auricles) oblong, usually obtuse, (rarely triangular, acute); inflorescences usually rather dense, stout (this emphasized by floral bracts usually long, often greatly exceeding flowers)</statement>
      <determination>18b.  Platanthera flava var. herbiola</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
