<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">trillium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="T. S. Patrick" date="1984">sulcatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Brittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>36: 27, figs. 1–4. 1984</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus trillium;species sulcatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes horizontal–slightly erect, thick, praemorse. Scapes 1–4+, round in cross section, 3–7 dm, 2–2.5 times as long as bract, stout, glabrous. Bracts subsessile; blade obovate to broadly elliptic, 13–20 × 8–22 cm, not glossy, base attenuate, apex acuminate. Flower facing outward at right angle to pedicel, above bracts, odor faintly musty, like fresh fungus; perianth gaping, strongly 3-dimensional; sepals spreading, usually streaked or entirely purplish maroon, occasionally entirely green except on margins, elliptic, 15–38 × 9–15 mm, margins entire, apex strongly sulcate-acuminate; petals carried somewhat forward to recurved-spreading in distal 1/2, usually dark reddish maroon to purplish, rarely cream to soft yellow, pink, white, or 2-colored, heavy-veined, ovate to broadly ovate-overlapping, 1.8–5 × 1–3 cm, heavy-textured, apex acuminate, rarely somewhat sulcate; stamens erect, ± equaling or slightly longer than ovary, 15–18 mm; filaments purple to white, 3–5 mm, slender; anthers straight, purplish to yellow, 5–12 mm, thick, dehiscence introrse; connectives equaling or ± shorter than anther sacs; ovary usually dark purple, globose to flask-shaped, 6-angled, 14–18 mm, broadly attached basally; stigmas prominent, recurved, distinct, purple, not lobed adaxially, basally thickened, gradually tapered, 2–5 mm, fleshy; pedicel usually stiffly erect (rarely almost horizontal above bracts), straight, reflexed ± 90° at tip, 6–11 cm. Fruits red, fragrance of fresh mushrooms, ± globose to pyramidal, 1.5–3 × 1.2–2.8 cm, juicy to pulpy. 2n = 10.</description>
  <description type="phenology">mid spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">apr</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="habitat">rich mesic woodlands</description>
  <description type="habitat">especially moist north- or east-facing slopes</description>
  <description type="habitat">wooded ledges and stream banks on neutral to slightly acid soil</description>
  <description type="elevation">300–400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ky.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tenn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Va.</description>
  <description type="distribution">W.Va.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering mid spring (Apr--May). Rich mesic woodlands, especially moist north- or east-facing slopes, wooded ledges and stream banks on neutral to slightly acid soil; 300--400 m; Ala., Ga., Ky., N.C., Tenn., Va., W.Va.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering mid spring (Apr--May).</phenology>
      <habitat>Rich mesic woodlands, especially moist north- or east-facing slopes, wooded ledges and stream banks on neutral to slightly acid soil;</habitat>
      <elevation>300--400 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Ala., Ga., Ky., N.C., Tenn., Va., W.Va.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>13.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Southern red trillium</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">Barksdale trillium</other_name>
  <discussion>Trillium sulcatum is present mainly on the Cumberland Plateau and is absent from the Great Smoky Mountains and the southern Blue Ridge Mountains.</discussion>
  <discussion>T. S. Patrick (1984) described Trillium sulcatum flowers as “relatively small and turned downward.” This is true of plants from the type locality; however, in most plants of the Cumberland Plateau, the flowers are quite large and flattened, and the petals are recurved distally and face outward.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Patrick, T. S. 1984. Trillium sulcatum (Liliaceae), a new species of the southern Appalachians. Brittonia 36: 26–36.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
