<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Charles J. Sheviak,Paul M. Catling,Susan J. Meades,Richard M. Bateman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ORCHIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="unknown" date="unknown">CRANICHIDEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">SPIRANTHINAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Necker ex Nevski" date="unknown">DACTYLORHIZA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trudy Bot. Inst. S.S.S.R., Ser. 1, Fl. Sist. Vyssh. Rast.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 332. 1937</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ORCHIDACEAE;tribe CRANICHIDEAE;subtribe SPIRANTHINAE;genus DACTYLORHIZA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek dactylos , finger, and rhiza , root, in reference to the fingerlike tuberoids of the more primitive species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>28.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Orchis</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 75 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Dactylorhiza is a taxonomically complex genus in which closely related species have been combined into species aggregates (P. Vermeulen 1947; R. M. Bateman et al. 1997). Recognition of the aggregate taxa alone reduces the number of species by more than half. Recent research synthesizing morphometric and allozyme data to circumscribe species (R. M. Bateman and I. Denholm 1983, 1985, 1989; M. Hédren 1996), and DNA sequences and chromosome studies to determine the relationships of those species (R. M. Bateman et al. 1997; A. M. Pridgeon et al. 1997), is shedding much light on the evolution of the genus. The diploid lineage (2n = 40) appears to have evolved in Asia, migrating and speciating to both the west and northeast. Several alloploidy events (hybridization followed by chromosome doubling) occurred recently in Europe, apparently between the distinct diploids D. fuchsii and D. incarnata. That generated a highly complex suite of poorly distinguishable “prospecies” of 2n = 80, treated as a single species by some authorities and as many species by others (L. V. Averyanov 1990). Of the two North American species, D. aristata is a native diploid originating during the northeasterly migration, and D. majalis is an allotetraploid that originated in Europe and presumably is naturalized in North America (H. J. Clase and S. J. Meades 1996).</discussion>
  <discussion>Despite an extensive literature, much taxonomic work still remains to be done.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Averyanov, L. V. 1990. A review of the genus Dactylorhiza. In: J. Arditti, ed. 1977+. Orchid Biology: Reviews and Perspectives. 7+ vols. Ithaca, N.Y. and New York. Vol. 5, pp. 159–206.  </reference>
    <reference>Bateman, R. M. and I. Denholm. 1983. A reappraisal of the British and Irish dactylorchids: 1. The tetraploid marsh orchids. Watsonia 14: 347–376.  </reference>
    <reference>Bateman, R. M. and I. Denholm. 1985. A reappraisal of the British and Irish dactylorchids: 2. The diploid marsh orchids. Watsonia 15: 321–355.  </reference>
    <reference>Bateman, R. M. and I. Denholm. 1989. A reappraisal of the British and Irish dactylorchids: 3. The spotted orchids. Watsonia 17: 319–349.  </reference>
    <reference>Bateman, R. M., A. M. Pridgeon, and M. W. Chase. 1997. Phylogenetics of subtribe Orchidinae (Orchidoideae, Orchidaceae) based on nuclear ITS sequences: 2. Infrageneric relationships and taxonomic revision to achieve monophyly of Orchis sensu stricto. Lindleyana 12: 113–141.   </reference>
    <reference>Hédren, M. 1996. Genetic differentiation, polyploidization and hybridization in northern European Dactylorhiza (Orchidaceae): Evidence from allozyme markers. Pl. Syst. Evol. 201: 31–55. </reference>
    <reference>Pridgeon, A. M. et al. 1997. Phylogenetics of subtribe Orchidinae (Orchidoideae, Orchidaceae) based on nuclear ITS sequences: 1. Intergeneric relationships and polyphyly of Orchis sensu lato. Lindleyana 12: 89–109.  </reference>
    <reference>Stace, C. A. 1991. New Flora of the British Isles. Cambridge and New York. Pp. 1166–1173.  </reference>
    <reference>Tyteca, D. and J.-L. Gathoye. 1993. On the morphological variability of Dactylorhiza praetermissa (Druce) Soó (Orchidaceae). Belg. J. Bot. 126: 81–99.  </reference>
    <reference>Vermeulen, P. 1947. Studies on Dactylorchids. Utrecht.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals and petals awned; lip often magenta- to red-spotted</description>
      <determination>1.  Dactylorhiza aristata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals and petals obtuse, hoodlike, or acute, not awned; lip with red-violet loops (continu-</description>
      <determination>2.  Dactylorhiza majalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
