<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>32.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>EPIPACTIS</genus_name><genus_authority>Zinn</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Cat. Pl. Hort. Gott.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>85. 1757</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Ancient Greek name used by Theophrastus for plant used to curdle milk]</etymology><conserved_name>name conserved</conserved_name><author>Paul Martin Brown</author><author>George W. Argus</author><description>Herbs perennial, terrestrial, glabrous or puberulent to glabrate. Roots from short rhizome, fibrous. Stems leafy. Leaves several, alternate, sheathing, plicate, grading into floral bracts. Inflorescences terminal racemes; floral bracts leaflike, often exceeding flowers. Flowers few to many, resupinate, pedicellate; perianth free, spreading or loosely connivent, subequal; sepals ovate to ovate-lanceolate, concave; petals often shorter than sepals; lip sessile at base of column, fleshy, divided into 2 parts by central constriction, proximal part (hypochile) deeply concave to saccate, distal part (epichile) triangular to oblanceolate, with pair of calli near base; column curved over lip, broadened distally, short; anther terminal, sessile; pollinia 4, mealy. Fruits capsules, pendent to spreading, obovoid to ellipsoid.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 25 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>Eurasia</global_distribution><global_distribution>North Africa.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip 3-lobed, distal part linear-oblanceolate to narrowly spatulate-oblanceolate; lateral</statement>
      <determination>2.  Epipactis gigantea</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip not 3-lobed, distal part triangular-ovate to broadly triangular; lateral sepals 6–13 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip 9–12 mm, distal part triangular-ovate, calli at base not rugose; ovary glabrous;</statement>
      <determination>3.  Epipactis helleborine</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip 5.5–6.5 mm, distal part broadly triangular, calli at base rugose; ovary tomentose;</statement>
      <determination>1.  Epipactis atrorubens</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
