<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>17.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Trillium</genus_name>
        <species_name>angustipetalum</species_name>
        <species_authority>(Torrey) J. D. Freeman</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Brittonia</publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>27: 55. 1975</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <common_name>Narrow-petaled trillium</common_name>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Trillium</genus_name>
        <species_name>sessile</species_name>
        <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
        <variety_name>angustipetalum</variety_name>
        <variety_authority>Torrey</variety_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Pacif. Railr. Rep. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>4(5): 151. 1857</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Trillium</genus_name>
        <species_name>giganteum</species_name>
        <species_authority>(Hooker &amp; Arnott) A. Heller</species_authority>
        <variety_name>angustipetalum</variety_name>
        <variety_authority>(Torrey) R. R. Gates</variety_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Plants tall, very robust. Rhizomes erect, brownish, thick, somewhat
        compressed-thickened, praemorse, not brittle. Scapes 1–2, round in cross section, 2.5–6 dm.
        Bracts held well above ground, spreading horizontally, subsessile; blade very sparsely
        mottled with dark greenish brown or rarely all green, mottling becoming obscure with age,
        broadly ovate, 10–22 × 8.7–15 cm, not glossy, often narrowed to falsely petiolate, very
        short, and narrowly cuneate base 10–20 mm, apex obtuse. Flower erect, odor spicy-musty,
        musty, or fetid; sepals conspicuous, spreading, often resting on bracts, maroon to green,
        linear to oblong-lanceolate, 35–47 × 8–10 mm, margins flat, entire, apex acute; petals
        long-lasting, erect, ± connivent, ± concealing stamens and ovary and partially obscuring
        stamens, dark purple to red-purple, not spirally twisted, veins obscure, linear, 5–10 ×
        0.7–1.4 cm, 8–10 times longer than wide, glossy, thick-textured, base linear, margins
        entire, at first flat but inrolling with age, apex variously acute-obtuse; stamens erect,
        12–22 mm; filaments dark maroon, 2–4 mm, slender, widest at base; anthers erect, straight,
        purple, 12–18 mm, dehiscence introrse; connectives purple, slightly extended 1–1.5 mm beyond
        anther sacs; ovary dark, ovoid-ellipsoid, 6-angled toward apex, 7.5–12 mm; stigmas erect,
        divergent-recurved, distinct, purple, sessile, awl-shaped, thickly subulate, 5 mm, thick,
        fleshy. Fruits dark purple, fragrance unknown, subglobose, 6-angled, almost winged, fleshy.
        2n = 10.</description>
    <phenology>spring</phenology>
    <phenology>summer</phenology>
    <phenology>jul</phenology>
    <phenology>aug</phenology>
    <phenology>mar</phenology>
    <phenology>apr</phenology>
    <phenology>may</phenology>
    <phenology>jun</phenology>
    <habitat>big-tree (sequoiadendron).groves and other mixed coniferous-deciduous
        flatwoods</habitat>
    <habitat>slightly damper depressions under maples and deciduous shrubs</habitat>
    <habitat>coastal mountains, oak (Quercus) groves in ravines and otherwise quite arid, almost
        treeless chaparral, wooded canyon slopes, dense woods near streams;</habitat> <elevation>30–200 m;</elevation>
    <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
    <discussion>Trillium angustipetalum occurs in the Sierra Nevada from Fresno County north to
        Placer County (J. D. Freeman 1975). It is disjunct in the coastal mountains and hills of
        Santa Barbara and San Luis Obispo counties.</discussion>
    <discussion>B. D. Ness (1993) listed Trillium kurabayashii as a synonym of T. angustipetalum. In
        bract orientation, color, and texture, and in petal shape, the two are quite different and
        certainly not the same species. Cytologist Masataka Kurabayashi found chromosomal
        differences between the two species (reported by J. D. Freeman 1975).</discussion>
</treatment>
