<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>3.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Listera</genus_name>
    <species_name>auriculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Wiegand</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>26: 166, plate 356, fig. 2. 1899</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Auricled twayblade</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Bifolium</genus_name>
    <species_name>auriculatum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Wiegand) Nieuwland</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Neottia</genus_name>
    <species_name>auriculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Wiegand) Szlachetko</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Ophrys</genus_name>
    <species_name>auriculata</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Wiegand) House</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 5–25 cm. Stems pale green, succulent, glabrous. Leaves: blade pale green,
    suborbiculate to suborbiculate-ovate or elliptic-ovate, 2.5–6 × 1.5–4.2 cm, apex subobtuse.
    Inflorescences 5–20-flowered, lax, 20–100 mm; floral bracts broadly elliptic to
    oblong-lanceolate, 2–7 × 1–2 mm, apex obtuse; peduncle and rachis densely glandular-puberulent;
    bracts, pedicel, and ovary glabrous to rarely glabrate. Flowers pale green to blue-green, fading
    whitish with age; pedicels stout, 2.5–5 mm, glabrous, rarely glabrate; sepals and petals
    reflexed away from column and lip; dorsal sepal elliptic-obovate, 3–3.5 × 1.5–2 mm, apex
    subobtuse; lateral sepals elliptic, oblong, or ovate-lanceolate, strongly falcate, 3–4 × 1–1.5
    mm, apex subobtuse to acute; petals linear-oblong to linear, falcate, 3–3.7 × 0.8 mm, apex
    obtuse; lip obovate to oblong, base of lip with auricles curving around and clasping base of
    column, apex slightly expanded, cleft approximately 1/5–1/3 its length, forming 2 broadly
    rounded lobes, margins ciliate; disc 3-veined with lateral veins branched, base with ridge in
    center; column arcuate, 2.5–3.3 × 1 mm, dilated at distal end. Capsules horizontal to
    semi-erect, ellipsoid, 8 × 4 mm.</description>
  <phenology>jun</phenology>
  <phenology>summer</phenology>
  <phenology>jul</phenology>
  <phenology>aug</phenology>
  <habitat>alluvial soils in low, moist, hardwood forests or mixed hardwood-coniferous
    forests</habitat>
  <habitat>shrub swamps</habitat>
  <habitat>sphagnum bogs</habitat>
  <habitat>requires soil that remains cool throughout summer, with high degree of acidity;</habitat> <elevation>0–1000
    m;</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>Man.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.B.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.S.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>P.E.I.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mich.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Minn.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.H.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Vt.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wis.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Leaves of Listera auriculata forma trifolia (Lepage) Lepage are three in a
    whorl.</discussion>
  <discussion>Listera auriculata crosses with L. convallarioides to produce a natural hybrid L.
    ×veltmanii Case, originally discovered by H. S. Veltman and F. W. Case in 1962. The hybrid is
    almost exactly intermediate between its putative parents, and it is usually associated with one
    or the other parent (P. M. Catling 1976). Occasionally it appears to backcross with the parent
    species. Plants of the hybrid, although intermediate between the two putative parents,
    frequently differ from the parents in being much taller (to 2.5 dm). Also, the glandular
    pubescence of the pedicels and ovaries of the hybrid is shorter and sparser than that of the
    rachis; in L. convallarioides the glandular pubescence is as dense and long on pedicels as on
    the rachis, continuing on the ribs of the ovary. Pedicels and ovaries of L. auriculata are
    glabrous. The hybrids may be distinguished by using the following key.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip not clawed, sessile or essentially so; auricles or lobes at base of lip curving
        around and clasping</statement>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Lip clawed, not sessile; auricles or lobes absent or projecting laterally away from
        column.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Auricles or lobes at base of lip absent</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Auricles or lobes present at base of lip, projecting laterally away from
        column</statement>
    </key_statement>
    <key_discussion>Listera ×veltmanii flowers in July and August. Its habitat is intermediate
      between those typical of the parents and apparently is often disturbed; 500–800 m. It is known
      from New Brunswick, Newfoundland and Labrador, Quebec, Ontario, Michigan, and
      Wisconsin.</key_discussion>
  </key>
</treatment>
