<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Epidendrum</genus_name><species_name>acunae</species_name><species_authority>Dressler</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Amer. Orchid Soc. Bull.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>28: 358, figs. 1–4. 1959</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><past_name>acuñae</past_name><common_name>Galé’s epidendrum</common_name><description>Plants hanging, 50–160 cm. Roots basal or from proximal branches, 2–3 mm diam. Stems branched, sinuous, terete, main stem to 160 cm, leaves 100–120 mm × 12–22 mm; vegetative branches to 60 cm, leaves 58–110 × 10–20 mm; flowering branchlets 3–8 cm, leaves 20–60 × 9–13 mm, flowering branchlets produced from both main stem and vegetative branches. Leaves many, distributed throughout stems; petiole to 4 cm; blade narrowly lanceolate, 2-lobed, fleshy-leathery. Inflorescences distichous-imbricate; peduncle 1 cm; bracts 2–3, conduplicate, 8–18 mm. Flowers 1–3, not resupinate, simultaneous, brownish green; sepals spreading, lanceolate, abaxially keeled, many veined, 12–21 × 3–6 mm, apex acute; petals partly open, elliptic, many veined, 12–18 × 2.5–5 mm, apex obtuse to rounded; lip cordate, callus V-shaped, prolonged into central keel, 9–14 × 5–9 mm; column suffused with purple, 5 mm; clinandrium erose, short; anther obovate, 2-cleft; ovary 15–20 mm. Capsules ovoid, body 18–24 × 10–12 mm, tapered beak 5–6 mm.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>epiphytic on main trunks of larger trees in fahkahatchee swamp</habitat><elevation>0–30 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies (Cuba)</global_distribution><global_distribution>Central America.</global_distribution><discussion>Epidendrum acunae, described from Cuba, was discovered in Florida in 1962, as a single population, and it has apparently become extirpated because of overcollecting (R. Sauleda, pers. comm.). Only one specimen from Florida has been found (Sauleda 942, FTG), of which a photograph of the live flower is at AMO, apart from the record in C. A. Luer (1972). The description has been prepared from Luer and from Cuban and Mexican material.</discussion></treatment>
