<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Paul M. Catling,Charles J. Sheviak</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">orchidaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="1818">TIPULARIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 195. 1818</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family orchidaceae;genus TIPULARIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin tippula , crane-fly, alluding to the resemblance of the flowers to crane-flies]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, terrestrial. Roots 3–10, from bases of newer corms, spongy. Stems produced in summer, solitary, subapical, opposite leaf, arising from ovate, angular corms. Leaves produced in autumn, persisting over winter, withering in spring, solitary; blade broad, ovate, pleated. Inflorescences lax racemes. Flowers resupinate, bilaterally asymmetric; lip with long, free basal spur; column slightly arcuate; anther terminal, deciduous but retained on pollinaria for short time; pollinia 4, in 2 pairs, yellow, attached to elastic caudicle 1 mm with basal viscidium; stigma entire; rostellum a 2-fid flap enclosing viscidium. Fruits capsules, pendent, ovoid. Seeds 0.5–0.6 mm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">1 in e North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">1 in the Himalayas</description>
  <description type="distribution">1 in Japan.</description>
  <number>52.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Crane-fly orchid</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Catling, P. M. and V. R. Catling. 1990. Anther cap retention in Tipularia discolor. Lindleyana 6: 113–116.  </reference>
    <reference>Snow, A. A. and D. F. Whigham. 1989. Costs of flower and fruit production in Tipularia discolor (Orchidaceae). Ecology 70: 1286–1293.  </reference>
    <reference>Stoutamire, W. P. 1978. Pollination of Tipularia discolor, an orchid with modified symmetry. Amer. Orchid Soc. Bull. 47: 413–415.  </reference>
    <reference>Whigham, D. F. and M. McWethy. 1980. Studies on the pollination ecology of Tipularia discolor (Orchidaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 67: 550–555.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
