<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Lawrence K. Magrath</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ORCHIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="unknown" date="unknown">EPIDENDREAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subtribe" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">PLEUROTHALLIDINAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Richard" date="unknown">LIPARIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>De Orchid. Eur.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21, 30, 38. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ORCHIDACEAE;tribe EPIDENDREAE;subtribe PLEUROTHALLIDINAE;genus LIPARIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek liparos , fat, greasy, or shining, referring to the almost oily feel and luster of the leaves typical of plants in this genus]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, terrestrial [lithophytic or epiphytic]. Roots slender, fibrous; pseudobulbs green, conic, ovoid, or ellipsoid, slightly compressed, soft (2 pseudobulbs typically present, parent pseudobulb enveloped in old leaf-bases, connected laterally by short rhizome to daughter pseudobulb, which gives rise to current year’s stem, parent pseudobulb often retaining dried stem of previous year). Stems somewhat angled, slender, glabrous; cauline bracts 2(–3), enclosing base of stem. Leaves 2 or 3–7, basal, sheathing pseudobulb and proximal part of stem, conduplicate or plicate, glabrous. Inflorescences terminal, 3–40-flowered racemes, lax; peduncle and rachis glabrous; floral bracts subulate to triangular-lanceolate. Flowers resupinate, maroon-purple, yellowish green, or green, pedicellate; dorsal sepal oblong-elliptic, linear-oblong, oblong-lanceolate, or lanceolate, margins revolute, apex obtuse to acute; lateral sepals oblong-lanceolate, lanceolate, ovate-oblong, or elliptic, falcate or not, margins revolute or involute, apex obtuse to acute; petals filiform, linear, linear-oblanceolate, or narrowly spatulate, tubular or strongly revolute; lip strongly arcuate-recurved, obcordate, oblong-flabellate, or suborbiculate, base broadly cuneate, slightly auriculate, apex emarginate or subtruncate, mucronate or not, apical margins erose-serrulate to crenulate-wavy; column arcuate, slender to stout, weakly to strongly winged at apex; anther apical, anther cap yellow or green; pollinia 2 pairs, yellow, waxy. Fruits capsules, erect, ellipsoid to ovoid, obscurely to prominently winged, glabrous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>53.</number>
  <discussion>Species 250 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 3–7, membranaceous, plicate; anthers bright green; pedicels stout</description>
      <determination>3.  Liparis nervosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 2, succulent, conduplicate; anthers yellow; pedicels slender.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip 8–12 mm, mauve purplish, rarely green; column 3–4 mm; pedicels of fruiting</description>
      <determination>1.  Liparis liliifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Lip 4–5.5 mm, green or yellowish green to yellowish white; column 2–3 mm; pedicels of</description>
      <determination>2.  Liparis loeselii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
