<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>24.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Trillium</genus_name><species_name>gracile</species_name><species_authority>J. D. Freeman</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sida</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3: 289. 1969</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Slender trillium</common_name><common_name>graceful trillium</common_name><description>Rhizomes horizontal, brownish, thick, short, praemorse, not brittle. Scapes 1–3, round in cross section, 1.6–3.5 dm, slender, glabrous. Bracts held well above ground, sessile; blade mottled with darker green blotches, mottling becoming obscure with age, elliptic-ovate to obovate, 6–8.5 × 2.6–4 cm, base rounded, apex obtuse or rounded, rarely acute. Flower odor musty or funguslike; sepals displayed above bracts, bases at right angle to scape axis, widely spreading with recurved tips, dark purple on adaxial surface, lanceolate to oblong, 20–25 × 4–5 mm, margins entire, apex obtuse; petals long-lasting, erect, weakly connivent, at least partially obscuring stamens, dark purple or maroon, rarely yellow, not spirally twisted, linear-elliptic to oblanceolate, 2–4 × 0.3–0.8 cm, ± thick-textured, margins entire, flat, apex acute; stamens erect, 12–16.5 mm; filaments purple, 2–3 mm, slender; anthers erect, straight, purple to yellow, 10–15 mm, slender, dehiscence introrse; connectives straight, extending 0.1–1 mm beyond anther sacs; ovary purple, ovoid, 3-angled, 4–11 mm; stigmas erect, spreading-recurved, distinct, purple to whitish, sessile, subulate, 2–4 mm, fleshy, thickened basally. Fruits dark greenish purple, fragrance not reported, ovoid, swollen enough to conceal its 3-angled nature, 1 cm, pulpy, moist.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><habitat>mature pine and hardwood forests</habitat><habitat>banks and ridges of dissected stream- beds</habitat><habitat>rather dense shade</habitat><habitat>low sandy flatwoods</habitat><elevation>0–10 m;</elevation><us_distribution>La.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution></treatment>
