<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>25.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Trillium</genus_name>
        <species_name>kurabayashii</species_name>
        <species_authority>J. D. Freeman</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Brittonia</publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>27: 56, fig. 12. 1975</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Rhizomes horizontal, brownish, thick, praemorse, not brittle. Scapes often 2 from
        single terminal bud, round in cross section, 2.5–5.5 dm, stout, glabrous. Bracts held well
        above ground, sessile; blade bright green (in early anthesis rather succulent in
        appearance), usually well-marked with lighter and darker green spots, occasionally obscurely
        or scarcely mottled, mottling becoming obscure with age, ovate to broadly ovate, 11–18 ×
        12–17 cm, somewhat glossy, apex acuminate. Flower odor spicy in fresh flowers, becoming
        fetid in older flowers; sepals displayed above bracts, spreading, divergent, green,
        purple-streaked, lanceolate, 40–75 × 10–14 mm, margins entire, apex acute to round-acute;
        petals long-lasting, conspicuous, spreading-erect to erect, tips incurving slightly, ±
        connivent, partially to completely concealing stamens and ovary, glossy dark maroon-red or
        purple, not spirally twisted, flat, oblanceolate, 5.5–11 × 2–3.5 cm, widest at or below
        middle, glossy, thick-textured, cuneate basally, margins ± flat, entire, apex round-acute;
        stamens erect, straight, 15–26 mm, slightly concealing ovary; filaments dark purple, 2–4 mm;
        anthers dark maroon, 13–24 mm, dehiscence introrse; connectives straight, barely extended
        beyond anther sacs; ovary inconspicuous, purple, ovoid, round to 6-angled, 8–15 mm; stigmas
        erect, distinct, subulate, 6–8 mm, fleshy, thickened basally. Fruits dark reddish purple,
        ovoid to ellipsoid or weakly angled, 20–50 mm, fleshy.</description>
    <phenology>spring</phenology>
    <phenology>mar</phenology>
    <phenology>apr</phenology>
    <phenology>may</phenology>
    <habitat>rich, moist conifer-hardwood forest</habitat>
    <habitat>slopes</habitat>
    <habitat>especially lower slopes</habitat>
    <habitat>predominantly deciduous flat woods along streams</habitat>
    <habitat>edges of sequoia groves</habitat>
    <habitat>and alder, vine maple, and fern thickets along streams</habitat>
    <habitat>especially older, higher flood terraces</habitat>
    <habitat>not the lowest and wettest</habitat>
    <habitat>at higher elevations, both in forests and in open grassy meadows with scattered oak
        trees;</habitat> <elevation>20–500+ m;</elevation>
    <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
</treatment>
