<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">trillium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Harbison" date="1901">ludovicianum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Biltmore Bot. Stud.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 23. 1901</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus trillium;species ludovicianum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes ± horizontal, brownish, short, thick, praemorse, not brittle. Scapes 1–3, round in cross section, 1.4–2.6 dm, ± slender, glabrous. Bracts held well above ground, sessile; blade strongly mottled in dark and bronzy green, often with central light strip, mottling becoming somewhat obscure with age, lanceolate-ovate, 5.3–9.5 × 2.3–5 cm, not glossy, margins of distal 1/3 convex-curved to apex, apex rounded-acute. Flower erect, odor of carrion; sepals displayed above bracts, spreading, green, lanceolate-oblanceolate, 19–35 × 2.7–4 mm, margins entire, apex rounded or acute to sometimes weakly reflexed; petals long-lasting, faintly introrsely curved-erect-spreading, weakly connivent, ± concealing stamens and ovary, dark maroon-brown, purplish, or dull greenish, or 2-colored, basal portion purple, distal portion grayish green, not spirally twisted, oblanceolate-linear, 3.5–5.5 × 0.4–0.8 cm, thick-textured, thickened and weakly clawed basally, margins entire, apex acute; stamens erect, straight, 10–18 mm; filaments olive-orange, 2–3 mm, widened basally; anthers erect, straight, olive to orange, 7–20 mm, slender, dehiscence latrorse; connectives olive to orange, straight, scarcely extended beyond anther sac; ovary purple, ovoid, 6-angled, 8–9 mm; stigmas erect, with spreading or coiled tips, distinct, pale purple, subulate, 3–6 mm, ± fleshy. Fruits dark purplish green, little or no odor, ovoid, 6-angled, pulpy.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late winter--early spring (early Mar--Apr).</description>
  <description type="habitat">Low flatwoods, floodplains along streams, steep ravine slopes leading to floodplains, mixed pine-beech woods;</description>
  <description type="elevation">50--500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">La., Miss.</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Louisiana trillium</other_name>
  <discussion>The range of Trillium ludovicianum is near to that of T. cuneatum in Mississippi, and the two appear to intergrade.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
