<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>31.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Trillium</genus_name><species_name>petiolatum</species_name><species_authority>Pursh</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 244. 1814</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Long-petioled trillium</common_name><common_name>purple trillium</common_name><common_name>round-leaved trillium</common_name><description>Rhizomes ± erect, often very deep, praemorse. Scapes typically 1, vertical but mostly subterranean, round in cross section, 0.4–1.7 dm, robust, glabrous. Bracts just at or slightly above soil, long-petiolate; blade medium green, not mottled, ovate to elliptic, 7–14 × 5.5–10.2 cm, not glossy, apex obtuse or rounded; petiole arising from scape apex at or near ground surface, 5–12 cm; bract and petiole strongly resembling leaves of Plantago. Flower in axil of bracts at or near ground level, ± erect, odor unknown; sepals erect to widely spreading, often weakly recurved near middle, green, oblong-elliptic to oblanceolate, 22–47 × 7–10 mm, margins entire, apex acute; petals long-lasting, ± connivent, ± concealing stamens and ovary, or erect-spreading early then ± connivent, erect to incurved, light maroon-red, purple, or greenish to yellowish, not spirally twisted, flat, linear-lanceolate, 3–5.5 × 0.4–1 cm, thick-textured, margins entire, apex acute; stamens erect, (15–) 22–30 mm; filaments olive, (3–)5–7 mm, slender; anthers straight, brown or olive, 16–20 mm, slender, dehiscence latrose; connectives yellow or orange, ± not extending beyond anther sacs; ovary white, greenish, purplish distally, ovoid, sharply angled, 4–9 mm; stigmas erect, divergent, distinct, purple or olive, linear-subulate, 7–20 mm, apex somewhat recurved. Fruits fragrance not reported, ovoid, strongly angled/winged, ca. 1 cm, pulpy, moist. 2n = 10.</description><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><habitat>lower rocky hillsides just above stream flats</habitat><habitat>under brush</habitat><habitat>edges of coniferous and deciduous forests</habitat><habitat>open grassy glades</habitat><habitat>river-flats</habitat><habitat>wet</habitat><habitat>seasonally swampy ground and edges of sloughs</habitat><elevation>400–1400 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution></treatment>
