<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Frederick H. Utech</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">LILIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey" date="unknown">SCOLIOPUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pacif. Railr. Rep.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4(5): 145, plate 22. 1857</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family LILIACEAE;genus SCOLIOPUS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek skolios , crooked, and - pous , footed, alluding to the tortuous, recurved pedicels]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, with short, knotty rhizomes; roots contractile. Stems subterranean, simple, vertical, short. Leaves 2–3(–4), petiolate or subsessile, sheathing at base; blade dark green distally, paler proximally, sometimes mottled with purple, elliptic to oblong, apex obtuse. Inflorescences umbellate, with several axillary fascicles of elongate, twisting pedicels. Flowers showy, odor unpleasant; perianth of 2 dissimilar whorls of tepals, outer spreading or recurving, distinct, petaloid, ovate to lanceolate to oblanceolate, with oblong gland basally, inner erect, distinct, linear, converging over pistil; stamens 3, opposite outer tepals; anthers versatile, 2-locular, oblong, extrorse; ovary superior, 1-locular, strongly 3-angled, placentation parietal; style erect, short; stigmas persistent, 3, spreading to recurved, linear, inner surface deeply channelled, ovules 20–40, in 2 rows on each placenta. Fruits capsular, brownish purple, oblong-lanceolate, strongly 3-angled, thin-walled, opening irregularly by decay, beaked by persistent style and stigmas. Seeds slightly curved, oblong, eliaosome present. x = 7, 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <number>17.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Slink pod</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">fetid adder’s-tongue</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">slink-lily</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Berg, R. Y. 1959. Seed dispersal, morphology and taxonomic position of Scoliopus, Liliaceae. Skr. Norske Vidensk.-Akad. Oslo, Mat.-Naturvidensk. Kl. 1959(4): 1–56.  </reference>
    <reference>Cave, M. S. 1966. The chromosomes of Scoliopus (Liliaceae). Madroño 18: 211–213.  </reference>
    <reference>Utech, F. H. 1979b. Floral vascular anatomy of Scoliopus bigelovii Torrey (Liliaceae-Parideae = Trilliaceae) and tribal note. Ann. Carnegie Mus. 48: 43–71.  </reference>
    <reference>Utech, F. H. 1992. Biology of Scoliopus (Liliaceae). I. Systematics and phytogeography. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 79: 126–142.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 14–24 cm; pedicel 11–22 cm; outer tepals 12.5–19 mm; style 4.5–6 mm</description>
      <determination>1.  Scoliopus bigelovii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 8–14 cm; pedicel 6–10 cm; outer tepals 6.5–10 mm; style 2–2.5 mm</description>
      <determination>2.  Scoliopus hallii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
