<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>12.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Calochortus</genus_name><species_name>subalpinus</species_name><species_authority>Piper</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>11: 195. 1906</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Calochortus</genus_name><species_name>lobbii</species_name><species_authority>(Baker) Purdy</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems usually not branching, straight or flexuous, often scapelike, 0.5–3 dm. Leaves: basal 1–3 dm × 2–15 mm, usually equaling or exceeding stem length; blade flat, adaxial surface glabrous. Inflorescences subumbellate, 1–5-flowered; bracts 2–several, lanceolate to linear, unequal, 1–5 cm, apex acuminate; peduncle slender, becoming stouter, deflexed in fruit. Flowers erect or spreading; perianth open, campanulate; sepals typically with purple glandular blotch near base, oblong-lanceolate, shorter than petals, adaxial surface minutely hairy, apex acute to acuminate; petals yellowish white, sometimes lavender-tinged, frequently with narrow purple crescent distal to gland, broadly obovate, cuneate, moderately bearded nearly to apex, adaxial surface densely hairy, margins fringed, apex obtuse or acute; glands transversely oblong, arched upward, ± deeply depressed, bordered proximally by narrow, ascending, deeply fringed membrane, distally by narrow, crenate membranes, gland surface with rather long, slender hairs toward distal portion; anthers lanceolate, apex long-apiculate. Capsules nodding, 3-winged, ellipsoid, apex usually acute. Seeds pale yellow. 2n = 20.</description><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>open forest in loose volcanic soils</habitat><elevation>1000–2200 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution></treatment>
