<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Frederick H. Utech,Loran C. Anderson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">LILIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="McDaniel" date="unknown">HARPEROCALLIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Arnold Arbor.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>49: 36, figs. 1, 2. 1968</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family LILIACEAE;genus HARPEROCALLIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Roland MacMillan Harper, 1878–1966, southeastern American botanist, and Greek kallos , beautiful, alluding to the attractive flower]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from slender, nodose rhizomes with scarious scale leaves. Stems erect, simple, bracteate; bracts 2–5, much reduced, widely spaced, chaffy. Leaves basal, equitant, simple, sheathing; blade unifacial, striate, stiff; sheath margin scarious. Inflorescences terminal, erect, 1-flowered, bracteolate; bracteoles (2–)3(–4), in epicalyx, distinct, deltate-rhombic, small. Flowers: tepals persistent, 6, spreading, erect in fruit, distinct, oblanceolate, apex acute; stamens 6, hypogynous; filaments distinct; anthers basifixed, linear-lanceolate, with short appendages, introrse; gynoecium 3(–6)-carpellate, distally apocarpous; ovary superior, sessile, tuberculate; intercarpellary nectary present; styles 3(–6), slightly recurved; stigmas capitate. Fruits capsular, ellipsoid, prominently tuberculate, subtended by persistent tepals, dehiscence septicidal, then adaxially loculicidal. Seeds pale yellow, narrowly fusiform, straight or curved, short-appendaged at both ends. x = 15, 16.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Florida.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Harper’s beauty</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Discovered in 1968, Harperocallis is the only genus endemic to the Apalachicola River region of Florida’s western panhandle, where numerous endemic species occur (D. B. Ward [1979]). Carpel numbers often greater than 3, to 6, are frequently encountered (J. D. Ambrose 1975, 1980; L. C. Anderson and G. L. Smith 1994). The capsule is primarily septicidal, similar to those in Tofieldia, Triantha, and Pleea (J. D. Ambrose 1975, 1980; F. H. Utech 1993), and not simply loculicidal as originally described (S. McDaniel 1968; R. K. Godfrey [1979]).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Godfrey, R. K. [1979.] Endangered: Harper’s beauty. In: D. B. Ward, ed. [1979.] Rare and Endangered Biota of Florida. Vol. 5. Plants. Gainesville. Pp. 32–33.  Mc</reference>
    <reference>Daniel, S. 1968. Harperocallis, a new genus of the Liliaceae from Florida. J. Arnold Arbor. 49: 35–40.  </reference>
    <reference>Utech, F. H. 1993. Floral vascular anatomy of Harperocallis flava McDaniel and its systematic relationship within the Tofieldieae (Liliaceae). [Abstract.] In: International Botanical Congress. 1993. Abstracts. XV International Botanical Congress. Congress Center of Pacifico Yokohama, Japan, August 28 to September 3, 1993. [Tokyo.] P. 207.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
