<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>PLEEA</genus_name><genus_authority>Michaux</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 247. 1803</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[for Auguste Plée, 1787–1825, French traveller in the New World]</etymology><common_name>Rush-featherling</common_name><author>John G. Packer</author><description>Herbs, perennial, rhizomatous, glabrous. Leaves 2-ranked, equitant, mostly basal; blade linear. Inflorescences terminal, racemose, open, bracteate, bracteolate; bracteoles connate in epicalyx. Flowers arising singly; tepals persistent, 6, in 2 somewhat dissimiliar series, distinct; stamens 9(–10), 2 opposite each outer tepal, 1 opposite each inner; filaments dilated basally, flattened; anthers versatile, 2-locular, introrse, without appendages; ovary superior, stipitate, apocarpous basally, glabrous; intercarpellary nectary present; styles 3. Fruits capsular, ovoid to broadly ellipsoid, glabrous, dehiscence septicidal, then adaxially loculicidal. Seeds appendaged. x =15.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America.</global_distribution><discussion>F. H. Utech (1978, 1979) clearly demonstrated the relationship of Pleea to Tofieldia sensu lato and reassigned the only species of the former to the latter. Morphologically, though, P. tenuifolia is a very distinctive species and, while it shares characteristics with both Tofieldia and Triantha, it is not in any way an intermediate.</discussion><references>
    <reference>  Utech, F. H. 1978. Floral vascular anatomy of Pleea tenuifolia Michx. (Liliaceae-Tofieldieae) and its reassignment to Tofieldia. Ann. Carnegie Mus. 47: 423–454.  Utech, F. H. 1979. Karyotype analysis, palynology, and external seed morphology of Tofieldia tenuifolia (Michx.) Utech (Liliaceae-Tofieldieae). Ann. Carnegie Mus. 48: 171–184.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
