<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>TRIANTHA</genus_name><genus_authority>(Nuttall) Baker</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>J. Linn. Soc., Bot.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>17: 490. 1879</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek tri- , three-, and anthos , flower, alluding to the flowers aggregated in threes]</etymology><author>John G. Packer</author><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Tofieldia</genus_name><genus_authority>Hudson</genus_authority><section_name>Triantha</section_name><section_authority>Nuttall</section_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 235. 1818</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, perennial, rhizomatous. Stems glandular and/or glandular-pubescent. Leaves mostly basal with 0–3 towards stem base, 2-ranked, equitant; blade linear. Inflorescences terminal, racemose, open or dense and spikelike, elongating in fruit, bracteate, bracteolate; bracteoles connate in epicalyx. Flowers borne in clusters of 2–7; tepals persistent, 6, in 2 somewhat dissimiliar series, distinct; stamens 6; filaments strongly flattened, dilated basally; anthers basifixed, 2-locular, introrse, without appendages; ovary superior, stipitate, apocarpous basally, glabrous; intercarpellary nectary present; styles 3. Fruits capsular, ovoid to broadly ellipsoid or cylindrical, glabrous, dehiscence septicidal, then adaxially loculicidal. Seeds appendaged. x = 15.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 4 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Japan.</global_distribution><discussion>Recognition here of the genus Triantha follows J. G. Baker (1879) and R. R. Gates (1918); see J. G. Packer (1993). R. W. Cruden (1991) provided cladistic evidence supporting this segregation from Tofieldia.</discussion><discussion>In the absence of any clear understanding of evolutionary relationships within Triantha, the species are here listed alphabetically.</discussion><references>
    <reference> Hitchcock, C. L. 1944. The Tofieldia glutinosa complex of western North America. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 31: 487–498.</reference>
    <reference> Packer, J. G. 1993. Two new combinations in Triantha (Liliaceae). Novon 3: 278–279.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Styles connate basally into column 1 / 4 – 2 / 3 their length; capsules hard, ± equaling or slightly</statement>
      <determination>3.  Triantha racemosa</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Styles distinct to base, not forming column; capsules chartaceous and easily ruptured, considerably longer than tepals and not enclosed by them.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Seed coat present; inflorescence sometimes forming globose head (subsp. occidentalis ); glandular hairs on stem below inflorescence sometimes uniformly 4–6 times longer than</statement>
      <determination>2.  Triantha occidentalis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Seed coat absent; inflorescence never forming globose head; glandular hairs on stem below inflorescence never uniformly 4–6 times longer than wide; widespread in Canada,</statement>
      <determination>1.  Triantha glutinosa</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
