<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">LILIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lilium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">superbum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 1: 434. 1762</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family LILIACEAE;genus Lilium;species superbum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lilium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">canadense</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="(Linnaeus) Baker" date="unknown">superbum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lilium;species canadense;subspecies superbum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lilium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Roane &amp; J. N. Henry" date="unknown">fortunofulgidum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lilium;species fortunofulgidum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lilium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Roane &amp; J. N. Henry" date="unknown">gazarubrum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lilium;species gazarubrum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lilium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Roane &amp; J. N. Henry" date="unknown">mary-henryae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lilium;species mary-henryae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>16.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Turk’s-cap lily</other_name>
  <discussion>The largest Lilium east of the Rocky Mountains and the commonest over most of its
        range, the Turk’s-cap lily is a familiar sight throughout much of the southern Appalachians
        and along the northern Atlantic coastal plain. Flowers are rather variable; those in the
        north are sometimes floridly colored with dark purple bases on the peri-anth parts. The
        single report from Vermont (F. C. Seymour 1993) remains unconfirmed; however, recent
        collections from Washington Parish in Louisiana, Perry County in Missouri, and Bamberg
        County in the coastal plain of South Carolina extend the range of this species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Lilium superbum shares distinctive features with L. michauxii, L. pyrophilum, and L.
        iridollae that indicate a close relationship and are diagnostically useful, namely paired
        ridges on the backs of the sepals and buds that are triangular in cross section. None has
        the red style characteristic of the other eastern pendent lily clade (L. michiganense, L.
        canadense, and L. grayi) centered to the northwest, and only L. iridollae sometimes has the
        leaf margins and veins roughened abaxially as is characteristic of L. canadense and its
        close relatives.</discussion>
  <discussion>Common inheritance of a suite of unique, derived features and peripheral allopatric
        distributions suggest that Lilium pyrophilum and L. iridollae may be geographical isolates
        of broadly distributed L. superbum ancestral stock; both restricted species occur in
        specialized wetland habitats. Geography aside, the three are unequivocally distinguished
        only by various combinations of leaf and bulb characteristics, flower color, habitat, and
        blooming time. However, the overall degree of separation is comparable to that between many
        other species in the genus. Lilium superbum blooms the earliest, is the largest, and has the
        most numerous and largest flowers, and the long, narrow leaves in many whorls are
        distinctive. Lilium michauxii overlaps in range with these three species but is easily
        separated morphologically and ecologically.</discussion>
  <discussion>Lilium superbum is pollinated primarily by the swallowtail butterflies that are
        common within its range, among them the spicebush (Papilio troilus Linnaeus, family
        Papilionidae), pipevine (Battus philenor Linnaeus), and eastern tiger (Papilio glaucus
        Linnaeus). Great spangled fritillaries [Speyeria cybele (Fabricius), family Nymphalidae]
        also visit the Turk’s-cap lily (R. M. Adams and W. J. Dress 1982).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
