<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>James L. Reveal,Frederick H. Utech</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall ex A. Gray" date="1837">LEUCOCRINUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Lyceum Nat. Hist. New York</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 108, 110. 1837</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus LEUCOCRINUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek leucos , white, and krinon , lily]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, acaulescent, glabrous, from short, deeply buried, fleshy roots. Leaves few, tufted, each tuft surrounded basally by membranous sheaths; blade linear. Inflorescences umbellike, central clusters at ground level. Flowers rather showy, fragrant; tepals 6, connate below middle, white, narrowly oblong, equal; perianth tube long, slender; limb lobes spreading; stamens 6, inserted near apex of perianth tube; filaments filiform, shorter than perianth lobes; anthers subversatile, often strongly curved or coiled after dehiscence, dehiscence introrse; ovary subterranean, 3-locular, ovoid, septal nectaries present; style filiform, elongate, 3-fid, lobes short; pedicel articulate, arising directly from rootstock, ebracteate. Fruits capsular, subterranean, obovoid, 3-angled, dehiscence loculicidal. Seeds black, angled. x = 11, 13, 14.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: w United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>w United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>38.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sand-lily</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">star-lily</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Molecular evidence (A. W. Meerow et al. 1999; M. F. Fay et al. 2000) indicates that Leucocrinum is most closely related to Echeandia.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Ornduff, R. and M. S. Cave. 1975. Geography of pollen and chromosomal heteromorphism in Leucocrinum montanum (Liliaceae). Madroño 23: 65–67.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
