<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Frederick H. Utech</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Lamarck ex Jussieu" date="1789">DIANELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>41. 1789</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus DIANELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin Diana , Roman sylvan goddess, and - ella , diminutive suffix, alluding to the forest habitat and small stature]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, evergreen, scapose, mat-forming, from stout, creeping, scaly rhizomes with fibrous, tuberous roots. Leaves basal, radical, distichous, crowded, sheathing, firm to subcoriaceous; blade linear to broadly ensiform, basal sheaths connate into short tubes, margins entire or serrulate, apex obtuse. Scape elongate, 0.5–1 m. Inflorescences paniculate, loosely branching with short, terminal racemes, bracteate; bracts small. Flowers nodding to ascending; tepals 6, persistent, withering, distinct, subequal, narrowly oblong to ovate, 3–7-veined; stamens 6, distinct; filaments barely adnate to tepal bases, thickened distally; anthers basifixed, dehiscence extrorse, opening by terminal pores that become longitudinal slits; ovary superior, 3-locular, septal nectaries present; style filiform; stigma minute, capitate; pedicel slender, articulate distally. Fruits rather long-persistent, baccate, blue to bluish purple, ovoid-globose. Seeds black, lustrous, ovate, somewhat flattened. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia</description>
  <description type="distribution">and Polynesia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 12–20 (1 in the flora): introduced; tropical Africa, Asia, Australia, and Polynesia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 12–20 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; tropical Africa, Asia, Australia, and Polynesia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>41.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Flax-lily</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 12–20 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Schlittler, J. 1940. Monographie der Liliaceengattung Dianella Lam. Mitt. Bot. Mus. Univ. Zürich 163: 1–283.  </reference>
    <reference>Schlittler, J. 1948. Unsere gegenwäertige Kenntnis über die Liliaceengattung Dianella in Malesien. Blumea 6: 200–228.  </reference>
    <reference>Schlittler, J. 1957. Die Verbreitung der Liliaceengattung Dianella Lam. in Zusammenhang mit der Organdifferenzierung und der Arealbildung. Mitt. Bot. Mus. Univ. Zürich 207: 1–38.  </reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
