<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1762">rotundum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 1: 423. 1762</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus allium;species rotundum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs 1–50+, ovoid, 0.2–1.5 × 0.2–1 cm; outer coats surrounding numerous, very dark purple bulbels, usually white or greenish, membranous, sometimes breaking into ± parallel, fibrous strips; inner coats white, cells obscure, quadrate. Leaves persistent, 2–5, sheathing 1/3–1/2 scape; blade solid, flat or channeled, carinate, 15–40 cm × 2–5(–7) mm, margins entire. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, ± solid, 25–90 cm × 1–4 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, very dense, 80–200-flowered, globose, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts caducous, 2, 7–12-veined, lanceolate, ± equal, apex narrowed to beak, beak to 2 cm. Flowers campanulate, 4–7 mm; tepals erect, purple, or inner with broad whitish margins and purple midvein, oblong to ovate, ± equal, becoming keeled and ± rigid in fruit, margins entire, apex acute to obtuse; stamens included; filaments: outer unlobed, inner with 2 prominent teeth on either side of anther, teeth 2–3 times anther-bearing portion, usually papillose to ciliate; anthers yellow or purple; pollen light yellow to white; ovary crestless; style linear, ± equaling anther-bearing portion of stamens; stigma capitate, unlobed; pedicels 5–30 mm, outer much shorter than inner. Seed coat dull; cells each with central papilla.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May--Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Disturbed fields and roadsides;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Mich.; c, s Europe.</description>
  <number>25.</number>
  <discussion>Allium rotundum is native to central and southern Europe. It is reported as established in southern Michigan, and is to be expected elsewhere in the Great Lakes region.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
