<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>27.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>validum</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Botany (Fortieth Parallel),</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>350. 1871</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Bulbs 2–20+, clustered on thick, iris-like rhizome, elongate, 2–5 × 1–2.5 cm; outer coats enclosing 1 or more bulbs, brownish, membranous, minutely striate, cells in regular vertical rows, elongate, not fibrous-reticulate, fibers persistent, parallel, few, coarse; inner coats reddish purple or whitish, minutely striate, cells in regular vertical rows, elongate. Leaves persistent, green at anthesis, 3–6, sheathing basally, sheaths not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, flat, 20–70(–80) cm × 4–15 mm, margins entire. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, solid, flattened and narrowly winged distally, 30–70 cm × 2–7 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 15–30-flowered, hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2, 3–5-veined, broadly ovate, ± equal, apex acute. Flowers ± campanulate, 8–10 mm; tepals erect to ± spreading, pink, narrowly lanceolate, ± equal, withering in fruit, margins entire, apex acuminate, midribs scarcely thickened; stamens exerted; anthers yellow or purple; pollen yellow; ovary crestless; style exserted, linear, longer than stamens; stigma capitate, unlobed; pedicel 10–15 mm, elongating and becoming stout in fruit. Seed coat dull; cells smooth or minutely roughened. 2n = 28, 56.</description><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>swampy meadows in mountains</habitat><elevation>1500–2900 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution><discussion>Allium validum is a Cascade-Sierran species extending east to northeastern Nevada, eastern Oregon, and western Idaho.</discussion></treatment>
