<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>42.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>shevockii</species_name><species_authority>McNeal</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>34: 150, fig. 1. 1987</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Bulbs 2–10+, forming threadlike rhizomes, rhizomes 3–10 cm, terminated by bulbels and/or 1–2 basal bulbels that in turn may produce threadlike rhizomes, ± globose, 1–1.5 × 1–1.5 cm; outer coats enclosing single bulb, brown, membranous, lacking cellular reticulation or cells arranged in only 2–3 rows distal to roots, ± quadrate, without fibers; inner coats light yellow, turning reddish on drying, cells obscure, ± quadrate. Leaves persistent, withering from tip by anthesis, 1, basally sheathing, sheath not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, terete, 20–40 cm × 2–4 mm. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 10–20+ cm × 1–5 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 12–30-flowered, globose, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, usually 3, 5–7-veined, lanceolate, ± equal, apex apiculate. Flowers campanulate, 12–14 mm; tepals spreading, unequal; outer tepals maroon, oblanceolate, margins irregularly shallow-toothed, apex acute to mucronate, reflexed-curled; inner tepals maroon distally, white proximally, ovate, withering in fruit, curled back at tip, margins entire, apex acute, reflexed; stamens included; anthers yellow; pollen yellow; ovary crested; processes 6, prominent, narrowly triangular, margins entire, apex emarginate; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, 3-lobed, lobes slender, recurved; pedicel 10–16 mm. Seed coat shining; cells minutely roughened. 2n = 14.</description><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>soil pockets on schist outcrops</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>2200–2400 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Allium shevockii is known only from the upper slopes of Spanish Needle Peak in the southern Sierra Nevada and from Horse Canyon, Tehachapi Mountains.</discussion></treatment>
