<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>44.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>munzii</species_name><species_authority>(Ownbey &amp; Aase ex Traub) McNeal</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Aliso</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>13: 415. 1992</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>fimbriatum</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><variety_name>munzii</variety_name><variety_authority>Ownbey &amp; Aase ex Traub</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Pl. Life </publication_title><place_in_publication>28: 64. 1972</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Bulbs usually solitary, not clustered on stout, primary rhizome, ovoid, 1–1.5 × 0.8–1.4 cm; outer coats enclosing single bulb, reddish brown, membranous, lacking cellular reticulation or cells arranged in only 2–3 rows proximal to roots, ± quadrate, without fibers; inner coats pale brown to white or pink, cells obscure, quadrate. Leaves persistent, withering from tip by anthesis, 1, basally sheathing, sheath not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, terete, 15–25 cm × 0.5–1.5 mm. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 15–35 cm × 1–2.5 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 10–35-flowered, hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2–3, 5–7-veined, lanceolate to ovate, ± equal, apex abruptly acuminate. Flowers campanulate, 6–8 mm; tepals erect, white with greenish midveins, becoming deep pink to red in fruit, ovate to nearly round, ± equal, becoming papery in fruit, margins entire to finely denticulate, apex obtuse (rarely acute), shallowly emarginate; stamens included; anthers yellow; pollen yellow; ovary crested; processes 6, prominent, ± triangular, margins entire, apex emarginate; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, 3-lobed, lobes slender, recurved; pedicel spreading, straight, 7–12 mm, becoming rigid and ± reflexed in fruit. Seed coat dull; cells minutely roughened. 2n = 14.</description><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><habitat>clay soil on grassy slopes</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>400–900 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution></treatment>
