<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>47.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>diabolense</species_name><species_authority>(Ownbey &amp; Aase ex Traub) McNeal</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Aliso</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>13: 425. 1992</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>fimbriatum</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><variety_name>diabolense</variety_name><variety_authority>Ownbey &amp; Aase ex Traub</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Pl. Life </publication_title><place_in_publication>28: 64. 1972</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Bulbs 1–3, not clustered on stout, primary rhizomes, ovoid to ± globose, 1–1.6 × 0.9–1.6 cm; outer coats enclosing 1 or more bulbs, reddish brown, membranous, lacking cellular reticulation or cells arranged in 2–3 rows proximal to roots, ± quadrate, without fibers; inner coats pale brown to white, cells obscure, quadrate. Leaves persistent, withering from apex by anthesis, 1, basally sheathing, sheath not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, terete, 10–30(–40) cm × 1–3 mm. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 7–20(–30) cm × 1–3 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact to ± loose, 10–50-flowered, hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2–3, 8–10-veined, lanceolate, ± equal, apex acuminate to long-acuminate. Flowers campanulate, 6–10 mm; tepals erect, white or tinged pink with dark red midveins, lanceolate to ovate, ± equal, becoming papery in fruit, margins entire, apex obtuse to acute or apiculate, not conspicuously recurved at tip; stamens included; anthers yellow; pollen yellow; ovary crested; processes 6, prominent, ± triangular, margins erose to ± laciniate; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, 3-lobed, lobes slender, recurved; pedicel 7–20 mm. Seed coat dull; cells minutely roughened. 2n = 14.</description><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>serpentine clay soils</habitat><elevation>500–1500 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Allium diabolense is known only from the southern Coast Ranges and western Transverse Ranges.</discussion></treatment>
