<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">LILIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. Watson" date="unknown">bigelovii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Botany (Fortieth Parallel),</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>487, plate 38, figs. 8, 9. 1871</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family LILIACEAE;genus Allium;species bigelovii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs usually solitary, not clustered on stout primary rhizome, ± globose, 1–1.5 × 1.2–1.5 cm; outer coats enclosing single bulb, dark brown, prominently reticulate, membranous, cells irregularly arranged, vertically elongate, rectangular to ± contorted, without fibers; inner coats white, cells obscure, quadrate. Leaves persistent, green at anthesis, 2, basally sheathing, sheaths not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, subterete to channeled, 16–21 cm × 2–4 mm, margins entire. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 5–12 cm × 1–4 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, loose to ± compact, 10–25-flowered, hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2, 2–11-veined, lance-ovate to ovate, ± equal, apex acute to acuminate. Flowers campanulate, (8–)10–14 mm; tepals erect, pink to reddish at tip and along midvein, otherwise white, lanceolate, ± equal, becoming papery and ± rigid in fruit, margins entire, apex acute; stamens included; anthers purple; pollen yellow; ovary crested; processes 6, prominent, flat, triangular, margins entire to coarsely toothed; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, scarcely thickened, obscurely 3-lobed; pedicel 10–15 mm. Seed coat shining; cells smooth. 2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">mar</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">apr</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="habitat">open, rocky, gravelly slopes</description>
  <description type="elevation">500–1700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex.</description>
  <number>59.</number>
  <discussion>Allium bigelovii is an anomalous species that does not appear to be closely related to any other from North America. With its prominent ovarian crests, a relationship with the group of species around A. fimbriatum, A. nevadense, and A. sanbornii is suggested. Allium bigelovii differs from this group, however, in having two leaves and a seed coat with smooth cells. In addition its bulb-coat reticulation is unlike that of any other North American species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
