<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Curran" date="1885">hyalinum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Calif. Acad. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 155. 1885</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus allium;species hyalinum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs generally 2–20+, increase bulbs absent or ± equaling parent bulbs, never appearing as basal cluster, not clustered on stout primary rhizome, ovoid to ± globose, 0.5–1.2 × 0.5–1.2 cm; outer coats enclosing 1 or more bulbs, gray-brown to brown, prominently cellular-reticulate, membranous, cells arranged in ± vertical rows, forming irregular herringbone pattern, transversely elongate, ± wavy, V-shaped, without fibers; inner coats yellow or white, cells obscure, arranged in vertical rows, forming a herringbone pattern or contorted, V-shaped. Leaves persistent, withering from tip by anthesis, 2–3, basally sheathing, sheaths not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, subterete or ± channeled, not carinate, 7–40 cm × 1–3 mm, margins entire. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 15–45 cm × 2–4 mm. Umbel shattering after seeds mature, each flower deciduous with its pedicel as a unit, erect, loose, 5–25-flowered, hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2, 3–5-veined, lanceolate to lance-ovate, ± equal, apex acuminate. Flowers stellate, 6–10 mm; tepals spreading at anthesis, white to pink, lance-ovate to broadly ovate, ± equal, becoming hyaline and connivent over capsule, margins entire, apex obtuse to rounded; stamens included; anthers yellow or purple; pollen yellow; ovary crestless; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, scarcely thickened, unlobed; pedicel 10–35 mm. Seed coat dull; cells minutely roughened. 2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">mar</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">apr</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="habitat">heavy, clay soils on shaded slopes</description>
  <description type="elevation">50–1500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <number>66.</number>
  <discussion>Allium hyalinum is known from the Sierra Nevada foothills and inner south Coast Range.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
