<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>71.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>fibrillum</species_name><species_authority>M. E. Jones ex Abrams</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in L. Abrams and R. S. Ferris, Ill. Fl. Pacific States</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 393. 1923</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Allium</genus_name><species_name>collinum</species_name><species_authority>Douglas ex S. Watson</species_authority><place_of_publication><place_in_publication>1889</place_in_publication><other_info>not Gussone 1831</other_info></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Bulbs 1–5+, without cluster of basal bulbels, not clustered on stout primary rhizome, ± globose, 0.5–1.2 × 0.5–1 cm; outer coats enclosing 1 or more bulbs, brownish, membranous, reticulate; cells very fine, often obscure, narrow, ± transversely elongate, intricately contorted, without fibers; inner coats white to pink, cells obscure, transversely elongate, intricately contorted. Leaves usually persistent, withering from tip by anthesis, 2, basally sheathing, sheaths not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, flat, ± falcate, linear, channeled, 7–24 cm × 0.5–3 mm, margins entire. Scape persistent, solitary, erect, solid, terete or slightly flattened to very narrowly winged, 3–15 cm × 0.5–2 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 10–20-flowered, hemispheric to globose, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2, 4–6-veined, ovate, ± equal, apex acuminate. Flowers campanulate, 5–8 mm; tepals erect, white with prominent greenish or pink midribs, lanceolate, ± equal, becoming papery in fruit, margins entire, apex obtuse to acuminate, ± involute at tip; stamens included; anthers yellow; pollen yellow; ovary crestless or obscurely crested; processes 3, low, rounded, margins entire; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, unlobed; pedicel 3–10 mm. Seed coat dull or shining; cells smooth. 2n = 14.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>moist, shallow soils</habitat><elevation>300–2600 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution><discussion>Allium fibrillum closely resembles A. madidum but does not have a cluster of basal bulbels.</discussion></treatment>
