<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lemmon" date="1890">obtusum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 69. 1890</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus allium;species obtusum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs 1–5, not clustered on stout primary rhizome, ovoid, 1–2 × 0.8–1.8 cm; outer coats enclosing 1 or more bulbs, brown, membranous, cellular-reticulate, cells quadrate, polygonal, or ± rectangular, ± transversely elongate, without fibers; inner coats white, reticulation absent or cells obscure, ± quadrate. Leaves usually deciduous with scape, withering from tip at anthesis, 1–2, basally sheathing, sheaths not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, flat or broadly channeled, ± falcate, 5–22 cm × 0.5–14 mm, margins entire. Scape usually forming abcission layer and deciduous with leaves after seeds mature, frequently breaking at this level after pressing, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 2–17 cm × 0.5–2 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 6–65-flowered, hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2–3(–5), 5-8-veined, ovate, ± equal, apex abruptly acuminate to apiculate. Flowers campanulate, 4–12 mm; tepals erect, white or pink with dark purplish midveins, lanceolate to oblong-elliptic, ± equal, becoming papery in fruit, margins entire, apex obtuse to acute; stamens included; anthers yellow or purple; pollen yellow; ovary crested; processes 3, obscure to ± prominent, rounded, central, margins entire; style linear, equaling stamens or longer; stigma capitate, scarcely thickened, obscurely 3-lobed; pedicel 2–14(–20) mm. Seed coat dull; cells ± smooth.</description>
  <description type="distribution">California, Nevada.</description>
  <number>81.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Allium obtusum is known only from the Sierra Nevada.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blade 0.5–4 mm wide; umbels 6–20-flowered; tepals white with prominent, dark midveins, oblong-elliptic, apex obtuse</description>
      <determination>81a. Allium obtusum var. obtusum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blade 2–14 mm wide; umbels 10–65-flowered; tepals pink with darker midveins, lanceolate,</description>
      <determination>81b. Allium obtusum var. conspicuum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
