<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Eastwood" date="1934">yosemitense</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Leafl. W. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 132. 1934</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus allium;species yosemitense</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs 1–12+, not basally clustered on stout primary rhizome, ovoid, 2–3 × 1.5–2 cm; outer coats enclosing 1 or more bulbs, brown, membranous, lacking cellular reticulation or cells arranged in only 2–3 rows distal to roots, ± quadrate, without fibers; inner coats white, cells very obscurely quadrate or not visible. Leaves usually deciduous with scape, withering from tip at anthesis, 2, basally sheathing, sheaths not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, flat or very broadly channeled, ± falcate, 15–40 cm × 2–18 mm, margins entire. Scape usually forming abcission layer and deciduous with leaves after seeds mature, frequently breaking at this level after pressing, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 6–23 cm × 1–3 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 20–100-flowered, globose to hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2–4, 7–9-veined, ovate, ± equal, apex acuminate. Flowers campanulate, 7–15 mm; tepals erect, white to pink with darker midveins, linear-oblong, ± equal, becoming membranous in fruit, margins entire, apex acute; stamens ± equaling tepals; anthers yellow or purple; pollen yellow; ovary crested; processes 3, 2-lobed, minute, margins entire; style short-exserted, linear; stigma capitate, scarcely thickened, unlobed; pedicel 7–34 mm. Seed coat dull; cells ± smooth. 2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="habitat">moist soil along cracks and margins of large metamorphic outcrops</description>
  <description type="elevation">800–2200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering May--Jun. Moist soil along cracks and margins of large metamorphic outcrops; of conservation concern; 800--2200 m; Calif.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering May--Jun.</phenology>
      <habitat>Moist soil along cracks and margins of large metamorphic outcrops;</habitat>
      <discussion>of conservation concern;</discussion>
      <elevation>800--2200 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Calif.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>88.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Allium yosemitense is known only from the central Sierra Nevada.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
