<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ownbey ex Traub" date="1972">hoffmanii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pl. Life</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>28: 63. 1972</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus allium;species hoffmanii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs usually solitary, not clustered on stout primary rhizomes, ovoid, 1.5–2.5 × 1–1.5 cm; outer coats enclosing single bulb, brown or gray, membranous, lacking cellular reticulation or cells arranged in only 2–3 rows distal to roots, ± quadrate, without fibers; inner coats white or pink, cells not visible. Leaves usually deciduous with scape, withering from tip at anthesis, 1, basally sheathing, sheath not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, flat or broadly channeled, ± falcate, 10–22 cm × 4–8 mm, margins entire. Scape usually forming abcission layer and deciduous with leaves after seeds mature, frequently breaking at this level after pressing, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 5–10 cm × 0.5–2 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 10–40-flowered, globose to conic, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 3–4, 3-veined, ovate, ± equal, apex acuminate. Flowers conical to campanulate, 8–10 mm; tepals strictly erect, pink to purplish with prominent greenish midvein, linear-lanceolate, ± equal, becoming membranous, withering in fruit, margins entire, apex acuminate; stamens exserted; filaments papillose-glandular proximally; anthers purple; pollen yellow or gray; ovary crested; processes 6, obscure, central, low, rounded, margins entire; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, scarcely thickened, obscurely 3-lobed; pedicel 8–15 mm. Seed coat dull; cells smooth. 2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="habitat">serpentine clay</description>
  <description type="elevation">1100–1800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <number>89.</number>
</bio:treatment>
