<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">LILIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Davidson" date="unknown">burlewii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. S. Calif. Acad. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 17. 1916</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family LILIACEAE;genus Allium;species burlewii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs usually solitary, not clustered on stout, primary rhizome, ovoid, 1.5–2.5 × 1–1.5 cm; outer coats enclosing single bulb, brown or grayish, membranous, lacking cellular reticulation or cells arranged in only 2–3 rows distal to roots, ± quadrate, without fibers; inner coats white, cells not visible. Leaves usually deciduous with scape, withering from tip at anthesis, 1, basally sheathing, sheath not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, flat or broadly channeled, ± falcate, 8–33 cm × 1–10 mm, margins entire. Scape usually forming abcission layer and deciduous with leaves after seeds mature, frequently breaking at this level after pressing, solitary, erect, solid, terete, 2–20 cm × 1–3 mm. Umbel persistent, erect, compact, 8–20(–30)-flowered, globose to conic, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 3, 9–13-veined, broadly ovate, ± equal, apex abruptly acuminate. Flowers conical to campanulate, 7–10 mm; tepals strictly erect, dull purplish with darker midveins, ovate, ± equal, becoming membranous, withering in fruit, margins entire, apex obtuse; stamens equaling tepals or ± exserted; filaments smooth proximally; anthers purple; pollen yellow or gray; ovary crestless or crested; processes 6, central, rounded, minute, margins entire; style linear, slightly longer than stamens; stigma capitate, scarcely thickened, unlobed; pedicel 6–10 mm. Seed coat shining; cells smooth. 2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">apr</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="habitat">granite sands</description>
  <description type="habitat">on dry slopes and ridges</description>
  <description type="elevation">1800–2800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <number>90.</number>
</bio:treatment>
