<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">allium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas ex S. Watson" date="1879">scilloides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>14: 229. 1879</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus allium;species scilloides</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Bulbs 1–5, not clustered on stout, primary rhizome, increase bulbs ± equaling parent bulbs, never appearing as basal cluster, rhizomes absent, globose to ovoid, 1–2 cm × 8–20 mm; outer coats enclosing renewal bulbs, reddish or brownish, membranous, lacking cellular reticulation or cells arranged in only 2–3 rows distal to roots, ± quadrate, without fibers; inner coats white or light brown, cells absent or obscure and ± quadrate. Leaves deciduous with scape after seeds mature, 2, basally sheathing, sheaths not extending much above soil surface; blade solid, flat, falcate, 6–15 cm × 2–4 mm, margins entire or obscurely papillose. Scape usually forming abcission layer and deciduous with leaves after seeds mature, frequently breaking at this level after pressing, solitary, erect, solid, strongly flattened, 2-edged or winged distally, wings obscurely papillose, 4–8 cm × 1–3 mm. Umbel decisuous with scape, erect, compact, 5–12-flowered, hemispheric, bulbils unknown; spathe bracts persistent, 2–3, 3-veined, broadly ovate, ± equal, apex acute. Flowers campanulate, 6–8 mm; tepals erect, white or pinkish with green midribs, becoming reddish purple, broadly elliptic-oblong, ± equal, becoming rigid, papery and ± connivent over fruit, margins entire, apex obtuse, not involute at tip; stamens included; anthers purple; pollen white to gray; ovary crestless or obscurely crested; processes 3, central, rounded, margins entire; style linear, equaling stamens; stigma capitate, unlobed or minutely 3-lobed; pedicel 2–10.5(–18.5 in fruit) mm. Seed coat dull; cells smooth. 2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Mar--Apr.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Barren, gravelly soils, arid interior slopes and ridges well back from Columbia River;</description>
  <description type="elevation">300--1300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wash.</description>
  <number>95.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Allium scilloides is known only from east of the Cascades.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
