<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gerald B. Straley†,Frederick H. Utech</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">GALANTHUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 288. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 140. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus GALANTHUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek gala , milk, and anthos , flower, alluding to the color of the flowers]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, scapose, from brown, tunicate, ovoid to globose bulbs; offset bulbs often present. Leaves 2(–3), basal, opposite, with sheathing blade, vernation flat and parallel, or convolute; nonsheathing blade erect to recurving at maturity, grayish green, linear-oblanceolate, glaucous; sheathing blade white, tubular, membranous, enclosing leaf bases and scape. Scape erect in flower, prostrate in fruit, green, solid. Inflorescences pendulous, 1-flowered, spathaceous; spathe bracteate, membranous; bracts 2, connate, split on 1 side. Flowers nodding, fragrant; perianath 2.5 cm or shorter; tepals 6, distinct, unequal; outer tepals spreading, white, narrowly obovate to almost orbicular, larger than inner; inner tepals overlapping, appearing tubular, green-spotted at apex only or apex and base, straight to semiorbicular, apex notched; stamens 6, inserted at bases of tepals, distinct; anthers basifixed, longer than filaments, bases lobed, apices tapered, dehiscense introrse, via terminal slits; ovary inferior, green, 3-locular, globose, septal nectaries present; style, white, unbranched, filiform; stigma indistinct to minutely capitate; pedicel wiry, short, slender. Fruits capsular, green, globose, fleshy, dehiscence loculicidal. Seeds 18–36, light brown, 3.5 mm, oblong to obtuse, elaiosomes fleshy. x = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Europe, sw Asia (Asia Minor, Iranian Caucasus, and Caspian Sea regions); introduced and naturalized elsewhere.</description>
  <number>47.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Snowdrop</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">perce-neige</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 14–17 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>A number of Galanthus species, especially G. nivalis, are commonly cultivated for their late- winter and early-spring flowers, which emerge through the snow. Species of Galanthus are sometimes confused with Leucojum, snowflakes, a spring-flowering relative. The plants of Leucojum are usually taller, bear 2–3 flowers per stem, and their tepals are all equal.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Davis, A. P. 1999. The Genus Galanthus. Portland.  </reference>
    <reference>Stern, F. C. 1956. Snowdrops and Snowflakes—A Study of the Genera Galanthus and Leucojum. London.  </reference>
    <reference>Yeo, P. F. 1975. The hybrid origin of some cultivated snowdrops (Galanthus–Amaryllidaceae). Baileya 19: 157–162.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inner tepals blotched with green at base and apex or with green stripe from base to apex;</description>
      <determination>1.  Galanthus elwesii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inner tepals blotched with green at apex only; leaves flat and parallel within basal sheath</description>
      <determination>2.  Galanthus nivalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
