<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eichhornia</genus_name><species_name>azurea</species_name><species_authority>(Swartz) Kunth</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Eichhornia,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4. 1842</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Rooted water-hyacinth</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Pontederia</genus_name><species_name>azurea</species_name><species_authority>Swartz</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Prodr., </publication_title><place_in_publication>57. 1788</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants perennial, typically rooted in mud. Vegetative stems elongate, developing to and growing at water surface. Flowering stems erect, 8–12 cm, glabrous, distal inter-node 2–10 cm. Sessile leaves submersed, alternate on elongate stem. Petiolate leaves emersed; stipule 7–13 cm, apex truncate; petiole never inflated, 11–25 cm; blade round, 7–16 × 2.3–16 cm. Spikes 7–50-flowered, individual flowers open 1 day only; spathes obovate, 3–6 cm; peduncle 1.9–15 cm, pubescent with orange hairs. Perianth blue or white, limb lobes obovate, 13–25 mm, margins erose, central distal lobe dark blue at base with yellow distal spot; proximal stamens 15–29 mm, distal 6–20 mm; anthers 1.2–2.3 mm; style 3-lobed. Seeds 10–13-winged, 1–1.8 × 0.8–1.1 mm.</description><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><phenology>sep</phenology><phenology>fall</phenology><phenology>oct</phenology><habitat>coastal rivers</habitat><habitat>lakes</habitat><elevation>0–100 m;</elevation><introduced>introduced;</introduced><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Central America to South America (n Argentina).</global_distribution><discussion>Eichhornia azurea is on the USDA/APHIS noxious weeds list (D. C. Schmitz 1990) and is known only as a waif from several locations in Florida (R. G. Westbrooks 1990). It has been reported from Texas (L. H. Shinners 1962b), but this record was based on a misidentified specimen (Jones 1160, SMU) that actually is E. crassipes. All known populations in Florida have been eradicated by the Florida Department of Natural Resources. R. G. Westbrooks specifically noted a population growing in a residential estate pool in Palm Beach that was eradicated in June 1988. Another collection from Columbia County (N. Coile 5793, NBYC) was also eradicated.</discussion><discussion>The breeding system of Eichornia azurea, a tristylous species, is more like that of Pontederia species than that of E. crassipes (S. C. H. Barrett 1978). Populations typically have a mix of all three floral morphs, allowing for outcrossing.</discussion><discussion>The above description is based on South American material.</discussion></treatment>
