<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>67.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>MUILLA</genus_name><genus_authority>S. Watson ex Bentham</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in G. Bentham and J. D. Hooker, Gen. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>3: 801. 1883</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Anagram of Allium ]</etymology><author>J. Chris Pires</author><author>James L. Reveal</author><description>Herbs, perennial, scapose, from fibrous-coated corms. Leaves 1–10, strictly basal; blade linear, elongate, flat, not keeled or channeled, surrounded by fibrous sheath. Scapes 1–2, cylindrical. Inflorescences umbellate, terminal, bracteate; bracts several, white or greenish white, scarious. Flowers: perianth subrotate, narrowly oblong; tepals 6, spreading, mostly distinct, only shortly connate at base, white to greenish white or bluish, sometimes tinged with lilac, subequal; stamens 6, epitepalous, inserted near base of tepals; filaments filiform, subulate, or conspicuously dilated, sometimes overlapping or connate; anthers versatile, introrse; pistil 3-carpellate; ovary superior, sessile, 3-locular, ovules several; style persistent, clavate; stigma 3-lobed, minute; pedicel slender, not articulate. Fruits capsular, slightly lobed, globose, dehiscence loculicidal. Seeds black, angled, coat with crust. x = 7, 8, 10.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w North America.</global_distribution><discussion>The distribution of the species in this genus is poorly documented (L. W. Lenz 1975b; J. R. Shevock 1984). R. F. Hoover (1955) transferred Bloomeria clevelandii to Muilla. However, molecular and morphological evidence indicates that B. clevelandii, B. crocea, and B. humilis, all treated here under Bloomeria, are more closely related to Triteleia, and that the three species treated here under Muilla are more closely related to Androstephium (R. Y. Berg and J. R. Maze 1966; J. C. Pires 2000).</discussion><references>
    <reference> Ingram, J. W. 1953. A monograph of the genera Bloomeria and Muilla (Liliaceae). Madroño 12: 19–27. Lenz, L. W. 1975b. The chromosomes of Bloomeria and Muilla (Liliaceae) and range extensions for Muilla coronata and Muilla transmontana. Aliso 8: 259–262. </reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Filaments filiform or subulate; anthers green, blue, or purple; tepals greenish white with</statement>
      <determination>1.  Muilla maritima</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Filaments conspicuously dilated; anthers yellow; tepals white often tinged with lilac, or whitish or bluish with green abaxial midvein; mountains and deserts of California and Nevada.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Filaments dilated entire length; scape 3–5 cm; leaves 1(rarely 2); tepals bluish or whitish, with green abaxial midvein; perianth lobes 3–6 mm; deserts of California and Nevada</statement>
      <determination>2.  Muilla coronata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Filaments dilated only basally; scape 15–50 cm; leaves 3–5; tepals white, often tinged</statement>
      <determination>3.  Muilla transmontana</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
