<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Dale W. McNeal Jr.</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cavanilles" date="1793">MILLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Icon.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 76, plate 196. 1793</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus MILLA</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, scapose, from corms. Corm solitary, coated with membrane. Leaves 2–7, basal; blade linear, channeled to terete; veins sometimes scabrous, particularly proximally. Scapes 1 or rarely 2, persistent, terete, sometimes scabrous, particularly proximally. Inflorescences falsely umbellate, 1–30-flowered, subtended by 4 narrowly triangular bracts that do not enclose flowers in bud. Flowers sessile but appearing pedicellate, 4–15 cm; perianth salverform; tepals 6, connate basally into long, slender tube; perianth lobes white with green, pink, or blue abaxial stripes, shorter than tube; stamens 6, inserted on perianth tube, distinct; ovary superior, 3-locular, long-stipitate, stipe adnate to perianth tube on 3 angles; style usually exserted; stigma obscurely 3-lobed; pseudopedicel formed by elongate perianth tube ± enlarged around ovary. Fruits capsular, beaked by persistent style base, dehiscence loculicidal. Seeds numerous, black, flattened, minutely cellularly reticulate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America (Guatemala).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 6–7 (1 in the flora): sw United States, Mexico, Central America (Guatemala).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 6–7 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>sw United States, Mexico, Central America (Guatemala).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>70.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Mexican star</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 6–7 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Moore, H. E. Jr. 1953. The genus Milla (Amaryllidaceae–Allieae) and its allies. Gentes Herb. 8: 262–294.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
