<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Peter Goldblatt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">IRIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family IRIDACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, rarely annual [or shrubs with woody caudex], evergreen or seasonal, sometimes cespitose; rootstock a rhizome, bulb, or corm. Flowering stems aerial (or subterranean in Romulea), simple or branched, terete or variously compressed, angled or winged. Leaves basal and cauline, distichous; proximal 2–3 sometimes membranous, not reaching much above ground; others with open or closed sheaths, usually unifacial [bifacial or terete], oriented edgewise to the stem; blade parallel-veined, plane or pleated, channeled. Inflorescences umbellate, monochasial cymes (rhipidia), spikes, or solitary flowers; rhipidia enclosed in 2, opposed, usually large, leafy to dry bracts (spathes); flowers except for the first subtended by 1 floral bract; spike flowers each subtended by 2, opposed bracts. Flowers usually pedicellate [± sessile]; per-ianth actinomorphic or zygomorphic, petaloid, with 2 equal or unequal whorls of 3 tepals each [1 whorl of 6]; tepals usually large, showy, distinct or connate in tube; stamens 3 [2], inserted at base of outer tepals or in tube, symmetrically arranged or unilateral, arcuate [declinate]; filaments distinct or partly to completely connate, sometimes weak, unable to support anthers; anthers with 2 pollen sacs, extrorse, occasionally latrorse, usually dehiscing longitudinally [rarely apically]; ovary inferior [superior in Tasmanian Isophysis], 3-locular [1-locular]; placentation axile [parietal]; ovules 2–few, anatropous; style single, filiform at least proximally, usually 3-branched or 3-lobed, branches either filiform, distally expanded, sometimes each divided in distal 1/2, stigmatic toward apices, or branches thickened, or flattened, petaloid, stigmas then abaxial below apices. Fruits capsular, loculicidal, rarely indehiscent, firm to cartilaginous, occasionally woody. Seeds globose to angular (prismatic) or discoid, sometimes broadly winged; seed coat usually dry (rarely fleshy); endosperm hard, with reserves of hemicellulose, oil, and protein; embryo small.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide but rare in tropical lowlands</description>
  <description type="distribution">best represented in southern Africa.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Genera ca. 65, species ca. 1810 (16 genera, 92 species; 9 genera, 19 species introduced, and various hybrid complexes in the flora): nearly worldwide but rare in tropical lowlands, best represented in southern Africa.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Genera ca. 65, species ca. 1810 (16 genera, 92 species</discussion>
      <distribution>9 genera, 19 species introduced, and various hybrid complexes in the flora): nearly worldwide but rare in tropical lowlands, best represented in southern Africa.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>223.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Iris Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 65, species ca. 1810 (16 genera, 92 species; 9 genera, 19 species introduced, and various hybrid complexes in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Iridaceae are currently divided into four subfamilies (P. Goldblatt 1990, 1991). Subfamily Isophysidoideae Takhtajan is monotypic, comprising the Tasmanian Isophysis T. Moore with a superior ovary. Only subfamily Iridoideae is native in North America. The remaining Nivenioideae Schulze ex Goldblatt and Ixioideae Klatt are centered in Africa south of the Sahara. Iridaceae are of considerable economic importance in ornamental horticulture and the cut-flower industry, especially Iris, Gladiolus, and Freesia. Several other genera (e.g., Crocus, Dietes, Sparaxis, Tritonia, Watsonia) are cultivated in gardens in both tropical and temperate areas. Moraea and Homeria are poisonous and pose significant problems in cattle- and sheep-raising areas, notably in southern Africa.</discussion>
  <discussion>In addition to the several genera and species escaped from cultivation and dealt with in detail below, the following are widely grown in areas of mild winter and may persist in and near abandoned gardens, sometimes reproducing successfully: Dietes Salisbury [D. iridioides (Linnaeus) Salisbury ex Klatt, D. grandiflora N. E. Brown]; Ixia Linnaeus (I. maculata Linnaeus, I. polystachya Linnaeus); Crocus cultivars and even some wild species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Arber, A. 1921. The leaf structure of the Iridaceae. Ann. Bot. (Oxford) 35: 301–336.  </reference>
    <reference>Goldblatt, P. 1975. Revision of the bulbous Iridaceae of North America. Brittonia 27: 373–385.  </reference>
    <reference>Goldblatt, P. 1990. Phylogeny and classification of Iridaceae. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 77: 607–627.  </reference>
    <reference>Goldblatt, P. 1991. An overview of the systematics, phylogeny and biology of the southern African Iridaceae. Contr. Bolus Herb. 13: 1–74.  </reference>
    <reference>Reeves, G. et al. 2001. Molecular systematics of Iridaceae: Evidence from four plastid DNA regions. Amer. J. Bot. 88: 2074–2087.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences spicate, 2–many-flowered, or flowers solitary and sessile, each subtended by pair of opposed bracts; rootstock a corm; flowers actinomorphic or zygomorphic; tepals tubular-connate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers solitary on aerial axes; leaves all inserted below ground; blade filiform, oval to</description>
      <determination>15.  Romulea , p. 407</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers in 2–many-flowered spikes; leaves some at least inserted above ground level; blade usually expanded, plane (rarely linear, cruciform in cross section).</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers actinomorphic, upright; bracts scarious, translucent, with brown streaking;</description>
      <determination>13.  Sparaxis , p. 404</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers zygomorphic, upright or facing side; bracts not scarious; perianth tube shorter or longer than limb.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style branches each divided for about 1 / 2 its length, filiform throughout.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikes inflexed, ± horizontal, flowers secund; seeds globose, without wings</description>
      <determination>14.  Freesia , p. 405</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikes erect, flowers distichous; seeds angular, 1–2-winged</description>
      <determination>10.  Watsonia , p. 401</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style branches each simple or apically notched, filiform throughout or expanded terminally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals variously colored; style branches expanded terminally, not filiform</description>
      <determination>16.  Gladiolus , p. 407</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals shades of orange to reddish; style branches apically notched, not expanded above; seeds not winged, globose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth tube obliquely funnel-shaped; tepals subequal (dorsal only</description>
      <determination>11.  Crocosmia , p. 402</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth tube narrow and cylindric proximally, abruptly widened and</description>
      <determination>12.  Chasmanthe , p. 403</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences rhipidiate, (1–)2–several-flowered; spathes 2, paired, opposed, often leafy; rootstock a rhizome, bulb, or indistinct; flowers actinomorphic, tepals distinct or tubular-connate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves plicate, occasionally so narrow that pleats are obscure; rootstock a bulb with brown, dry tunics.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals unequal, inner whorl less than 1 / 2 outer</description>
      <determination>6.  Herbertia , p. 396</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals subequal or inner whorl only slightly smaller than outer.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style eccentric and recurving; style branches fairly short, undivided, ascending</description>
      <determination>9.  Calydorea , p. 400</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style straight, central; style branches each deeply divided into filiform arms.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style branches divided for 1 / 2 their length, rarely more; style arms arching</description>
      <determination>7.  Alophia , p. 397</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style branches divided almost to base; style arms extending horizontally</description>
      <determination>8.  Nemastylis , p. 398</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves plane; rootstock a rhizome or indistinct.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style branches broad, petaloid, terminating in paired crests; anthers appressed to</description>
      <determination>4.  Iris , p. 371</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style branches not broad or petaloid; anthers not appressed to style branches.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Filaments distinct; style branches flattened, relatively short, not extending</description>
      <determination>5.  Belamcanda , p. 395</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Filaments partly connate; style branches filiform, relatively short or long, extending between stamens.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals white or yellow, spreading from base; style branches relatively long, extending between stamens below anthers.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals white, inner exceeding outer</description>
      <determination>1.  Libertia , p. 350</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals yellow, inner ± equaling to slightly smaller than outer</description>
      <determination>3.  Sisyrinchium (in part) , p. 351</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals blue, purple, pink, or white; style branches relatively short, extend-ing between anthers.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves centric, somewhat inflated; stem simple; seeds brown, angular</description>
      <determination>2.  Olsynium , p. 350</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves plane; stem simple or branched; seeds blackish, globose, with</description>
      <determination>3.  Sisyrinchium (in part) , p. 351</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
