<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Anita F. Cholewa,Douglass M. Henderson†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="1836">OLSYNIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>New Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 72. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus OLSYNIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[said by Rafinesque to mean hardly united, alluding to the stamens]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, strongly cespitose, rootstock indistinct. Stems simple, terete. Leaves 2–4, cauline, alternate, reduced basally; blade basally clasping or terete. Inflorescences rhipidiate, 1–5-flowered; spathes 2, green, leaflike, unequal, apex acute or, rarely, obtuse. Flowers not fragrant, actinomorphic; tepals distinct, reddish purple to magenta, occasionally pink or white, not clawed, ± equal; stamens symmetrically arranged; filaments connate to 1/2 their length; anthers parallel, not appressed to style branches; style branches 3, filiform, short, extending between anthers. Capsules globose to obovoid or broadly turbinate, ± smooth to distended around seeds, apex broadly rounded, basal 0.2 mm of styles sometimes persistent. Seeds many, obconic, angular; seed coat brown, coarsely rugulose. x = 32.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 12 (1 in the flora): North America, South America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 12 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, South America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Grass widow</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 12 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Goldblatt, P., P. J. Rudall, and J. E. Henrich. 1990. The genera of the Sisyrinchium alliance (Iridaceae: Iridoideae): Phylogeny and relationships. Syst. Bot. 15: 497–510. </reference>
    <reference>  Henderson, D. M. 1972. A Biosystematic Study of the Genus Sisyrinchium (Iridaceae) in the Pacific Northwest. Ph.D. dissertation. University of Washington.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
