<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Anita F. Cholewa,Douglass M. Henderson†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">SISYRINCHIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 954. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 409. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus SISYRINCHIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek sys , pig, and rynchos , snout, alluding to swine grubbing the roots for food]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, often cespitose, rhizomatous (sometimes only obscurely, especially when cespitose) or not, sometimes with thickened, fleshy roots. Stems scapelike or branched, compressed, and 2-winged. Leaves 2–6, basal or basal and cauline, alternate, basally equitant; blade plane, ensiform, usually glabrous. Inflorescences rhipidiate, usually terminal (basal flowers occasionally produced in some montane populations), 1–11(–15)-flowered; spathes 2, opposed, green or with purplish tinge, equitant, equal or unequal, smooth to scabrous, margins hyaline, apex undifferentiated, acute to obtuse or bifid, margins of outer spathe usually connate basally. Flowers not fragrant, actinomorphic; tepals widely spreading to reflexed (S. minus and S. rosulatum with campanulate bases), ± distinct, bluish violet to light blue, white, lavender to pink, magenta, purple, or yellow, not clawed, subequal; stamens symmetrically arranged; filaments distinct, connate basally or into tube, tapering evenly to apex (basally inflated in S. rosulatum); anthers parallel, surrounding but not appressed to style branches; styles 3, erect, connate at least basally, filiform, not broad and petaloid, long, extending between stamens usually beyond anthers. Fruits capsular, ± globose, smooth to roughened by underlying seeds, apex usually rounded. Seeds many, globose to obconic or hemispheric; seed coat black, granular to rugulose. x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">New World, Hawaii; 1 species in New Zealand and 1 in Great Britain probably naturalized.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Blue-eyed grass</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 80 (37 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Sisyrinchium is a complex polyploid taxon in which the species are not always easily distinguished. When immature, plants of branched species appear to be simple-stemmed (internodes do not elongate until just before anthesis) and those of usually simple-stemmed species occasionally are branched. White flowers may occur in otherwise blue-flowered species, and vivipary occasionally occurs. Furthermore, vegetative characteristics, while distinctive in some species, may overlap greatly in wide-ranging species. Writers of past floras sometimes were unaware of such phenotypic plasticity, or were inconsistent in their use of terminology (spathes, for instance, have variously been called leaves or valves). Some taxonomists have thought differences too subtle and chosen to lump species (e.g., S. angustifolium and S. montanum have been considered synonymous by several authors).</discussion>
  <discussion>Flowers and spathes provide the best characters but require fresh material or extreme care during pressing. Many older herbarium collections have been misidentified due to improper collecting/pressing techniques that obscured critical characters. Additionally, variability within populations makes accurate identification based on only one individual nearly impossible.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chromosome counts can be useful in differentiating species but consistent numbers seem to be obtained only with meiotic counts. Some of the unusual counts reported in the literature were obtained with mitotic material or were from misidentified plants. A definite ploidal series seems to be evident, however, at least among the blue-flowered species. Limited breeding studies have shown that ploidal levels are strong barriers to reproduction (A. F. Cholewa and D. M. Henderson 1984; D. M. Henderson 1976). There is some indication, however, that true hybrids may exist (D. B. Ward 1959; D. S. Correll and M. C. Johnston 1970; G. Ajilvsgi 1984). Much more work, especially with molecular data and cladistic analyses, needs to be done to understand species relationships.</discussion>
  <discussion>In eastern Texas (especially) and adjacent states, intermediates between Sisyrinchium ensigerum, S. pruinosum, S. langloisii, and perhaps S. sagittiferum can be found. These have been referred to S. texanum E. P. Bicknell (D. S. Correll and M. C. Johnston 1970), and Bicknell’s original description of that entity does mention a high degree of variability. Many of the specimens that we examined that were previously labeled S. texanum exhibit character states intermediate between those of S. langloisii and S. pruinosum or S. ensigerum. The types of S. texanum that we examined (Bray s.n., NY; Bush 32, NY; Hall 636, NY) would key to S. langloisii or S. pruinosum but exhibit several intermediate character states. Further, although K. L. Hornberger (1987, 1991) and D. S. Correll and M. C. Johnston (1970) considered S. texanum synonymous with S. sagittiferum (which they described as a branched species), E. P. Bicknell (1899, 1901) clearly indicated that the latter is unbranched, and thus it probably does not play a role in S. texanum. Much more work is needed to resolve the proper disposition of S. texanum and the true nature of this complex of southern species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Characters critical for distinguishing species of Sisyrinchium are often found in floral material, requiring extra care in collecting and pressing. Accurate identification requires examining more than one individual in order to discount uncommon or atypical character states (generally not accounted for in this key). In branched individuals, leaves will be associated with one or more branches or peduncles that are narrower than the primary stem. Peduncles are morphologically indistinguishable from branches and are, hereafter, referred to simply as branches.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cholewa, A. F. and D. M. Henderson. 1984. Biosystematics of Sisyrinchium section Bermudiana (Iridaceae) of the Rocky Mountains. Brittonia 36: 342–363.  </reference>
    <reference>  Goldblatt, P., P. J. Rudall, and J. E. Henrich. 1990. The genera of the Sisyrinchium alliance (Iridaceae: Iridoideae): Phylogeny and relationships. Syst. Bot. 15: 497–510.</reference>
    <reference>Henderson, D. M. 1972. A Biosystematic Study of the Genus Sisyrinchium (Iridaceae) in the Pacific Northwest. Ph.D. dissertation. University of Washington.  </reference>
    <reference>Henderson, D. M. 1976. A biosystematic study of Pacific Northwestern blue-eyed grasses (Sisyrinchium, Iridaceae). Brittonia 28: 149–176.  </reference>
    <reference>Hornberger, K. L. 1987. Systematics of the Genus Sisyrinchium (Iridaceae) in the Southeastern United States. Ph.D. dissertation. University of Arkansas.  </reference>
    <reference>Hornberger, K. L. 1991. The blue-eyed-grasses (Sisyrinchium: Iridaceae) of Arkansas. Sida 14: 597–604.  </reference>
    <reference>Rudall, P. J., A. Y. Kenton, and T. J. Lawrence. 1986. An anatomical and chromosomal investigation of Sisyrinchium and allied genera. Bot. Gaz. 147: 466–477.  </reference>
    <reference>Ward, D. B. 1968. The nomenclature of Sisyrinchium bermudiana and related North America species. Taxon 17: 270–276.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals yellow to orange; seeds usually hemispherical with depression on flattened side, or globose with or without obvious depression; filaments distinct or connate only basally.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 2–8 mm wide; capsules 6–19 mm; tepals usually 12+ mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems simple; seeds 0.7–1.5 mm, hemispherical with shallow depression</description>
      <determination>1.  Sisyrinchium californicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched; seeds 1.5–2.2 mm, globose, lacking depression</description>
      <determination>2.  Sisyrinchium arizonicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 0.5–2(–2.3) mm wide; capsules 3–9 mm; tepals usually less than 12 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants annual; tepals 2.6–5 mm; seeds 0.9–1.1 mm, with deep depression</description>
      <determination>5.  Sisyrinchium cernuum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; tepals 7.5–11 mm; seeds 1–1.7 mm, with shallow depression.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting pedicels recurved to spreading; capsules globose or turbinate to broadly</description>
      <determination>3.  Sisyrinchium elmeri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting pedicels ascending to erect; capsules slightly turbinate to ± globose</description>
      <determination>4.  Sisyrinchium longipes</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals purple to light blue, white, lavender, pink, or magenta, occasionally yellow; seeds globose to obconic, depression absent or occasionally slight; filaments connate ± full length (only basally in S. rosulatum ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth campanulate basally, flaring distally; plants annual or occasionally short-lived perennial; tepals lavender, pink, magenta, yellow, or occasionally white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with 3–6 nodes; filaments connate ± full length, tapering evenly, stipitate-glandular on proximal 0.8–1.2 mm; capsule turbinate to broadly fusiform, uni-</description>
      <determination>6.  Sisyrinchium minus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with 1–2(–3) nodes; filaments connate basally or occasionally to 1 / 2 length, inflated basally, stipitate-glandular on proximal 0.5–0.8 mm; capsule ± globose,</description>
      <determination>7.  Sisyrinchium rosulatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth widely flaring or reflexed from base, not campanulate; plants perennial; tepals purple to violet, blue, or white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhipidia usually paired, rarely borne singly, sessile or rarely outer with branch to 7 mm; rhipidia and associated spathes closely subtended by enveloping bractlike leaf (because the 2 rhipidia are nearly enveloped by the leaf, these species can be mistaken as having a single rhipidium).</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 1.5–3.4 mm wide, obviously winged, not wiry</description>
      <determination>8.  Sisyrinchium albidum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 0.5–1 mm wide, hardly or not winged, wiry</description>
      <determination>9.  Sisyrinchium capillare</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhipidia borne singly, terminating stem or branch; rhipidium and associated spathes not subtended by leaf.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched or populations predominantly with branched individuals (see discussion).</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with 2–5 nodes; spathes ± equaling branches in width</description>
      <determination>10.   Sisyrinchium dichotomum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with 1–3 nodes; spathes much wider than branches.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Main stems usually more than 2 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">First internode equaling or shorter than longest leaf, if equaling leaves then apex of hyaline margins of inner spathe acute to acuminate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves glabrous; hyaline margins of inner spathe broadly acute to obtuse</description>
      <determination>11.  Sisyrinchium ensigerum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and leaves usually scabrous, at least apically on margins; hyaline margins of inner spathe tapering to acute to acuminate apex, never projecting as lobes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases persistent as fibrous tufts; outer spathe 0.5–1.8 mm longer than</description>
      <determination>12.  Sisyrinchium xerophyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases not persistent or fibrous; outer spathe 2.5–5.5 mm longer than inner</description>
      <determination>13.  Sisyrinchium pruinosum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">First internode equaling or longer than longest leaf, if equaling leaves then hyaline margins of inner spathe broadly obtuse or acute apically.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases persistent as fibrous tufts</description>
      <determination>14. Sisyrinchium nashii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases not persistent or fibrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe 0.1–0.3 mm wide; e of the Rocky Mountains.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules dark brown or black; plants usually drying dark olive green,</description>
      <determination>15.  Sisyrinchium angustifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules tan to nearly white; plants drying light green to yellowish green</description>
      <determination>16.  Sisyrinchium strictum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe (0.1–)0.4–1.1 mm wide; w of the Rocky Mountains.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe usually equaling or longer than green apex;</description>
      <determination>17.  Sisyrinchium funereum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe usually shorter than green apex; foliage various but usually not strongly glaucous; tepals usually bluish violet to violet-purple.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals elliptic to oblanceolate; stem margins white or translucent cartilaginous; filament column usually stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>18.  Sisyrinchium radicatum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals often broadly cuneate; stem margins same color and texture as stem body; filament column usually not stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>19.  Sisyrinchium bellum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Main stems usually 2 mm or less wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of outer spathe connate basally (1.5–)2–4 mm (–5 mm in S. langloisii ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer spathe 2.5–5.5 mm longer than inner; spathes usually scabrous</description>
      <determination>13.  Sisyrinchium pruinosum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer spathe shorter or no more than 2.7 mm longer than inner; spathe usually glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases persistent as thick, fibrous tufts</description>
      <determination>20.  Sisyrinchium fuscatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases not persistent as fibrous tufts.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovary and capsule black, contrasting with much lighter foliage; hyaline margins of inner spathe broadly rounded or truncate apically</description>
      <determination>21.  Sisyrinchium atlanticum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovary and capsule not contrasting with foliage; hyaline margins of inner</description>
      <determination>22. Sisyrinchium langloisii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of outer spathe connate basally 3.5–9 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries and capsules black, contrasting with much lighter foliage</description>
      <determination>21.  Sisyrinchium atlanticum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries and capsules not contrasting with foliage.</description>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe broadly rounded or truncate apically.</description>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe usually equaling or longer than green apex;</description>
      <determination>17.  Sisyrinchium funereum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe usually shorter than green apex; foliage various, not strongly glaucous; tepals bluish violet to violet-purple.</description>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals elliptic to oblanceolate; stem margins white or translucent-cartilaginous; filament column usually stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>18.  Sisyrinchium radicatum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals often broadly cuneate; stem margins similar to stem body;</description>
      <determination>19.  Sisyrinchium bellum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hyaline margins of inner spathe usually acute or acuminate apically.</description>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">First internode equaling or shorter than leaves.</description>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants drying brownish olive to bronze; rhizomes obvious</description>
      <determination>23.  Sisyrinchium miamiense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants drying yellowish green to olive, occasionally bronze; rhizomes</description>
      <determination>24.  Sisyrinchium biforme (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">First internode longer than leaves.</description>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 4–7.5+; sw United States</description>
      <determination>25.  Sisyrinchium demissum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 3.5–4.9 mm; Great Lakes region</description>
      <determination>16.  Sisyrinchium strictum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems simple or populations predominantly with simple-stemmed individuals.</description>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of outer spathe distinct basally or rarely connate to 1 mm, and then stems</description>
      <determination>26.  Sisyrinchium campestre</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Margins of outer spathe obviously connate basally 1 mm or more (rarely connate less than 1 mm and then spathes tinged strongly purple), usually glabrous or rarely slightly scabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases persisting in fibrous tufts</description>
      <determination>35. Sisyrinchium sagittiferum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf bases not persisting in fibrous tufts.</description>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes obvious and elongate; tepals purple to dark reddish purple or very</description>
      <determination>30.  Sisyrinchium hitchcockii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes scarcely discernable; tepals bluish violet, occasionally purple or purplish blue, to light blue or white, base yellow.</description>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spathes subequal, or outer up to 4.5 mm longer than inner.</description>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 2.2–4 mm; hyaline margins of inner spathe broadly rounded to truncate apically, often extending as 2 lobes beyond green apex;</description>
      <determination>31.  Sisyrinchium halophilum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 5–7 mm; hyaline margins of inner spathe acute to acuminate or occasionally lobed and slightly exceeding green apex; s United States</description>
      <determination>24.  Sisyrinchium biforme (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spathes distinctly unequal, outer at least 6 mm longer than inner.</description>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals pale blue; outer tepals usually rounded apically to slightly emarginate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals greater than 10 mm; Columbia River Gorge</description>
      <determination>33.  Sisyrinchium sarmentosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer tepals 10 mm or less; elsewhere.</description>
      <next_statement_id>40.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer spathes usually connate more than 2.6 mm; outer tepals</description>
      <determination>28.  Sisyrinchium pallidum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer spathes connate less than 2.6 mm; outer tepals rounded apically, never emarginate; elsewhere.</description>
      <next_statement_id>41.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules dark brown to black; Greenland</description>
      <determination>36.  Sisyrinchium groenlandicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules beige to light brown; w Canada, Washington</description>
      <determination>37.  Sisyrinchium septentrionale</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tepals blue-violet to purplish blue, occasionally purple; outer tepals emarginate, truncate or occasionally rounded apically.</description>
      <next_statement_id>42.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems with very narrow or scarcely discernable wings, almost wiry,</description>
      <determination>29.  Sisyrinchium mucronatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems obviously winged, 1–3.7 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>43.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 6.2–8.1 mm; outer tepals usually rounded to slightly</description>
      <determination>32.  Sisyrinchium littorale</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 3–6.8 mm; outer tepals usually emarginate or truncate apically (rarely rounded and capsules shorter than 6 mm).</description>
      <next_statement_id>44.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer spathes usually at least (12–)16 mm longer than inner; stems usually (1.5–)2–3.7 mm wide; keel of inner</description>
      <determination>27.  Sisyrinchium montanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Outer spathes no more than 16 mm longer than inner; stems 1–2.5 mm wide; keel of inner spathe not gibbous;</description>
      <determination>34.  Sisyrinchium idahoense</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
