<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sisyrinchium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rothrock" date="1877">arizonicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 125. 1877</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus sisyrinchium;species arizonicum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, cespitose, dark olive to blackish when dry, to 6 dm, not glaucous; roots conspicuously fleshy-thickened. Stems branched, with 2–4 nodes, 3.5–8 mm wide, glabrous to scabrous, margins denticulate at least apically, similar in color and texture to stem body; first internode 14–27 cm, shorter than leaves; distalmost node with 1–2 branches. Leaf blades glabrous to scabrous, bases not persistent in fibrous tufts. Inflorescences borne singly; spathes green, obviously wider than supporting branch, scabrous or glabrous, keels denticulate; outer 30–55 mm, equaling or to 3.7 mm longer than inner, tapering evenly towards apex, margins basally connate 5–6 mm; inner with keel evenly curved or abruptly gibbous, hyaline margins 0.3–0.8 mm wide, apex acuminate or rounded, ending just proximal to green apex. Flowers: tepals yellow to orange, usually with brownish veins; outer tepals 11–23 mm, apex rounded to acute, aristate; filaments connate only basally, base glabrous or occasionally stipitate-glandular; ovary similar in color to foliage. Capsules black or blackish brown, obovoid to turbinate, 8–19 mm; pedicel erect to ascending. Seeds globose, lacking depression, 1.5–2.2 mm, rugulose. 2n = 34, 36, 72.</description>
  <description type="habitat">moist meadows</description>
  <description type="habitat">stream banks</description>
  <description type="habitat">open places in coniferous forest</description>
  <description type="elevation">1600–3000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Mex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering mid--late summer. Moist meadows, stream banks, open places in coniferous forest; 1600--3000 m; Ariz., N.Mex.; nw Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering mid--late summer.</phenology>
      <habitat>Moist meadows, stream banks, open places in coniferous forest;</habitat>
      <elevation>1600--3000 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Ariz., N.Mex.; nw Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>2.</number>
</bio:treatment>
