<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sisyrinchium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="E. P. Bicknell" date="1899">strictum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>26: 299. 1899</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus sisyrinchium;species strictum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, cespitose, generally light green to yellowish green when dry, to 4.8 dm, not glaucous. Stems branched, with 1 node, 1.4–2.3 mm wide, glabrous, margins usually minutely denticulate, similar in color and texture to stem body; internode with 1–2 branches, 22–42 cm, usually longer than leaves. Leaf blades glabrous, bases not persistent in fibrous tufts. Inflorescences borne singly; spathes usually with purplish tinge on margins, obviously wider than supporting branch, glabrous, keels entire to occasionally denticulate; outer 16–22.8 mm, 0.2 mm shorter to 4 mm longer than inner, tapering evenly towards apex, margins basally connate 4.2–6.9 mm; inner with keel usually straight, hyaline margins 0.1–0.3 mm, apex acute, occasionally obtuse, sometimes separated as 2 lobes, ending 0–0.4 mm proximal to green apex. Flowers: tepals pale to deep bluish violet, bases yellow; outer tepals 9–19.5 mm, apex rounded or truncate, aristate; filaments connate ± entirely, usually stipitate-glandular basally; ovary similar in color to foliage. Capsules tan to nearly white, occasionally light brown, sometimes with purplish apex, ± globose to ± turbinate, 3.5–4.9 mm; pedicel erect or ascending. Seeds globose to obconic, lacking obvious depression, 0.9–1.2 mm, rugulose or granular.</description>
  <description type="habitat">moist meadows</description>
  <description type="habitat">stream banks</description>
  <description type="habitat">edges of open woods</description>
  <description type="habitat">mostly on sandy soil</description>
  <description type="elevation">150–200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mich.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wis.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering early--mid summer. Moist meadows, stream banks, edges of open woods, mostly on sandy soil; 150--200 m; Mich., Wis.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering early--mid summer.</phenology>
      <habitat>Moist meadows, stream banks, edges of open woods, mostly on sandy soil;</habitat>
      <elevation>150--200 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Mich., Wis.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>16.</number>
</bio:treatment>
