<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Norlan C. Henderson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">IRIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 38. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 24. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus IRIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek iris , rainbow]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from rhizomes [bulbs or fascicles of fleshy roots]; rhizomes homogeneous with branches like primary in size and texture, or heterogeneous, branches cordlike with scalelike leaves, enlarging at apex to produce vegetative leaves, additional cordlike branches, and flowering stems. Flowering stems simple or branched, erect (declining or semierect and obviously zigzag in I. brevicaulis and some of its hybrids), solid or hollow, terete or slightly flattened. Leaves: basal 3–10, in fan; blade monofacial (except at base), smooth or ridged, sometimes centrally thickened, veins obscure to prominent; cauline 0–4 on branched stems, usually similar to basal, subtending each branch, decreasing in length distally, sometimes bracteiform and sheathing stem. Inflorescences rhipidiate, units 1 or more-flowered, spathaceous; spathes 2, herbaceous with scarious tips, or completely scarious, with or without distinct keel, often persisting and enclosing capsule(s) at maturity. Flowers lasting 1–4 days, upward-facing, usually somewhat fragrant (odor extremely unpleasant in I. foetidissima), pedicellate or sessile; perianth epigynous, white, yellow, tan, brown, copper-red, maroon, blue, blue-violet, or purple, often with markings of contrasting colors, differentiated into sepals and petals, actinomorphic, 4–18 cm diam.; floral tube distal to ovary, terete or occasionally ridged, solid proximally, hollow distally; sepals 3, spreading or reflexed, expanding either gradually or abruptly from claw into broader limb, with signal of prominent ridge, crest, distinct lines or dots, pubescence, or band of multicellular hairs (beard) along midline of claw and for short distance along midrib of limb; petals 3, erect, spreading or rarely reflexed, sometimes very reduced and mostly hidden by sepal bases; stamens opposite sepals, free but appressed to style branches; style dividing distally into petaloid branches, these arching outward and over stamens and claws of sepals, dividing at apex into 2 rounded or triangular lobes (style crests); stigma a lip of tissue on adaxial surface of style arm at base of crest; ovary terete or roundly 3- or 6-angled or -grooved. Fruits capsular, wall papery or becoming dry and hardened, sometimes indehiscent (in I. giganticaerulea). Seeds 4–20, in 1–2 rows per locule, often flattened in contact with others, rounded on outer surface; seed coat tan to dark brown (red in I. foetidissima), thin, membranous, and smooth, or conspicuously roughened to extensively corky (usually in wetland species), with or without obvious aril. x = uncertain.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Northern Hemisphere.</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 280 (34 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Because irises have large, handsome flowers, have many different forms, colors, and color patterns, and are easily grown and propagated, they have become popular garden ornamentals. Many non-native irises may be found in the flora area, not only in specialized gardens, but in casual plantings and persisting around old dwellings, in cemeteries, and along roadsides. These include not only the more common bearded irises, but members of the Sibirian, Spuria, Japanese, and Dutch groups. In the Pacific Coast and southeastern areas of the flora, repeated hybridization, both natural and artificial, of some of the local species has produced hundreds of garden forms that have added greatly to the popularity of this genus. Asexual reproduction in many Iris species may be more important than sexual reproduction in their persistence, and many hybrid clones may persist for decades in sites no longer cultivated.</discussion>
  <discussion>The species of Iris differ from members of other native genera of the Iridaceae in North America in three ways: 1) the sets of outer and inner perianth members (sepals and petals herein) differ from each other in shape, orientation, and, in some cases, coloration; 2) the parts of the flowers—petals, sepals, stamens, and styles—are united basally into a floral tube that surmounts the ovary; and 3) the styles are petaloid and modified with some specialized structures to insure cross pollination.</discussion>
  <discussion>T. Holm (1929) restricted the term rhizome to a horizontal, usually subterranean, stem that produces roots from its lower surface and green leaves from its apex, developed directly from the plumule of the embryo. He recognized stolons as axillary, subterranean branches that do not bear green leaves but only membranaceous, scalelike ones. The rhizomes of Iris are of two basic kinds: homogeneous, with the branches like the primary one in size and texture, and heterogeneous, with the branches of the primary rhizome like stolons with scalelike leaves. These enlarge at the apex to produce green leaves and more stolonlike branches.</discussion>
  <discussion>According to B. Mathew (1990), Iris includes six subgenera. Species of subgenera Iris and Limniris are rhizomatous; the others are either bulbous or perennial from a fascicle of fleshy roots. Three species of subg. Iris are sometimes found naturalized from cultivation in the flora area. Other species of the subgenus are found here only in cultivation or as waifs. The native North American species of Iris all belong to subg. Limniris, usually referred to as the beardless irises. The four other subgenera, which are found in the flora area only in cultivation or as waifs, have all been recognized sometimes as separate genera: subg. Nepalensis (Dykes) Lawrence as Junopsis Schulze; subg. Xiphium (Miller) Spach as Xiphion Miller; subg. Scorpiris Spach as Juno Trattinnick; and subg. Hermodactyloides Spach as Iridodictyum Rodionenko. F. Köhlein (1987) accepted these four segregate genera; however, most current authors circumscribe Iris in the broad sense, as here.</discussion>
  <discussion>Elevation is unimportant in the taxonomy and ecology of Iris, and very rarely is it recorded on specimen labels. Consequently, elevations are not reported in the species treatments that follow.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Anderson, E. 1936. The species problem in Iris. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 23: 457–509. British Iris Society. 1997. A Guide to Species Irises: Their Identification and Cultivation. Cambridge and New York.</reference>
    <reference>Foster, R. C. 1937. A cytotaxonomic survey of the North American species of Iris. Contr. Gray Herb. 119: 3–79.</reference>
    <reference>Henderson, N. C. 1991. Iris ×pacifica. Bull. Amer. Iris Soc. 280: 85–87.</reference>
    <reference>Henderson, N. C. 1994. The Louisiana irises. Bull. Amer. Iris Soc. 293: 73–82. Köhlein, F. 1987. Iris, transl. M. C. Peters. Portland.</reference>
    <reference>Dykes, W. R. 1913. The Genus Iris. Cambridge.</reference>
    <reference>Foster, M. 1889. On irises. J. Roy. Hort. Soc. 11: 131–149.</reference>
    <reference>Mathew, B. 1990. The Iris, rev. ed. Portland.</reference>
    <reference>Wister, J. C. 1927. The Iris: A Treatise on the History, Development and Culture of the Iris for the Amateur Gardener. New York and London.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals with multicellular hairs (beard) along midrib of claw and base of blade.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems absent or not more than 1 cm; floral tubes 6–10 cm; capsules borne on tips of</description>
      <determination>1.  Iris pumila</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 6–12 dm; floral tubes 1–2.5 cm; capsules borne on ends of stems and branches.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spathes entirely scarious, silvery white</description>
      <determination>2.  Iris pallida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spathes herbaceous with narrow scarious margins and tip, green, sometimes purple</description>
      <determination>3.  Iris germanica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals without beard, usually with signal of contrasting color, fine pubescence, ridges, or cockscomblike crest.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes heterogeneous, innovations appearing at some distance from parent rhizome.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals with 3-ridged, toothed crests.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 2.5–4.5 cm; floral tubes filiform, 4–8 cm; spathes sharply keeled</description>
      <determination>4.  Iris cristata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 0.8–4 cm; floral tubes funnelform, 1–2 cm; spathes slightly keeled</description>
      <determination>5.  Iris lacustris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals without crests or crests inconspicuous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cordlike portions of rhizomes 4 dm; stems 3–8 dm; pedicels 3–7 cm; floral</description>
      <determination>34.  Iris prismatica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cordlike portions of rhizomes 0.1–2 dm; stems 0–3.5 dm; pedicels 0.4–3.5 cm; floral tubes 0.3–6.5 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cordlike portions of rhizomes 10–20 cm; stems 1–2-branched; leaf blades</description>
      <determination>6.  Iris tenuis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cordlike portions of rhizomes 1–15 cm; stems simple; leaf blades 3–13 mm</description>
      <determination>7.  Iris verna</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes homogeneous; innovations appearing close to parent rhizome.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals 1–2 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals without apical bristle; se United States</description>
      <determination>8.  Iris tridentata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals with apical bristle 3–8 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched; Alaska, British Columbia, and Yukon</description>
      <determination>9.  Iris setosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems usually simple, with single, clasping leaf at midstem; Maritime Pro-</description>
      <determination>10.  Iris hookeri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals 2–9.5 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hollow</description>
      <determination>11.  Iris sibirica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems solid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 6-angled or -ridged.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths copper colored or reddish brown, rarely yellow; petals spread-</description>
      <determination>29.  Iris fulva</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths blue-violet or rarely white; petals erect or spreading-erect.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems declining or semierect, sharply zigzag</description>
      <determination>30.  Iris brevicaulis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems erect, not obviously zigzag.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules with 3 plane faces and 3 faces with 2 rounded ridges;</description>
      <determination>28.  Iris hexagona</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules approximately circular in cross section, only slightly if at all hexagonal, with 6 narrow, winglike ridges or 6 broadly rounded lobes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules with 6 sharp, winglike ridges, dehiscent</description>
      <determination>31.  Iris savannarum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules with 6 broad, rounded lobes, indehiscent</description>
      <determination>32.  Iris giganticaerulea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 3-angled or nearly round in cross section.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes stout, 1–4 cm diam.; roots fleshy.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths yellow or white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths entirely yellow</description>
      <determination>25.  Iris pseudacorus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths white with large yellow patch at base of sepals</description>
      <determination>33.  Iris orientalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianths blue-violet or rarely white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigmas unlobed; leaf blades prominently veined; e, c United States and Canada.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals with yellow pubescent signal at base of blade</description>
      <determination>27.  Iris virginica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals with pubescent, green or greenish yellow patch surrounded by heavily</description>
      <determination>26.  Iris versicolor</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigmas 2-lobed; leaf blades not prominently veined; w United States.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pedicels slender; spathes scarious, 3.5–7 cm; perianths veined deep blue-violet on lighter background; capsules 4–5 cm; w Great Plains and moun-</description>
      <determination>23.  Iris missouriensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pedicels stout; spathes herbaceous, 8–15 cm; perianths pale blue-violet or nearly white with prominent yellow ridge on sepal claws; capsules 8–9 cm;</description>
      <determination>24.  Iris longipetala</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes slender, 3–12 mm diam.; roots fibrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 1–4-branched</description>
      <determination>13.  Iris douglasiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems simple.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades of fan leaves with margins thickened</description>
      <determination>17.  Iris purdyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Blades of fan leaves with margins not thickened.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves bractlike, imbricated, blade inflated.</description>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes 0.8–0.9 cm</description>
      <determination>16.  Iris bracteata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes 3–12 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes linear; capsules 2–3 cm; pedicels absent or 0.5–1 cm</description>
      <determination>18.  Iris chrysophylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes funnelform; capsules 3–4 cm; pedicels 0.8–1.8 cm at</description>
      <determination>19.  Iris tenuissima</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves foliaceous, spreading, blade not inflated.</description>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes greater than 1.5 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes 1.5–3 cm</description>
      <determination>20.  Iris innominata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes 3–8 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spathes broadly lanceolate; leaf blades 7–8 mm wide; peri-</description>
      <determination>21.  Iris fernaldii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spathes linear-lanceolate; leaf blades 4–6 mm wide; perianths</description>
      <determination>14.  Iris macrosiphon</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Floral tubes 0.5–1.5 cm (occasionally to 2 cm in I. tenax ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes creeping, not producing dense clumps</description>
      <determination>15.  Iris hartwegii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes many-branched, producing dense clumps.</description>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 1.5–2.7 dm; inflorescence units 1–2-flowered; style crests</description>
      <determination>12.  Iris tenax</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems 6–7 dm; inflorescence units 3(–4)-flowered; style crests</description>
      <determination>22. Iris munzii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
