<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">iris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. Watson" date="1882">tenuis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 380. 1882</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus iris;species tenuis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes superficial or very shallow, cordlike portion 1–2 dm × 2 mm, expanding to 10–15 mm diam., nodes with brown, scalelike leaves and few to no roots. Stems 1–2-branched, 3–3.2 dm. Leaves: basal with blade pale green, 3.2 dm × 1.5 cm, margins scarious basally, apex acute, proximal 2 semi- sheathing, blade 5 cm, scarious; cauline 1–2, sheathing branch and stem for ca. 1/2 their length, blade ca. 5 cm, semimembranous. Inflorescences 2–3-branched, each unit with single flower, all borne at approximately the same level; spathes 2–3 cm × 5 mm, subequal, scarious except basally and along midrib. Flowers: perianth white or blue tinged with deep violet lines; floral tube funnelform, 0.3 cm; sepals oblong-spatulate, 2.8 × 1 cm, apex deeply emarginate, signal an inconspicuous crest with low, yellow, undissected ridge; petals bluish white, oblanceolate-spatulate, base gradually attenuate into claw; ovary elliptical, 0.4–0.7 cm; style 1.8 cm, crests broadly obovate, 0.7 cm, margins erose; stigmas triangular-acuminate, margins entire; pedicel 0.4–1 cm, not lifting flower clear of spathes. Capsules depressed-globose, roundly triangular, 0.9–1.5 × 1.2 cm. Seeds pale brown, with whitish raphe, D-shaped, pitted. 2n = 28.</description>
  <description type="phenology">may</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="habitat">open, wooded slopes in leafy soil with douglas fir and dense shrubs</description>
  <description type="distribution">Oreg.</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Clackamas iris</other_name>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Iris tenuis was originally placed in ser. Californicae, but R. C. Foster (1937) stated, “It is with some hesitation that I leave it in association with them. The broad, pale green leaves are much like those of a giant I. cristata.” F. H. Smith and Q. D. Clarkson (1956) said, “It clearly does not belong in the subsection with the other members of the Californicae,” and Clarkson in a later treatment (1958) created a new subsection, the Oregonae, for it. L. W. Lenz (1959b) moved this species into subsect. Evansia (= sect. Lophiris), with which it shows many relationships.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
