<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>11.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Iris</genus_name><species_name>sibirica</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 39. 1753</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Siberian iris</common_name><description>Rhizomes compact, freely branching, forming dense clumps, 0.9–1.2 cm diam., covered with remnants of old leaves. Stems simple or 1–3-branched, hollow, 6–12 dm. Leaves dying back in winter, blade dark green, often tinged pink at base, 4–8 dm × 0.4–0.6 cm. Inflorescence units 3–5-flowered, lateral units 2–3-flowered; spathes brown, to 4 cm, narrow, papery, apex acute. Flowers: perianth light to dark blue-violet to white; floral tube with indistinct ribs, circular, ca. 1 cm; sepals flaring or curving downward apically, widely orbiculate, 5–7 × 2–2.5 cm, base abruptly attenuate into claw with two narrow flanges basally, signal white, semicircular, with dark violet veins basally; petals erect, narrowly elliptic-obovate, 4.5–5.5 × 1.5–1.8 cm; ovary roundly triangular, spindle-shaped, 1.5–2 cm; style pale blue, bluntly keeled, 4–5 cm, crests overlapping, triangular, margins crenate; stigmas tonguelike projections, triangular; pedicel 1–15 cm, unequal, later flowers in each spathe with longer pedicel. Capsules roundly triangular with low ridges at angles, 3–4.5 × 1–1.3 cm, smooth, apex with extremely short tip, opening only in upper 1/4–1/3 of capsule. Seeds in 2 rows per locule, dark brown, D-shaped, flattened, 5 × 3 mm, slightly roughened by small, rounded protuberances. 2n = 28.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>widely cultivated</habitat><habitat>found along roadsides</habitat><introduced>introduced;</introduced><ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Conn.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mass.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Pa.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Vt.</us_distribution><global_distribution>expected elsewhere</global_distribution><global_distribution>Eurasia.</global_distribution><discussion>Many forms of Iris sibirica have been cultivated widely across North America, where it is quite hardy and persistent.</discussion></treatment>
