<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>14.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Iris</genus_name><species_name>macrosiphon</species_name><species_authority>Torrey</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Pacif. Railr. Rep.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4(5): 144. 1857</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Ground iris</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Iris</genus_name><species_name>elata</species_name><species_authority>Piper</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Rhizomes many-branched, forming tufts, with fibrous remains of old leaves at nodes, slender, 0.6–0.8 cm diam.; roots few, fibrous. Stems simple, solid, almost absent or to 2.5 dm. Leaves: basal longer than stem, blade light green, finely veined, narrowly linear, 3–4 dm × 0.4–0.6 cm, glaucous, margins not thickened, apex acute; cauline 1–2, spreading, sheathing for about 1/2 length, foliaceous, blade not inflated, 0.7–1 dm. Inflorescence units (1–)2-flowered; spathes nearly opposite, connivent, linear-lanceolate, 4–9.5 cm × 4–6 mm, subequal or outer longer. Flowers: perianth indigo, purple, lavender, white, cream, or yellow; floral tube linear, gradually dilating apically, 6 cm; sepals usually with fine, dark veins basally, becoming coarser on claw, oblanceolate or obovate, 3.9–7 × 2 cm, base abruptly attenuate into claw; petals oblanceolate, 3.5–6 × 0.5–1.6 cm, base gradually attenuate; ovary ovoid, ca. 1 cm; style 2–3.5 cm, crests overlapping, reflexed, semiovate, 0.8–1.8 cm, margins denticulate; stigmas triangular, margins entire; pedicel 1.5–2 cm. Capsules oblong to ovoid, somewhat 3-angled in cross section, 2.5–3 cm. Seeds dark brown, angular, finely wrinkled. 2n = 40.</description><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>sunny hillsides</habitat><habitat>meadows</habitat><habitat>roadsides</habitat><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Iris macrosiphon hybridizes with I. chrysophylla, I. douglasiana, I. fernaldii, I. hartwegii, I. innominata, I. munzii, I. purdyi, I. tenax, and I. tenuissima.</discussion><discussion>The invalid name “Iris californica” Leichtlin has sometimes been applied to a portion of this species.</discussion></treatment>
