<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">iris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. Watson" date="1885">bracteata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20: 375. 1885</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus iris;species bracteata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes sheathed with old leaf bases, slender, 0.6–0.9 cm diam.; roots few, fibrous. Stems simple, solid, 1.5–3 dm. Leaves: basal with abaxial surface of blades deep glossy green on one side of fan, light yellow-green on other side, pink or red-tinged basally, strongly ribbed, 4–6 dm × 0.8–1 cm, rigid, margins not thickened; cauline 3–6, imbricated, closely sheathing stem ca. 2/3 length, spreading distally, bractlike, blade inflated, often shorter than basal leaves. Inflorescences simple, units 1–2-flowered; spathes closed tightly around pedicel and ovary, lanceolate, 5.2–9 cm × 6–8 mm, subequal, herbaceous, margins scarious, apex acuminate. Flowers: perianth cream to buff-yellow; floral tube 0.8–0.9 cm; sepals with deeper yellow signal, veined with purple or brown, obovate-lanceolate, 6.5 × 2.5 cm, base gradually attenuate into wide claw; petals narrowly oblanceolate, 7–9 × 0.8–2 cm, base gradually attenuate; ovary nearly circular in cross section, 1.5–2.5 cm, base gradually attenuate into pedicel, apex abruptly acuminate into floral tube; style 2.2–3 cm, crests spreading, yellow, not veined, 1.2 × 0.9–1.7 cm, margins toothed; stigmas triangular or tongue-shaped, margins entire; pedicel 3–6.2 cm. Capsules nearly circular in cross section, tapering abruptly at each end, 2–2.5 × 1–1.5 cm. Seeds dark brown, irregular in shape, wrinkled. 2n = 40.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May--Jun.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shady forests, particularly ponderosa pine;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif., Oreg.</description>
  <number>16.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Siskiyou iris</other_name>
  <discussion>Iris bracteata is limited to one county each in northern California and southern Oregon. It hybridizes with I. chrysophylla, I. douglasiana, I. innominata, I. munzii, I. purdyi, and I. tenax.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
