<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>21.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Iris</genus_name><species_name>fernaldii</species_name><species_authority>R. C. Foster</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Iridis Sp. Nov.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1. 1938</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Fernald’s iris</common_name><description>Rhizomes many-branched, producing dense clumps, compact, slender, ca. 0.6 cm diam., base covered with remains of old leaves; roots fibrous. Stems simple, solid, 2–4 dm. Leaves: basal with blade gray-green, usually brilliantly colored basally, drying to unusual gray-green, veins fairly prominent, to 4 dm × 0.7–0.8 cm, often quite glaucous, margins not thickened; cauline 2–several, spreading, sheathing stem for about 1/2 length, foliaceous, blade not inflated. Inflorescence units 2-flowered; spathes opposite, connivent, often flushed red basally, broadly lanceolate, 5–9 cm × 6–11 mm, subequal. Flowers: perianth pale creamy yellow with gold or gray veins; floral tube funnelform, 3–6.2 cm, spreading apically to form wide throat; sepals horizontally spreading, claw with deep yellow median line, oblanceolate to spatulate, 4.5–7 × 1–2 cm, base gradually attenuate into broad claw; petals narrowly oblanceolate, 4.3–6 × 0.6–1.4 cm, base gradually attenuate into narrow claw; ovary elliptical, nearly circular in cross section, 1.5–2.3 cm; style 2.2–3 cm, crests divergent, linear to narrowly oblong, 1–1.7 cm; stigmas triangular, margins entire; pedicel 0.9–2.2 cm at anthesis. Capsules oblong, roundly trigonal, distinctly beaked, 2.5–3.5 cm. Seeds dark brown, wrinkled. 2n = 40.</description><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>mixed evergreen forest</habitat><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Iris fernaldii hybridizes with I. douglasiana, I. innominata, and I. macrosiphon.</discussion></treatment>
