<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Peter Goldblatt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">IRIDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Herbert" date="unknown">ALOPHIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Mag.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>66: under plate 3779. 1840</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family IRIDACEAE;genus ALOPHIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek a , not, and lophos , crest, referring to the absence of style crests]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Engelmann &amp; A. Gray" date="unknown">Eustylis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eustylis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from tunicate, ovoid bulbs; tunic brown, dry, brittle, papery. Stems simple or branched. Leaves few, basal larger; blade pleated, linear-lanceolate. Inflorescences rhipidiate, few-flowered; spathes green, unequal, outer shorter than inner, apex acute. Flowers short-lived, ± nodding [sometimes drooping], actinomorphic; tepals spreading, distinct, blue to purple, clawed, unequal, outer whorl larger than [± equaling] inner, claw surface sometimes folded or pinched basally forming lobes that partly obscure nectary zone, often with band of nectar-bearing hairs; stamens closely appressed to style; filaments distinct [occasionally connate], usually weak, unable to support anthers; anthers fused lightly to style, fiddle-shaped; pollen sacs marginal, connective visible; style slender proximally, gradually widening and branched distally; branches fairly deeply divided into 2 recurved arms, arching over or between anthers, filiform, apically stigmatic. Capsules ovoid to oblong, cartilaginous, apex truncate. Seeds many, irregularly globose; seed coat brown. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America (incl. Mexico)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical South America.</description>
  <number>7.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pinewoods-lily</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">purple pleat-leaf</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 5 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Goldblatt, P. and T. M. Howard. 1992. Notes on Alophia (Iridaceae) and a new species, A. veracruzana, from Vera Cruz, Mexico. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 79: 901–905.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
