<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Peter Goldblatt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="unknown">WATSONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fig. Pl. Gard. Dict.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>184, plate 276. 1758</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus WATSONIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For William Watson, 1715–1787, British botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from corms. Stems simple or branched. Leaves several; blade plane, lanceolate to linear, usually coarse, fibrotic. Inflorescences spicate, erect, many-flowered; bracts green, often flushed with red, unequal, usually outer exceeding inner, apex acute, inner forked apically, firm to leathery. Flowers short-lived, odorless [rarely fragrant], zygomorphic [actinomorphic], distichous; tepals horizontal or suberect, connate into tube, orange, red, or purple [pink, rarely white], ± equal [equal]; perianth tube funnel-shaped or elongate, expanded distally into wide, horizontal upper part; stamens unilateral [symmetrical], arcuate [declinate], extended horizontally below dorsal tepal; anthers parallel [diverging]; style arching below or above filaments [central], dividing opposite to [beyond] anthers into 3 filiform branches each divided for ca. 1/2 their length, apically stigmatic. Capsules [globose to] oblong, wood-textured, rounded [acute or attenuate]. Seeds several to many, angular, 1- or 2-winged [prismatic]; seed coat light brown. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">s Africa.</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <discussion>Species 52 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Several species of Watsonia are cultivated in the flora area where the winters are mild, especially in California; only W. meriana is truly naturalized. The following have been recorded as persisting for some years around abandoned dwellings, in cemeteries and garbage dumps, and along roads and highways: W. borbonica (Pourret) Goldblatt (both pink- and white-flowered forms), W. fourcadei J. W. Mathews &amp; L. Bolus, and W. marginata (Linnaeus f.) Ker Gawler.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Goldblatt, P. 1989. The genus Watsonia. A systematic monograph. Ann. Kirstenbosch Bot. Gard. 17.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
