<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Peter Goldblatt</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">iridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Maratti" date="unknown">ROMULEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pl. Romul. Saturn.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13. 1772</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family iridaceae;genus ROMULEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Romulus, one of the mythical founders of Rome, the type species of the genus being common around that city]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from corms. Stems: true stem aerial [subterranean and only peduncles of individual flowers aerial], simple or branched. Leaves 1–several; blade linear, oval to terete in cross section, 4-grooved (2 on each surface, on either side of thickened midrib) [2-grooved]. Inflorescences solitary flowers, interpreted as sessile, thus without pedicels; bracts inserted at ovary base, green or flushed with purple, unequal, outer exceeding inner, firm, inner bract margins membranous to scarious (rarely entirely scarious). Flowers odorless [fragrant], actinomorphic; tepals forming wide cup, connate into tube, subequal, outer whorl often slightly larger than inner; perianth tube funnel-shaped [or cylindric]; stamens symmetrical; filaments distinct [connate]; anthers usually erect, contiguous; style branching opposite or beyond anthers into 3 slender branches divided for ± 1/2 length. Capsules ovoid-oblong, walls firm, cartilaginous. Seeds many, globose; seed coat light to dark brown, often smooth, shiny. x = 13 or 14.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">s Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Middle East.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species ca. 90 (1 in the flora): introduced; Africa, s Europe, Middle East.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species ca. 90 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; Africa, s Europe, Middle East.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>15.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 90 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Vos, M. P. 1972. The genus Romulea in South Africa. J. S. African Bot., suppl. 9. De</reference>
    <reference>Manning, J. C. and P. Goldblatt. 2001. A synoptic review of Romulea (Iridaceae: Crocoideae) in sub-Saharan Africa, the Arabian Peninsula and Socotra including new species, biological notes, and a new infrageneric classification. Adansonia, sér. 3, 23: 59–108.</reference>
    <reference>Vos, M. P. 1983. Romulea. In: Department of Agricultural Technical Services [South Africa]. 1963+. Flora of Southern Africa.... 19+ vols. (some partial). Pretoria. Vol. 7, part 2, fasc. 2, pp. 10–73.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
