<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Walter C. Holmes,Heather L. White</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Batsch" date="unknown">ALOACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ALOACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Trees, shrubs, and succulents, perennial, simple to sparsely branched, rhizomatous, some tuberous-thickened. Leaves simple, alternate, usually crowded at bases of stems or ends of branches, sessile; blade fleshy, margins often prickly, venation parallel. Inflorescences terminal, axillary, or lateral, spicate, racemose, or paniculate. Flowers 3-merous, short- to long-pedicellate, rarely sessile; perianth red, brown, yellow, orange, or whitish; tepals petaloid, connivent or connate basally to almost entirely into tube, sometimes fleshy; stamens sometimes 3, usually 6, exserted or included; anthers dorsifixed, dehiscence antrorse; pollen grains monosulcate; ovary 3-carpellate, placentation axile, usually with septal nectaries; style terminal; stigmas punctate, discoid, or 3-lobed. Fruits capsular, rarely baccate, dehiscence loculicidal, apical. Seeds usually winged or flattened.</description>
  <description type="distribution">all introduced</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Madagascar</description>
  <description type="distribution">Arabia</description>
  <description type="distribution">and Atlantic islands.</description>
  <number>224.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Aloe Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 5, species ca. 700 (1 genus, 2 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Aloaceae are closely related to and included by some authors in Liliaceae.</discussion>
  <discussion>The juice of some Aloe species is used to make a purgative called bitter aloe; active ingredients include aloin and other anthraquinones. Additionally, the thick, mucilaginous gel of some species is widely used to treat minor thermal burns, itching, and sunburn.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
