<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>3.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>DASYLIRION</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Zuccarini</genus_authority>
  <place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Allg. Gartenzeitung</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>6: 258. 1838</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[Greek dasy- , thick- or dense-, and lirion , white lily, alluding to the compact
    arrangement of flowers in the inflorescence]</etymology>
  
  <common_name>Sotol</common_name>
  <author>David J. Bogler</author>
  <description>Plants perennial, polycarpic; roots spreading, 2–8 mm diam. Stems short or elongate,
    often with erect or reclining trunk. Leaves persistent, numerous, forming rosettes, spreading;
    blade long-linear, fibrous, glabrous, sometimes waxy-glaucous, bases expanded, overlapping,
    spoon-shaped, margins with sharp, curved prickles, apex fibrous. Inflorescences paniculate,
    racemose, bracteate; panicles narrow, borne on long, woody stalks; bracts leaflike proximally,
    stramineous distally, lanceolate; fascicles of dense racemes in axils of bracts. Flowers small,
    functionally unisexual, some plants with only male flowers, others with only female flowers;
    floral bracts laciniate, membranous; tepals 6, distinct, whitish, greenish, or purple, obovate,
    margins denticulate; stamens 6, rudimentary in pistillate flowers; ovary superior, 3-angled,
    abortive in staminate flowers; style short, ± strap-shaped, slightly expanded at tip; stigma
    3-lobed, lobes weakly connate into tube; pedicel of pistillate flowers articulate. Fruits
    capsular, 1-locular, dry, indehiscent, 3-winged. Seed 1, golden brown, 3-angled, turbinate. x =
    19.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>dasylirion species 17 (3 in the flora)</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>arid, mountainous regions of sw united states and
    mexico</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Dasylirion was once a major food source in the desert southwest. The bulbs were
    roasted in rock-lined pits and pounded into cakes. A potent alcoholic beverage, known as
    “sotol,” is distilled from the baked and fermented bulbs. Leaves of Dasylirion are widely used
    to weave baskets.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>  Bogler, D. J. 1994. Taxonomy and Phylogeny of Dasylirion (Nolinaceae). Ph.D.
      dissertation. University of Texas.  Trelease, W. 1911. The desert group Nolineae. Proc. Amer.
      Philos. Soc. 50: 404–443.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves whitish or bluish green, waxy-glaucous, papillose, dull; marginal prickles
        all antrorse; fascicles of flowers elongate, branches lateral, pendent, 10–20 cm from base
        to tip; capsules obovoid, 5–8 × 4–5(–7) mm, distal wing lobes 2–2.5 mm, often indented;
        Arizona, New</statement>
      <determination>1.  Dasylirion wheeleri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves bright green, glabrous, not waxy, smooth, shiny; marginal prickles antrorse,
        retrorse, or mix of both; fascicles of flowers short, condensed, branches mostly basal, not
        pendent, 5–12 cm from base to tip; capsules ellipsoid or obovoid, 5–7 × 4–5 mm, distal wing
        lobes less than 2 mm, rounded, not indented; New Mexico, Texas.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Majority of prickles antrorse; leaves 1–2 cm wide; capsules ellipsoid, 5.5–6 × 4–5
        mm,</statement>
      <determination>2.  Dasylirion texanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Majority of leaf prickles retrorse; leaves 1.5–3 cm wide; capsules ellipsoid to
        obovoid,</statement>
      <determination>3.  Dasylirion leiophyllum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
