<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>R. Laurie Robbins</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">agavaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Engelmann" date="1871">HESPERALOE</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in S. Watson, Botany (Fortieth Parallel),</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>497. 1871</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family agavaceae;genus HESPERALOE</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hesperos , western, and aloe , a kind of plant]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, cespitose, acaulescent, semisucculent, primarily short- to long-rhizomatous. Leaves in basal rosettes; blade linear, thick and striate-ridged abaxially, margins with threadlike, detaching filaments, apex frayed or with hard spine. Inflorescences paniculate [racemose], loose, 3–8-branched. Flowers bisexual; perianth narrowly tubular to broadly campanulate; tepals 6; stamens 6, inserted on receptacle or at tepal bases, included; filaments glabrous; anthers sagittate, with septal nectaries; receptacle fleshy; ovary superior; style slender, barely exceeding tepals. Fruits capsular, ovoid, dehiscence septicidal. Seeds many, black, flattened. x = 30.</description>
  <description type="distribution">arid regions of Texas and Mexico (Coahuila, Nuevo León, San Luis Potosí, Sonora).</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <discussion>Species 5 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Hesperaloe parviflora, and to a much lesser extent H. funifera, are cultivated in the semiarid and arid Southwest. The original distribution of H. parviflora is likely much obscured because of a long history of roadside and ornamental plantings throughout the area.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Engard, R. G. 1980. Hesperaloe: Potential for arid lands. In: Centro de Investigación en Química Aplicada. 1970. Yucca. Saltillo. Pp. 115–123. Starr. G. 1995. Hesperaloe: Aloes of the West. Desert Pl. 11(4): 3–8. </reference>
    <reference>Starr, G. 1997. A revision of the genus Hesperaloe (Agavaceae). Madroño 44: 282–296.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers green, tinged with purple, broadly campanulate; leaf blade yellowish green, 1–2</description>
      <determination>1.  Hesperaloe funifera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers rosy red to salmon, narrowly tubular; leaf blade dark green, 1–1.25 m × 2.5 cm</description>
      <determination>2.  Hesperaloe parviflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
