<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Frederick H. Utech</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">liliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">AMIANTHIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Lyceum Nat. Hist. New York</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 121. 1837</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family liliaceae;genus AMIANTHIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[merged Greek amiantos , unsoiled, and anthos , flower, alluding to the glandless
    tepals]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">Chrosperma</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>1825</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>name rejected</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Chrosperma;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, from bulbs; bulbs tunicate, ovoid-oblong, ca. 5 × 2.5 cm; roots
    contractile. Stems erect, simple. Leaves mostly basal, reduced distally, spiral, arching
    downward, sheathing proximally; blade linear-elongate, strap-shaped, glabrous, apex obtuse to
    abruptly acute. Inflorescences terminal, racemose, dense, bracteate, glabrous. Flowers bisexual
    or both bisexual and unisexual flowers borne on the same or on different plants, cup-shaped to
    widely spreading, pedicellate; tepals persistent, 6, distinct, white, turning reddish green,
    claws absent, oblong-obovate, equal to subequal, apex acute; tepal glands absent; stamens 6,
    perigynous, distinct; filaments subulate, apex acute; anthers basifixed, 1-locular,
    cordate-ovate, extrorse, opening into peltate disc (apical/valvate dehiscence); pollen sacs
    apically confluent; ovary superior to partly inferior, 3-locular, diverging; septal nectaries
    absent; styles persistent, 3, widely diverging, distinct; stigmas terminal, minute. Fruits
    capsular, deeply 3-lobed, thin-walled, dehiscence septicidal, then adaxially loculicidal. Seeds
    1–2 per locule, brownish to purplish black, wingless, ellipsoid, lustrous; testa fleshy. x =
    8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e North America.</description>
  <number>15.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Fly-poison</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">crow-poison</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">St. Elmo’s-feather</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">staggergrass</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Amianthium is frequently included in a broadly circumscribed Zigadenus (J. D. Ambrose
    1975, 1980; S. M. Kupchan et al. 1961; S. J. Preece 1956; W. B. Zomlefer 1997b). The absence of
    tepal nectaries or glands is a major generic characteristic of this Appalachian–Ozark taxon (F.
    H. Utech 1986). Narrow-leaved specimens of Amianthium are often confused with Zigadenus
    densus.</discussion>
  <discussion>A self-incompatible, pollination-breeding system involving primarily beetles occurs in
    Amianthium (M. E. Palmer et al. 1989; A. M. Redmon et al. 1989; J. Travis 1984). An associated
    tepal color shift, as in Zigadenus densus, may represent possible pollinator signals (J. Travis
    1984).</discussion>
  <discussion>Two unique, toxic alkaloids, jervine and amianthine, found in Amianthium roots and
    leaves (N. Neuss 1953; S. M. Kupchan et al. 1961; R. F. Raffauf 1970; I. W. Southon and J.
    Buckingham 1989; G. E. Burrows and R. J. Tyrl 2001), caused deaths in cattle and sheep. Native
    Cherokee used the plant as a dermatological cure for itch and as a crow poison (D. E. Moerman
    1986). Root extracts mixed with molasses or honey have been used as a housefly insecticide (C.
    D. Marsh et al. 1918).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Utech, F. H. 1986. Floral morphology and vascular anatomy of
      Amianthium muscaetoxicum (Walter) A. Gray (Liliaceae–Veratreae) with notes on distribution and
      taxonomy. Ann. Carnegie Mus. 55: 481–504. </reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
