<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">agavaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">agave</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="W. C. Hodgson" date="2001">phillipsiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 410, fig. 1. 2001</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family agavaceae;genus agave;species phillipsiana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants acaulescent, freely suckering; rosettes solitary to cespitose, 7.5–10 × 7.5–10 dm, open. Leaves erect, 76–78 × 10–11 cm; blade glaucous-green to dark green, lightly cross-zoned, lanceolate, rigid, adaxially concave toward apex, abaxially convex at base; margins straight or undulate, armed, teeth single, well defined, brittle, 4–7 mm, 1–2.5 cm apart, interstitial teeth (2–)3–7, mostly along distal 2/3 of margins; apex not conspicuously incurved, spine brownish gray, slender, 2.5–4 cm. Scape 2.7–5.5 m. Inflorescences narrowly paniculate, not bulbiferous, open; bracts persistent, triangular, 1–2+ cm; lateral branches 9–16, ascending to nearly perpendicular, comprising distal 1/3–1/2 of inflorescence, longer than 10 cm. Flowers 32–45 per cluster, erect, 7.4–8.6 cm; perianth greenish cream, tube campanulate, 15.5–20 × 15–23 mm, limb lobes persistent and often leathery during and after anthesis, spreading, unequal, 15–22 mm, apex often flushed with maroon; stamens long-exserted; filaments inserted subequally below rim of perianth tube, erect, yellow, 4.8–6.4 cm, apex flushed with maroon; anthers yellow, 17–25 mm; ovary 3.3–4.6 cm, neck slightly constricted, 4–8 mm. Capsules not seen. Seeds unknown. 2n = ca. 120.</description>
  <description type="phenology">early summer</description>
  <description type="habitat">sandy to gravelly places with desert scrub</description>
  <description type="elevation">700–1100 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz.</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Phillips agave</other_name>
  <discussion>Agave phillipsiana is known from only four sites within Grand Canyon National Park. All are found on terraces along permanent waterways. Three of the sites are near pre-Columbian agricultural features or habitation sites. Two sites occur near a Kayenta-Anasazi Pueblo cliff dwelling (a.d. 1000–1150), on a terrace presumably once farmed by the early inhabitants. Agave phillipsiana possesses traits that would be advantageous to those harvesting it for food, since it is a plant that freely offsets and has open rosettes with large, long leaves that are easily cut. The species is possibly an ancient cultivar selected by pre-Columbian people from populations related to A. palmeri, A. colorata Gentry, or other closely related taxa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
