<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>
      <title>FNA V24</title>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <number></number>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <rank>species</rank>
    <name_authority_date></name_authority_date>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology"></description>
  <key>
    <key_heading>POEAE SUBKEY II</key_heading>
    <key_discussion>Synoecious, monoecious, or dioecious grasses with spikelets having 2-22 sexual florets, the lower florets sexual, the distal florets sometimes sterile.</key_discussion>
    <key_body>
1. One or both glumes exceeding the adjacent lemmas, sometimes exceeding the distal floret. 
2. All lemmas within a spikelet unawned or with awns shorter than 2 mm.
3. Spikelets usually with 2 florets, lemmas of the lower florets unawned, lemmas of the upper florets awned, the awns strongly curved or hooked .....14.53 Holcus (in part)
3. Spikelets with 2-22 florets, all lemmas unawned or if awned, the awns straight.
4. Leaf sheaths closed for at least 1/2 their length; caryopses falling free of the lemma and palea; plants of arctic or subarctic regions.
5. Lemma apices obtuse; paleas subequal to the lemmas  .....14.17 Arctophila (in part)
5. Lemma apices acute to acuminate; paleas shorter than the lemmas.....14.15 Dupontia (in part)
4. Leaf sheaths open for most of their length; caryopses usually falling with the lemma and palea attached; plants of temperate, arctic, or subarctic regions.
6. Glumes 15-50 mm long; plants annual.....14.52 Avena (in part)
6. Glumes 0.4-9 mm long; plants annual or perennial.
7. Lemmas inflated, about as wide as long, with broadly rounded backs; calluses glabrous; spikelets pendulous    .....14.21 Briza (in part)
7. Lemmas not inflated, longer than wide, keeled to rounded over the midvein; calluses usually with hairs, sometimes glabrous; spikelets not pendulous.
8. Plants annual; spikelets with 2 florets; lemmas evenly hairy, 3-veined  .....14.46 Dissanthelium 
8. Plants usually perennial, sometimes annual; spikelets with 2-10 florets; lemmas usually glabrous or with unevenly distributed hairs, never both annual and with evenly distributed hairs, 3-9-veined. 
9. Rachilla internodes hairy, hairs at least 1 mm long.
10. Lemma apices truncate, erose to 2-4-toothed  .....14.26 Deschampsia (in part)
10. Lemmas apices acute, bifid .....14.56 Trisetum (in part)
9. Rachilla internodes glabrous or with hairs shorter than 1 mm on the distal portion.
11. Plants strongly rhizomatous; glumes 5-9 mm long   .....14.51 Scolochloa (in part)
11. Plants not or weakly rhizomatous; glumes 0.4-9 mm long.
12. Panicle branches densely pubescent, hairs 0.1-0.2 mm long; lemma apices entire, sometimes mucronate;  lemma  veins converging distally .....14.57 Koeleria (in part)
12. Panicles branches glabrous, sometimes scabrous; lemma apices entire or serrate to erose, not mucronate; lemma veins more or less parallel distally .....14.06 Puccinellia (in part)
2. One or all lemmas within a spikelet awned, the awns at least 2 mm long.
13. Lemmas 14-40 mm long; glumes 7-11-veined  .....14.52 Avena
13. Lemmas 1.3-16 mm long; glumes 1-9-veined. 
14. Lemmas 7-16 mm long.
15. Adaxial surfaces of the leaves ribbed; rachillas pilose on all sides; ligules truncate to rounded, 0.5-1.5 mm long .....14.47 Helictotrichon (in part)
15. Adaxial surfaces of the leaves unribbed; rachillas glabrous on the side adjacent to the paleas, hairy elsewhere; ligules acute to truncate, 0.5-7 mm long .....14.45 Avenula (in part)
14. Lemmas 1.3-7 mm long.
16. Lemmas 1-veined, awned, awns articulated near the middle, the proximal segment yellow-brown to dark brown, the distal segment pale green to whitish, the junction marked by a ring of minute, conical protuberances .....14.55 Corynephorus
16. Lemmas 3-7-veined, at least some lemmas awned, awns not articulated.
 
17. Disarticulation below the glumes.
18. Spikelets usually with 2 florets, the lower florets bisexual with unawned lemmas, the upper florets staminate or sterile with awned lemmas  .....14.53 Holcus (in part)
18. Spikelets with 2-5 florets, all florets bisexual or sometimes the distal florets sterile; all lemmas awned.....14.56 Trisetum (in part)
17. Disarticulation above the glumes.
19. Lowest lemma within a spikelet unawned or with a straight awn up to 4 mm long, the distal lemmas within a spikelet always awned, awns 10-16 mm long, geniculate .....14.36 Ventenata (in part)
19. All lemmas within a spikelet similarly awned or the awns of the lower lemmas longer than those of the upper lemmas, or the upper lemmas with awns shorter than 10 mm.
20. Callus hairs about 1/2 as long as the lemmas; rachillas not prolonged or prolonged about 0.5 mm or less beyond the base of the distal floret; plants loosely cespitose .....14.41 Vahlodea
20. Calluses usually glabrous or the hairs much shorter than 1/2 the length of the lemmas, if about 1/2 as long, the rachillas prolonged more than 0.5 mm beyond the base of the distal floret and the plants usually densely cespitose. 
21. Plants annual; culms 1-60 cm tall; rachillas not prolonged beyond the base of the distal florets .....14.22 Aira (in part)
21. Plants perennial or annual; culms 5-150 cm tall; rachillas prolonged beyond the base of the distal florets, the prolongations hairy.
22. Rachilla internodes glabrous or with hairs shorter than 1 mm on the distal portion; panicle branches densely pubescent, not scabrous .....14.57 Koeleria (in part)
22. Rachilla internodes hairy, hairs at least 1 mm long; panicles branches usually glabrous, sometimes scabrous. 
23. Lemma apices truncate, erose or 2-4-toothed .....14.26 Deschampsia (in part)
23. Lemmas apices acute, bifid   .....14.56 Trisetum (in part)
1. Both glumes shorter than or subequal to the adjacent lemmas.
24. Upper lemma(s) in a spikelet with hooked or geniculate awns, awns 2-16 mm long; lowest  lemmas unawned or terminally awned, awns straight, to 4 mm long. 
25. Spikelets 9-15 mm long, with 2-20 florets; awns of the distal florets 10-16 mm long .....14.36 Ventenata (in part)
25. Spikelets 3-7 mm long, with 2 florets; awns of the distal floret 2-5 mm long .....14.53 Holcus (in part) 
24. Lemmas all similarly awned or unawned.
26. Lower lemmas with awns longer than 2 mm.
27. Calluses hairy; rachillas prolonged beyond the base of the distal florets.
28. Glumes shorter than the adjacent lemmas; ligules 4.5-20 mm long   .....14.48 Amphibromus
28. Glumes subequal to the adjacent lemmas; ligules 0.5-6 mm long .....14.56 Trisetum (in part)
27. Calluses glabrous or sparsely hairy; rachillas sometimes prolonged beyond the base of the distal florets.
29. Panicles dense, spikelike; plants annual.....14.59 Rostraria (in part)
29. Panicles not both dense and spikelike; plants perennial or annual.
30. Anthers 1; plants annual.....14.04 Vulpia (in part)
30. Anthers 3; plants perennial.
31. Leaves without auricles; blades flat, conduplicate, involute, or convolute .....14.01 Festuca (in part)
31. Lower leaves with auricles; blades flat   .....14.03 Schedonorus (in part)
26. Lower lemmas unawned, mucronate, or with awns up to 2 mm long.
32. Lemmas inflated, about as wide as long; spikelets pendulous   .....14.21 Briza (in part)
 
32. Lemmas not inflated, longer than wide; spikelets appressed to divergent, not pendulous. 
33. Lemmas apices rounded, truncate, obtuse, or emarginate.
34. Lemmas conspicuously 3-veined; lower glumes 0-3-veined.
35. Lower glumes without veins; lemmas not keeled over the lateral veins .....14.19 Catabrosa
35. Lower glumes 1-3-veined; lemmas keeled over each vein .....14.20 Cutandia (in part)
34. Lemmas (3)5-9-veined, the veins often inconspicuous; lower glumes 1-5-veined.
36. Inflorescences usually exceeded by the leaves; lemmas indurate at maturity; pedicels 0.5-0.8 mm thick; culms usually prostrate to procumbent,  sometimes  ascending;  upper glumes 2.6-6.2  mm long .....14.09 Sclerochloa (in part)
36. Inflorescences exceeding the leaves at maturity; lemmas usually membranous at maturity, sometimes coriaceous; pedicels less than 0.5 mm thick; culms usually erect; upper glumes 0.7-4.5(9) mm long. 
37. Lower glumes about as long as the upper glumes but no more than 1/2 as wide; disarticulation below the glumes .....14.25 Sphenopholis (in part)
37. Lower glumes shorter than the upper glumes or subequal and more than 1/2 as wide; disarticulation above the glumes.
38. Sheaths closed for more than 1/2 their length.....14.17 Arctophila (in part)
38. Sheaths open their entire length.
39. Panicle branches stiff; lemmas coriaceous; plants annual; culms to 60 cm tall ..... 14.35 Desmazeria (in part)
39. Panicle branches flexible; lemmas usually membranous, sometimes coriaceous; plants usually perennial, sometimes annual or biennial; culms 2-145 cm tall.
40. Lemma veins excurrent, lemma apices indistinctly 3-lobed or toothed; plants strongly rhizomatous, rhizomes succulent .....14.51 Scolochloa (in part)
40. Lemma veins not excurrent, lemma apices entire, serrate, or erose; plants sometimes rhizomatous, rhizomes not succulent. 
41. Lemma veins  (5)7-9, prominent; plants  of non-saline and non-alkaline habitats .....14.18 Torreyochloa (in part)
41. Lemma veins (3)5(7), inconspicuous or prominent; plants of saline and alkaline habitats .....14.06 Puccinellia (in part)
33. Lemma apices acute to acuminate, sometimes mucronate or shortly awn-tipped.
42. Lemmas (3)5-9-veined, veins more or less parallel distally, conspicuous. 
43. Lemma veins (5)7-9; plants rhizomatous, growing in non-saline and non-alkaline habitats  .....14.18 Torreyochloa (in part)
43. Lemma veins (3)5(7); plants not truly rhizomatous, sometimes the culms rooting at buried lower nodes, growing in saline and alkaline habitats .....14.06 Puccinellia (in part)
42. Lemmas 3-9-veined, veins converging distally, usually inconspicuous, sometimes conspicuous.
44. Lemmas conspicuously 3-veined, keeled over each vein; panicle branches divaricate; plants annual .....14.20 Cutandia (in part)
 
44. Lemmas inconspicuously (3)5-9-veined, sometimes keeled over the midvein, not over the other veins; panicle branches divaricate or not; plants annual or perennial. 
45. Disarticulation below the glumes; lower glumes subequal to the upper glumes but no more than 1/2 as wide  .....14.25 Sphenopholis (in part)
45. Disarticulation above the glumes, sometimes above the basal floret; lower glumes shorter than the upper glumes or, if subequal, more than 1/2 as wide.
46. Panicle branches smooth, hairy, hairs soft   .....14.57 Koeleria (in part)
46. Panicle branches smooth or scabrous, glabrous or strigose, never covered with soft hairs. 
47. Rachillas pilose, hairs at least 2 mm long (see Stipeae, p. 110) .....10.01 Ampelodesmos
47. Rachillas glabrous or with hairs shorter than 1 mm.
48. Basal leaves with auricles   .....14.03 Schedonorus (in part)
48. No leaves with auricles.
49. Lemma veins parallel distally; plants of saline and alkaline habitats ..... 14.06 Puccinellia (in part)
49. Lemma veins converging distally; plants of many habitats, including saline habitats.
50. Leaf blades with translucent lines on either side of the midvein, apices often prow-tipped; lemmas often with a tuft of hair at the base of the midvein; hila round to oval .....14.13 Poa (in part)
50. Leaf blades without translucent lines on either side of the midvein, apices not prow-tipped, often flat; lemmas without a tuft of hair below the midvein hila usually linear, always linear in perennial species. 
51. Plants perennial.
52. Plants and florets bisexual; glumes not translucent; caryopses obovoid-oblong   .....14.01 Festuca (in part)
52. Plants unisexual; glumes translucent; caryopses fusiform.....14.02 Leucopoa
51. Plants annual.
53. Ligules up to 1 mm long; lemma apices mucronate or awned  .....14.04 Vulpia (in part)
53. Ligules 1-4  mm long; lemma apices never awned,  sometimes mucronate.
54. Panicle branches up to 2 cm long, stiff, spikelet-bearing to the base; culms procumbent to erect   .....14.35 Desmazeria (in part)
54. Panicles branches 2-10 cm long, flexible, spikelets confined to the distal portion; culms erect  .....14.24 Eremopoa

    </key_body>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
