<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>
      <title>FNA V24</title>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <number></number>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <rank>genus</rank>
    <name_authority_date></name_authority_date>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology"></description>
  <key>
    <key_heading>Poa Subkey IV</key_heading>
    <key_discussion>Plants perennial, not rhizomatous, not stoloniferous, loosely to densely tufted. Culms not bulbous-based. Basal sheaths not swollen. Spikelets not bulbiferous, florets developing normally. Anthers (1.2)1.3-4 mm long and dehiscent, or all rudimentary, having no or poorly formed pollen.</key_discussion>
    <key_body>
1. Calluses usually dorsally webbed, webs sometimes with 1 to few minute hairs, rarely the hairs somewhat diffuse [for opposite lead, see p. 503].
2. Lemma lateral veins pronounced, keels pubescent, marginal veins glabrous or softly puberulent at the base, lemmas glabrous elsewhere; lower glumes 1-veined, subulate to narrowly lanceolate, usually arched to sickle-shaped; callus web well developed   .....49. P. trivialis (in part)
2. Lemma lateral veins obscure to pronounced, keels glabrous throughout or, if pubescent, the marginal veins distinctly pubescent for more than 1/4 their length, lemma lateral veins and intercostal regions glabrous or pubescent, or, if pubescent as in P. trivialis, then the callus web short, scant, poorly developed and the lower glumes 3-veined and lanceolate or broader.

 
3. Panicles open, conical, with whorls of (2)3-10, spreading to eventually reflexed, scabrous-angled branches at the lower nodes; lemmas hairy on the keel and veins, sometimes the intercostal regions also hairy; callus webs well developed .....3. P. sylvestris (in part)
3. Panicles contracted to open, if open then not conical and without whorls of (2)3-10, eventually reflexed, scabrous-angled branches at the lower nodes; branches smooth or scabrous-angled; lemmas glabrous or hairy; calluses glabrous, with diffuse hairs, or with a scanty or well-developed web. 
4. Sheaths closed for (1/5)1/3-3/4 their length.
5. Culms 8-35 cm tall, 0.5-0.8 mm thick; panicle branches smooth or sparsely scabrous; anthers to 1.3 mm long; plants alpine  .....50. P. laxa (in part)
5. Culms 23-120 cm tall, 0.5-2 mm thick; panicle branches smooth or scabrous; anthers to 1.8 mm long; plants of many habitats, including alpine habitats.
6. Lemmas usually hairy on the keel and marginal veins, usually also on the intercostal regions; palea keels softly puberulent to short-villous at midlength; panicles open and erect, broadly pyramidal at maturity; callus webs sparse, poorly developed  .....6. P. autumnalis (in part)
6. Lemmas glabrous or with a few hairs at the base of the keel or marginal veins; palea keels scabrous, glabrous; panicles contracted to loosely contracted or open and lax; callus webs scant and short or well developed. 
7. Callus webs well developed; lemma keels glabrous; plants of eastern North America  ...... P. saltuensis (in part)
7. Callus webs minute, sometimes somewhat diffuse; lemma keels glabrous or sparsely softly puberulent near the base; plants of western North America .....42. P. cusickii (in part)
4. Sheaths closed for 1/20 – 1/4(1/3) their length.
8. Basal branching all or mostly intravaginal; plants not stoloniferous.
9. Culms 30-90 cm tall; panicles open; plants of the mountains in and around the Chihuahuan Desert .....26 P. strictiramea (in part)
9. Culms 5-15(20) cm tall; panicles contracted; alpine plants of the Rocky Mountains .....61. P. abbreviata (in part)
8. Basal branching all or mostly extra vaginal, or extra- and intravaginal and the plants stoloniferous.
10. Flag leaf nodes usually in the lower 1/10-1/3 of the culms; flag leaf blades usually distinctly shorter than their sheaths; lemmas sometimes softly puberulent between the veins, lateral veins usually with at least a few minute hairs; ligules 1-4(5) mm long .....57. P. glauca (in part)
10. Flag leaf nodes usually in the upper 2/3 of the culms; flag leaf blades shorter or longer than their sheaths; lemmas glabrous between the veins, lateral veins usually glabrous, rarely with 1 to several minute hairs; ligules 0.2-6 mm long.
11. Spikelets narrowly lanceolate to lanceolate; glumes subulate to narrowly lanceolate, gradually tapering to narrowly acuminate apices; lower glume lengths 6.4-11 times the widths; ligules 0.2-0.5(1) mm long, truncate; flag leaf nodes at or above the middle of the culms; flag leaf blades usually longer than their sheaths; rachillas usually hairy, hairs to 0.15 mm long; webs usually short, scanty .....55. P. nemoralis (in part)
11. Spikelets and glumes not as above or, if so, the ligules 1.5-6 mm long, truncate to acute, and the rachillas glabrous; flag leaf nodes at or above the lower 1/3 of the culm; flag leaf blades longer or shorter than their sheaths; webs short or long, scanty or not.
12. Panicles (9)13-30(41) cm long, branches 4-15 cm long; culms closely spaced to isolated at the base; lower glumes tapering to the apices, lengths 6.4-10 times the widths; lemma keels abruptly inwardly arched beneath the scarious apices; lemma margins distinctly inrolled; rachillas usually muriculate, rarely sparsely hispidulous; web hairs usually longer than 2/3 the length of the lemmas .....54. P. palustris (in part)

 
12. Panicles (1.5)3-15(17) cm long, branches 0.4-8(9) cm long; culms closely spaced at the base; lower glumes abruptly narrowing to the apices, lengths 4.5-6.3 times the widths; lemma keels not abruptly inwardly arched beneath the scarious apices; lemma margins not or slightly inrolled; rachillas usually muriculate or softly puberulent; web hairs shorter than 1/2(2/3) the length of the lemmas .....56. P. interior (in part)
1. Callus glabrous or with a crown of hairs, hairs 0.1-2 mm long [for opposite lead, see p. 501]. 
13. Lemmas and calluses glabrous [for opposite lead, see p. 505].
14. Blades (4) 6-15 mm wide, flat or folded; sheaths closed for 1/2-1/4 their length, strongly compressed, keeled, keels winged  .....25. P. chaixii
14. Blades 0.5-5 mm wide, flat, folded, or involute; sheaths closed for ^ha-h their length, not strongly compressed, if keeled, keels not winged.
15. Sheaths closed for 2/5 – 4/5 their length; panicles 1-5(8) cm long, with (1)6-17(22) spikelets, nodes with 1-2 branches; branches appressed to spreading, smooth or sparsely scabrous; spikelets strongly compressed, lanceolate to broadly ovate; ligules hyaline, smooth, (1)2-4 mm long; blades 0.5-1 mm wide, thin, lax, filiform, soon withering; plants from the Columbia Plateau to southwestern Idaho and northwestern Nevada  ..... 45. P. leibergii
15. Sheaths closed for 1/20-3/4 their length, if for 2/5-3/4 , then the panicles longer than 8 cm or with more than 20 spikelets or the ligules of the innovations (and sometimes also the culms) 0.5-2.5 mm long and scabrous and often milky white; blades (0.5)1-5 mm wide, sometimes moderately thick and firm and holding their form; plants of many regions, including the range of P. leibergii. 
16. Panicles (7)10-30 cm long, open, pyramidal, nodes with 2-5 moderately to densely scabrous branches; sheaths closed for 1/20 – 1/10 their length; basal branching intravaginal; plants of the Chisos Mountains of Texas to Mexico.....26. P. strictiramea (in part)
16. Panicles 1-25 cm long, contracted to loosely contracted or, if open, nodes with 1-3(5) smooth or scabrous branches; sheaths closed for 1/20 – 3/4 their length; basal branching intravaginal, extravaginal, or both; plants of many regions, including the range of P. strictiramea.
17. Sheaths closed for (1/4)1/3 - 3/4 their length; florets often unisexual, anthers 2-3.5 mm long or nonfunctional and to 1.8 mm long; uppermost ligules of the innovation leaves 0.2-0.5(2.5) mm long, scabrous, usually truncate; innovation blades usually involute; panicles contracted, loosely contracted, or open; lower glumes distinctly shorter than the lowest lemmas.
18. Flag leaf blades usually absent or to 1 cm long; blades of the culm leaves sharply reduced in length upwards, similar in thickness and form to those of the innovations, moderately firm, usually involute; plants of southeastern Arizona and southwestern New Mexico.....41. P. fendleriana (in part)
18. Flag leaf blades usually present and 1+ cm long; blades of the culm leaves not sharply reduced in length upwards, sometimes differing in thickness or form from those of the innovations, soft, narrow and withering or broader and flat; plants from other parts of the Flora region.
19. Panicles contracted or loosely contracted, branches smooth or sparsely to densely scabrous; innovation blades 0.5-2 mm wide, abaxial surfaces smooth or scabrous, adaxial surfaces usually densely scabrous or hispidulous; plants from southern Yukon Territory to California and Colorado.....42. P. cusickii (in part)
 
19. Panicles open or slightly contracted, branches smooth or sparsely  scabrous; innovation blades 1-2 mm wide, abaxial surfaces smooth, adaxial surfaces usually smooth or sparsely scabrous; plants of Alaska, Yukon Territory, and Northwest Territories .....44. P. porsildii
17. Sheaths closed for 1/20 – 2/5 their length; if sheaths closed for 1/4-2/5 their length then all florets bisexual, or the functional anthers 1.2-1.8 mm long, or the ligules of the uppermost innovation leaves 2+ mm long and smooth or scabrous, or the lower glumes subequal to the lowest lemmas; blades of the innovation leaves involute or not; panicles contracted; lower glumes shorter than to equaling the lowest lemmas.
20. Culms 5-40 cm tall; panicles 3-7 cm long, densely contracted, nearly cylindrical; culm blades to 5 mm wide, often a bit fleshy and broader than those of the innovations, those of the innovations usually thin and soon withering, infrequently all blades flat and a bit fleshy; florets bisexual; plants of the Pacific coast .....71. P. unilateralis (in part)
20. Culms 2-120 cm tall; panicles 1-25 cm long, densely to loosely contracted, not cylindrical; culm blades 0.5-5 mm wide and soft, culm and innovation blades not much differentiated or, if differentiated, then the basal blades moderately firm and involute; florets unisexual or bisexual; plants of non-coastal regions.
21. Culms 30-120 cm tall; panicles (4)5-25 cm long; spikelet lengths 3-5 times the widths; plants of saline or non-saline habitats, often below the subalpine zone, if of non-saline habitats, the spikelet lengths (3.8)4-5 times the widths and the panicles usually over 10 cm long.
22. Spikelets (4)7-10 mm long, subterete, narrowly lanceolate, lengths usually (3.8)4-5 times the widths; plants of many habitats, widespread.....64. P. secunda (in part)
22. Spikelets 4.5-7 mm long, compressed, lengths 3-3.5 times the widths; plants of mineralized soils around hot springs in Napa County, California .....70. P. napensis (in part)
21. Culms 2-40 cm tall; panicles 1-8 cm long; spikelet lengths 2-4 times the widths; plants of non-saline, subalpine or alpine habitats.
23. Ligules of the innovations 2.5-6 mm long, hyaline, smooth; panicles loosely contracted or contracted; basal branching extravaginal; lower glumes distinctly shorter than the lowest lemmas; florets often unisexual .....46. P. stebbinsii
23. Ligules of the innovations 0.5-2.5 mm long, usually milky, often scabrous; panicles contracted; some or all basal branching intravaginal; lower glumes distinctly shorter than or subequal to the lowest lemmas; florets bisexual or unisexual. 
24. Florets unisexual; anthers 2-4 mm long; blades involute .....47. P. pringlei
24. Florets bisexual; anthers 0.6-3.5 long; blades flat, folded, or involute.
25. Anthers 2.2-3.5 mm long; culms 15-40 cm tall; longest culm blades 1-3 cm long and fairly firm, with thick white margins and broadly prow-tipped apices, basal blades similar; plants of serpentine soils in Washington .....66. P. curtifolia (in part)
25. Anthers 0.6-1.2(2) mm long; culms 2-25 cm tall; basal and upper culm leaves not always similar, culm leaves without the above combination of characteristics; plants of non-serpentine soils from British Columbia to California.

 
26. Abaxial  surfaces  of the  innovation  blades smooth or sparsely scabrous, epidermes with papillae on the long cells (at l00x); abaxial surfaces of the flag leaf blades with 7-15 closely spaced ribs; culms 2-6(10) cm tall; plants of California .....62. P. keckii (in part)
26. Abaxial surfaces of the innovation blades densely hispidulous, scabrous, or softly puberulent, rarely smooth and glabrous, lacking papillae on the long cells (at 100x); abaxial surfaces of the flag leaf blades with 5-9 well-spaced ribs; culms 7-25 cm tall; plants of British Columbia, Washington, and Oregon .....63. P. suksdorfii (in part)
13. Lemmas with hairs; calluses glabrous or hairy [for opposite lead, see p. 503].
27. Sheaths closed for 1/2-3/4 their length; lemmas mostly glabrous, lower lemmas of some spikelets usually sparsely softly puberulent near the base of the keels and/or marginal veins, lemmas glabrous elsewhere; panicles 4-7 cm long, with 13-50 spikelets, branches smooth or sparsely scabrous; spikelets 7-10 mm long, strongly laterally compressed; florets pistillate; plants of subalpine to alpine habitats, from southern British Columbia to California .....42. P. cusickii (in part)
27. Sheaths closed for 1/20 – 3/4 their length, if closed for 1/2 - 3/4 their length, the lemmas pilose between the veins or the panicle branches moderately to densely scabrous; lemmas variously pubescent, frequently pilose between the veins; panicles 1-30 cm long, with 9-100+ spikelets; branches smooth or sparsely to densely scabrous; spikelets 3-12 mm long, subterete to strongly laterally compressed; florets bisexual or unisexual; plants of various habitats, including subalpine to alpine habitats, widely distributed, including from British Columbia to California.
28. Sheaths closed for 1/3-1/2 their length; panicles (5)8-20 cm, erect or lax, broadly pyramidal at maturity, open, lower axils sometimes sparsely hairy; panicle branches spreading to reflexed, angled, longest branches 5-12 cm long, with 3-8 spikelets in the distal 1/3-1/4; paleas pilose; florets bisexual; plants of eastern North American woods .....6. P. autumnalis (in part)
28. Sheaths closed for 1/20 – 3/4 their length, if closed for 1/3 – 3/4 their length, then the panicles contracted or loosely contracted, or the branches smooth, or the longest branches shorter than 5 cm, or the paleas glabrous, or the spikelets unisexual; panicles 1-40 cm long, lower axils glabrous; panicle branches erect, ascending, or widely divergent, terete or angled; plants widely distributed, including eastern North American woods.
29. Basal branching mainly extra vaginal, usually occurring late in the season; sheaths closed for 1/10 – 1/5 their length; blades usually flat, sometimes folded, thin, soft; panicle branches usually scabrous-angled; lemmas distinctly keeled; spikelets laterally compressed, lengths 2-3 times the widths. 
30. Lemmas glabrous on the lateral veins and intercostal regions; culms usually with 1-2(3) nodes exserted, uppermost node usually at or above the lower 1/3 of the culm .....56. P. interior (in part)
30. Lemmas usually at least sparsely softly puberulent on the lateral veins, intercostal regions with similar hairs or glabrous; culms with 0-1 nodes exserted, uppermost node usually in the lower 1/10-1/3 of the culms .....57. P. glauca (in part)
29. Basal branching intra- or extra vaginal or mixed, if mostly extravaginal, branching often occurring early in the season; sheaths closed for 1/20 – 3/4 their length; blades involute, flat, or folded, thin and soft to thick and firm; panicle branches terete or angled, smooth or scabrous; lemmas weakly to distinctly keeled; spikelets subterete or laterally compressed, lengths 1.5-5 times the widths.
 
31. Spikelets ovate, rachilla internodes 0.5-0.8 mm; panicles 2-6(8) cm long, open or loosely contracted; branches terete, usually smooth or sparsely scabrous, rarely moderately densely scabrous, longest branches 1-3(4) cm; leaves mostly basal, blades 1-6(12) cm long, 2-4.5 mm wide, flat, soft; calluses glabrous; lemmas distinctly keeled, keels and marginal veins long- to short-villous, intercostal regions short-villous; paleas softly puberulent to short-villous at midlength; florets bisexual  .....9. P. alpina (in part)
31. Spikelets lanceolate to narrowly ovate, rachilla internodes 0.5-2 mm long; panicles 1-40 cm long, open or contracted; branches terete or angled, smooth or variously scabrous, longest branches 0.5-15 cm; leaves not as above; calluses glabrous or with a crown of hairs; lemmas weakly to distinctly keeled, variously hairy; paleas glabrous or softly puberulent; florets bisexual or unisexual.
32. Panicles contracted; florets usually unisexual, rarely bisexual, commonly pistillate; blades usually involute.
33. Sheaths closed for 1/7- 1/3 their length; lemmas weakly keeled; calluses usually with a crown of hairs around the base of the lemma; adaxial surfaces of the innovation blades smooth or somewhat scabrous; anthers late-aborted, 0.8-1.8 mm long; plants of the high arctic .....67. P. hartzii (in part)
33. Sheaths closed for 1/4 - 3/4 their length; lemmas strongly keeled; calluses glabrous; adaxial surfaces of the innovation blades usually hispidulous to softly puberulent on and between the veins; anthers of pistillate plants rudimentary, 0.1-0.2 mm long; plants not arctic.
34. Sheaths closed for about 1/3 their length; culm leaf blades sharply reduced in length upwards, the flag leaf blades absent or vestigial, commonly less than 1 cm long, always less than 1/5 the sheath length, when present usually firm, not withering; innovation blades usually 1-3 mm wide; lemmas short- to long-villous on the keel and marginal veins .....41. P. fendleriana (in part)
34. Sheaths closed for 1/4 - 3/4 their length; culm leaf blades gradually reduced in length upward along the culm or some midculm blades longer than the lower culm blades, culm blades narrow, thin and withering; innovation blades usually 0.5-1(2) mm wide; lemmas usually softly puberulent, sometimes short-villous on the keel and marginal veins ..... 43. P. xnematophylla
32. Panicles contracted or open; florets usually bisexual, if unisexual, the panicles open; blades flat, folded, or involute. 
35. Panicles open or loosely contracted at maturity, 5-30 cm long, spikelets not crowded.
36. Spikelets laterally compressed, lengths usually 3-3.8 times the widths; lemmas distinctly keeled, intercostal regions glabrous or with hairs distinctly shorter than those over the keel and marginal veins.
37. Lemmas 2.5-3.5 mm long, usually glabrous throughout, infrequently with keels and marginal veins softly puberulent to short- or long-villous and/or intercostal regions sparsely softly puberulent; blades usually involute, rarely flat, scabrous; calluses usually glabrous, rarely sparsely and shortly webbed; panicles (7)10-30 cm long; plants of the Chisos Mountains in Texas and northern Mexico .....26. P. strictiramea (in part)
 
37. Lemmas 4-6 mm long, keels and marginal veins, sometimes also the lateral veins, short- to long-villous, intercostal regions glabrous or sparsely pilose or hispidulous near the bases; blades flat or folded, smooth or sparsely scabrous; calluses glabrous or with a crown of hairs, hairs 0.2-2 mm; panicles 5-18(25) cm long; plants of coastal Alaska, the Pacific Northwest, and Rocky Mountains .....69. P. stenantha (in part)
36. Spikelets subterete, lengths usually (3.8)4-5 times the widths; lemmas weakly keeled, usually at least sparsely softly puberulent, infrequently short-villous, between the veins, the hairs usually about the same length as those of the keel and marginal veins.
38. Ligules of the culm leaves usually 2-6 mm long, smooth or scabrous, truncate to acuminate; basal tuft of leaves narrow or loosely clumped; basal leaves reaching 2-20+ cm, blades filiform or to 3 mm wide; panicle branches capillary or stouter, smooth or scabrous; plants widespread, sometimes on serpentine soils, often in wet habitats ..... 64. P. secunda (in part)
38. Ligules of the culm leaves 0.5-1.5(2.5) mm long, scabrous, apices truncate to obtuse (acute); basal tuft of leaves narrow, tightly clumped; basal leaves reaching 2-8(13) cm, basal blades filiform; panicle branches capillary, distinctly scabrous; plants of thin, early drying serpentine soils in the Sierra Nevada foothills of California .....65. P. tenerrima
35. Panicles contracted at maturity, sometimes open during anthesis, 1-30 cm long, spikelets crowded or not. 
39. Plants 2-6(10) cm tall; panicles 1-4(6) cm long; cauline blades soft, folded, 1-3.5(4.5) cm long, upper cauline blades 0.9-1.8 mm wide, abaxial surfaces with 7-15 ribs; spikelets 3.5-6 mm long; calluses glabrous; lemmas glabrous or the keel and marginal veins sparsely softly puberulent near the base; plants of high alpine habitats in the Sierra Nevada and adjacent ranges .....62. P. keckii (in part)
39. Plants 5-120 cm tall; panicles 2-30 cm long; leaves not as above in all respects; spikelets 3-10 mm long; lemmas nearly glabrous to copiously pubescent, if hairy, only so near the base on the keel and marginal veins, the hairs softly to crisply puberulent; calluses glabrous or with a crown of hairs; plants widespread.
40. Plants 5-40 cm tall; panicles 3-7 cm long, usually densely contracted, rarely loosely contracted, nearly cylindrical; culm blades 2-5 mm wide, flat or folded; innovation blades usually 1-1.5 mm wide, involute, infrequently similar to the culm blades; anthers fully developed; plants of the Pacific coast .....71. P. unilateralis (in part)
40. Plants 10-120 cm tall; panicles 2-30 cm long, densely to loosely contracted, not nearly cylindrical; culm and innovation blades similar, 1-5 mm wide; anthers sometimes aborted late in development; plants of the high arctic or interior habitats of western North America.
 
41. Anthers usually sterile and to 1.5 mm long, infrequently well developed and 2-2.8 mm long; plants 10-33(45) cm tall; blades folded to involute, 1.5-3 mm wide, abaxial surfaces smooth or sparsely scabrous; spikelets lustrous; lemmas usually weakly keeled, more or less evenly and loosely short- to long-villous on the lower 1/3-1/2, hairs mostly longer than 0.5 mm; calluses usually with a crown of hairs to 2 mm long; panicle branches smooth or sparsely to moderately scabrous; plants of the high arctic .....67. P. hartzii (in part)
41. Anthers well developed, 1.2-3.5 mm long; plants 10-120 cm tall; blades flat, folded, or involute, 0.5-5 mm wide, abaxial surfaces smooth or scabrous; spikelets lustrous or not; lemmas weakly keeled or not, if the intercostal regions hairy, the hairs distinctly shorter than those on the keels or, if the lemmas more or less evenly hairy, then the hairs usually shorter than 0.5 mm; calluses usually glabrous, infrequently with a crown of hairs to 2 mm long; panicle branches smooth or sparsely to densely scabrous; plants of the high arctic or western North America, if of the high arctic, the lemma hairs shorter than 0.3 mm.
42. Lemmas usually evenly strigulose across the lower 1/3-1/2, hairs 0.1-0.2 mm long, rarely to 0.3 mm on the keel and marginal veins; blades soft, involute; culms 10-30 cm tall; panicles 3-6 cm long, longest branches 1-3(4) cm long, smooth or sparsely scabrous .....68. P. ammophila
42. Lemmas variously hairy, if as above, the panicle branches usually scabrous and/or the blades flat and soon withering; culms (10)20-120 cm tall; panicles 2-30 cm long; branches 1-15 cm long, sparsely to densely scabrous.
43. Culm blades 1-3 cm long, flat, (1)1.5-3 mm wide, with thick, white margins and broadly prow-shaped apices; panicles 4-8 cm long, narrowly lanceoloid; spikelets 7-9 mm long; plants of serpentine slopes in the Wenatchee Mountains of Washington   .....66. P. curtifolia (in part)
43. Culm blades longer or narrower than above, margins not thick and white, apices narrowly prow-shaped; panicles 2-30 cm long, narrowly lanceoloid to ovoid; spikelets (4)5-10 mm long; plants widespread.
 
44. Spikelets subterete to weakly laterally compressed, (4)5-10 mm long, lengths 3.5-5 times the widths; rachilla internodes usually 1-2 mm long; lemmas usually weakly keeled, 3.5-6 mm long, nearly glabrous or hairy all over the basal 2/3; culms (10)15-120 cm tall; panicles 2-25(30) cm long .....64. P. secunda (in part)
44. Spikelets laterally compressed, (4)4.5-7 mm long, lengths 3-3.5 times the widths; rachilla internodes usually shorter than 1 mm; lemmas distinctly keeled, 3-4 mm long, usually glabrous, keels and marginal veins rarely sparsely puberulent proximally; culms 30-100 cm tall; panicles 5-15 cm long .....70. P. napensis (in part)

    </key_body>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
