<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Paysonia</genus_name><species_name>lasiocarpa</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker ex A. Gray) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>12: 381. 2002</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Roughpod bladderpod</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Vesicaria</genus_name><species_name>lasiocarpa</species_name><species_authority>Hooker ex A. Gray</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>5(6): 13. 1853</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name><species_name>lasiocarpa</species_name><species_authority>(Hooker ex A. Gray) S. Watson</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Annuals, biennials, or peren-nials; pubescent, trichomes branched, or mixed with simple, larger ones. Stems decumbent to procumbent, (slender), 1–5 dm. Basal leaves: blade (oblanceolate), 3–10 cm × 10–30 mm, margins sinuate-dentate to somewhat lobed or incised, surfaces densely pubescent. Cauline leaves: blade obovate-elliptic to oblong, 1–4 cm × 5–20 mm, base cuneate to auriculate (narrowed toward base), margins sinuate-dentate to incised, (surfaces densely pubescent). Fruiting pedicels recurved, slightly curved, 1–3 cm, (racemes lax in fruit), densely pubescent. Flowers: sepals (green), 4–5.5 × 1.5–2 mm, (nearly acuminate), pubescent or hirsute (trichomes branched); petals light yellow (often drying purplish), 5–9 × 4–6 mm, (claw relatively short), apex rounded; filaments not dilated basally, (2.5–3.5 mm, anthers sagittate, 2–3 mm, glands with horn-like projections at base of filaments). Fruits sessile, orbicular, elliptic, or cordate, 5–9 × 4–9 mm, (angustiseptate or slightly so); valves (rounded or strongly keeled), densely pubescent, trichomes branched, sometimes with simple, larger ones; replum oblong to nearly elliptical; septum complete, (transparent); ovules 14–32 per ovary, (attached in proximal 1/2); style 1–1.5 mm; stigma expanded. Seeds suborbicular (slightly longer than broad), 1–2.2 mm.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>s United States</global_distribution><global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals; trichomes simple and branched; fruits inflated, valves rounded</statement>
      <determination>4a. Paysonia lasiocarpa subsp. lasiocarpa</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals, biennials, or perennials; trichomes usually simple, sometimes mixed with smaller, branched ones; fruits not inflated, valves somewhat to strongly keeled</statement>
      <determination>4b. Paysonia lasiocarpa subsp. berlandieri</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
