<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>14.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Physaria</genus_name><species_name>carinata</species_name><species_authority>(Rollins) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>12: 322. 2002</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Idaho bladderpod</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name><species_name>carinata</species_name><species_authority>Rollins</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. Gray Herb. </publication_title><place_in_publication>171: 42, fig. 1E–H. 1950</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials; caudex simple, (often enlarged by persistent leaf bases); densely pubescent, trichomes (sessile or short-stalked), rays furcate or bifurcate, (nearly smooth to finely tuberculate). Stems simple from base, decumbent, (occasionally few-branched), 0.5–1.5(–2) dm. Basal leaves: blade elliptic to broadly obovate, triangular, rhombic, or round, 1.5–3(–4) cm, margins often sinuate or shallowly lobed. Cauline leaves (sessile or shortly petiolate); blade elliptic to oblanceolate to obovate, 0.5–1.5 cm, (base narrowed to petiole), margins entire. Racemes compact to loose. Fruiting pedicels (ascending or divaricate-spreading, straight to loosely sigmoid or curved), 4–10 mm. Flowers: sepals oblong to broadly elliptic, 4–7.5 mm, (lateral pair saccate or not); petals spatulate, 7.5–10 mm. Fruits (sessile or substipitate), elliptic, suborbicular, or oblong, strongly compressed (angustiseptate), 5–9 mm, (rounded to sharply keeled on 1 side, edges ± keeled); valves: (margins covering replum edges or not), usually pubescent throughout or, rarely, glabrous inside; ovules (4–)8–14(–16) per ovary; style 2–4.5(–5) mm. Seeds slightly flattened.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>wc United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Differences in fruit morphology become blurred and the three subspecies are often indistinguishable where their ranges meet near the intersection of Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits elliptic, not keeled, valve margins (thin, rounded), not covering replum edges</statement>
      <determination>14b. Physaria carinata subsp. paysonii</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits elliptic, suborbicular, or broadly oblong, keeled on one side, valve margins covering replum edges.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits elliptic, bases narrow-rounded to acute,</statement>
      <determination>14a. Physaria carinata subsp . carinata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits suborbicular to elliptic or broadly oblong, bases and apices rounded</statement>
      <determination>14c. Physaria carinata subsp . pulchella</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
