<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>17.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Physaria</genus_name><species_name>condensata</species_name><species_authority>Rollins</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>41: 407, plate 556, figs. 1, 9, 10. 1939</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Tufted twinpod</common_name><description>Perennials; caudex usually simple, rarely branched, (enlarged with persistent leaf bases, cespitose); (silvery) pubescent throughout, trichomes several-rayed, rays typically furcate, (fused at base, arms slender, tuberculate throughout). Stems several from base, decumbent to ascending, (arising laterally beneath a dense rosette), less than 0.1 dm. Basal leaves: (petiole slender); blade (horizontal on the ground), obovate, 0.5–1.5 cm (width 4–8 mm, base tapering abruptly to petiole), margins entire, (apex usually acute, surfaces silvery from a dense incrustation of appressed, stellate trichomes). Cauline leaves: blade oblanceolate, 0.5–1 cm (width 2–3 mm), margins entire, (surfaces densely stellate pubescent). Racemes congested, (subumbellate, often almost sessile, barely exceeding basal leaves). Fruiting pedicels (divaricate, straight), 5–10 mm. Flowers: sepals (yellowish green), narrowly lanceolate, 4–5 mm; petals (erect), oblanceolate, 6–7 mm, (claw weakly differentiated from blade). Fruits didymous, ovate, inflated, 4.8–6 × 6–10 mm, (papery, basal and apical sinuses deep); valves (retaining seeds after dehiscence), pubescent, trichomes loosely spreading; replum obovate, 3–4 mm, as wide as or wider than fruit; ovules 8 per ovary (2–4 abortive); style 4–6 mm. Seeds flattened.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>calcareous knolls and ridges</habitat><habitat>clay banks</habitat><habitat>limey slopes</habitat><habitat>shaley hills</habitat><habitat>clay patches</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>1800–2400 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Wyo.</us_distribution></treatment>
