<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>21.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Physaria</genus_name>
    <species_name>densiflora</species_name>
    <species_authority>(A. Gray) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 322. 2002</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Denseflower or low bladderpod</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Vesicaria</genus_name>
    <species_name>densiflora</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Boston J. Nat. Hist.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 145. 1850</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name>
    <species_name>densiflora</species_name>
    <species_authority>(A. Gray) S. Watson</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Annuals or biennials; caudex simple or branched, (relatively small, cespitose); densely pub-escent, trichomes (spreading, sessile or short-stalked), 5–7-rayed, rays distinct and simple, (tuberculate, finely tubercled with a U-shaped notch on one side). Stems simple or few to several from base, erect or decumbent, (rarely branched, usually leafy), to 4 dm. Basal leaves: blade lyrate-pinnatifid, 1–7 cm, margins entire or shallowly dentate. Cauline leaves (sessile or shortly petiolate); blade narrowly obovate to elliptic, 0.5–6 cm, margins entire, repand, or shallowly dentate. Racemes dense, (elongated in fruit, often subtended by distal cauline leaves). Fruiting pedicels (usually divaricate-spreading, straight or slightly curved, delicate, sometimes drooping, especially on herbarium specimens), 7–10 mm, (somewhat rigid). Flowers: sepals elliptic, 3.7–7.2 mm, (lateral pair somewhat cucullate, median pair thickened apically); petals (yellow to orange-yellow), obovate to obdeltate, (4.5–)7–10(–11) mm, (tapering to short claw, apex often emarginate). Fruits (sessile or substipitate), globose or broadly obovate, not inflated, 4–6 mm, (smooth); valves (not retaining seeds after dehiscence), glabrous; replum as wide as or wider than fruit; ovules 8–16 per ovary; style 2–5 mm. Seeds flattened. 2n = 14.</description>
  <phenology>mar</phenology>
  <phenology>spring</phenology>
  <phenology>apr</phenology>
  <phenology>may</phenology>
  <habitat>sandy, granitic, or calcareous soils</habitat>
  <habitat>sandy ledges</habitat>
  <habitat>limestone outcrops</habitat>
  <habitat>rocky prairies</habitat>
  <habitat>uplands</habitat>
  <elevation>30–400 m;</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Alyssum densiflorum (A. Gray) Kuntze (1891), not Desfontaines (1808) is an illegitimate name, sometimes found in synonymy with Physaria densiflora.</discussion>
</treatment>
