<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>25.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Physaria</genus_name><species_name>eburniflora</species_name><species_authority>Rollins</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Brittonia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>33: 333. 1981</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Devils Gate twinpod</common_name><description>Perennials; caudex usually simple; densely pubescent, trichomes (sessile), rays often furcate, fused toward base, (nearly smooth). Stems simple from base, prostrate, (arising lateral to rosette), 0.1–0.5 dm. Basal leaves: blade suborbicular, (1–)2.5(–3) cm, (base abruptly narrowed to petiole), margins entire, (flat), (surfaces densely silvery pubescent, trichomes in multiple layers, appressed). Cauline leaves (2–4); blade oblanceolate, ca. 1 cm, (base cuneate), margins entire, (apex acute). Racemes condensed. Fruiting pedicels (divaricate-ascending, nearly straight), 6–10 mm. Flowers: sepals (erect, purplish to greenish), linear-oblong or boat-shaped, 5.5–6.5 mm, (lateral pair more saccate than median); petals (white), spatulate, 9–12 mm, (claw undifferentiated from blade). Fruits strongly didymous, irregular in shape and size, (base slightly cordate, apex with a deep closed sinus), strongly to somewhat inflated, 6–8 × 6–8 mm (± bladderlike, papery); valves (retaining seeds after dehiscence), pubescent; replum elliptic to obovate, not constricted, as wide as or wider than fruit, apex obtuse; ovules 4–8 per ovary; style 4–5 mm, (sparsely pubescent or glabrous). Seeds plump.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>limestone hills</habitat><habitat>red soil</habitat><habitat>rocky calcareous slopes</habitat><habitat>clay depressions</habitat><habitat>granite and marble detritus</habitat><elevation>1800–3000 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Wyo.</us_distribution></treatment>
