<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>39.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Physaria</genus_name><species_name>hemiphysaria</species_name><species_authority>(Maguire) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>12: 323. 2002</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Intermountain or skyline bladderpod</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name><species_name>hemiphysaria</species_name><species_authority>Maguire</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Amer. Midl. Naturalist </publication_title><place_in_publication>27: 466. 1942</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials; caudex simple or branched (tightly); sparsely to densely pubescent, trichomes (sessile or short-stalked), 4–6-rayed, rays furcate or bifurcate, distinct or slightly fused at base, (sometimes umbonate, tuberculate throughout). Stems few to several from base, decumbent, 0.5–1(–2) dm, (rather stout, sparsely pubescent). Basal leaves: blade elliptic to suborbicular, 1.5–3.5(–5.5) cm, margins entire or shallowly dentate (at base, surfaces densely pubescent, silvery). Cauline leaves (petiolate or distal nearly sessile); blade elliptic to obovate, 0.5–1.5 cm, margins entire. Racemes dense, congested, (few-flowered). Fruiting pedicels (spreading or recurved, sometimes loosely sigmoid), 2–6.5 mm. Flowers: sepals lanceolate, oblanceolate, or narrowly elliptic, 3.8–5 mm, (median pair thickened apically, cucullate); petals narrowly lanceolate to linear, 6–10(–13) mm. Fruits (sessile or substipitate), broadly obcordate, obdeltate, or obcompressed, slightly compressed (angustiseptate), 3–5(–7) mm; valves (not retaining seeds after dehiscence), sparsely pubescent or glabrous, trichomes appressed; replum as wide as or wider than fruit; ovules 8–16 per ovary; style (1.8–)3–6(–7) mm. Seeds slightly flattened, (ellipsoid to suborbicular).</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>wc United States</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Styles 3–5 mm; fruiting pedicels 4–6.5 mm; fruit valves pubescent, often sparsely so</statement>
      <determination>39a. Physaria hemiphysaria subsp. hemiphysaria</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Styles 1.8–2.5(–3) mm; fruiting pedicels 2–4(–5.5) mm; fruit valves glabrous or sparsely pubescent</statement>
      <determination>39b. Physaria hemiphysaria subsp. lucens</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
