<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">SALICACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bebb" date="unknown">wolfii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. T. Rothrock, Rep. U. S. Geogr. Surv., Wheeler,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>241. 1879</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SALICACEAE;genus Salix;species wolfii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>54.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Idaho willow</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The two varieties of Salix wolfii are distinguished mainly by ovary hairiness; other characters in the key overlap. Ovaries of the typical var. wolfii are glabrous and those of var. idahoensis are hairy. In the latter variety, ovaries are sometimes hairy throughout, but most have hairs in streaks or in a patch at the base of the ovary and on the stipes. These plants usually do not set seed and may be infertile hybrids. Occasional occurrence of staminate flowers with abaxial nectaries suggests that this variety may be a hybrid with S. glauca or S. brachycarpa, although it could also be with S. eastwoodiae, as suggested by S. J. Brunsfeld and F. D. Johnson (1985). The presence of both abaxial and adaxial nectaries in staminate flowers of S. wolfii (staminate plants cannot be identified to variety) is an unusual character in subg. Vetrix; it rarely occurs in S. argyrocarpa, S. breweri, and S. orestera, but is common in S. wolfii. Both hairy ovaries and abaxial nectaries could have been acquired through hybridization and introgression, or polyploidy, with S. glauca or S. brachycarpa. Cytological study of S. wolfii may help answer this question.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries glabrous; pistillate adaxial nectaries 0.4–0.8 mm; stipes 0.2–0.9 mm</description>
      <determination>54a. Salix wolfii var . wolfii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries pubescent or tomentose (hairs in streaks or patches); pistillate adaxial nectaries 0.4–1.1 mm;</description>
      <determination>54b. Salix wolfii var . idahoensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
