<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>59.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Physaria</genus_name><species_name>obdeltata</species_name><species_authority>(Rollins) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>12: 326. 2002</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Middle Butte bladderpod</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name><species_name>obdeltata</species_name><species_authority>Rollins</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Cruciferae Continental N. Amer., </publication_title><place_in_publication>640. 1993</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials; caudex simple; densely pubescent, trichomes (appressed in layers), 5–7-rayed, rays usually bifurcate, sometimes furcate, (thickened toward center). Stems simple from base, prostrate to decumbent, (unbranched, from within and below leaf clusters, slender), 0.2–0.8 dm. Basal leaves (tufted, erect or ascending, silvery); blade linear to oblanceolate or (outer) oblanceolate to obovate or rhombic, 1.5–3.3 cm, (base sometimes subhastate), margins entire or dentate, (often involute). Cauline leaves: blade nearly linear, to 1.5 cm, margins entire. Racemes dense, (subcorymbose). Fruiting pedicels (recurved), 5–8 mm. Flowers: sepals (yellow-green), lanceolate, (2.5–)3.5–4.5 mm; petals spatulate to oblanceolate, 4–6.5 mm. Fruits (usually pendent), obdeltate, compressed (angustiseptate), 2–4 mm, (wider than long, base tapered to acute angle, apex truncate with inflated shoulders); valves densely pubescent; (septum obsolete or with a narrow fringe inside of replum, funicles attached close to replum apex); ovules 4 per ovary; style 2–4 mm, (slender). Seeds plump, (mucilaginous when wetted).</description><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>clayey, silty, or gravelly soils</habitat><habitat>overlaying basalt lava flows</habitat><habitat>silty playas</habitat><habitat>sagebrush</habitat><habitat>barren areas</habitat><elevation>1300–1700 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Idaho.</us_distribution><discussion>Physaria obdeltata is known from the eastern Snake River Plain.</discussion></treatment>
