<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>62.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Physaria</genus_name><species_name>ovalifolia</species_name><species_authority>(Rydberg) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>12: 326. 2002</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Roundleaf bladderpod</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name><species_name>ovalifolia</species_name><species_authority>Rydberg</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in N. L. Britton and A. Brown, Ill. Fl. N. U.S. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 137, fig. 1749. 1897</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name><species_name>engelmannii</species_name><species_authority>(A. Gray) S. Watson</species_authority><subspecies_name>ovalifolia</subspecies_name><subspecies_authority>(Rydberg ex Britton) C. Clark</subspecies_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials; caudex simple or branched, (thickened by persistent leaf bases); densely pubescent (foliage usually scabrous), trichomes (sessile or short-stalked), several-rayed, rays furcate near base, (usually strongly umbonate, roughly tuberculate, less so over umbo). Stems few to several from base, erect or outer decumbent, 0.5–2.5 dm. Basal leaves: blade suborbicular to elliptic or ovate or deltate, 0.5–2(–6.5) cm, margins entire or shallowly dentate. Cauline leaves: (proximal shortly petiolate, distal usually sessile); blade narrowly elliptic or obovate, (0.5–)1–2.5(–4) cm, margins entire. Racemes compact, (± subumbellate to densely corymbiform, elongated or not). Fruiting pedicels (usually spreading at right angles, sometimes nearly erect, ± straight), 5–15(–20) mm, (stout). Flowers: sepals ± elliptic, 4.5–7(–8.5) mm, (median pair thickened apically); petals (sometimes white), suborbicular to obovate or obdeltate, 6.5–15 mm, (base narrowing to broad claw, apex sometimes emarginated). Fruits (sessile or shortly stipitate, less than 1 mm), subglobose to broadly ellipsoid, inflated or slightly compressed (terete or subterete), (4–)5–8(–9) mm; valves (not retaining seeds after dehiscence), glabrous; replum as wide as or wider than fruit; ovules 8–16 per ovary; style 4–8(–9) mm. Seeds flattened.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>wc United States.</global_distribution><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Caudices branched (well-developed); petals usually yellow, rarely white, 6.5–12(–14) mm, usually 1.5 times or less as long as sepals; racemes usually not elongated (subumbellate)</statement>
      <determination>62a. Physaria ovalifolia subsp. ovalifolia</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Caudices usually simple; petals white, (9–)11–15 mm, often 2 times as long as sepals; racemes usually elongated</statement>
      <determination>62b. Physaria ovalifolia subsp. alba</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
