<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>70.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Physaria</genus_name>
    <species_name>pruinosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Greene) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 327. 2002</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Frosty or Pagosa bladderpod</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name>
    <species_name>pruinosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 307. 1901</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Perennials; caudex simple or branched, (covered with persistent leaf bases); densely pubescent, trichomes (sessile or subsessile), 4–7-rayed, rays furcate or bifurcate, (tuberculate throughout). Stems simple or several from base, decumbent or erect, (unbranched), to 2 dm. Basal leaves: (petiole sharply differentiated from blade, slender); blade suborbicular or obovate to rhombic, 4–8 cm, (base abruptly narrowed to petiole), margins entire, sinuate, or shallowly dentate, (abaxial surface densely pubescent, adaxial lightly pubescent). Cauline leaves: (proximal petiolate, distal sessile); blade obovate to rhombic, 0.8–2.3 cm, margins entire or shallowly toothed. Racemes dense, (somewhat elongated in fruit). Fruiting pedicels (horizontal to ascending, sigmoid or slightly curved), 8–11 mm, (stout). Flowers: sepals elliptic or oblong, ca. 6 mm, (lateral pair not saccate or subsaccate, cucullate, median pair thickened apically, cucullate); petals spatulate, ca. 9 mm, (claw expanded at base). Fruits (sessile or substipitate, often becoming copper-red in age), subglobose or ellipsoid, inflated, 6–9 mm, (firm, glossy); valves (not retaining seeds after dehiscence), glabrous throughout; replum as wide as or wider than fruit; ovules 4–8(–12) per ovary; style 3.5–7 mm. Seeds somewhat flattened.</description>
  <phenology>may</phenology>
  <phenology>spring</phenology>
  <phenology>jun</phenology>
  <phenology>summer</phenology>
  <phenology>aug</phenology>
  <habitat>mancos slate or shale</habitat>
  <habitat>meadows</habitat>
  <habitat>gentle slopes</habitat>
  <habitat>edges of ponderosa pine stands</habitat>
  <conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation>
  <elevation>2100–2600 m;</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Colo.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>The one New Mexico population is near the border with Colorado, in Rio Arriba County.</discussion>
</treatment>
