<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">salicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Dumortier) Dumortier" date="1862">vetrix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Fries) A. Kerner" date="1860">hastatae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Andersson" date="unknown">pseudomyrsinites</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Öfvers. Kongl. Vetensk.-Akad. Förh.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: 129. 1858</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family salicaceae;genus salix;subgenus vetrix;section hastatae;species pseudomyrsinites</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Andersson" date="unknown">myrtillifolia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Andersson) Dorn" date="unknown">cordata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Salix;species myrtillifolia;variety cordata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Andersson" date="unknown">myrtillifolia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Andersson) C. R. Ball ex Hultén" date="unknown">pseudomyrsinites</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Salix;species myrtillifolia;variety pseudomyrsinites;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">novae-angliae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Andersson" date="unknown">cordata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Salix;species novae-angliae;variety cordata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 1–7 m. Stems: branches gray-brown, red-brown, or yellow-brown, glaucous to
        strongly so (slightly to highly glossy), villous to glabrescent; branchlets gray-brown,
        red-brown, yellow-brown, or yellow-green, (not or weakly glaucous), pilose, densely villous,
        or tomentose. Leaves: stipules rudimentary or foliaceous on early ones, foliaceous on late
        ones, (0.6–8 mm), apex acute or obtuse; petiole shallowly to deeply grooved adaxially, 2.5–8
        mm, glabrous or villous adaxially; largest medial blade (sometimes amphistomatous), narrowly
        to broadly elliptic, oblong to oblanceolate or obovate, 32–109 × 10–47 mm, 1.8–4.8 times as
        long as wide, base convex, cuneate, or subcordate, sometimes cordate, margins flat, entire,
        crenate, or serrulate, apex acute, convex, or acuminate, abaxial surface not glaucous,
        glabrous or pilose, hairs (white, sometimes also ferruginous), wavy, adaxial slightly
        glossy, glabrous, pilose, pubescent, moderately densely short-silky, or velvety, midrib
        remaining pilose or short-hairy, (hairs sometimes also ferruginous, straight and
        geniculate); proximal blade margins serrulate or entire; juvenile blade sometimes reddish or
        yellowish green, abaxially glabrous, or midrib sparsely pubescent, or densely villous or
        short-silky, hairs white, sometimes also ferruginous. Catkins flowering as leaves emerge;
        staminate stout, 16.5–35.5 × 7–15 mm, flowering branchlet 0.5–12 mm; pistillate moderately
        or densely flowered, slender or stout, 10.5–68 × 5–20 mm, flowering branchlet 0.5–10 mm;
        floral bract brown, black, tawny, or bicolor, 0.6–1.1 mm, apex retuse, abaxially hairy,
        hairs long-wavy or curly. Staminate flowers: adaxial nectary oblong square, 0.2–0.4–0.6 mm;
        filaments distinct, glabrous; anthers purple turning yellow, 0.4–0.7 mm. Pistillate flowers:
        adaxial nectary square or oblong, 0.2–0.4 mm, shorter than stipe; stipe 0.8–1.4 mm; ovary
        pyriform, glabrous, beak slightly bulged below styles; ovules 11–18 per ovary; styles
        0.4–1.6 mm; stigmas flat, abaxially non-papillate with rounded tip, or 2 plump lobes,
        0.16–0.24–0.32 mm. Capsules 4.4–6.4 mm. 2n = 76.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering early May-early Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shores of lakes and streams, dwarf-birch thickets, fens, marl bogs, rarely in treed bogs;</description>
  <description type="elevation">40-1000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Man., N.W.T., Nunavut, Ont., Sask., Yukon; Alaska.</description>
  <number>57.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">pseudo-myrsinites</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">Tall blueberry willow</other_name>
  <discussion>Salix pseudomyrsinites occurs in Nunavut on Akimiski Island in James
        Bay.</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix pseudomyrsinites and S. myrtillifolia, although sometimes treated as
        conspecific (R. D. Dorn 1975), deserve species rank. They differ in chromosome number and
        are distinct in habit, habitat, and general appearance, including glossiness of leaves, as
        well as a number of technical characteristics (L. A. Viereck and E. L. Little Jr. 1972; G.
        W. Argus 1973, 1997). There is no field evidence of hybridization, but some herbarium
        specimens appear to be intermediates, having the habit or habitat of one species and the
        leaf hairiness of the other.</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix myrtillifolia is distinguished from S. pseudomyrsinites by having shrubs low,
        decumbent, 0.1–0.6 m, rarely to 1 m, of treed bogs and fens, juvenile and mature leaves
        typically glabrous, stipules usually rudimentary, 0.2–1.8(–5) mm, and styles often shorter,
        0.3–0.7 mm; S. pseudomyrsinites has shrubs tall, erect, 1–7 m, of riparian habitats,
        juvenile leaves pubescent with hairs persisting on mature leaves, at least on adaxial
        midrib, stipules usually prominent and foliaceous, 0.6–8 mm, and styles often longer,
        0.4–1.6 mm.</discussion>
  <discussion>The nomenclature of these species is confusing. When treating them as varieties E.
        Hultén (1968) used the name Salix myrtillifolia var. pseudomyrsinites and R. D. Dorn (1975)
        used the name S. myrtillifolia var. cordata. At the species level, the name S. novae-angliae
        was used (L. A. Viereck and E. L. Little Jr. 1972; G. W. Argus 1973), but that name is
        illegitimate (Dorn) and is replaced by S. pseudomyrsinites (Argus 1997).</discussion>
  <discussion>Hybrids:</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix pseudomyrsinites forms natural hybrids with S. barrattiana.</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix pseudomyrsinites × S. barrattiana is a rare hybrid that combines the
        characters of the two parents.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
