<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>77.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Physaria</genus_name><species_name>rollinsii</species_name><species_authority>G. A. Mulligan</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Canad. J. Bot.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>44: 1663, fig. 2, plate 1, fig. 4. 1966</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Rollins’s twinpod</common_name><description>Perennials; (compact); caudex usually simple, (cespitose); (silvery) pubescent throughout, trichomes 6–8-rayed, rays furcate near base, fused at base, (umbonate, strongly tuberculate throughout). Stems several from base, decumbent, (unbranched, slender), 0.5–1 dm. Basal leaves (strongly rosulate); blade usually oblanceolate or broader, sometimes triangular, 2–3.5 cm (width 5–10 mm), margins entire or with 1 or 2 broad teeth, (apex acute). Cauline leaves: blade oblanceolate, 1–1.5 cm (width 2–4 mm), margins entire, (apex acute). Racemes congested, (elongated moderately in fruit). Fruiting pedicels (spreading, straight or somewhat sigmoid), 5–8 mm. Flowers: sepals linear, 5–7 mm; petals spatulate, 8–10 mm, (apex often somewhat truncate). Fruits (erect), didymous, suborbicular, inflated, 2–5(–8) × 4–8(–10)mm, (coriaceous, base slightly cordate or nearly obtuse, sinus obsolete or absent, apical sinus broad and deep); valves (retaining seeds after dehiscence), pubescent, trichomes appressed, (silvery on ovaries and immature fruit; replum obovate to oblong, as wide as or wider than fruit, rarely somewhat constricted basally, apex obtuse; ovules 4 per ovary; style 5–7 mm. Seeds slightly flattened. 2n = 8.</description><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>sagebrush</habitat><habitat>granitic talus</habitat><habitat>open knolls</habitat><habitat>limestone chiprock, steep slopes</habitat><habitat>clay banks</habitat><habitat>near granite boulders</habitat><elevation>2300–2500(–3900) m;</elevation><us_distribution>Colo.</us_distribution></treatment>
