<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="B. L. Robinson" date="unknown">Physarieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Physaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rollins" date="unknown">saximontana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Gray Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>214: 13. 1984</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Physarieae;genus Physaria;species saximontana;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; caudex usually simple; (silvery) pubescent throughout, trichome rays furcate. Stems several from base, prostrate to decumbent, 0.3–1 dm. Basal leaves (rosulate; petiole winged); blade orbicular to broadly obovate, 1.5–3 cm, margins entire or with broad, obscure toothlike angles each side at apex, (apex obtuse, surfaces densely pubescent, trichomes appressed). Cauline leaves: blade broadly spatulate to linear-oblanceolate, 1–1.5 cm, margins entire. Racemes condensed, (subumbellate to slightly more elongated, few-flowered). Fruiting pedicels (divaricate-ascending, straight to slightly curved), 6–10 mm. Flowers: sepals (yellowish, often with some purple), narrowly lanceolate, 5–6 mm; petals spatulate, 7.3–9.2 mm, (not clawed). Fruits didymous, irregular, suborbicular, deeply bilobed, inflated in age, 10–12 × 12–15 mm, (papery, basal sinus absent or obsolete, apical sinus deep); valves (retaining seeds after dehiscence), densely pubescent, trichomes spreading, (ovaries and immature fruit downy); replum narrowly ovate to broadly oblong, not narrowed at middle, as wide as or wider than fruit, apex acute to obtuse; ovules 4 per ovary; style 3–7 mm. Seeds flattened.</description>
  <description type="distribution">wc United States.</description>
  <number>78.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Rocky Mountain or Fremont County twinpod</other_name>
  <discussion>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Physaria saximontana (especially subsp. dentata) is morphologically similar to 22. P. didymocarpa.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaf blades: margins entire, apices rounded</description>
      <determination>78a. Physaria saximontana subsp. saximontana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaf blades: margins dentate (teeth broad), apices angled; styles 4–7 mm</description>
      <determination>78b. Physaria saximontana subsp. dentata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
