<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>84.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Physaria</genus_name>
    <species_name>thamnophila</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Rollins &amp; E. A. Shaw) O’Kane &amp; Al-Shehbaz</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 328. 2002</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Zapata bladderpod</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Lesquerella</genus_name>
    <species_name>thamnophila</species_name>
    <species_authority>Rollins &amp; E. A. Shaw</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Lesquerella,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>86, plates 15, 16. 1973</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Perennials; caudex simple or branched, (woody); densely (silvery) pubescent, trichomes (short-stalked), 4–8-rayed, rays furcate or bifurcate, (finely tuberculate throughout). Stems simple or few from base, decumbent, (straggling and flexuous, usually branched distally), 4–8 dm. Basal leaves: blade narrowly elliptic to oblanceolate, 4–12 cm, margins entire, sinuate, or shallowly dentate, (apex acute). Cauline leaves (sessile or proximal shortly petiolate); blade linear to narrowly elliptic, 3–4 cm, margins entire, sinuate, or remotely dentate, (apex acute). Racemes loose, (sometimes greatly elongated). Fruiting pedicels (recurved), 15–20(–25) mm. Flowers: sepals elliptic, 3.5–4 mm, (lateral pair subsaccate, median pair thickened apically, cucullate); petals broadly obovate, 4–5 mm, (sometimes with short, broad claw). Fruits (pendent), subglobose or broadly ovoid, slightly compressed, 5–7 mm; valves (not retaining seeds after dehiscence), glabrous throughout; ovules per ovary unknown; style 1.5–2 mm. Seeds flattened. 2n = 16.</description>
  <phenology>apr</phenology>
  <phenology>spring</phenology>
  <habitat>sandy soils</habitat>
  <habitat>entangled in shrubs</habitat>
  <habitat>cactus clumps</habitat>
  <conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation>
  <elevation>1700–1800 m;</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Physaria thamnophila is found in sandy areas with shrubs and cactus in sparse shrubland communities of Starr and Zapata counties. It sometimes flowers through September with sufficient moisture.</discussion>
</treatment>
