<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="B. L. Robinson" date="unknown">Physarieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">SYNTHLIPSIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Amer. Acad. Arts, n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 116. 1849</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Physarieae;genus SYNTHLIPSIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek synthlipsis , compression, alluding to flattened fruits]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or perennials; (short-lived, sometimes cespitose); not scapose;
    pubescent throughout, trichomes dendritic, base of plant sometimes mixed with fewer, simple or
    forked, stalked ones. Stems ascending to decumbent, unbranched or branched distally. Leaves
    basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate, petiolate, blade margins usually
    sinuately lobed to dentate, rarely repand; cauline petiolate or sessile, blade similar to basal.
    Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered), slightly or considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting
    pedicels divaricate or divaricate-ascending, slender. Flowers: sepals spreading, narrowly
    oblong, (equal), lateral pair not saccate basally; petals white to violet [purple], broadly
    obovate, (much longer than sepals), claw differentiated from blade, (much shorter, apex
    rounded); stamens tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally, (somewhat spreading); anthers
    linear [narrowly oblong]; nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits silicles,
    sessile, broadly oblong [broadly elliptic], smooth, angustiseptate; valves carinate; replum
    rounded; septum complete; ovules 10–50 per ovary; style distinct; stigma broadly capitate,
    entire. Seeds ± biseriate, flattened, not winged, narrowly margined, broadly ovate; seed coat
    (nearly smooth), copiously mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 10.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Texas</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>79.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Synthlipsis densiflora Rollins is known from Mexico (Coahuila).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1959. The genus Synthlipsis (Cruciferae).
      Rhodora 61: 253–264.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
