<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Prantl" date="unknown">Thelypodieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">CHLOROCRAMBE</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>34: 435. 1907</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Thelypodieae;genus CHLOROCRAMBE;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chlor -, green, and Crambe , a genus of Brassicaceae]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; (caudex simple or few-branched, woody, without persistent leaf remains); not scapose; glabrous. Stems erect, unbranched or branched (few) distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate; basal not rosulate, long-petiolate, (soon withered); cauline petiolate, blade (base hastate, not auriculate), margins entire or proximalmost lobed. Racemes (reflexed at anthesis, several-flowered, lax, proximal flowers sometimes bracteate), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels straight or curved upward, stout. Flowers: sepals ascending, narrowly lanceolate, lateral pair not saccate basally; petals (ascending), white, linear, (only slightly longer than sepals, slightly crisped), claw obovate or oblanceolate, (distinctly wider than blade); stamens subequal (well-exserted beyond petals); filaments slightly dilated basally; anthers linear, (apiculate, coiled after dehiscence); nectar glands confluent, lateral annular or semi-annular, median glands present. Fruits long-stipitate, linear, subtorulose, subterete or slightly compressed; valves each with prominent midvein extending full-length; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 40–60 per ovary; style obsolete or distinct; stigma capitate, entire. Seeds uniseriate, plump, winged distally, oblong; seed coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons obliquely accumbent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <number>83.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
