<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Prantl" date="unknown">Thelypodieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">DRYOPETALON</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5(6): 11, plate 11. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Thelypodieae;genus DRYOPETALON;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek drys , oak, and petalon , leaf, alluding to resemblance of petal shape to leaves of some oaks]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Al-Shehbaz" date="unknown">Rollinsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Rollinsia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals or biennials; not scapose; usually pubescent or hirsute, rarely glabrous. Stems erect or ascending, unbranched or branched basally or distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate or not, petiolate, blade margins entire, dentate to runcinate, or pinnatifid; cauline petiolate or [sub]sessile, blade (base not auriculate, or auriculate to amplexicaul), margins entire or dentate to pinnatifid. Racemes (corymbose, initially congested), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels ascending, divaricate, or horizontal, slender. Flowers: sepals erect to ascending, oblong [ovate], lateral pair slightly saccate or not basally, (glabrous or pubescent); petals white or purplish, spatulate or obovate (longer than sepals), claw gradually narrowed from blade to base, (margins sometimes pinnatifid, or deeply 2-lobed); stamens tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally, (glabrous or papillate basally); anthers oblong; nectar glands: lateral annular, median glands confluent with lateral. Fruits sessile or shortly stipitate, usually linear, rarely linear-oblong, torulose or smooth, terete or flattened (latiseptate); valves each with a distinct midvein, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete, not veined; ovules 10–110 per ovary; style distinct; stigma capitate, usually entire, rarely slightly 2-lobed. Seeds uniseriate, plump, usually not winged, rarely narrowly so, ovate [oblong]; seed coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent [incumbent]. x = [10] 12, 14.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>85.</number>
  <discussion>Species 8 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Al-Shehbaz, I. A. 2007. Generic limits of Dryopetalon, Rollinsia, Sibara, and Thelypodiopsis (Brassicaceae) and a synopsis of Dryopetalon. Novon 17: 397–402.</reference>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1941c. The cruciferous genus Dryopetalon. Contr. Dudley Herb. 3: 199–207.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves shortly petiolate or sessile, blade bases not auriculate; fruits 0.5–1.2 mm</description>
      <determination>1. Dryopetalon runcinatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves sessile, blade bases auriculate; fruits 2–3 mm wide; ovules 10–28 per ovary;</description>
      <determination>2. Dryopetalon viereckii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
