<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>89.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>STANLEYA</genus_name><genus_authority>Nuttall</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 71. 1818</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[For Edward Smith Stanley, 1775–1851, British statesman and ornithologist]</etymology><common_name>Prince’s plume</common_name><author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author><description>Annuals, perennials, shrubs, or subshrubs; (base usually woody); not scapose; glabrous or pubescent. Stems usually erect, rarely ascending, unbranched or branched. Leaves cauline and, sometimes, basal; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate, petiolate, blade margins entire, lyrately lobed or 1- or 2-pinnatifid; cauline blade (base sometimes auriculate or amplexicaul), margins entire or dentate to pinnatifid. Racemes considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels horizontal, divaricate, or divaricate-ascending, slender. Flowers: sepals spreading to reflexed, oblong-linear or linear, lateral pair not saccate basally; petals usually yellow or whitish, rarely white or yellow-orange, obovate, orbicular, oblong, linear, filiform, or oblanceolate, claw distinctly differentiated from blade (claw glabrous or papillose); stamens (exserted), equal; filaments not dilated basally, (often papillose basally); anthers linear, (strongly spirally coiled after dehiscence); lateral nectar glands annular, median present or absent, confluent with lateral ones. Fruits long-stipitate, linear, often torulose, terete or latiseptate; valves each with prominent midvein, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 22–70 per ovary; style obsolete or distinct (to 1.7 mm); stigma capitate, entire. Seeds uniseriate, plump, not winged, usually oblong, rarely ovoid; seed coat (obscurely reticulate), slightly mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent to incumbent. x = 14.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 7 (7 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>w</global_distribution><global_distribution>c United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Both R. C. Rollins (1993) and N. H. Holmgren (2005b) reported n = 12 and 2n = 24 for various species of Stanleya. However, those counts, all reported previously by Rollins (1939c), are erroneous; no species of the genus has numbers deviating from n = 14 or 28.</discussion><discussion>All species of Stanleya are well-defined, and interspecific hybridization has not yet been reported. One species, S. pinnata, is a hyperaccumulator of selenium and is a good indicator for the presence of this element in soils. Poisoning of livestock results from their feeding on large quantities of plants of this species.</discussion><references>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1939c. The cruciferous genus Stanleya. Lloydia 2: 109–127.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaves sessile, blade bases auriculate to sagittate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Annuals or biennials (without caudex); racemes dense; sepals 6–12 mm; petals linear to</statement>
      <determination>3. Stanleya confertiflora</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perennials (with caudex); racemes loose; sepals 12–18 mm; petals narrowly oblanceolate, 1–3 mm wide, margins usually erose, rarely subentire and crisped; fruiting pedicels</statement>
      <determination>7. Stanleya viridiflora</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaves petiolate, blade bases not auriculate or sagittate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaf blades: surfaces densely tomentose; fruiting pedicels 11–22 mm; petals with</statement>
      <determination>6. Stanleya tomentosa</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Basal leaf blades: surfaces usually glabrous, rarely sparsely pubescent; fruiting pedicels 3–11(–15) mm; petals with pubescent claws (except S. elata ); fruits terete or subterete.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf blades: margins usually entire, rarely dentate proximally.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Petals linear, 0.3–1 mm wide, claws glabrous; ovules 46–70 per ovary; filaments</statement>
      <determination>4. Stanleya elata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Petals oblanceolate to oblong, 2–3 mm wide, claws pubescent; ovules 10–38 per ovary; filaments 11–28 mm; Colorado, Kansas, Nevada, sw Texas, Utah,</statement>
      <determination>5. Stanleya pinnata (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf blades: margins often pinnatisect, pinnatifid, 2-pinnatifid, lyrate-pinnatifid, or runcinate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Biennials; petals orbicular to broadly obovate, (2.5–)3–6 mm wide; fruits suberect to</statement>
      <determination>1. Stanleya albescens</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perennials; petals oblanceolate or oblong, 0.8–3 mm wide; fruits usually spreading or divaricate, rarely ascending, sometimes curved downward.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf blades: margins sometimes 2-pinnatifid; sepals 6.5–10 mm; petals 5–12</statement>
      <determination>2. Stanleya bipinnata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf blades: margins not 2-pinnatifid; sepals 9–16 mm; petals 10–20 mm; filaments pilose basally; gynophores 7–28 mm; fruits smooth, not tortuous</statement>
      <determination>5. Stanleya pinnata (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
