<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">SALICACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="C. R. Ball" date="unknown">pseudomonticola</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>22: 321. 1921</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SALICACEAE;genus Salix;species pseudomonticola;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Andersson" date="unknown">barclayi</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(C. R. Ball) Kelso" date="unknown">pseudomonticola</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Salix;species barclayi;variety pseudomonticola;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>65.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">False mountain willow</other_name>
  <discussion>Salix pseudomonticola is characterized by precocious flowering; catkins sessile; juvenile leaf blades, petioles, and proximal midribs reddish; stipules prominent; and leaves and branchlets sparsely hairy. Branches older than two years have a distinctive pattern, which consists of a series of longitudinal splits in epidermis produced as the branch expands. The edge of epidermis around the split, where it has separated from the branch, is yellow and contrasts with the red-brown branch to which the epidermis still adheres.</discussion>
  <discussion>Vegetative specimens of Salix pseudomonticola with yellow-brown branches can be confused with S. famelica. They may be separated by their juvenile leaf margins prominently and closely gland-dotted; stipules usually prominent, sometimes early deciduous; leaves broader (1.4–3 times as long as wide versus 2.6–7 in S. famelica); and petioles slender and often longer in relation to blade length. The possibility of hybridization needs study.</discussion>
  <discussion>Vegetative specimens of Salix pseudomonticola can be distinguished from S. pyrifolia by juvenile leaves reddish and almost always with some ferruginous hairs, versus yellowish-green and glabrous or with white hairs, and mature leaves usually dull adaxially versus glossy.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
