<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Prantl" date="unknown">Thelypodieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">STREPTANTHELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Rocky Mts.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>364, 1062. 1917</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Thelypodieae;genus STREPTANTHELLA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Streptanthus and Latin -ella , diminutive]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals; not scapose; (often glaucous), glabrous throughout. Stems erect, usually branched distally, rarely unbranched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal not rosulate, petiolate, blade similar to cauline; cauline petiolate or sessile, blade (base not auriculate), margins entire, dentate, sinuate, or pinnatifid. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered, lax), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels usually reflexed, rarely divaricate, slender or stout. Flowers: sepals erect, oblong, (unequal), lateral pair subsaccate basally; petals white or yellow (often veins purplish), spatulate, (slightly exceeding sepals, margins crisp), claw well-differentiated from blade, (apex obtuse); stamens in 3 unequal pairs; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate to oblong, (apiculate); nectar glands lateral, semi-annular, subtending lateral stamens, median glands absent. Fruits sessile, linear, smooth, latiseptate; valves each with prominent midvein; replum rounded or slightly flattened; septum complete; ovules (12–)16–28(–34); style distinct, (well-developed, adnate with valves and replum apex); stigma subentire. Seeds uniseriate, flattened, winged, oblong; seed coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>90.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
