<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Prantl in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="unknown">thelypodieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="1825">streptanthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="T. W. Nelson &amp; J. P. Nelson" date="2009">oblanceolatus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>56: 127, fig. 1. 2009</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe thelypodieae;genus streptanthus;species oblanceolatus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials; (glaucous), glabrous throughout. Stems: (base woody), virgately branched distally, 5–10 dm. Basal leaves rosulate; petiolate; blade oblanceolate, 3.5–7 cm, margins coarsely dentate distally. Cauline leaves: blade linear-lanceolate, 2–10 cm, (much smaller distally), base auriculate, margins entire. Racemes bracteate below or between proximalmost 1 or 2 flowers, (lax). Fruiting pedicels ascending, 3–6 mm, (strongly expanded at receptacle). Flowers: calyx shape unknown; sepals yellow, 8–9 mm, slightly keeled, (apex acuminate, recurved); petals yellowish, 12–16 mm, blade 4–5 × 0.5–1 mm, (adaxial pair slightly longer), margins not crisped, claw 7–9 mm, wider than blade, (apex recurved); stamens in 3 unequal pairs; filaments: abaxial pair (distinct), 9–11 mm, lateral pair 7–9 mm, adaxial pair (connate distal to middle of their length), 13–16 mm; anthers: abaxial and lateral pairs fertile, 3–3.5 mm, adaxial pair sterile, ca. 1 mm. Fruits divaricate ascending, torulose, flattened, 4–8 cm × 1.5–2 mm; replum straight; ovules per ovary unknown; style to 1 mm; stigma entire. Seeds oblong, ca. 2 × 1 mm; wing distal.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jun-Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cliffs and canyon walls in conifer forests;</description>
  <description type="elevation">ca. 400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Streptanthus oblanceolatus is known from Box Canyon, Trinity River, Trinity County.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
