<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>35.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Streptanthus</genus_name>
    <species_name>vimineus</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Greene) Al-Shehbaz &amp; D. W. Taylor</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 281. 2008</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Mesoreanthus</genus_name>
    <species_name>vimineus</species_name>
    <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Leafl. Bot. Observ. Crit.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 90. 1904</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Mesoreanthus</genus_name>
    <species_name>fallax</species_name>
    <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Annuals; (glaucous), usually glabrous throughout (some-times sepals pubescent). Stems branched distal to base, 1–7.5 dm. Basal leaves (soon withered); not rosulate; petiolate; blade narrowly ovate to oblong, 2.5–5 cm, margins entire. Cauline leaves: blade linear to narrowly linear-lanceolate, 2–12 cm × 1–3(–4) mm, (smaller distally), base auriculate, margins entire. Racemes ebracteate, (lax, usually secund). Fruiting pedicels divaricate, (straight), 1–3(–6) mm. Flowers: calyx urceolate; sepals greenish to purplish, ovate-lanceolate, 6–8 mm, keeled, (apex recurved, usually glabrous, rarely sparsely pubescent); petals white (abaxial pair with purple veins), 8–12 mm, blade 3–5 × 2–3 mm, (unequal, abaxial longer than adaxial), margins not crisped, claw 5–7 mm, narrower than blade; stamens in 3 unequal pairs; filaments: abaxial pair (connate 1/2 their length), 4–7 mm, lateral pair 2–4 mm, adaxial pair (connate their whole length, recurved), 7–11 mm; anthers: abaxial and lateral pairs fertile, 2–2.7 mm, adaxial pairs sterile, 0.5–1.2 mm; gynophore 0.2–0.5 mm. Fruits divaricate, slightly torulose, recurved, flattened, 3.5–6.5 cm × 1–1.2 mm; valves each with obscure midvein; replum straight; ovules 28–40 per ovary; style 0.1–0.3 mm; stigma entire. Seeds narrowly oblong, 1–1.5 × 0.6–0.8 mm; wing 0–0.1 mm wide, distal.</description>
  <phenology>may</phenology>
  <phenology>spring</phenology>
  <phenology>jun</phenology>
  <phenology>summer</phenology>
  <phenology>jul</phenology>
  <habitat>serpentine grasslands</habitat>
  <habitat>ridges and barrens</habitat>
  <habitat>openings in chaparral</habitat>
  <conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation>
  <elevation>200–800 m;</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Streptanthus vimineus is restricted to Colusa, Lake, and Napa counties. The taxon has long been unrecognized by various authors, including recent ones (e.g., R. C. Rollins 1993; R. E. Buck et al. 1993). It remained under Mesoreanthus and was often treated as a synonym of S. barbiger. The latter always has non-auriculate (versus auriculate) cauline leaves.</discussion>
</treatment>
