<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Thelypodiopsis</genus_name><species_name>divaricata</species_name><species_authority>(Rollins) S. L. Welsh &amp; Reveal</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Great Basin Naturalist</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>37: 355. 1978</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Caulanthus</genus_name><species_name>divaricatus</species_name><species_authority>Rollins</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. Gray Herb. </publication_title><place_in_publication>201: 8, plate 2. 1971</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Annuals or biennials; pubescent proximally, glabrate distally. Stems usually branched distally, rarely unbranched, 2–8.5(–10) dm, (often densely pubescent proximally, trichomes flat, crisped). Basal leaves (soon withered); not rosulate; blade oblong, 2–10 cm × 10–30 mm, margins entire or dentate, (surfaces glabrous or sparsely pubescent). Cauline leaves sessile; blade (proximalmost) oblong or (distal) oblong to ovate, base auriculate to amplexicaul, margins usually entire or dentate (rarely dentate distally). Racemes dense. Fruiting pedicels divaricate-ascending to spreading, straight, (slender), 6.5–14(–21) mm, (glabrous or pubescent). Flowers: sepals (calyx often urceolate), erect, yellowish, 3.5–5.5 × 1.5–2 mm, (sparsely pubescent); petals yellow, oblong, 6.5–9(–10) × 1–1.7 mm, (margins crisped), claw 3.5–5 mm (to 2 mm wide); median filament pairs 4–5 mm; anthers linear, 2.5–3.5 mm; gynophore (stout), 0.5–1.5 mm. Fruits suberect to divaricate-ascending or spreading, straight, slightly torulose, 4–8(–9.5) cm × 1.2–1.7 mm; (valves sparsely pubescent at least when immature); ovules 70–94 per ovary; style subclavate, 0.7–2 mm; stigma 2-lobed. Seeds 1–1.7 × 0.7–1 mm. 2n = 22.</description><phenology>apr</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>may</phenology><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><habitat>rocky knolls</habitat><habitat>sandy or clay grounds in juniper and shrub communities</habitat><elevation>1200–2100 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Utah.</us_distribution><discussion>Thelypodiopsis divaricata is known from Carbon, Emery, Garfield, Grand, Kane, San Juan, and Wayne counties.</discussion></treatment>
