<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Prantl in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="unknown">thelypodieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Endlicher" date="1839">THELYPODIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 876. 1839</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe thelypodieae;genus THELYPODIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek thelys , female, and podion , little foot, alluding to gynophore carrying pistil]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="unknown">Pachypodium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Torrey and A. Gray, Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 96. 1838,</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>not Lindley 1830</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pachypodium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">Pleurophragma</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pleurophragma;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rydberg" date="unknown">Stanleyella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Stanleyella;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials, perennials, or, rarely, annuals; not scapose; glabrous or pubescent. Stems (simple or few to several from base), usually erect, rarely decumbent, branched basally and/or distally, (glabrous or pubescent). Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate or not, petiolate, blade margins usually entire, dentate, lyrate or pinnately lobed, rarely laciniate; cauline petiolate or sessile, blade (base cuneate, attenuate, auriculate, sagittate, or amplexicaul), margins often entire, sometimes dentate or pinnately lobed. Racemes (corymbose, dense or lax), usually slightly to considerably elongated in fruit (sometimes not elongated in T. integrifolium). Fruiting pedicels usually horizontal, erect to ascending, or divaricate, rarely reflexed, slender or stout, (flattened or not basally, glabrous). Flowers: sepals usually erect or ascending, rarely spreading to reflexed, ovate to oblong, linear, lanceolate, or oblanceolate, lateral pair slightly saccate or not basally; petals (erect or spreading), white, lavender, or purple, spatulate to obovate, or oblanceolate to linear, (margins crisped or not), claw differentiated or not from blade, (apex rounded); stamens subequal or tetradynamous, (exserted or included); filaments (erect or spreading, usually distinct, very rarely median ones united), not dilated basally; anthers usually linear to linear-oblong, rarely oblong or ovate, (sometimes apiculate, often circinately coiled after dehiscence); nectar glands confluent and subtending bases of stamens, or 2 or 4 and lateral. Fruits stipitate, linear, torulose or smooth, terete, slightly 4-angled, or flattened; valves each with prominent midvein, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 12–128 per ovary; style distinct, (often cylindrical, rarely subclavate or subconical); stigma capitate, entire. Seeds uniseriate, plump or flattened, not winged, usually oblong, rarely ovate; seed coat (minutely reticulate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons oblique, rarely incumbent or accumbent. x = 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w</description>
  <description type="distribution">wc North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico.</description>
  <number>93.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Thelypody</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 16 (16 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>As recognized herein and by recent authors (e.g., I. A. Al-Shehbaz 1973; R. C. Rollins 1993), Thelypodium is somewhat heterogeneous and the segregate Stanleyella might merit recognition, as by E. B. Payson (1923). Thelypodium has erect sepals, petals, and stamens, terete fruits, prominently veined fruit septa, and, often, cylindrical styles. In contrast, species of Stanleylla have spreading sepals, petals, and stamens, flattened fruits, veinless fruit septa, and clavate, subclavate, or subconical styles.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Al-Shehbaz, I. A. 1973. The biosystematics of the genus Thelypodium (Cruciferae). Contr. Gray Herb. 204: 3–148.</reference>
    <reference>Payson, E. B. 1923. A monographic study of Thelypodium and its immediate allies. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 9: 233–324.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves petiolate, (proximal blades: margins usually pinnately lobed, rarely dentate); petal claws widest at base.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Racemes dense; sepals erect; styles usually cylindrical, rarely subclavate in fruit.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems solid; basal leaves: petioles glabrous; fruiting pedicels straight, horizontal;</description>
      <determination>7. Thelypodium laciniatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hollow; basal leaves: petioles ciliate; fruiting pedicels strongly curved upward;</description>
      <determination>9. Thelypodium milleflorum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Racemes often lax; sepals spreading or ascending; styles usually clavate, subclavate, or subconical, rarely cylindrical in fruit.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems hirsute or glabrous basally; fruits terete, submoniliform to strongly torulose</description>
      <determination>8. Thelypodium laxiflorum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous basally; fruits flattened, torulose (replum not constricted between seeds).</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaf blades usually ovate or obovate, rarely orbicular or spatulate, margins usually sinuate and repand, or dentate; petals lavender or purple, (2.5–)3–4</description>
      <determination>11. Thelypodium repandum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaf blades lanceolate, oblanceolate, or spatulate, margins mostly pinnately lobed; petals usually white, rarely lavender, (3.5–)4–7.5(–9) mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals; styles conical or subconical in fruit; petals spatulate; distalmost</description>
      <determination>15. Thelypodium texanum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Biennials; styles clavate to subclavate in fruit; petals oblong to linear; distalmost cauline leaf blade margins usually entire or dentate, rarely</description>
      <determination>16. Thelypodium wrightii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves sessile (blade bases often auriculate, sagittate, or amplexicaul, proximal blades: margins often entire); petal claws narrowest at base.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials, with (woody) caudex, covered with persistent petiolar remains; stems</description>
      <determination>4. Thelypodium flexuosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Biennials or perennials (short-lived), without caudex, not covered with persistent petiolar remains; stems straight.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaf blade bases cuneate to attenuate, not auriculate or sagittate</description>
      <determination>6. Thelypodium integrifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaf blade bases usually sagittate or amplexicaul, rarely auriculate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Terminal racemes often corymbose, not elongated in fruit.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves: petioles not ciliate, blade margins usually dentate to repand, rarely entire; cauline leaves erect (partly to completely appressed to stems); anthers exserted; fruits usually strongly incurved, overtopping buds</description>
      <determination>12. Thelypodium rollinsii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves: petioles ciliate, blade margins entire; cauline leaves ascending; anthers usually included; fruits often straight, not overtopping buds.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals 2.5–5(–6) mm wide; fruits (0.8–)1.5–2.3 mm wide; seeds</description>
      <determination>10. Thelypodium paniculatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals (0.5–)1–3(–4) mm wide; fruits (0.5–)0.8–1(–1.2) mm wide;</description>
      <determination>13. Thelypodium sagittatum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Terminal racemes not corymbose, considerably elongated in fruit.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Racemes densely flowered; petal margins crisped throughout.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals lanceolate to linear-lanceolate or ovate; fruiting pedicels horizontal to divaricate, stout, base flattened, 1–2(–2.5) mm; seeds</description>
      <determination>1. Thelypodium brachycarpum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals oblong to linear-oblong; fruiting pedicels erect or erect-ascending (appressed to rachis at least basally), slender, base not flattened,</description>
      <determination>2. Thelypodium crispum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Racemes lax; petal margins not crisped or crisped between blade and claw.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals linear, 0.3–0.5(–0.8) mm wide; s California</description>
      <determination>14. Thelypodium stenopetalum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals spatulate to oblanceolate, (0.5–)1–3(–4) mm wide; not s California.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flower buds oblong-linear; anthers exserted; gynophores (1–)2.5– 6</description>
      <determination>3. Thelypodium eucosmum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flower buds ovate to lanceolate; anthers partially to wholly included; gynophores (0.2–)0.5–1(–3.5) mm in fruit.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting pedicels ascending, straight; fruits forming straight</description>
      <determination>5. Thelypodium howellii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting pedicels horizontal to divaricate, often curved upward; fruits forming arc with pedicels; not Oregon</description>
      <determination>13. Thelypodium sagittatum (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
