<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Prantl in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="unknown">thelypodieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Endlicher" date="1839">thelypodium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="B. L. Robinson in A. Gray et al." date="1895">eucosmum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray et al., Syn. Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(1,1): 175. 1895</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe thelypodieae;genus thelypodium;species eucosmum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials or perennials; (short-lived); glaucous, glabrous (except petioles). Stems branched distally, 2–10 dm. Basal leaves: petiole (0.9–)1.4–3(–4.5) cm, ciliate; blade usually oblanceolate to oblong or lanceolate, rarely ovate or elliptic, (2.8–)3.5–8.8(–11) cm × (7–)10–25(–35) mm, margins often entire or repand, sometimes sinuate. Cauline leaves (ascending); sessile; blade lanceolate to oblong, 1.8–4.5(–6) cm × 5–16(–24) mm, (base amplexicaul to strongly auriculate), margins entire. Racemes lax, slightly elongated in fruit, (flower buds oblong-linear). Fruiting pedicels horizontal to divaricate, usually straight, rarely slightly incurved, slender, (2.5–)3–5.5(–6.5) mm, slightly flattened at base. Flowers: sepals erect, linear-oblong, 5–7(–8) × (0.8–)1–1.5(–1.8) mm; petals dark purple, spatulate to oblanceolate, (6.6–)7.5–10(–11.5) × 1–1.8(–2) mm, margins not crisped, claw differentiated from blade, [slender, (3–)3.5–5(–5.5) mm, narrowest at base]; nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens; filaments subequal, (4.5–)6–9(–10) mm; anthers exserted, linear to narrowly oblong, 2.5–4(–4.5) mm, circinately coiled; gynophore (1–)2.5–6(–7.5) mm. Fruits divaricate to ascending, torulose, straight or slightly incurved, terete, (2–)2.4–5(–6.5) cm × 0.7–1(–1.3) mm; ovules 44–58 per ovary; style usually cylindrical, rarely subclavate, 0.5–1.5(–2) mm. Seeds 0.7–1.5 × 0.5–0.8 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May-Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shady slopes and canyons, pinyon-juniper and oak woodland communities, stream beds, streamsides;</description>
  <description type="elevation">700-1000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Oreg.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Thelypodium eucosmum is known only from Baker, Grant, and Wheeler counties. It is in the Center for Plant Conservation’s National Collection of Endangered Plants.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
