<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>94.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>THYSANOCARPUS</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Hooker</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 69, plate 18, fig. A. 1830</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[Greek thysanos , fringe, and karpos , fruit, alluding to fruit margin]</etymology>
  <common_name>Fringepod</common_name>
  <common_name>lacepod</common_name>
  <author>Patrick J. Alexander</author>
  <author>Michael D. Windham</author>
  <description>Annuals; not scapose; (glaucous), glabrous or pubescent. Stems erect, unbranched or branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal (often withered by anthesis or fruiting), not or, rarely, rosulate, shortly petiolate, blade margins subentire, dentate, pinnatifid, or pinnatisect [rarely entire]; cauline sessile, blade (base usually auriculate), margins entire, dentate, or pinnatifid to pinnatisect. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels often recurved, sometimes divaricate-ascending, slender. Flowers: sepals ascending, oblong to ovate, lateral pair not saccate basally; petals white to purplish, spatulate to oblong, (subequaling or longer than sepals), claw not differentiated from blade; stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments slightly dilated basally; anthers ovate; nectary glands each side of lateral stamen or semi-annular, median glands absent. Fruits (pendulous), sessile, cymbiform, orbicular, obovate [ovate, elliptic], smooth, strongly latiseptate; valves each with prominent midvein, glabrous or pubescent; replum entire or crenate, often perforated, (winged, wing flattened, with radiating rays); septum obsolete; ovule 1 per ovary; style distinct (relatively short) or obsolete; stigma entire. Seeds aseriate, flattened, not winged, elliptical to orbicular; seed coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 5 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>w North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>nw Mexico.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Thysanocarpus erectus S. Watson occurs in northwestern Mexico on Cedros and Guadalupe islands and on the mainland of Baja California.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits cymbiform, wings strongly incurved (toward flat side of fruit); raceme internodes</statement>
      <determination>1. Thysanocarpus conchuliferus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits flat or plano-convex, wings not strongly incurved; raceme internodes (1.5–)2–18 mm in fruit.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting pedicels weakly ascending, straight or nearly so (geniculately reflexed apically),</statement>
      <determination>4. Thysanocarpus radians</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruiting pedicels smoothly recurved or straight and stiffly spreading, 2–7(–12) mm; fruits 2.5–6(–9) mm wide, wings with indistinct rays or (0–)0.2–0.5 mm wide.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf blades lanceolate, widest at base, bases auriculate-clasping, auricles extending around stems (at least some leaves); basal leaf blade margins subentire to sinuate-dentate, never pinnatifid, surfaces often hirsute, sometimes glabrous</statement>
      <determination>2. Thysanocarpus curvipes</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaf blades linear to narrowly elliptic, widest near middle or equally wide throughout, bases not auriculate or inconspicuous auricles not extending around stems; basal leaf blade margins pinnatifid, sinuate-dentate, or subentire, surfaces</statement>
      <determination>3. Thysanocarpus laciniatus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
