<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">thlaspideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Heister ex Fabricius" date="1759">ALLIARIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>161. 1759</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe thlaspideae;genus ALLIARIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Allium , garlic or onion, and Latin –aria , connection, alluding to odor of crushed plant]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants with garlic smell when crushed; not scapose; glabrous or pubescent, trichomes simple. Stems erect [decumbent], often branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate; basal (often withered by anthesis or fruiting), rosulate, long-petiolate, blade margins crenate, dentate, or sinuate; cauline shortly petiolate, blade margins dentate. Racemes elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate or ascending, stout (almost as broad as fruit [slender, narrower than fruit]). Flowers: sepals erect, oblong, lateral pair not saccate basally, (glabrous); petals oblanceolate, (longer than sepals), claw obscurely differentiated from blade, (apex obtuse); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate or oblong, (apex obtuse); nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits siliques, sessile, linear [oblong], torulose or subtorulose, terete, subterete, or 4-angled; valves each with prominent midvein and distinct marginal veins, glabrous [scabrous]; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules [4–]6–22 per ovary; style obsolete or distinct (to 6 mm); stigma capitate, entire. Seeds plump, not winged, oblong; seed coat (longitudinally striate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Eurasia, n Africa.</description>
  <number>96.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Garlic mustard</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Alliaria brachycarpa M. Bieberstein is endemic to Caucasus.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cavers, P. B., M. I. Heagy, and R. F. Kokron. 1979. The biology of Canadian weeds. 35. Alliaria petiolata (M. Bieb.) Cavara and Grande. Canad. J. Pl. Sci. 59: 217–229.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
