<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>94.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Salix</genus_name>
    <species_name>tweedyi</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Bebb ex Rose) C. R. Ball</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>40: 377. 1905</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Tweedy’s willow</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Salix</genus_name>
    <species_name>barrattiana</species_name>
    <species_authority>Hooker</species_authority>
    <variety_name>tweedyi</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>Bebb ex Rose</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 572. 1896</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 1–3 m. Stems: branches red-brown, not glaucous, villous to glabrescent; branchlets yellow-brown, (sometimes strongly glaucous), pilose or moderately densely villous, (buds caprea- or arctica-type, scale inner membranaceous layer free, separating from outer layer). Leaves: stipules (sometimes marcescent), foliaceous, (3.5–10–23 mm, 1–1.4–2.8 times as long as wide, usually lanceolate, ovate, or suborbiculate, (pleated when pressed), apex rounded, convex, or acute; petiole shallowly grooved adaxially, 3–11.3–26 mm, villous adaxially; largest medial blade elliptic to broadly elliptic, 36–65–100 × 17–35.5–85 mm, 1.1–1.9–2.9 times as long as wide, base convex, rounded, subcordate, or cordate, margins thickened, serrulate or spinulose-serrulate (sometimes teeth absent, margins with spherical glands), apex acuminate, acute, or convex, abaxial surface glaucous or not, pilose or villous, hairs curved, adaxial dull, pilose or villous to glabrescent; proximal blade margins entire (glands only) or serrulate; juvenile blade green, glabrous, pilose, or moderately densely villous abaxially, hairs white. Catkins flowering before leaves emerge; staminate stout, 39–56 × 14–22 mm, flowering branchlet 0–2 mm; pistillate densely flowered, stout, 39–70(–110 in fruit) × 13–22 mm, flowering branchlet 0–2 mm; floral bract dark brown, 1.8–4 mm, apex acute or rounded, abaxially sparsely hairy, hairs straight or wavy. Staminate flowers: adaxial nectary oblong, 0.6–1.2 mm; filaments distinct, glabrous or hairy basally; anthers yellow or purple turning yellow, 0.6–1 mm. Pistillate flowers: adaxial nectary oblong, narrowly oblong, or square, 0.5–1 mm, (unlobed), shorter to longer than stipe; stipe 0.4–1.5 mm; ovary pyriform, beak gradually tapering to styles; ovules 18–30 per ovary; styles 1.1–2.8 mm; stigmas slenderly cylindrical, 0.32–0.53–1 mm. Capsules 4–7 mm.</description>
  <phenology>jul</phenology>
  <phenology>summer</phenology>
  <habitat>subalpine and alpine</habitat>
  <habitat>streamsides and bottoms</habitat>
  <habitat>lakeshores</habitat>
  <habitat>marshes</habitat>
  <habitat>spruce bogs</habitat>
  <habitat>talus slopes</habitat>
  <habitat>tundra</habitat>
  <habitat>quartzite, granite</habitat>
  <habitat>or, sometimes, limestone substrates</habitat>
  <elevation>1400–4000 m;</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wyo.</us_distribution>
</treatment>
