<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">SALICACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Raup" date="unknown">silicicola</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Arnold Arbor.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 236, plate 194. 1936</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SALICACEAE;genus Salix;species silicicola;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Andersson) Coville" date="unknown">alaxensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Raup) B. Boivin" date="unknown">silicicola</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Salix;species alaxensis;variety silicicola;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>96.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Blanket-leaf willow</other_name>
  <discussion>Comparisons of genetic variation in Salix alaxensis var. alaxensis from British Columbia and S. silicicola from Lake Athabasca sand dunes, Saskatchewan, based on isozyme loci, fit predicted relationships between progenitor and derived taxon (B. G. Purdy and R. J. Bayer 1995). Allelic diversity of S. silicicola was a subset of that of S. alaxensis, there was less genetic variation in S. silicicola than in S. alaxensis, and interspecific genetic variation within the two species was similar and relatively very high. This suggested a recent origin for the derived S. silicicola.</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix silicicola is a uniform population that differs from S. alaxensis in its very densely villous or tomentose leaves and branchlets. These characters seem to be an adaptation to reduce sand abrasion and water loss in a sand dune environment. It is unlikely that it would have evolved in situ but probably derived from a pre-adapted source such as the one represented by specimens of putative S. silicicola from Pelly Lake, Nunavut. The isozyme study did not include specimens from that population or of S. alaxensis from Northwest Territories from which S. silicicola is likely to have been derived. Occurrence of S. silicicola-like plants in northern continental Nunavut suggests that during the late Pleistocene, it had a wider range, which now is represented by two disjunct populations. The question of appropriate taxonomic rank for the derived taxon is still unresolved. Although S. silicicola is different from S. alaxensis in its general appearance, they are very similar genetically, and argument could be made for treating them as varieties (B. Boivin 1966b).</discussion>
  <discussion>Hybrids:</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix silicicola forms natural hybrids with S. brachycarpa var. psammophila.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
