<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">SALICACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker" date="unknown">barrattiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 146, plate 181. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SALICACEAE;genus Salix;species barrattiana;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">barrattiana</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Raup" date="unknown">marcescens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Salix;species barrattiana;variety marcescens;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>97.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Barratt’s willow</other_name>
  <discussion>Salix barrattiana has stipules and buds that are typically strongly oily or resinous, staining pressing sheets yellow. The Montana and Wyoming records are the basis for a conservation assessment by J. A. R. Ladyman (www.fs.fed.us/r2/projects/scp/assessments/salixbarrattiana.pdf). The Wyoming population is represented by three staminate specimens. Their buds and stipules are not conspicuously oily and further verification is needed.</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix barrattiana is placed here in sect. Villosae, but it is morphologically similar also to members of sect. Lanatae. The most conspicuous difference is its hairy ovaries. Inconsistent phenetic clustering of this species (G. W. Argus 1997) shows the difficulty in determining its sectional placement. The suggestion that it may link the two sections by hybridization and introgression, or by alloploidy, still remains to be assessed.</discussion>
  <discussion>Hybrids:</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix barrattiana forms natural hybrids with S. barclayi, S. commutata, and S. pseudomyrsinites.</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix barrattiana × S. commutata: This hybrid, known from Alberta and the Yukon, usually resembles S. barrattiana, but ovaries are hairy in patches, stipes at ca. 1 mm are long for that species, and buds and stipules are not oily. A British Columbia specimen has glabrous ovaries and oily stipules.</discussion>
  <discussion>Salix barrattiana × S. pseudomyrsinites is a rare putative hybrid that combines characteristics of the two parents.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
