<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>0</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><family_name>MORINGACEAE</family_name><family_authority>Martinov</family_authority></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Drumstick Tree Family</common_name><author>Mark E. Olson</author><description>Trees or shrubs; glabrous or puberulent; roots tuberous [massive, fibrous, or shrubs canelike with underground tubers], (producing glucosinolates and isothiocyanates, especially in roots and leaves; strongly odoriferous). Stems erect to pendent; unbranched [branched]. Leaves (drought-deciduous) alternate, (imparipinnate), compound; stipules present (glandular); petiole present; leaflets opposite, blade margins entire. Inflorescences axillary, paniculate, with (2–)3–4(–5) orders of branching; bracts (and bracteoles) usually present (glandular). Pedicels present. Flowers strongly zygomorphic [nearly actinomorphic]; perianth and androecium perigynous; sepals 5, distinct; petals 5 (bannerlike petal borne abaxially), distinct; stamens 5, opposite petals (inserted on rim of hypanthium); staminodes [3–]5, similar to filaments, alternate with stamens; anthers monothecal, bisporangiate; ovary 3-carpellate, 1-locular, (on gynophore); placentation probably marginal (sometimes interpreted as medial); ovules anatropous; style 1 (hollow, with a gaping stigmatic aperture). Fruits capsular, valvate, laxly dehiscent, fibrous. Seeds 10–35, brown, globular, winged or not; cotyledons oily.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Genus 1, species 13 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><introduced>introduced;</introduced><global_distribution>sw Asia</global_distribution><global_distribution>sw</global_distribution><global_distribution>ne Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution>Indian Ocean Islands (Madagascar)</global_distribution><global_distribution>introduced also pantropically.</global_distribution><discussion>Moringaceae are closely related to Caricaceae, with which they share glandular appendages at the apex of the petiole.</discussion><discussion>The bark of Moringaceae is conspicuous with bundles of phloem, schizogenous gum ducts are present in the pith and also on trauma in the bark, and exudes a straw- or pinkish-colored gum. The wood is white or yellowish and the plants are fibrous to mostly parenchymatous.</discussion><references>
    <reference>Olson, M. E. 2002. Intergeneric relationships within the Caricaceae-Moringaceae clade (Brassicales), and potential morphological synapomorphies of the clade and its families. Int. J. Pl. Sci. 163: 51–65.</reference>
    <reference>Olson, M. E. 2002b. Combining data from DNA sequences and morphology for a phylogeny of Moringaceae. Syst. Bot. 27: 55–73.</reference>
    <reference>Olson, M. E. 2003. Developmental origins of floral bilateral symmetry in Moringaceae. Amer. J. Bot. 90: 49–71.</reference>
    <reference> Verdcourt, B. 1985. A synopsis of the Moringaceae. Kew Bull. 40: 1–-23.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
