<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">MORINGACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Moringa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lamarck" date="unknown">oleifera</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Lamarck et al., Encycl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 398. 1785</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family MORINGACEAE;genus Moringa;species oleifera;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Guilandina</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">moringa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 381. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Guilandina;species moringa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Hyperanthera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Vahl" date="unknown">moringa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Hyperanthera;species moringa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Drumstick or horseradish or Ben tree</other_name>
  <discussion>Moringa oleifera is probably native to lowland dry tropical forests of northwestern India; recent collection information is lacking. It is cultivated in tropical countries as an ornamental and agricultural crop. It is occasionally reported as re-seeding along roadways and in other disturbed areas; there are no reports of M. oleifera invading intact habitats.</discussion>
  <discussion>Moringa oleifera is often mistaken for a papilionoid legume or for a member of the Bignoniaceae. It is easily distinguished from both by stalked glands at the leaf base and at rachis articulations and by its pungent horseradish odor. The three-valved fruits with three-winged seeds also readily distinguish M. oleifera from both of those families. All parts of the plant are of economic importance: leaves are highly nutritious, flowers are edible, seeds contain large quantities of high-quality oil, and presscake remaining after oil extraction contains one of the most powerful plant-derived flocculants known, used for clarifying turbid water. Roots are used as a horseradishlike condiment. Moringa oleifera is extremely fast growing (to 7 m in first year from seed), with fruit yields ca. 10 tons/ha/yr.</discussion>
  <discussion>Moringa pterygosperma Gaertner is a commonly cited synonym of M. oleifera. However, the name is illegitimate as it is based on Guilandia moringa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
