<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">LIMNANTHACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Limnanthes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Trelease" date="unknown">macounii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Boston Soc. Nat. Hist.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 85. 1888</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family LIMNANTHACEAE;genus Limnanthes;species macounii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Macoun’s meadowfoam</other_name>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Limnanthes macounii is native on Vancouver Island and adjacent islands in British Columbia from East Sooke Park to Victoria, Inskip, Chatham, and Trial islands, to Yellow Point, Saltspring, Gabriola, and Hornby islands. It grows in seasonally moist depressions (including edges of vernal pools) in acidic soils that often have a high nutrient content. The population in California is in an agricultural field in San Mateo County; first discovered there in 1998 (E. G. Buxton 1998), it appears to be persisting. Phylogenetic analyses suggest this may be an aberrant population of L. douglasii (S. Meyers, pers. comm.)</discussion>
  <discussion>The angular and comparatively massive tubercles of the nutlets of Limnanthes macounii, with the base equaling 1/4–1/3 the width of the nutlet, are unique in the genus (H. H. Hauptli et al. 1978). Allozyme studies by R. V. Kesseli and S. K. Jain (1984b) showed that L. macounii had alleles found in no other taxa at three loci. M. S. Plotkin (1998) concluded that L. macounii should be included in L. douglasii based on ITS analysis. Because of its unique characteristics and highly disjunct distribution, L. macounii is maintained as a species here pending further study.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Committee on the Status of Endangered Wildlife in Canada. 2004. COSEWIC assessment and update status report on the Macoun’s meadowfoam Limnanthes macounii in Canada. Ottawa.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
