<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gordon C. Tucker</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Engler" date="unknown">KOEBERLINIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family KOEBERLINIACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees (deciduous); (thorny) spines absent: glabrous or glabrate. Stems erect; profusely branched. Leaves alternate, spirally arranged, (minute, scalelike); venation pinnate; stipules present (caducous, scalelike); petiole absent. Inflorescences axillary, racemose, corymbose, or flowers solitary; pedunculate; bud scales usually persistent; bracts usually absent, sometimes present. Pedicels present. Flowers bisexual, actinomorphic, rotate to crateriform, campanulate, or urceolate; perianth and androecium hypogynous; sepals persistent, 4, distinct or connate basally; petals 4, attached directly to receptacle, imbricate, distinct, equal; intrastaminal nectary-discs or glands usually present; stamens 8; filaments distinct, glabrous or pubescent; anthers dehiscing bylongitudinal slits; pistil 1; ovary 1-carpellate, 2-locular; placentation axile; ovules anatropous, bitegmic; style 1 (straight, short and thick); stigma 1, capitate, unlobed. Fruits: berries, indehiscent (spheroidal). Seeds (1 or) 2–4, blackish; not arillate; endosperm scanty or absent, sometimes a persistent perisperm present; cotyledons incumbent. x = 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America (Bolivia).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Genus 1, species 2 (1 in the flora): sw North America, n Mexico, South America (Bolivia).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Genus 1, species 2 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>sw North America, n Mexico, South America (Bolivia).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>0</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Allthorn Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genus 1, species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Koeberlinia has been included in the traditional Capparaceae by some authors, including A. Cronquist (1981). Recent molecular studies support its removal from Capparaceae and a relationship with Bataceae and Salvadoraceae (P. F. Stevens, www.mobot.org/MOBOT/research/APweb).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Holmes, W. C., K. L. Yip, and A. E. Rushing. 2008. Taxonomy of Koeberlinia (Koeberliniaceae). Brittonia 60: 171–184.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
