<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Santiago Martín-Bravo,Gordon C. Tucker,Thomas F. Daniel</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">RESEDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family RESEDACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>0</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Mignonette Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 6, species ca. 85 (2 genera, 5 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Placement of Resedaceae in the Capparales or Brassicales is well settled, based on morphological, anatomical, and molecular criteria, and the shared presence of glucosinolates (mustard oil glucosides). The family has been traditionally considered closest to Brassicaceae and Capparaceae. Molecular data (J. C. Hall et al. 2002, 2004) revealed an unexpected relationship to the Australian endemic Gyrostemonaceae and two genera of Capparaceae (Forchhammeria and Tirania). The foundations of the taxonomy of Resedaceae were established in the nineteenth century primarily through the work of J. Müller Argoviensis (1857, 1868), who recognized three tribes within the family (Astrocarpeae, Cayluseae, Resedeae) based on ovary and placentation type. Validity of his tribal classification was confirmed by later morphological and molecular studies (M. S. Abdallah and H. C. D. de Wit 1978; S. Martín-Bravo et al. 2007). Apparently, the only species of the family native to the New World is Oligomeris linifolia (see below).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Abdallah, M. S. and H. C. D. de Wit. 1978. The Resedaceae: A taxonomical revision of the family (final installment). Meded. Landbouwhoogeschool 78.</reference>
    <reference>Carlquist, S. 1998b. Wood anatomy of Resedaceae. Aliso 16: 127–135.</reference>
    <reference>Edmonson, J. R. 1993. Resedaceae. In: T. G. Tutin et al., eds. 1993+. Flora Europaea, ed. 2. Cambridge and New York Vol. 1, pp. 417–420. El</reference>
    <reference>Hennig, L. 1929. Beiträge zur Kenntnis der Resedaceen—Blüte und Frucht. Planta 9: 507–563.</reference>
    <reference>Kubitzky, K. 2003. Resedaceae. In: K. Kubitzky et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 9+ vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 5, pp. 334–338. Martín-</reference>
    <reference>Mitra, K. and S. N. Mitra. 1979. Pollen morphology in relation to taxonomy and geography of Resedaceae. Bull. Bot. Surv. India 18: 194–202.</reference>
    <reference>Sobick, U. 1983. Blutenentwicklungsgeschichtliche Untersuchungen an Resedaceen unter besonderer Berucksichtigung von Androeceum und Gynoeceum. Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 104: 203–248.</reference>
    <reference>Weberling, F. 1968. Über die Rudimentärstipeln der Resedaceae. Acta Bot. Neerl. 17: 360–372.</reference>
    <reference>Bolle, F. 1936. Resedaceae. In: H. G. A. Engler et al., eds. 1924+. Die Natürlichen Pflanzenfamilien..., ed. 2. 26+ vols. Leipzig and Berlin. Vol. 17b, pp. 659–693.</reference>
    <reference>Naggar, S. M. 2002. Taxonomic significance of pollen morphology in some taxa of Resedaceae. Feddes Repert. 113: 518–527. González</reference>
    <reference>Aguilera, J. J. and A. M. Fernández Peralta. 1984. Phylogenetic relationships in the family Resedaceae. Genetica 64: 185–197.</reference>
    <reference>Bravo, S. et al. 2007. Molecular systematics and biogeography of Resedaceae based on ITS and trnL-F sequences. Molec. Phylogen. Evol. 44: 1105–1120.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 0.8–5 × 0.05–0.2 cm, margins usually entire, sometimes toothed near base with 1–2 hyaline teeth; inflorescences usually dense spikes (or spikelike racemes); pedicels</description>
      <determination>1. Oligomeris , p. 190</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 3–15 × 0.5–5 cm, margins entire, pinnatisect, or lobed; inflorescences racemes;</description>
      <determination>2. Reseda , p. 191</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
