<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">RESEDACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cambessèdes" date="unknown">OLIGOMERIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in V. Jacquemont, Voy. Inde</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4(Bot.): 23. 1839</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family RESEDACEAE;genus OLIGOMERIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek oligos , few, and meros , part, alluding to fewer stamens and petals than in other genera of family]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual [biennial], or perennial. Stems erect to ascending, branched basally. Leaves not rosulate; alternate (sometimes fasciculate); petiolate, petiole shorter than blade, winged; blade margins usually entire, sometimes toothed near base, teeth 1–2, hyaline. Inflorescences usually dense spikes (or spikelke racemes). Pedicels absent or nearly so. Flowers: sepals persistent, 2–4(–5), distinct, equal; petals 2–3[–5], distinct or basally connate, margins entire or shallowly incised; intrastaminal nectary-discs absent; stamens 3–4[–10]; filaments persistent, distinct or basally connate; ovaries 4(–5)-carpelled. Capsules erect, angled, subglobose to obovoid, walls membranous. Seeds smooth (glossy). x = 15.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw</description>
  <description type="distribution">c Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n</description>
  <description type="distribution">s Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Atlantic Islands.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Whitepuff</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Molecular research has shown that Oligomeris is a monophyletic group nested within Reseda in tribe Resedeae and sister to Reseda sect. Glaucoreseda (S. Martín-Bravo et al. 2007). Nonetheless, it seems preferable to maintain the genus; it has clear-cut diagnostic morphological characteristics. Hyaline teeth at the base of the leaves may be vestiges of a laminar segmentation of the leaves (F. Weberling 1968); some have interpreted the teeth as stipular.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
