<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">salicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family salicaceae;genus salix;subgenus Salix</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 1–25 m, usually not clonal, or clonal by stem fragmentation. Stems usually erect (pendulous in S. babylonica); branches flexible to highly brittle at base, not glaucous, (usually slightly or highly glossy). Buds alba-type, scale margins connate. Leaves: stipules on early ones usually absent or rudimentary, sometimes foliaceous, on late ones rudimentary or foliaceous, (deciduous spring or autumn); petiole convex, flat, or shallowly to deeply grooved adaxially, not glandular, or with spherical or foliaceous glands distally or throughout; largest medial blade amphistomatous, hemiamphistomatous, or hypostomatous, lorate, narrowly oblong, narrowly elliptic, elliptic, lanceolate, narrowly ovate, or oblanceolate, 2–14.4 times as long as wide, angle of base and of apex less than 90o, surface hairs white and/or ferruginous; juvenile blade hairs white and/or ferruginous. Catkins flowering as leaves emerge (sometimes before in S. babylonica), from lateral buds; staminate on flowering branchlet or sessile, usually slender or stout, sometimes subglobose; pistillate on flowering branchlet, densely or loosely flowered, slender, stout, or subglobose; floral bract usually tawny, sometimes greenish, apex usually entire, toothed, or erose, rarely sinuate; pistillate bract deciduous or persistent after flowering. Staminate flowers: abaxial nectary usually present; stamens 2–10; filaments distinct or connate less than 1/2 their lengths, hairy on proximal 1/2 or basally, rarely glabrous; anthers usually yellow, sometimes reddish turning yellow. Pistillate flowers: abaxial nectary absent or present; ovary not glaucous, glabrous or, rarely, villous, beak usually gradually tapering to styles; ovules 2–36 per ovary; styles connate or distinct; stigmas usually flat, abaxially non-papillate, tip rounded, sometimes stigmas cylindrical, or 2 plump lobes.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia.</description>
  <number>2b.</number>
  <discussion>Species 85 (9 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Five of the eight sections recognized in this subgenus are found in the flora area.</discussion>
  <discussion>See 2a. Salix subg. Protitea for the rationale for including the multistaminate species of sect. Salicaster in subg. Salix.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trees; stems pendulous; pistillate bracts persistent after flowering; pistillate adaxial nectaries longer than stipes; styles 0.15–0.3 mm; stipes 0–0.2 mm; ovules 2–8 per ovary; capsules 1–3.5 mm; stamens 2 [2b1. Salix sect. Subalbae ].</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches yellowish, yellow-green, or yellow-brownSalix × sepulcralis (in part) [p. 40]</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches yellow-brown to red-brown or gray-brown.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate catkins on flowering branchlets (0–)2–4 mm; ovaries: beak abruptly</description>
      <determination>8. Salix babylonica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate catkins on flowering branchlets 3–14 mm; ovaries: beak gradually tapering to styles; anthers 0.5–0.8 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles short-silky adaxially; branches yellowish, yellow-green, or yellow-brown; staminate catkins moderately densely flowered, slender, nectaries</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles glabrous, pilose, or velvety to glabrescent adaxially; branches yellow-brown, gray-brown, or red-brown; staminate catkins loosely flowered, stout,</description>
      <next_statement_id>1.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees; stems erect; pistillate bracts deciduous after flowering (persistent in S. maccalliana , sometimes persistent until fruiting in S. triandra ); pistillate adaxial nectaries shorter than or equal to stipes; styles 0.1–1.2 mm; stipes 0.2–4 mm; ovules 8–30 per ovary; capsules 3.5–12 mm; stamens 2–10.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles without spherical glands or lobes distally; stamens 2; anthers purple turning yellow in age; ovaries densely villous; pistillate bracts persistent after flowering; leaf</description>
      <determination>15. Salix maccalliana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles with spherical glands or lobes distally; stamens 2 or 3–10; anthers yellow; ovaries glabrous; pistillate bracts deciduous after flowering (sometimes persistent in S. triandra ); leaf blades: abaxial surface glaucous or not.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: abaxial surface usually not glaucous; stamens 3–10 [2b3. Salix sect. Salicaster (in part), 2b5. Salix sect. Triandrae ].</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: adaxial surface dull or ± slightly glossy; styles</description>
      <determination>16. Salix triandra (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: adaxial surface slightly or highly glossy; styles 0.3–1 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules on early leaves foliaceous; juvenile blade hairs white and</description>
      <determination>13. Salix lucida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules on early leaves absent or rudimentary; juvenile blades glabrous; branchlets glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blade margins crenate or crenulate; stamens 2; floral</description>
      <determination>10. Salix euxina</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blade margins serrulate; stamens 3–10; floral bracts 1.2–4 mm; capsules 6–12 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches highly glossy; pistillate catkins slender to stout; floral bracts sparsely hairy proximally; ovaries: beak gradually tapering</description>
      <determination>11. Salix pentandra</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches dull or slightly glossy; pistillate catkins stout to globose; floral bracts moderately densely hairy; ovaries: beak slightly</description>
      <determination>12. Salix serissima</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: abaxial surface glaucous (except usually not glaucous in S. triandra ); stamens 2 or 3–6.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile and largest medial blades with white hairs; stamens 2 [2b2. Salix sect. Salix ].</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades persistently silky on both surfaces; petioles long-</description>
      <determination>9. Salix alba</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades glabrescent or glabrous on both surfaces; petioles glabrous or puberulent adaxially; styles 0.4–1 mm; branches highly brittle</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile and largest medial blades with white and ferruginous hairs; stamens usually more than 2 [2b3. Salix sect. Salicaster (in part)].</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles convex to shallowly grooved adaxially; leaf blades: abaxial surface long-silky to glabrescent; stipes 0.3–0.6 mm; pistillate flowering</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles deeply grooved adaxially; leaf blades: abaxial surface usually glabrous or pubescent; stipes 0.8–2 mm; pistillate flowering branchlets 6–56 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules: apex convex or rounded; petioles: margins not touching;</description>
      <determination>14. Salix lasiandra</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules: apex acuminate or acute; petioles: margins covering groove;</description>
      <determination>16. Salix triandra (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
