<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gordon C. Tucker</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Berchtold &amp; J. Presl" date="unknown">cleomaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Engelmann in F. A. Wislizenus" date="1848">WISLIZENIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in F. A. Wislizenus, Mem. Tour N. Mexico,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>99. 1848</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cleomaceae;genus WISLIZENIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Friedrich (later Frederick) Adolph Wislizenus, 1810–1889, botanical collector in southwestern United States and adjacent Mexico]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, shrubs, or subshrubs, annual or perennial. Stems sparsely branched laterally; puberulent, glabrous, or glabrate (scabrid when dry). Leaves: stipules minute tufts of filiform hairs; petiole without pulvinus (equal to or longer than leaflets); leaflets (1 or) 3, (conduplicate). Inflorescences terminal, racemes (dense); bracts usually absent; (pedicels 3–5 mm, glabrous). Flowers: zygomorphic; sepals usually persistent (eventually deciduous), distinct, equal; petals slightly unequal (in pairs); stamens 6 (well-exserted, ± equal); filaments inserted on gynophore, glabrous; anthers (oblong), coiling after dehiscence; gynophore reflexed in fruit; (pistil 2-lobed basally, style filiform, eventually spinelike). Fruits schizocarps, indehiscent, obovate, (reticulate, ± tuberculate, valves disarticulating from persistent, round septum). Seeds 2(–4), globose, not arillate. x = 10.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sc</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 3 (3 in the flora): sc, sw United States, nw Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 3 (3 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>sc, sw United States, nw Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>5.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Jackass-clover</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">spectacle-fruit</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Wislizenia has been the object of diverse taxonomic opinions; as many as eight or as few as one species have been recognized. S. Keller (1979) documented three geographically and morphologically distinct groups within the genus. Although she treated those as subspecies, recognition as species seems more appropriate (H. H. Iltis, pers. comm.). The differentiation among the taxa seems equal to or greater than that among species in other genera of the family.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Greene, E. L. 1906b. Revision of the genus Wislizenia. Proc. Biol. Soc. Wash. 19: 127–132.</reference>
    <reference>Keller, S. 1979. A revision of the genus Wislizenia (Capparidaceae) based on population studies. Brittonia 31: 333–351.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Subshrubs or shrubs; leaflets 3 proximally, 1 distally, blade ovate to obovate, 3–8(–12) times</description>
      <determination>2. Wislizenia palmeri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals; leaflets 3 throughout, blade ovate to obovate, 1.5–4(–5.5) times as long as wide; sepals lanceolate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaflets less than 2.8 times as long as wide; gynophore ca. 5 mm in fruit; anthers</description>
      <determination>1. Wislizenia californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaflets 1.5–4(–5.5) times as long as wide; gynophore 2–12 mm in fruit; anthers</description>
      <determination>3. Wislizenia refracta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
