<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>8.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>CLEOSERRATA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>H. H. Iltis</genus_authority>
  <place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>17: 447. 2007</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[Genus Cleome and serrata , serrate, alluding to leaflet margins]</etymology>
  
  <author>Gordon C. Tucker</author>
  <description>Herbs, annual [perennial]. Stems unbranched or sparsely [profusely] branched;
    glabrous or glandular-pubescent. Leaves: stipules absent; petiole with pulvinus basally or
    distally, (petiolule base adnate, forming pulvinar disc; leaflets 3 or 5–9. Inflorescences
    terminal or axillary (from distal leaves), racemes (flat-topped or elongated); bracts present.
    Flowers (often appearing unisexual due to incomplete development), zygomorphic; sepals
    persistent or deciduous, distinct, equal (each often subtending a nectary); petals equal;
    stamens 6; filaments inserted on a discoid or conical androgynophore, usually glabrous; anthers
    coiling as pollen is released; gynophore recurved in fruit. Fruits capsules, dehiscent, oblong.
    Seeds 10–30+, subglobose [reniform], not arillate, (cleft fused between ends). x =
    12.</description>
  <discussion>segregation of cleoserrata from tarenaya is based on the absence of prickles on the
    minutely serrulate leaf, the x = 12 chromosomal complement, and molecular evidence suggesting a
    more basal clade than that of tarenaya (l. a. inda et al. 2008).</discussion>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 5 (2 in the flora)</number_of_infrataxa>
  <introduced>introduced</introduced>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>West Indies</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>South America</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Petals usually brilliant pink to purple, fading to pink or white, rarely initially
        white; bracts</statement>
      <determination>1. Cleoserrata speciosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Petals white or whitish, with pinkish or red distally; bracts subulate, to 1 mm;
        gynophore</statement>
      <determination>2. Cleoserrata serrata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
