<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>6.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Alyssum</genus_name>
    <species_name>murale</species_name>
    <species_authority>Waldstein &amp; Kitaibel</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Descr. Icon. Pl. Hung.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 5. 1799</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Perennials; (cespitose, sometimes caudex woody); canescent or not, trichomes stellate, 5–20-rayed. Stems often several from caudex (sterile shoots absent or few), usually erect or ascending, (2.5–)3–6(–7) dm. Cauline leaves subsessile; blade narrowly oblanceolate to linear, (0.5–)0.7–2.5(–3) cm × 1–5(–8) mm (gradually smaller distally), base cuneate to attenuate, apex obtuse to subacute, (surfaces often more grayish abaxially than adaxially). (Racemes corymbose, in panicles terminating each stem.) Fruiting pedicels divaricate-ascending, straight or slightly curved distally, slender, (2–)2.5–6(–8) mm, trichomes uniformly stellate. Flowers: sepals oblong, 1.2–2 × 0.4–0.7 mm, stellate-pubescent; petals yellow, spatulate, 2.5–3.5 × 0.5–1 mm, base attenuate, apex often obtuse or rounded, glabrous abaxially; filaments: median pairs broadly winged, apically 1-toothed, lateral pair with lanceolate or narrowly oblong basal appendage, apically subacute, 1.5–2.5 mm; anthers oblong, 0.2–0.3 mm. Fruits broadly elliptic to orbicular, 3.5–5 × 2.5–5 mm, apex obtuse to rounded; valves not inflated, flattened and slightly undulate, stellate-pubescent; ovules 1 per ovary; style (slender) 1–2 mm, sparsely pubescent. Seeds suborbicular to broadly ovoid, compressed, 3–3.8 × 2–3.2 mm, margins winged, wing 0.5–0.9 mm wide. 2n = 16, 32.</description>
  <phenology>may</phenology>
  <phenology>spring</phenology>
  <phenology>jun</phenology>
  <phenology>summer</phenology>
  <phenology>jul</phenology>
  <habitat>waste areas</habitat>
  <habitat>roadsides</habitat>
  <elevation>1500–1800 m;</elevation>
  <introduced>introduced;</introduced>
  <ca_distribution>Alta.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Colo.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Utah</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>sw Asia.</global_distribution>
</treatment>
