<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>4.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>MATTHIOLA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>W. T. Aiton</genus_authority>
  <place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in W. Aiton and W. T. Aiton, Hortus Kew.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>4: 119. 1812</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[For Pietro Andrea Matthioli, 1500–1577, Italian artist and botanist]</etymology>
  
  <past_name>Mathiola</past_name>
  <common_name>Stock</common_name>
  <conserved_name>, name and orthography conserved</conserved_name>
  <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Lonchophora</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Durieu</genus_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Annuals, biennials, or perennials [subshrubs]; (base sometimes woody); not scapose;
    (glandular or not), pubescent, trichomes stalked, stellate or dendritic, or, rarely, forked or
    simple. Stems erect to ascending or decumbent, unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline;
    petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate or not, petiolate, blade margins entire, dentate, or
    pinnatisect. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered). Fruiting pedicels divaricate or ascending
    [erect], slender or stout. Flowers: sepals (connivent), oblong to lanceolate or linear, lateral
    pair strongly saccate basally; petals yellow, white, pink, purple, violet, or brown [yellowish
    green], broadly obovate, spatulate, oblong, or linear (much longer than sepals, flat or
    circinately rolled inwards, margins crisped or not), claw differentiated from blade, (apex
    obtuse, rounded, subacute, or emarginate); stamens strongly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated
    basally; anthers linear [oblong], (apex obtuse); nectar glands (4 and) lateral, 1 on each side
    of lateral stamen, or (2 and) semiannular, intrastaminal. Fruits sessile, linear, subtorulose
    [torulose], often straight, terete or latiseptate; valves each with prominent midvein,
    pubescent; replum rounded; septum complete, (often opaque, veinless); style obsolete or
    distinct; stigma conical, 2-lobed (lobes prominent, distinct or connate, decurrent, with or
    without 2 or 3 hornlike appendages). Seeds flattened, narrowly winged or not winged, oblong,
    ovate, suborbicular, or orbicular; seed coat (minutely reticulate), not mucilaginous when
    wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>species ca. 50 (2 in the flora)</number_of_infrataxa>
  <introduced>introduced;</introduced>
  <global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Asia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Africa</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Atlantic Islands (Canary Islands)</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>introduced also in Australia.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits compressed, 3–6 mm wide, without stigmatic horns; cauline leaf blade margins
        entire or repand, rarely sinuate; fruiting pedicels (6–)10–20(–25) mm, thinner than fruit;
        petals</statement>
      <determination>1. Matthiola incana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits terete, 1–2 mm wide, with 2 stigmatic horns; cauline leaf blade margins
        dentate to pinnatifid, rarely entire; fruiting pedicels (0.5–)1–2(–3) mm, nearly as thick as
        fruit; petals</statement>
      <determination>2. Matthiola longipetala</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
