<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>5.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>APHRAGMUS</genus_name><genus_authority>Andrzejowski ex de Candolle</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 209. 1824</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek a-, not or without, and phragma , septum, alluding to its lack in fruit of some species]</etymology><author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Oreas</genus_name><genus_authority>Chamisso &amp; Schlechtendal</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Orobium</genus_name><genus_authority>Reichenbach</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Staintoniella</genus_name><genus_authority>H. Hara</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants not scapose; (sometimes rhizomatous, caudex thick, covered with persistent petiolar remains); glabrous or pubescent, trichomes simple or forked, (less than 0.1 mm). Stems erect or ascending, branched basally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate, petiolate, blade margins entire; cauline petiolate or sessile, blade margins entire. Racemes (few- to several-flowered), bracteate throughout or basally. Fruiting pedicels [erect] ascending, divaricate, sometimes recurved, slender. Flowers: sepals (sometimes persistent), oblong; petals broadly obovate or spatulate, claw subequaling sepal, (apex rounded [obtuse]); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments dilated or not basally; anthers obtuse; nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits silicles or siliques, sessile or subsessile, oblong, elliptic, or lanceolate [ovate, linear]; valves each with obscure or distinct midvein, (smooth), glabrous; replum flattened basally; septum absent [complete and membranous]; style obsolete or distinct (to 2 mm); stigma capitate. Seeds plump, not winged, oblong or ovoid (on filiform funicles often longer than seeds); seed coat (minutely reticulate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x = 7.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 11 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>nw North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Asia (Himalaya).</global_distribution><global_distribution>Asia (Russian Far East).</global_distribution><references>
    <reference>Al-Shehbaz, I. A. 2003. Aphragmus bouffordii, a new species from Tibet and a synopsis of Aphragmus (Brassicaceae). Harvard Pap. Bot. 8: 25–27.</reference>
    <reference> Ebel, A. L. 1998. Notes on genus Aphragmus Andrz. (Brassicaceae). Turczaninowia 1(4): 20–27.</reference>
  </references></treatment>
