<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">salicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Dumortier" date="1827">salicaster</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">pentandra</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1016. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family salicaceae;genus salix;subgenus salix;section salicaster;species pentandra</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, 5–15 m. Stems: branches flexible at base, brownish or yellow-green, highly glossy, glabrous; branchlets yellow-green, red-brown, or brownish, glossy, glabrous. Leaves: stipules absent or rudimentary on early ones, rudimentary or foliaceous on late ones, apex rounded; petiole deeply to shallowly grooved adaxially, 5–15 mm, with pairs or clusters of spherical glands distally or throughout, glabrous adaxially; largest medial blade hypostomatous, narrowly elliptic, elliptic, or lanceolate, 50–135 × 20–50 mm, 2–4 times as long as wide, base convex, margins slightly revolute or flat, serrulate, apex acuminate, abaxial surface pale not glaucous, glabrous, adaxial highly glossy, glabrous; proximal blade margins entire or serrulate; juvenile blade reddish, glabrous abaxially. Catkins: staminate 27–81 × 9–13 mm, flowering branchlet 9–21 mm; pistillate moderately to densely flowered, slender or stout, 29–68 × 7–15 mm, flowering branchlet 9–42 mm; floral bract 2–4 mm, apex acute or rounded to truncate, entire or toothed, abaxially sparsely hairy (mainly proximally), hairs wavy or straight. Staminate flowers: abaxial nectary 0.6–1.7 mm, adaxial nectary square, ovate, or oblong, 0.5–1.5 mm, nectaries distinct or ± connate and cup-shaped; stamens 4–10; filaments distinct, hairy on proximal 1/2; anthers ellipsoid or globose, 0.5–0.6 mm. Pistillate flowers: (abaxial nectary present or absent), adaxial nectary oblong, square, or ovate, 0.4–0.8 mm, (nectaries distinct or connate and shallowly cup-shaped), shorter than or equal to stipe; stipe 0.5–1.6 mm; ovary pyriform, beak bulged below or tapering to styles; ovules 18–22 per ovary; styles connate or distinct, 0.4–0.6 mm; stigmas flat, abaxially non-papillate with rounded tip, or slenderly cylindrical, 0.4–0.6 mm. Capsules 6–9 mm. 2n = 76.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late May-mid Jun.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shores of streams and lakes, marshes, roadsides, waste places;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-2300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Ont., Que., Sask.; Alaska, Colo., Conn., D.C., Ill., Iowa, Ky., Maine, Md., Mass., Minn., Mont., Nebr., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., R.I., S.Dak., Vt., Va., Wis., Wyo.; Eurasia.</description>
  <number>11.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Bay-leaf or bay or laurel willow</other_name>
  <discussion>The Ohio occurrence is based on information from T. Cooperrider (pers. comm.).</discussion>
  <discussion>Only pistillate plants of Salix pentandra are known to occur in the flora area.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
