<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">Arabideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Arabis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. M. Harper" date="unknown">georgiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Torreya</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 88. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Arabideae;genus Arabis;species georgiana;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials; sparsely to moderately hirsute (at least basally), trichomes simple, mixed with fewer, short-stalked, forked ones, subsessile cruciform or 3-rayed stellate trichomes commonly on abaxial blade surfaces, sometimes plants glabrous distally. Stems simple or few from base (rosette), erect, unbranched or branched (few) distally, 3–7 dm, (hirsute basally, glabrous distally). Basal leaves: petiole 0.5–2 cm, (ciliate or not); blade spatulate, oblanceolate, or obovate, 1.5–6 cm × 5–15 mm, margins dentate, apex obtuse or acute, abaxial surface moderately to sparsely pubescent, trichomes subsessile stellate, adaxial surface subglabrate or sparsely stellate. Cauline leaves 7–26; blade oblong, lanceolate, or linear-lanceolate, 1.5–7 cm × 3–18 mm, base auriculate to subamplexicaul, margins dentate or entire, apex acute or obtuse, pubescent as basal leaves except distalmost leaves often glabrous. Racemes often simple. Fruiting pedicels erect to erect-ascending, 7–16 mm, (glabrous). Flowers: sepals oblong, 2.5–4.5 × 1–1.5 mm, lateral pair subsaccate basally; petals white, narrowly spatulate or oblanceolate, 6–9 × 1–1.5 mm, apex obtuse; filaments 3–4.5 mm; anthers oblong, 0.8–1 mm. Fruits erect to erect-ascending, (often subappressed to rachis), smooth, 4–7 cm × 0.7–0.8 mm; valves each with midvein extending full length or to middle; ovules 38–44 per ovary; style 0.7–1.8 mm. Seeds narrowly winged throughout, oblong, 0.9–1.9 × 0.5–0.7 mm; wing to 0.1 mm wide distally.</description>
  <description type="phenology">mar</description>
  <description type="phenology">spring</description>
  <description type="phenology">apr</description>
  <description type="habitat">stream banks</description>
  <description type="habitat">roadsides</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <number>5.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Arabis georgiana is most closely related to A. pycnocarpa, from which it is easily distinguished by having narrower fruits, longer petals, and subsessile cruciform or 3-rayed trichomes on abaxial surfaces of basal leaves. It is known only in Alabama from Bibb and Elmore counties and in Georgia from Stewart County.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
