<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>8.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>AUBRIETA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Adanson</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fam. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 420. 1763</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[For Claude Aubriet, 1663–1743, French artist]</etymology>
  <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
  <description>Perennials; (often loosely pulvinate or cespitose, caudex many-branched); not
    scapose; pubescent, trichomes stellate, short-stalked or sessile, mixed with coarser, stalked,
    forked, and simple ones. Stems erect to decumbent, branched basally, (slender). Leaves basal and
    cauline; petiolate or sessile [subsessile]; basal rosulate, petiolate, blade margins entire or
    dentate; cauline petiolate or sessile [subsessile], blade (base not auriculate), margins entire
    or dentate. Racemes (few- to several-flowered), elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels erect to
    divaricate, slender. Flowers: sepals erect, oblong, lateral pair saccate basally, (glabrous or
    pubescent); petals usually purple to violet, rarely white [pink], obovate [spatulate], (apex
    obtuse); stamens tetradynamous; filaments narrowly winged, (lateral pair with toothed
    appendage); anthers oblong [ovate]; nectar glands lateral, semi-annular, extrastaminal. Fruits
    siliques or, rarely, silicles, sessile, ellipsoid, [linear, oblong, or elliptic], not torulose,
    terete or latiseptate; valves each with distinct midvein, pubescent or, rarely, glabrous; replum
    rounded; septum usually complete, sometimes perforate; ovules 10–40 per ovary; (style
    persistent); stigma capitate. Seeds biseriate, flattened, not winged, ovoid [elliptical]; seed
    coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 15 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <introduced>introduced</introduced>
  <global_distribution>California</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>sw Asia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>nw Africa.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Aubrieta is taxonomically challenging and is centered primarily in Greece and Turkey.
    The delimitation of species is often difficult, possibly because species have resulted from
    hybridization.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Mattfield, J. 1939. The species of the genus Aubrieta Adanson. Quart. Bull. Alpine
      Gard. Soc. 7: 157–181, 217–227.</reference>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1982. Another alien in the California flora. Rhodora 84:
      153–154.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>
