<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>56.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Draba</genus_name><species_name>lemmonii</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>in W. H. Brewer et al., Bot. California</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>2: 430. 1880</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><past_name>lemmoni</past_name><description>Perennials; (cespitose, not pulvinate); caudex branched (covered with persistent petiole remains, branches sometimes terminating in sterile rosettes); scapose. Stems unbranched, 0.3–1(–1.5) dm, hirsute throughout, trichomes simple, 0.2–0.7 mm, with short-stalked, 2-rayed ones, (smaller). Basal leaves rosulate; shortly petiolate; petiole base and margin ciliate, (trichomes simple, 0.5–1 mm, midvein obscure); blade (somewhat fleshy), oblanceolate to obovate, 0.4–1(–1.8) cm × 1.5–4(–6) mm, margins entire, surfaces hirsute, abaxially mostly with stalked, 2-rayed trichomes, 0.1–0.8 mm, rarely with fewer, simple ones, adaxially with mostly simple ones, 0.5–1 mm. Cauline leaves 0. Racemes 4–15(–21)-flowered, ebracteate, elongated in fruit; rachis not flexuous, hirsute as stem. Fruiting pedicels horizontal to divaricate-ascending (often somewhat decurrent basally), straight or curved upward, 4–10(–14) mm, hirsute as stem. Flowers: sepals ovate, 2–2.7 mm, pubescent, (trichomes simple, short-stalked, 2-rayed); petals yellow, spatulate, 4–6 × 1.5–2.5 mm; anthers oblong, 0.4–0.6 mm. Fruits ovate to ovate-lanceolate, slightly twisted, flattened, 4–9 × 3.5–5 mm; valves pubescent, trichomes usually simple, 0.1–0.45 mm, rarely with fewer, short-stalked, 2-rayed ones; ovules 10–14(–16) per ovary; style 0.1–0.6(–0.8) mm. Seeds ovoid, 1–1.4 × 0.6–1 mm. 2n = 50.</description><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>granitic rock outcrops</habitat><habitat>boulder slopes</habitat><habitat>alpine fellfields</habitat><elevation>3000–4000 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Draba lemmonii was so broadly circumscribed by C. L. Hitchcock (1941) and R. C. Rollins (1993) that it included plants here assigned to three different species. For a list of features distinguishing D. lemmonii from the recently-segregated D. longisquamosa and D. cyclomorpha, see I. A. Al-Shehbaz and M. D. Windham (2007). Draba lemmonii is apparently restricted to alpine areas of the Sierra Nevada in Fresno, Inyo, Madera, Mono, and Tuolumne counties.</discussion></treatment>
