<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">arabideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">draba</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hultén" date="1966">ogilviensis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Not.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>119: 315, fig. 2. 1966</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe arabideae;genus draba;species ogilviensis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; (stoloniferous); cau-dex branched (sparsely covered with petiole remains, branches slender, creeping, loosely matted); often scapose. Stems unbranched, 0.4–1.5 dm, gla-brous or pubescent throughout, trichomes simple and short-stalked, 2- or 3-rayed, 0.1–0.5 mm. Basal leaves not rosulate; (subopposite); petiolate; petiole base and margin ciliate or not, (trichomes simple, 0.2–0.8 mm); blade oblanceolate or lanceolate, 0.5–1.5 cm × 1.5–5 mm, margins entire, surfaces glabrous or sparsely pubescent with simple and stalked, 2–4-rayed trichomes, 0.1–0.5 mm, (midvein obscure abaxially). Cauline leaves (0 or) 1 or 2; (subopposite); sessile; blade ovate or oblong, margins entire, surfaces pubescent as basal. Racemes 5–13-flowered, ebracteate, elongated in fruit; rachis not or slightly flexuous, glabrous or pubescent as stem. Fruiting pedicels horizontal to divaricate, often curved upward, 6–13(–17) mm, glabrous or sparsely pubescent, trichomes simple and 2-rayed. Flowers: sepals ovate, 2–3 mm, glabrous or pubescent, (trichomes simple); petals golden yellow, obovate, 3.5–6 × 2–3 mm; anthers ovate, 0.3–0.5 mm. Fruits oblong, plane, flattened, 6–9 × 2–3 mm; valves glabrous; ovules 8–20 per ovary; style 0.4–1 mm. Seeds ovoid, 0.9–1 × ca. 0.6 mm. 2n = 16.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jun-Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Tundra, river flats and banks, exposed talus slopes, hummocks in wet sedge meadows;</description>
  <description type="elevation">900-2200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.W.T., Yukon; Alaska.</description>
  <number>72.</number>
  <discussion>The limits of Draba ogilviensis were confused by authors who reduced it to synonymy of D. juvenilis or D. sibirica. A thorough discussion of the three species and their distinguishing characteristics was provided by D. F. Murray and C. L. Parker (1999).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
