<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">arabideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">draba</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Rollins &amp; R. A. Price) Windham" date="2004">pedicellata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Madroño</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>50: 221. 2004</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe arabideae;genus draba;species pedicellata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Draba</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="B. L. Robinson ex O. E. Schulz" date="unknown">cusickii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Rollins &amp; R. A. Price" date="unknown">pedicellata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Harvard Pap. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(3): 73. 1991</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Draba;species cusickii;variety pedicellata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Draba</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">pedicellata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="N. H. Holmgren" date="unknown">wheelerensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Draba;species pedicellata;variety wheelerensis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; (loosely cespitose); caudex branched (with persistent leaf bases, branches sometimes terminating in sterile rosettes); scapose. Stems unbranched, (0.15–)0.3–1.3(–1.6) dm, pubescent proximally, glabrous or nearly so distally, trichomes 2- or 3-rayed and simple, 0.1–1 mm. Basal leaves rosulate; subsessile; blade oblanceolate to obovate, 0.4–1.6(–2) cm × 2–4(–6) mm, margins entire, (not ciliate), surfaces pubescent with stalked, 2–4-rayed trichomes, 0.2–0.9 mm, rarely adaxially with simple trichomes, (midvein obscure abaxially). Cauline leaves 0. Racemes 3–20(–27)-flowered, ebracteate, slightly to considerably elongated in fruit; rachis straight or flexuous, usually glabrous, rarely pubescent, trichomes simple and 2–4-rayed. Fruiting pedicels divaricate to horizontal, straight or curved upward (expanded basally or not), 4–9(–13) mm, glabrous or pubescent, trichomes simple and 2–4-rayed. Flowers: sepals broadly ovate, 1.8–2.5 mm, glabrous or pubescent, (trichomes simple and branched); petals yellow, spatulate, 3.5–5.5 × 1.5–2.2 mm; anthers ovate, 0.4–0.5 mm. Fruits lanceolate to ellipsoid or ovoid, plane (not curved), inflated or slightly flattened, (4.2–)5.3–10(–13) × 2.5–4.5(–5.5) mm; valves glabrous or pubescent, trichomes simple and short-stalked, 2-rayed, 0.05–0.3 mm; ovules 8–16 per ovary; style 0.3–1(–1.2) mm. Seeds oblong, 1.2–1.6 × 0.7–0.9 mm. 2n = 20.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May-Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rock outcrops, talus, steep gravel slopes in pinyon-juniper, mixed conifer, and subalpine meadow communities;</description>
  <description type="elevation">2300-3800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nev., Utah.</description>
  <number>81.</number>
  <discussion>Draba pedicellata is known from Elko, Eureka, Nye, and White Pine counties in northeastern Nevada and to Tooele County in northwestern Utah. It was considered a variety of D. cusickii by R. C. Rollins (1993); chromosome number, morphology, and geographic distribution suggest a closer relationship to D. sphaeroides. For a detailed discussion and comparison of these species, consult M. D. Windham (2004). N. H. Holmgren (2005b) divided D. pedicellata into two varieties: var. pedicellata, which is found on limestone throughout the species range, and var. wheelerensis, which is found on non-calcareous substrates in White Pine County. Although var. wheelerensis has slightly more spreading pedicels on somewhat more flexuous rachises, it appears to be little more than a dwarf alpine form of the species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
