<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">arabideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">draba</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rollins" date="1983">pennellii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Arnold Arbor.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>64: 502. 1983</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe arabideae;genus draba;species pennellii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; (cespitose, often forming mats); caudex branched (elongated, with persistent leaf bases, branches sometimes terminating in sterile rosettes); sometimes scapose. Stems unbranched, (0.15–)0.3–0.7(–1) dm, pubescent proximally, trichomes simple and spurred, 0.4–0.8 mm, and short-stalked, 2–4-rayed, 0.1–0.4 mm, (sometimes with simple trichomes distally). Basal leaves subrosulate; sessile; blade oblanceolate to oblong, (0.3–)0.5–0.8 cm × 1–3 mm, (base ciliate, trichomes simple, 0.2–0.8 mm), margins entire, (not ciliate), surfaces usually pubescent, with stalked, (2–)4 (or 5)-rayed trichomes, 0.2–0.5 mm, adaxially sometimes glabrate, or primarily with simple trichomes, 0.3–0.8 mm. Cauline leaves (0 or) 1–4; sessile; blade ovate to oblong, margins entire, surfaces pubescent as basal. Racemes (3–)7–15(–20)-flowered, ebracteate, elongated in fruit; rachis not flexuous, pubescent as stem. Fruiting pedicels divaricate-ascending to ascending, straight, 3–10 mm, pubescent, trichomes simple and short-stalked, 2–4-rayed, (0.1–0.4 mm). Flowers: sepals ovate to oblong, 2–3 mm, pubescent, (trichomes simple, with fewer, short-stalked, 2-rayed ones); petals white, obovate, 3.5–6 × 1.5–2.8 mm; anthers oblong, 0.5–0.6 mm. Fruits broadly or, rarely, narrowly lanceolate to elliptic or ovate, plane or slightly twisted, flattened, (4)5–8(–10) × 2–3.2 mm; valves (each with distinct midvein), pubescent, trichomes simple and short-stalked, 2-rayed, 0.08–0.2 mm; ovules 12–24 per ovary; style (0.7–)1–1.8(–2.1) mm. Seeds oblong, 0.9–1.3 × 0.7–1 mm. 2n = 32.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May-Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rock outcrops and talus slopes in pinyon-juniper, sagebrush, mountain shrub, and mixed conifer communities;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1900-3500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nev.</description>
  <number>82.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Draba pennellii is known from White Pine County in east-central Nevada. It is easily distinguished from other white-flowered species in the region by its elongated, many-branched caudices, long styles, usually few-leaved or, rarely, leafless flowering stems, and distinct midvein on fruit valves.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
