<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>93.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Draba</genus_name>
    <species_name>ruaxes</species_name>
    <species_authority>Payson &amp; H. St. John</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Biol. Soc. Wash.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>43: 117. 1930</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Draba</genus_name>
    <species_name>ventosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority>
    <variety_name>ruaxes</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(Payson &amp; H. St. John) C. L. Hitchcock</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Perennials; (cespitose, forming tufts); caudex branched (with persistent leaf bases, branches some terminating in sterile rosettes); scapose. Stems un-branched, 0.2–0.6(–0.8) dm, often pubescent throughout, sometimes glabrate distally, trichomes simple, 0.4–1 mm, and 2–4-rayed, 0.1–0.4 mm. Basal leaves rosulate; subsessile; petiole base and margin ciliate, (trichomes simple, 0.4–1.4 mm); blade oblanceolate to obovate or suborbicular, 0.3–1 cm × 2–4.5 mm, margins entire, surfaces pubescent, abaxially with stalked, 2–10-rayed, stellate trichomes, 0.2–0.8 mm, adaxially with simple trichomes, 0.4–1 mm, sometimes with smaller, 2–4-rayed ones, (midvein obscure). Cauline leaves 0. Racemes (2–)4–10(–14)-flowered, ebracteate, elongated in fruit; rachis not flexuous, pubescent as stem or glabrous. Fruiting pedicels ascending to divaricate-ascending, straight or slightly curved upward, 3–7(–9) mm, pubescent or glabrous, trichomes simple and 2–4-rayed. Flowers: sepals ovate, 2–3 mm, pubescent, (trichomes simple with fewer, 2-rayed ones); petals bright yellow, obovate, 4–6 × 2–3.5 mm; anthers oblong, 0.4–0.5 mm. Fruits elliptic to lanceolate or ovate to suborbicular, plane, flattened, 4–8(–10) × 3–4.5 mm; valves puberulent, trichomes simple with fewer 2-rayed ones, 0.1–0.35 mm; ovules 12–16 per ovary; style 0.5–0.9(–1.1) mm. Seeds oblong, 1.5–2 × 1–1.3 mm. 2n = 72.</description>
  <phenology>jun</phenology>
  <phenology>summer</phenology>
  <phenology>jul</phenology>
  <habitat>rock outcrops</habitat>
  <habitat>talus slopes</habitat>
  <habitat>ridges</habitat>
  <habitat>alpine summits</habitat>
  <elevation>500–2400 m;</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>Alta.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>C. L. Hitchcock (1941) treated Draba ruaxes as a variety of D. ventosa; as demonstrated by G. A. Mulligan (1971b), the two are quite distinct. Draba ruaxes is an outcrossing hexaploid with well-formed anthers and pollen, and abundant, simple trichomes on leaves, stems, sepals, and fruits. By contrast, D. ventosa is an apomictic triploid with abortive anthers and/or pollen, and no simple trichomes anywhere on the plant.</discussion>
</treatment>
