<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>107.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Draba</genus_name><species_name>standleyi</species_name><species_authority>J. F. Macbride &amp; Payson</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5: 150. 1918</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Draba</genus_name><species_name>gilgiana</species_name><species_authority>Wooton &amp; Standley</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb. </publication_title><place_in_publication>16: 124. 1913,</place_in_publication><other_info>not Muschler 1906</other_info></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Draba</genus_name><species_name>chrysantha</species_name><species_authority>S. Watson</species_authority><variety_name>gilgiana</variety_name><variety_authority>O. E. Schulz</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials; (densely pulvinate); caudex branched (with persistent, thickened petioles, branches compact); not scapose. Stems unbranched, 0.3–1.3(–1.7) dm, usually glabrous throughout or sparsely pubescent proximally, rarely sparsely pubescent distally, trichomes simple and 2-rayed, 0.1–0.7 mm. Basal leaves (not imbricate); rosulate; petiolate; petiole ciliate, (trichomes usually simple, rarely 2-rayed, not setiform); blade narrowly oblanceolate to linear-lanceolate, (strongly differentiated into blade and petiole), (1.2–)1.8–6(–8.5) cm × 1–5(–7) mm, margins entire or sparsely denticulate, (ciliate as petiole; midvein not prominent), surfaces glabrous or pubescent, usually with simple trichomes 0.1–0.8 mm, rarely 2-rayed. Cauline leaves 1–8; sessile; blade lanceolate to narrowly oblong, margins usually entire, surfaces pubescent as basal. Racemes 5–17(–23)-flowered, ebracteate, elongated in fruit; rachis not flexuous, usually glabrous, rarely pubescent, trichomes simple and 2-rayed, (non-crisped). Fruiting pedicels divaricate-ascending or ascending, straight, 3–9(–13) mm, usually glabrous, rarely sparsely pubescent, trichomes simple. Flowers: sepals ovate, 2–2.5 mm, pubescent, (trichomes simple); petals yellow, oblanceolate, 4–6 × 1.5–2 mm; anthers oblong, 0.6–0.8 mm. Fruits linear-elliptic to elliptic, twisted or plane, flattened, 5–10(–13) × 1.5–2.5 mm; valves usually glabrous, rarely puberulent, trichomes simple, 0.05–0.1 mm; ovules 12–24 per ovary; style 0.7–1.4(–1.8) mm. Seeds ovoid, 1–1.2 × 0.7–0.8 mm.</description><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><phenology>aug</phenology><habitat>igneous rock outcrops</habitat><habitat>stabilized talus slopes</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>1800–3100 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution><discussion>Draba standleyi is a distinctive species that is sporadically distributed in the mountains of southwestern United States. It is known from the Chiricahua Mountains (Cochise County, southeastern Arizona), the Organ Mountains and Black Range (Dona Ana and Sierra counties, south-central New Mexico), and the Davis Mountains (Jeff Davis County, western Texas). It has not been reported from Mexico, though it is very likely to occur there.</discussion></treatment>
