<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>10.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>ANELSONIA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>J. F. Macbride &amp; Payson</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>64: 81. 1917</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[For Aven Nelson, 1859–1952, American botanist who studied the flora of Wyoming and neighboring states]</etymology>
  <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
  <description>Perennials; (cespitose, deep-rooted); scapose; pubescent, trichomes short-stalked, dendritic or irregularly forked, (soft). Stems erect, unbranched. Leaves (persistent) basal; rosulate; petiolate; blade margins entire. Racemes (corymbose, few- to several-flowered), not or slightly elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels ascending to suberect, slender. Flowers: sepals (early caducous, erect), oblong, (pubescent), base of lateral pair not saccate; petals white to purplish, oblanceolate, (slightly longer than sepals); stamens tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate; nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits (erect, siliques or silicles), sessile or short-stipitate, lanceolate, broadly oblong to narrowly ovate, not torulose, latiseptate; valves each with prominent midvein and somewhat anastomosing lateral veins, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 10–24 per ovary; stigma capitate. Seeds biseriate, somewhat flattened, not winged, oblong to ovoid; seed coat (silvery, papillate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>w United States.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Anelsonia is most closely related to Boechera and Phoenicaulis, from which it is readily distinguished by its scapose habit and papillate seeds.</discussion>
</treatment>
