<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>35.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Boechera</genus_name><species_name>glaucovalvula</species_name><species_authority>(M. E. Jones) Al-Shehbaz</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>13: 385. 2003</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Arabis</genus_name><species_name>glaucovalvula</species_name><species_authority>M. E. Jones</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Contr. W. Bot. </publication_title><place_in_publication>8: 40. 1898</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials; short- to long-lived; sexual; caudex usually not woody. Stems usually 1 per caudex branch, arising from center of rosette near ground surface, (0.6–)1–4.5 dm, densely pubescent proximally, trichomes short-stalked, 4–8-rayed, 0.1–0.4 mm, similarly pubescent distally. Basal leaves: blade linear to linear-oblanceolate, 2–4(–6) mm wide, margins entire, usually ciliate at petiole base, trichomes (simple or spurred), to 1.5 mm, surfaces densely pubescent, trichomes short-stalked, 4–8-rayed, 0.1–0.4 mm. Cauline leaves: 6–10, not concealing stem; blade auricles absent, surfaces of distalmost leaves densely pubescent. Racemes (5–)10–25-flowered, usually unbranched. Fruiting pedicels reflexed, strongly curved at base, 2–10 mm, pubescent, trichomes appressed, branched. Flowers divaricate at anthesis; sepals pubescent; petals light purple to lavender, 6–9 × 1.5–2.5 mm, glabrous; pollen ellipsoid. Fruits strongly reflexed, sometimes appressed to rachis, often secund, straight, edges parallel, (1.8–)2.5–4.5 cm × 5–8 mm; valves glabrous; ovules 24–62 per ovary; style 0.2–0.6 mm. Seeds biseriate, 5–6 × 4–5 mm; wing continuous, 1.8–2.5 mm wide. 2n = 14.</description><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><phenology>apr</phenology><habitat>rocky slopes and gravelly soil</habitat><habitat>usually under shelter of desert shrubs</habitat><elevation>600–1600 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution><discussion>Boechera glaucovalvula, a distinctive sexual diploid that has the widest fruits in the genus, is known from Inyo, Mono, Riverside, and San Bernardino counties, California, and Clark and Nye counties, Nevada.</discussion></treatment>
