<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>43.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Boechera</genus_name><species_name>hoffmannii</species_name><species_authority>(Munz) Al-Shehbaz</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>13: 386. 2003</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><past_name>hoffmanii</past_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Arabis</genus_name><species_name>maxima</species_name><species_authority>Greene</species_authority><variety_name>hoffmannii</variety_name><variety_authority>Munz</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bull. S. Calif. Acad. Sci. </publication_title><place_in_publication>31: 63. 1932</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Arabis</genus_name><species_name>hoffmannii</species_name><species_authority>(Munz) Rollins</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Perennials; long-lived; sexual; caudex woody (sometimes with persistent, crowded leaf bases). Stems usually 1 per caudex branch, arising from center of rosette, often elevated above ground surface on woody base, 5–7 dm, glabrous or sparsely pubescent proximally, trichomes short-stalked, 2- or 3-rayed, 0.15–0.4 mm, glabrous or sparsely pubescent distally. Basal leaves: blade narrowly oblanceolate, 3–8 mm wide, margins coarsely dentate, ciliate, trichomes (simple and 2-rayed), to 0.6 mm, surfaces sparsely to densely pubescent, trichomes short-stalked, 2–7-rayed, 0.15–0.4 mm. Cauline leaves: 15–65, concealing stem; blade auricles 1–4 mm, surfaces of distalmost leaves pubescent. Racemes 30–70-flowered, sometimes branched. Fruiting pedicels divaricate-ascending, straight, 10–45 mm, glabrous. Flowers ascending at anthesis; sepals pubescent; petals white or pale lavender, 8–10 × 1.5–2 mm, glabrous; pollen ellipsoid. Fruits divaricate-ascending to horizontal, not appressed to rachis, not secund, usually curved, rarely straight, edges parallel, 6–10 cm × 2.5–3 mm; valves glabrous; ovules 170–220 per ovary; style 0.05–0.5 mm. Seeds biseriate, 1.2–1.6 × 0.9–1.2 mm; wing continuous, 0.1–0.2 mm wide.</description><phenology>feb</phenology><phenology>winter</phenology><phenology>mar</phenology><phenology>spring</phenology><habitat>sea cliff ledges and crevices of volcanic outcrop in chaparral communities</habitat><conservation>of conservation concern;</conservation><elevation>0–100 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Boechera hoffmannii is a distinctive sexual species that appears to be restricted to Santa Cruz Island in Santa Barbara County. It is in the Center for Plant Conservation’s National Collection of Endangered Plants.</discussion></treatment>
