<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Mirbel" date="unknown">salicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subgenus" authority="(Dumortier) Nasarow in V. L. Komarov et al." date="1936">Chamaetia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in V. L. Komarov et al., Fl. URSS</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 31. 1936</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family salicaceae;genus salix;subgenus Chamaetia</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Salix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">Chamaetia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bijdr. Natuurk. Wetensch.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 56. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Salix;section Chamaetia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, 0.005–6 m, clonal by layering or rhizomes, rarely root shoots, or not clonal. Stems erect, trailing, or decumbent; branches flexible at base, usually not glaucous (usually slightly or highly glossy). Buds usually arctica-type (alba-type in S. athabascensis), scale margins connate. Leaves: stipules usually absent or rudimentary, sometimes foliaceous; petiole shallowly or deeply grooved, convex, or flat adaxially, often not glandular, sometimes with 1 or 2 pairs of spherical glands distally; largest medial blade amphistomatous, hemiamphistomatous, or hypostomatous, (usually pinnately veined), narrowly to broadly elliptic, obovate, subcircular, circular, oblanceolate, narrowly oblong, oblong, or broadly obovate, 0.8–5.5 times as long as wide, angle of base and of apex usually less than or greater than 90o, (abaxial surface usually glaucous), surface hairs usually white, rarely ferruginous; juvenile blade (usually yellowish green), hairs usually white, rarely ferruginous. Catkins flowering as leaves emerge, usually from lateral buds (sometimes subterminal); staminate on flowering branchlet or sessile; pistillate on flowering branchlet, usually stout, globose, or subglobose, sometimes slender; floral bract brown, tawny, or bicolor, apex usually entire, sometimes toothed; pistillate bract usually persistent after flowering. Staminate flowers: abaxial nectary present or absent; stamens 2 (1 in S. uva-ursi); filaments distinct or connate, glabrous or hairy; anthers usually purple, or red turning yellow. Pistillate flowers: abaxial nectary absent or present; ovary usually not glaucous, hairy or glabrous, hairs flattened, ribbonlike, or cylindrical, beak abruptly or gradually tapering to styles or slightly bulged below styles; ovules 4–23 per ovary; styles usually connate; stigmas flat, abaxially non-papillate with rounded tip, or stigmas slenderly or broadly cylindrical, or 2 plump lobes.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia.</description>
  <number>2</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 133 (27 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Eight of the 14 sections recognized in this subgenus are found in the flora area.</discussion>
  <discussion>Subgenus Chamaetia is difficult to separate from subg. Vetrix by morphological characters. It has diverged in habit, which is often dwarfed and rhizomatous; in leaf venation, which often is almost palmate with several veins that diverge from near the base of the blade; in buds, which often contain all the vegetative and reproductive structures that will be produced during the growing season; and less-needed structures such as cataphylls, and in some axillary buds, which are highly reduced. It is possible, as A. K. Skvortsov (1999) pointed out, that this reduction has gone so far that relationships are obscured. The primary characters that distinguish subg. Chamaetia are adaptations to arctic-alpine environments that involve simplification through reduction (Skvortsov). Molecular studies have not resolved any species usually placed in subg. Chamaetia from subg. Vetrix (E. Leskinen and C. Alström-Rapaport 1999; T. Azuma et al. 2000); two unpublished DNA studies also have not revealed a “Chametia” clade. A phenetic study (G. W. Argus 1997) revealed a distinct group separated at a level similar to other subgenera. The exception to this was sect. Glaucae, which sometimes clustered with subg. Chamaetia and other times with subg. Vetrix. This inconsistent clustering may be due to high polyploidy in sect. Glaucae, which may have evolved through hybridization with members of subg. Vetrix, perhaps sect. Hastatae. Although it is clear that subg. Chamaetia is more closely related to subg. Vetrix than to subg. Salix, it is highly probable that it is polyphyletic and does not deserve subgeneric rank. Until more information is available, it is taxonomically useful to treat it as a subgenus.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 0.08–6 m, (relatively low to tall) not dwarf.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants forming clones by root shoots; branchlets woolly; largest medial blades</description>
      <determination>27. Salix setchelliana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not clonal or forming clones by layering; branchlets glabrous or velvety; largest medial blades hypostomatous [2d7. Salix sect. Myrtilloides (in part)].</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches red-brown, weakly glaucous; petioles 1–3.5 mm; stipes 0–0.4 mm;</description>
      <determination>46. Salix chlorolepis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches yellow-brown or gray-brown, not glaucous; petioles 2–9 mm; stipes 0.4–3.2 mm; staminate abaxial nectaries present or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules rudimentary; largest medial blades dull, glaucous or sparsely short-silky adaxially; proximal blade margins entire; staminate abaxial nectaries absent; stipes 2.1–3.2 mm; styles 0.1–0.2 mm; pistillate flowering</description>
      <determination>44. Salix pedicellaris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules foliaceous; largest medial blades slightly glossy, not glaucous adaxially; proximal blade margins serrulate; staminate abaxial nectaries present; stipes 0.4–1.2 mm; styles 0.6–0.8 mm; pistillate flowering</description>
      <determination>47. Salix raupii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries hairy (sometimes glabrescent in S. fuscescens ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile blades glabrous; branchlets glabrous; largest medial blades glabrous</description>
      <determination>33. Salix fuscescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile blades hairy; branchlets hairy or glabrescent; largest medial blades hairy abaxially, margins entire or toothed throughout.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile and largest medial blades: hairs usually white, sometimes also</description>
      <determination>45. Salix athabascensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile and largest medial blades: hairs white; branchlets pilose, villous, tomentose, woolly, or long-silky to glabrescent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: veins strongly impressed-reticulate adaxially, margins strongly revolute; branches dull; petioles with 2 dark spherical</description>
      <determination>24. Salix vestita</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: veins not strongly impressed-reticulate adaxially, margins slightly revolute or flat; branches slightly to highly glossy; petioles without glands distally; catkins from lateral buds.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles 1–27 mm, much longer than subtended buds; stipes 0.3–2.8 mm; largest medial blades narrowly elliptic, elliptic, oblanceolate,</description>
      <determination>50. Salix glauca</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles 1.3–5 mm, often shorter than or barely exceeding subtended buds; stipes 0–0.6 mm; largest medial blades narrowly oblong, oblong, narrowly to broadly elliptic, narrowly oblanceolate or oblanceolate, obovate or ovate, apex acuminate, acute, rounded, or convex.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules absent or rudimentary on early leaves; ovules 2–10 per ovary; pistillate catkins stout to globose, densely flowered, 0.3–20 mm; floral bracts usually tawny; largest medial blades with flat</description>
      <determination>48. Salix brachycarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stipules foliaceous on early leaves; ovules 8–20 per ovary;</description>
      <determination>49. Salix niphoclada</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 0.005–0.15 m, dwarf.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Catkins from subterminal buds.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades glaucous abaxially; staminate abaxial nectaries present.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 3–15 cm; stipules often rudimentary; largest medial blades amphistomatous or hemiamphistomatous, oblong to obovate or circular, usually broader, 1–1.5 times as long as wide, margins crenulate or entire; anthers 0.3–0.4 mm; filaments hairy throughout or on proximal 1 / 2 ; ovaries</description>
      <determination>25. Salix reticulata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 1–4 cm; stipules usually absent; largest medial blades hypostomatous, elliptic to broadly elliptic, usually narrower, 1.1–2.8 times as long as wide, margins entire; anthers 0.4–0.6 mm; filaments glabrous or hairy basally;</description>
      <determination>26. Salix nivalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades not glaucous abaxially; staminate abaxial nectaries present or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: margins crenulate, bases subcordate or cordate; styles</description>
      <determination>28. Salix herbacea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: margins entire, bases cuneate, rounded, or convex; styles 0.5–1.2 mm; pistillate abaxial nectaries absent; floral bracts 1.5–2.8 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries villous or pilose; leaves deciduous (in autumn); catkins more</description>
      <determination>30. Salix polaris (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries glabrous or puberulent (hairs in patches, especially on beaks); leaves usually marcescent; catkins 2–15-flowered; petioles 0.4–5.5 mm;</description>
      <determination>31. Salix rotundifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Catkins from lateral buds.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades not glaucous abaxially</description>
      <determination>29. Salix nummularia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades glaucous abaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades highly glossy adaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stamens usually 1; largest medial blades 4–23 mm; petioles 2–6.5 mm; ovules 4–9 per ovary; ovaries not glaucous; arctic-alpine northeastern</description>
      <determination>35. Salix uva-ursi (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stamens 2; largest medial blades 8.5–46 mm; petioles 1.1–20 mm; ovules 10–15 per ovary; ovaries glaucous or not; arctic northwestern North America.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches trailing or erect, not or weakly glaucous; ovaries: beak gradually tapering to styles; styles 0.6–2 mm; largest medial blades amphistomatous or hemiamphistomatous; plants often</description>
      <determination>37. Salix stolonifera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branches trailing, not glaucous; ovaries: beak abruptly tapering to styles; styles 0.2–0.8 mm; largest medial blades hypostomatous;</description>
      <determination>38. Salix ovalifolia (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades slightly glossy adaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and stipules marcescent; juvenile leaves yellow-green; stamens 1; staminate abaxial nectaries absent; largest medial blades: margins</description>
      <determination>35. Salix uva-ursi (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and stipules deciduous; juvenile leaves reddish; stamens 2; staminate abaxial nectaries present or absent; largest medial blades: margins entire.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate catkins 5.5–14 mm; ovaries obnapiform, beak</description>
      <determination>39. Salix jejuna (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate catkins 21–53 mm; ovaries obclavate to pyriform, beak gradually tapering to styles or slightly bulged distally; Alaska,</description>
      <determination>42. Salix sphenophylla (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovaries hairy.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile leaves reddish.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate catkins 21–53 mm, flowering branchlets 8–20 mm; ovaries: beak gradually tapering to or slightly bulged below styles; largest medial blades</description>
      <determination>42. Salix sphenophylla (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate catkins 4.8–15 mm, flowering branchlets 1–7 mm; ovaries: beak abruptly tapering to styles; largest medial blades 8–25 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 5.2–9.6 mm; largest medial blades hypostomatous, highly glossy adaxially; pistillate abaxial nectaries sometimes present; petioles 1.1–7(–16)</description>
      <determination>38. Salix ovalifolia (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Capsules 3–5 mm; largest medial blades amphistomatous or hemiamphisto-matous, slightly glossy adaxially; pistillate abaxial nectaries absent; petioles</description>
      <determination>39. Salix jejuna (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Juvenile leaves yellowish green.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades not glaucous abaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades deciduous, slightly glossy adaxially; petioles glabrous</description>
      <determination>30. Salix polaris (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades marcescent (becoming skeletonized), highly glossy adaxially; petioles hairy adaxially; floral bracts 1–1.3 mm; pistillate nectaries</description>
      <determination>36. Salix phlebophylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades glaucous abaxially.</description>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovary hairs ribbonlike, usually crinkled (refractive); staminate abaxial nectaries absent; largest medial blades: margins closely and prominently serrulate or crenulate (sometimes entire in S. arctophila ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: margins closely and prominently serrulate or spinulose-serrulate (teeth 7–14 per cm); stipes 0.2–0.4 mm; pistillate</description>
      <determination>32. Salix chamissonis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades: margins inconspicuously crenulate or entire (teeth 1–8 per cm); stipes 0.8–1.4 mm; pistillate nectaries shorter than</description>
      <determination>34. Salix arctophila</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ovary hairs flattened, not crinkled (white, not refractive); staminate abaxial nectaries present or absent; largest medial blades: margins entire.</description>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades 9–26 × 3.8–7.5 mm, petioles 1.5–5 mm; plants forming rhizomatous mats; pistillate catkins 10–23 mm,</description>
      <determination>43. Salix cascadensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Largest medial blades 10–85 × 5.5–60 mm, petioles 2–35 mm; plants not forming rhizomatous mats (often trailing and rooting); pistillate catkins 20–145 mm, 18–80-flowered; stipes 0.2–1.6 mm; staminate abaxial nectaries present or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branchlets usually villous or pilose, sometimes glabrous; floral bracts brown or black; stipules usually foliaceous; stipes 0.2–1.6 mm; styles</description>
      <determination>40. Salix arctica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Branchlets usually glabrous, sometimes pilose to glabrescent; floral bracts tawny or light brown; stipules absent or rudimentary;</description>
      <determination>41. Salix petrophila</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
