<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Al-Shehbaz" date="unknown">boechereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="N. H. Holmgren" date="2004">NEVADA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Brittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>56: 240, fig. 1. 2004</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe boechereae;genus NEVADA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For the state of Nevada, where endemic]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; (cespitose, caudex simple or few-branched); not scapose; pubescent or glabrous, trichomes simple. Stems erect, unbranched or branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate, petiolate, blade margins entire; cauline sessile, blade (base not auriculate), margins entire. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels ascending to suberect, slender. Flowers: sepals (erect), oblong-ovate, (glabrous); petals white, obovate to spatulate, (longer than sepals, claw obscurely differentiated from blade, apex obtuse); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments not or slightly dilated basally; anthers ovate, (apex obtuse); nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits sessile or subsessile, linear to linear-lanceolate, torulose, terete; valves each with obscure midvein extending to middle, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 6–12 per ovary; stigma capitate. Seeds uniseriate, plump, not winged, narrowly oblong; seed coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nevada.</description>
  <number>13.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
