<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Al-Shehbaz" date="unknown">boechereae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall in J. Torrey and A. Gray" date="1838">PHOENICAULIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Torrey and A. Gray, Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 89. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe boechereae;genus PHOENICAULIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek phoenix , date palm, and kaulos , stem, alluding to petiolar remains]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; (caudex well-developed, woody, covered with persistent petiolar remains); not scapose; glabrous or pubescent, trichomes finely dendritic. Stems erect, usually unbranched, rarely branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal (persistent), rosulate, long-petiolate, blade margins entire; cauline sessile, blade (base auriculate), margins entire. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate, slender. Flowers: sepals (erect), oblong, (lateral pair saccate basally); petals purple or lavender, spatulate to oblanceolate, (longer than sepals, apex obtuse); stamens tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers oblong, (apex obtuse); nectar glands confluent, lateral annular. Fruits sessile or stipitate, lanceolate to linear, not torulose, latiseptate; valves each with prominent midvein (lateral veins often conspicuous), glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete, (opaque); ovules (6–)8–16(–18) per ovary; stigma capitate. Seeds uniseriate, slightly flattened, not winged, oblong to broadly ovate; seed coat (smooth), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w United States.</description>
  <number>14.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
