<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Brassica</genus_name><species_name>elongata</species_name><species_authority>Ehrhart</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Beitr. Naturk.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>7: 159. 1792</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Biennials or perennials; (short-lived, often woody basally); glabrous or hirsute. Stems (several from base), branched basally, 5–10 dm, (usually glabrous, rarely sparsely hirsute). Basal leaves: blade (usually bright green), obovate to elliptic (not lobed), (3–)5–20(–30) cm × (5–)10–35(–60) mm, (base cuneate), margins subentire to dentate, (surfaces glabrous or often with trichomes minute, tubercled-based, curved, coarse). Cauline leaves (distal) shortly petiolate; blade (oblong or lanceolate, to 10 cm) base not auriculate or amplexicaul. Racemes paniculately branched. Fruiting pedicels spreading to divaricately ascending, (6–)8–18 mm. Flowers: sepals 3–4(–4.5) × 1–1.5 mm; petals bright yellow to orange-yellow, obovate, (5–)7–10 × 2.5–3.5(–4) mm, claw 2.5–4 mm, apex rounded; filaments 3.5–4.5 mm; anthers 1–1.5 mm; gynophore 1.5–4(–5) mm in fruit. Fruits (stipitate), spreading to ascending (not appressed to rachis), torulose, terete, (1.5–)2–4(–4.8) cm × (1–)1.5–2 mm; valvular segment with (2–)5–11(–13) seeds per locule, (1.2–)1.6–4(–4.5) cm, terminal segment seedless, 0.5–2.5(–3) mm. Seeds grey to brown, 1–1.6 mm diam.; seed coat reticulate, mucilaginous when wetted. 2n = 22.</description><phenology>jun</phenology><phenology>summer</phenology><phenology>jul</phenology><habitat>roadsides</habitat><habitat>disturbed ground</habitat><habitat>adjacent open juniper and sagebrush desert areas</habitat><elevation>0–2700 m;</elevation><introduced>introduced;</introduced><us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Europe</global_distribution><global_distribution>Asia</global_distribution><global_distribution>n Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution>introduced also in Australia.</global_distribution><discussion>The earliest North American collections of Brassica elongata were from ballast at Linnton, near Portland, Oregon, in 1911, and from a garden in Bingen, Klickitat County, Washington, in 1915. The species does not appear to have persisted at, or spread from, either location (R. C. Rollins and I. A. Al-Shehbaz 1986). It was next collected in 1968 from east-central Nevada, where it is now well-established in Eureka and White Pine counties, and just into Lander County, and spreading rapidly along both roadsides and adjacent high desert (Rollins 1980; Rollins and Al-Shehbaz; Rollins 1993). The semiarid region of North America appears to be a well-suited habitat for B. elongata and the species appears destined to become a permanent part of the flora of the Intermountain Basin (Rollins and Al-Shehbaz).</discussion><discussion>According to R. C. Rollins (1980), the Nevada plants belong to subsp. integrifolia (Boissier) Breistroffer, but the species is so variable that dividing it into infraspecific taxa is not practical.</discussion></treatment>
