<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>19.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>CARRICHTERA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>de Candolle</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Mus. Hist. Nat.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 244, 250. 1821</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[For Bartholomaeus Carrichter, sixteenth-century herbalist, alchemist, and physician
        to Emperor Maximilian II]</etymology>
  <conserved_name>name conserved</conserved_name>
  <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
  <description>Annuals; not scapose; hirsute [glabrous], (trichomes often retrorse). Stems usually
        erect or ascending, rarely decumbent, usually branched, rarely simple. Leaves basal and
        cauline; petiolate or subsessile; basal not rosulate, petiolate, blade 1- or 2-pinnatisect,
        margins entire; cauline subsessile or shortly petiolate, blade 1- or 2-pinnatisect, (base
        not auriculate), margins entire. Racemes (lax), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting
        pedicels strongly recurved, often secund, not thickened. Flowers: sepals erect,
        oblong-linear, lateral pair slightly saccate basally; petals cream or pale yellow (with dark
        purple or brown veins, longer than sepals), spatulate to obovate, claw strongly
        differentiated from blade; stamens tetradynamous, (erect); filaments not dilated basally;
        anthers ovate to oblong, (apiculate); nectar glands: lateral intrastaminal, globose to
        semi-annular, median glands present (distinct). Fruits silicles, dehiscent, sessile,
        segments 2, ovoid to ellipsoid, terete; (proximal segment not torulose, 4–6-seeded; terminal
        segment indehiscent, flattened, cochleariform to short-lingulate, seedless); valves each
        with prominent midvein and distinct marginal veins, glabrous except setose or hirsute on
        veins; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 4–6 per ovary; (style obscure); stigma
        capitate, 2-lobed. Seeds biseriate, plump, not winged, subglobose; seed coat (smooth),
        mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons conduplicate. x = 8.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa>
  <introduced>introduced</introduced>
  <global_distribution>California</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>s Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>sw Asia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Africa</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>introduced also in Australia.</global_distribution>
</treatment>
