<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Suzanne I. Warwick</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">brassiceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">ERUCA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict. Abr. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4, vol. 1. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe brassiceae;genus ERUCA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin uro , burn, alluding to the burning taste of seeds]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals; not scapose; glabrous, hirsute, or hispid, (trichomes often retrorse). Stems erect, branched [unbranched]. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate or not, petiolate, blade margins usually lyrate-pinnatifid or pinnatipartite, rarely bipinnatisect or undivided; cauline shortly petiolate or sessile, blade (base not auriculate), margins entire, dentate, or pinnatifid. Racemes (corymbose), greatly elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels erect to ascending, stout. Flowers: sepals (sometimes persistent), erect, oblong [linear], (connivent), lateral pair saccate basally; petals cream or yellow (with dark brown or purple veins), broadly obovate, claw differentiated from blade (± equal to sepals, apex obtuse or emarginate); stamens strongly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers oblong or linear, (base sagittate, apex obtuse); nectar glands (4), distinct, median pair present. Fruits siliques, dehiscent, sessile, segments 2, linear or oblong [elliptic], not torulose, terete or slightly 4-angled; (terminal segment indehiscent, flattened and ensiform, seedless); valves each with prominent midvein, (coriaceous), glabrous, hirsute, or hispid; replum rounded; septum complete, (membranous); ovules 10–50 per ovary; (style obsolete); stigma conical, 2-lobed (lobes connivent, decurrent). Seeds biseriate, plump, not winged, [sub]globose or ovoid; seed coat (minutely reticulate), mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons conduplicate. x = 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced also in Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Atlantic Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>23.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
