<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Suzanne I. Warwick</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">brassiceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="C. Presl" date="1826">ERUCASTRUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Sicul.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>92. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe brassiceae;genus ERUCASTRUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Eruca and Latin - astrum , resembling]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals or biennials [perennials, subshrubs]; not scapose; pubescent. Stems erect or ascending, unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate or not, petiolate, blade margins dentate to lyrate-pinnatifid, [pinnatipartite]; cauline shortly petiolate or sessile, blade (base not auriculate), similar to basal. Racemes (corymbose, bracteate throughout or basally), greatly elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels ascending to divaricate [spreading], slender. Flowers: sepals erect, oblong [linear], lateral pair not saccate basally; petals yellow or white, obovate to oblanceolate or oblong, gradually attenuated to short claw, (apex rounded); stamens tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers oblong or linear, (base sagittate, apex obtuse); nectar glands distinct, median glands present. Fruits siliques, dehiscent, subsessile, segments 2, linear, often torulose, subterete or 4-angled; (terminal segment stylelike, seedless); valves each with prominent midvein, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 10–60 per ovary; stigmas capitate, entire or 2-lobed. Seeds uniseriate, plump, not winged, elliptic [oblong, ovoid]; seed coat (usually reticulate), slightly mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons conduplicate. x = 7, 8, 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 19 (1 in the flora): introduced; Europe, Asia, Africa.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 19 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; Europe, Asia, Africa.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>24.</number>
  <discussion>Species 19 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Luken, J. O., J. W. Thieret, and J. T. Kartesz. 1993. Erucastrum gallicum (Brassicaceae): Invasion and spread in North America. Sida 15: 569–582.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
