<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Horaninov" date="1847">calepineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Adanson" date="1763">Calepina</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fam. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 423. 1763</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe calepineae;genus Calepina</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chalepaino , term used by Theophrastus probably in connection with weedy plants; some authors believe it derived from Arabic Haleb (erroneously rendered Chaleb by some), name for the Syrian city Aleppo, but highly unlikely since Adanson based it on Bauhin’s Myagrum monospermum minus , collected in southern France]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants not scapose. Stems erect to ascending, unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal usually rosulate, petiolate, blade margins dentate to lyrate-pinnatifid; cauline blade (base sagittate or amplexicaul), margins dentate or subentire. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate or ascending, slender. Flowers: sepals ascending to spreading; petals oblanceolate, (apex obtuse or slightly emarginate); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments dilated basally; anthers ovate; nectar glands: lateral intrastaminal, median glands present (distinct). Fruits subsessile or shortly stipitate (gynophore relatively slender, fruit readily detached at maturity), nutlike, ovoid or ellipsoid, terete; valves reticulate and usually longitudinally 4-ribbed; replum rounded; septum absent; stigma capitate. Seeds (pendulous) plump, not winged, ovoid; seed coat (smooth), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons involute in distal 1/2. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Europe, e, c, sw Asia, n Africa.</description>
  <number>31.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Calepina cochlearioides (Murray) Dumortier is distributed in Asia (China, Kazakhstan, Mongolia, and adjacent Russia).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Blake, S. F. 1957. A new cruciferous weed, Calepina irregularis, in Virginia. Rhodora 59: 278–280.</reference>
    <reference>Hardin, J. W. 1958. Calepina irregularis in North Carolina. Castanea 23: 111.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
