<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>32.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Salix</genus_name>
    <species_name>chamissonis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Andersson</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>16(2): 290. 1868</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Chamisso willow</common_name>
  <description>Plants 0.03–0.1 m, (dwarf), forming clones by layering. Stems long-trailing; branches red-brown, glabrous; branchlets yellow-green, glabrous. Leaves: stipules foliaceous; petiole 5–13 mm, (sometimes with 1–2 pairs of spherical glands distally); largest medial blade hypo-stomatous, broadly elliptic, subcircular, or obovate, 30–50 × 17–30 mm, (1.1–)1.6–1.9(–2.1) times as long as wide, base cuneate, margins flat, closely and prominently serrulate or spinulose-serrulate, (teeth 7–14 per cm), apex acuminate, convex, acute, or rounded, abaxial surface glaucous, glabrous, adaxial slightly glossy, glabrous; proximal blade margins entire, closely gland-dotted, or serrulate; juvenile blade glabrous or sparsely long-silky abaxially. Catkins: staminate 30–64 × 12–22 mm, flowering branchlet 4–28 mm; pistillate densely or moderately densely flowered, stout, 32–73(–105 in fruit) × 10–17 mm, flowering branchlet 4–28 mm; floral bract brown or black, 1.2–2.8 mm, apex convex or rounded, entire, abaxially moderately densely hairy, hairs straight. Staminate flowers: abaxial nectary absent, adaxial nectary square, 0.5–0.9 mm; filaments distinct, glabrous; anthers ellipsoid or shortly cylindrical, 0.5–0.6 mm. Pistillate flowers: abaxial nectary absent, adaxial nectary square or oblong, 0.3–1 mm, equal to or longer than stipe; stipe 0.2–0.4 mm; ovary obclavate, pilose or villous, hairs ribbonlike, (sometimes in patches or streaks, refractive), beak gradually tapering to styles; ovules 12–18 per ovary; styles 0.8–1.2 mm; stigmas flat, abaxially non-papillate with rounded or pointed tip, or slenderly cylindrical, 0.4–0.7 mm. Capsules 5–7 mm. 2n = 114.</description>
  <habitat>arctic-alpine</habitat>
  <habitat>dryas heath tundra</habitat>
  <habitat>dwarf birch-lichen tundra</habitat>
  <habitat>sandy lakeshores</habitat>
  <habitat>snowbeds</habitat>
  <habitat>rock stripes or gravel</habitat>
  <habitat>wet seepage areas</habitat>
  <habitat>sedge meadows</habitat>
  <habitat>willow-dwarf birch-sphagnum bogs</habitat>
  <habitat>limestone and shale substrates</habitat>
  <elevation>0–1500 m;</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia (Chukotka).</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia (Commander Islands).</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia (Russian Far East).</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia (disjunct in Sakhalin).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Salix chamissonis is disjunct on Attu Island in Alaska.</discussion>
</treatment>
