<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">camelineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Medikus" date="unknown">CAPSELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pfl.-Gatt.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>85. 1792</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe camelineae;genus CAPSELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin capsa , box or case, alluding to fruit resembling medieval wallet or
    purse]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Boehmer" date="unknown">Bursa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Bursa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="P. Gaertner, B. Meyer &amp; Scherbius" date="unknown">Rodschiedia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication />
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Rodschiedia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Borbás" date="unknown">Solmsiella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Solmsiella;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals or biennials; not scapose; mostly pubescent, trichomes sessile and stellate,
    sometimes mixed with simple or forked ones. Stems erect or ascending, unbranched or branched.
    Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate, petiolate, blade margins
    pinnately lobed, lyrate, runcinate, or, rarely, entire, dentate, or repand [sinuate]; cauline
    blade (base sagittate, amplexicaul, or auriculate), margins entire, dentate, or sinuate. Racemes
    (corymbose, several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate,
    slender. Flowers: sepals erect or ascending, [ovate-]oblong, (glabrous or pubescent); petals
    [sometimes absent] usually white or pink [reddish], obovate [spatulate], (much longer or shorter
    than sepals), claw differentiated from blade, (apex obtuse); stamens tetradynamous; filaments
    not dilated basally; anthers ovate [oblong], (apex obtuse); nectar glands (4), lateral, 1 on
    each side of lateral stamen. Fruits silicles, dehiscent, sessile, obdeltoid to
    obdeltoid-obcordiform, strongly flattened, strongly keeled, angustiseptate; valves (papery),
    each prominently veined, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules (12–)20–40 per ovary;
    (style included or exserted from apical notch); stigma capitate. Seeds uniseriate, plump, not
    winged, oblong; seed coat (reticulate), mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x =
    8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Europe, Asia, n Africa; introduced also in Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Atlantic Islands, Pacific Islands, Australia.</description>
  <number>34.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Shepherd’s-purse</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 4 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The number of species to be recognized in Capsella is controversial, and some authors
    (e.g., S. Svensson 1983; R. C. Rollins 1993; O. Appel and I. A. Al-Shehbaz 2003) treated the
    genus as monotypic, whereas others (e.g., H. Hurka and B. Neuffer 1997; P. Nutt et al. 2003)
    recognized three or four species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hurka, H. and B. Neuffer. 1997. Evolutionary processes in the
      genus Capsella (Brassicaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 206: 295–316.</reference>
    <reference>Neuffer, B. and H. Hurka. 1999. Colonizing history and introduction dynamics of
      Capsella bursa-pastoris in North America: Isozymes and quantitative traits. Molec. Ecol. 8:
      1667–1681.</reference>
    <reference>Nutt, P. et al. 2006. Capsella as a model system to study the evolutionary relevance
      of floral homeotic mutants. Pl. Sys. Evol. 259: 217–235.</reference>
    <reference>Slotte, T. et al. 2006. Intrageneric phylogeny of Capsella (Brassicaceae) and
      the origin of the tetraploid C. bursa-pastoris based on chloroplast and nuclear DNA sequences.
      Amer. J. Bot. 93: 1714–1724.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
