<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">camelineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Al-Shehbaz &amp; O’Kane" date="2003">TRANSBERINGIA</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe camelineae;genus TRANSBERINGIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin trans- , across, and Bering Sea, alluding to distribution]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. A. Price, Al-Shehbaz &amp; O’Kane" date="unknown">Beringia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 333. 2001,</place_in_publication>
      <other_info_on_pub>not Perestenko 1975</other_info_on_pub>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 396. 2003</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Beringia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; not scapose; glabrous or pubescent, trichomes simple, forked, stalked,
        or dendritic. Stems erect or ascending, unbranched or branched basally and distally. Leaves
        basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate, petiolate, blade margins often
        entire, sometimes dentate, rarely sinuate; cauline blade (base not auriculate, sagittate),
        margins usually entire, rarely dentate. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered), elongated in
        fruit. Fruiting pedicels ascending to subdivaricate, slender (terete). Flowers: sepals
        erect, oblong, (pubescent); petals white, oblanceolate, (longer than sepals), claw obscurely
        differentiated from blade, (apex obtuse); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments not
        dilated basally; anthers oblong, (apiculate); nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of
        stamens. Fruits siliques, dehiscent, sessile or subsessile, linear, smooth, terete; valves
        each with prominent midvein and marginal veins, secondary veins anastomosing and distinct or
        obscure, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 70–150 per ovary; (style obsolete
        or distinct); stigma capitate. Seeds biseriate, plump, not winged, narrowly oblong; seed
        coat (minutely reticulate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x =
        8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">n</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">e Asia (Russian Far East).</description>
  <number>36.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>For discussion of the generic limits of Transberingia, see the original description
        and also under 60. Halimolobos.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
