<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">Cardamineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="P. Gaertner, B. Meyer &amp; Scherbius" date="unknown">ARMORACIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Oekon. Fl. Wetterau</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 426. 1800</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Cardamineae;genus ARMORACIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Ancient Greek name for horseradish, or perhaps Celtic ar , near, mor , sea, and rich , against, alluding to habitat]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; (aquatic or of mesic habitats, with rootstocks); not scapose; glabrous. Stems erect, branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate and sessile; basal rosulate, long-petiolate, blade margins crenate or pinnatifid [entire]; cauline petiolate or sessile distally, blade margins crenate, serrate, pinnatifid, pinnatisect [laciniate]. Racemes ([often corymbose-paniculate], several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels ascending, divaricate, or slightly reflexed, slender. Flowers: sepals spreading or ascending, ovate or oblong, lateral pair not saccate basally, (glabrous); petals white, obovate, or oblanceolate [spatulate, oblong], claw somewhat differentiated from blade (relatively short, apex obtuse); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments slightly dilated basally; anthers ovate [oblong or linear], (apex obtuse); nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens, median glands present. Fruits: silicles, sessile, oblong, ovate, elliptic, or orbicular, angustiseptate; valves each not veined; replum rounded; septum perforated or reduced to a rim; ovules 8–12[–20] per ovary; style obsolete or distinct; stigma capitate, (sometimes 2-lobed). Seeds biseriate, plump, not winged, ovate [oblong]; seed coat (punctate) not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">s Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia (Russian Far East).</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia (Siberia).</description>
  <number>38.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Horseradish</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fosberg, F. R. 1965. Nomenclature of the horseradish (Cruciferae). Baileya 13: 1–4.</reference>
    <reference>Lawrence, G. H. M. 1971. The horseradish Armoracia rusticana. Herbarist 37: 17–19.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
