<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">Cardamineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Torrey &amp; A. Gray) Steudel" date="unknown">IODANTHUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Nomencl. Bot. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 1: 812. 1840</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Cardamineae;genus IODANTHUS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek iodes , violet-colored, and anthos , flower]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Cheiranthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="unranked" date="unknown" authority="Torrey &amp; A. Gray">Iodanthus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 72. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cheiranthus;unranked Iodanthus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials; not scapose; glabrous or sparsely pubescent. Stems erect, branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal (withered by flowering), not rosulate, petiolate, blade margins lobed or not; cauline petiolate (petioles winged) or sessile, blade (base auriculate), margins dentate, entire, or lyrately lobed. Racemes (lax), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate to ascending, slender or stout. Flowers: sepals erect to ascending, oblong, lateral pair not or slightly saccate basally; petals purple, pink, or white, spatulate, (longer than sepals), claw differentiated from blade; stamens tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers linear to narrowly oblong, (apiculate); nectar glands: lateral annular, median glands confluent with lateral. Fruits siliques, sessile or shortly stipitate, linear, smooth, terete; valves each with distinct midvein, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 22–36 per ovary; style distinct; stigma capitate. Seeds uniseriate, plump, not winged, oblong; seed coat (minutely reticulate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">e United States.</description>
  <number>41.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>R. C. Rollins (1993) recognized four species in Iodanthus, of which three are endemic to Mexico. As summarized by R. A. Price and I. A. Al-Shehbaz (2001), molecular data clearly support treatment of the genus as monospecific and closely allied to Cardamine, as well as recognition of the three Mexican species as members of Chaunanthus, a genus unrelated to Iodanthus and members of the Thelypodieae.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1942. A systematic study of Iodanthus. Contr. Dudley Herb. 3: 209–215.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
