<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Dumortier" date="1827">cardamineae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">SUBULARIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 642. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 290. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe cardamineae;genus SUBULARIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin subula , awl, alluding to leaf shape of type species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals; (littoral or aquatic); scapose; glabrous throughout. Stems erect, unbranched. Leaves (persistent); basal; rosulate; sessile; blade margins entire; cauline absent. Racemes (lax or somewhat congested), slightly or considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels usually ascending, rarely divaricate, divaricate-ascending, or suberect, slender or stout. Flowers: sepals (sometimes persistent), ascending to erect, ovate-oblong, lateral pair not saccate basally; petals (rarely absent), white, narrowly oblanceolate to lingulate, (slightly exceeding sepals), claw undifferentiated from blade, apex obtuse; stamens subequal; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate; nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits silicles, shortly stipitate, obovoid to ellipsoid [oblong], smooth, terete or slightly inflated; valves each not veined; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 4–18 per ovary; style absent; stigma capitate. Seeds biseriate, slightly compressed, not winged, oblong; seed coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x = 14, 15.</description>
  <description type="distribution">n North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe (n)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe (Russia)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 2 (1 in the flora): n North America, Europe (n, Russia), Africa.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>n North America, Europe (n, Russia), Africa.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>47.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Awlwort</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The second species of the genus, Subularia monticola A. Brown ex Schweinfurth, is endemic to high elevations of tropical Africa. For a discussion and distinguishing characteristics of all taxa of the genus, as well as a map of the North American distribution, see G. A. Mulligan and J. A. Calder (1964).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Mulligan, G. A. and J. A. Calder. 1964. The genus Subularia (Cruciferae). Rhodora 66: 127–135.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
