<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Ledebour_ C. A. Meyer &amp; Bunge in C. F. von Ledebour" date="unknown">chorisporeae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown ex de Candolle" date="unknown">CHORISPORA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Mus. Hist. Nat.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 237. 1821</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe chorisporeae;genus CHORISPORA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek choris , asunder or separate, and spora , seed, alluding to fruit breaking at constrictions into one-seeded segments]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals [perennials]; not scapose; usually glandular, rarely eglandular, glabrous or pubescent. Stems erect or decumbent, branched basally [and distally] (leafy or not). Leaves basal and sometimes cauline; petiolate; basal not rosulate [rosulate], blade margins sinuate-dentate, [pinnatifid, or pinnatisect, rarely entire]; cauline absent or shortly petiolate, blade (base not auriculate) margins often entire. Racemes (corymbose [or, rarely, flowers solitary on long pedicels from axils of rosettes], several-flowered), slightly or considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate, stout [slender] (nearly as thick as fruit). Flowers: sepals linear [ovate, or oblong]; petals usually purple or lavender [yellow], rarely white, (much longer than sepals), oblanceolate [broadly obovate or obcordate], claw strongly differentiated from blade, (apex obtuse [emarginate]); stamens strongly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers narrowly oblong [linear], (apex obtuse); nectar glands (2 or 4), lateral, intrastaminal or each side of lateral stamen. Fruits sessile, segments 2, linear, slightly [strongly] torulose or submoniliform, terete; (segments breaking into 1-seeded units, lomentaceous with thick, corky, or woody wall); valves usually glandular, rarely eglandular; replum flattened, (persistent after segments fall off); septum becoming corky, splitting at middle; ovules 5–30 per ovary; (style beaklike); stigma conical, 2-lobed (lobes decurrent, strongly connivent). Seeds flattened, not winged, oblong; seed coat not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Europe, Asia, n Africa.</description>
  <number>48.</number>
  <discussion>Species 11 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
