<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz,Marcus Koch</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Buchenau" date="unknown">cochlearieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">COCHLEARIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 647. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe cochlearieae;genus COCHLEARIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin cochlear , spoon, alluding to leaf shape of some species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Á. Löve &amp; D. Löve" date="unknown">Cochleariopsis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 292. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cochleariopsis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(O. E. Schulz) Pobedemova" date="unknown">Glaucocochlearia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Glaucocochlearia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or, rarely, perennials; not scapose. Stems erect or decumbent,
    unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate or not,
    petiolate, blade margins usually entire, repand, or dentate, rarely sinuate-dentate; cauline
    petiolate or sessile, blade (base auriculate or not), margins entire, repand, or dentate.
    Racemes (corymbose), slightly to greatly elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels erect,
    divaricate, or ascending, slender. Flowers: sepals ovate or oblong; petals oblanceolate or
    spatulate, [oblong, lingulate, elliptic], claw not differentiated from blade; stamens subequal
    or slightly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate; nectar glands lateral,
    1 on each side lateral stamens. Fruits sessile, ovoid, ellipsoid, obovoid, orbicular,
    ovoid-orbicular, or elliptic to oblong, [sub]terete or angustiseptate; valves each with distinct
    midvein (sometimes inflated); replum rounded; septum complete, fenestrate, or absent; ovules
    [5–]8–14[–32] per ovary; stigma capitate. Seeds plump, not winged, ovoid-oblong or ovoid to
    subglobose [ellipsoid]; seed coat (smooth or papillose), not mucilaginous when wetted;
    cotyledons accumbent, rarely incumbent. x = 6, 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Africa.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 21 (3 in the flora): North America, Europe, Asia, nw Africa.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 21 (3 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Europe, Asia, nw Africa.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>50.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Scurvy-grass</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 21 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Molecular data (M. Koch et al. 1999) provide some evidence that Ionopsidium
    Reichenbach could be integrated into Cochlearia as a section, consisting of at least five
    species in Eurasia.</discussion>
  <discussion>Molecular studies (M. Koch 2002; Koch et al. 1996, 1998, 1999, 2003) as well as
    cytological ones (D. M. Pegtel 1999, and references therein) have demonstrated that in
    Cochlearia hybridization and polyploidization have created in Europe extensive complexes based
    on x = 6; the circumpolar and subarctic taxa form different complexes based on x = 7. It appears
    that all North American taxa belong to the latter group. The North American taxa have not been
    studied as comprehensively as the European ones.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Koch, M. et al. 1998. Isozymes, speciation and evolution in the
      polyploid complex Cochlearia L. (Brassicaceae). Bot. Acta 111: 411–425.</reference>
    <reference>Koch, M. et al. 1999. Molecular phylogenetics of Cochlearia (Brassicaceae) and allied
      genera based on nuclear ribosomal ITS DNA sequence analysis contradict traditional concepts of
      their evolutionary relationship. Pl. Syst. Evol. 216: 207–230.</reference>
    <reference>Koch, M., H. Hurka, and K. Mummenhoff. 1996. Chloroplast DNA restriction site
      variation and RAPD-analyses in Cochlearia (Brassicaceae): Biosystematics and speciation.
      Nordic J. Bot. 16: 585–603.</reference>
    <reference>Pobedimova, E. 1969. Revisio generis Cochlearia L., 1. Novosti Sist. Vyssh. Rast. 6:
      67–106.</reference>
    <reference>Pobedimova, E. 1970. Revisio generis Cochlearia L., 2. Novosti Sist. Vyssh.
      Rast. 7: 167–195.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals; fruits oblong or elliptic, 8–12 mm; stems simple from base; cauline leaves
        sessile,</description>
      <determination>2. Cochlearia sessilifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Biennials or perennials; fruits ovoid, obovoid, orbicular, or ellipsoid, rarely to
        9 mm; stems usually few to several from base; (proximal) cauline leaves petiolate, blade
        margins dentate, repand, or entire.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits obovoid, ovoid, or ellipsoid, terete or slightly angustiseptate, valves
        usually not or obscurely reticulate, rarely distinctly so; proximal and median cauline
        blades:</description>
      <determination>1. Cochlearia groenlandica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits orbicular or ovoid-orbicular, distinctly angustiseptate, valves
        prominently</description>
      <determination>3. Cochlearia tridactylites</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
