<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Suzanne I. Warwick</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="D. A. German &amp; Al-Shehbaz" date="unknown">conringieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Heister ex Fabricius" date="1759">CONRINGIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>160. 1759</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe conringieae;genus CONRINGIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Hermann Conring, 1606–1681, German professor of medicine and philosophy at Helmstedt]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants not scapose; (usually glaucous). Stems erect, unbranched or branched proximally. Leaves basal and cauline; subsessile or sessile; basal not rosulate, subsessile, blade margins usually entire; cauline blade (base cordate-amplexicaul or, rarely, auriculate), margins usually entire, rarely crenulate. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered). Fruiting pedicels ascending, stout (almost as thick as fruit, or, rarely, much narrower). Flowers: sepals oblong; petals usually narrowly obovate, rarely oblanceolate, claw differentiated from blade [undifferentiated], (apex obtuse); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated, slender; anthers oblong (base slightly sagittate); nectar glands lateral, median glands often absent. Fruits sessile, linear, torulose, 4-angled or terete; valves each with prominent midvein; replum rounded; septum complete; stigmas capitate-flattened, entire. Seeds not winged, oblong [ellipsoid]; seed coat (papillose), copiously mucilaginous (granular) when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x = 7 [9].</description>
  <description type="distribution">c Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">e Mediterranean region</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia (Afghanistan)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia (Pakistan)</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced also in Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 6 (1 in the flora): introduced; c Europe, e Mediterranean region, Asia (Afghanistan, Pakistan); introduced also in Mexico, nw Africa, Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 6 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; c Europe, e Mediterranean region, Asia (Afghanistan, Pakistan); introduced also in Mexico, nw Africa, Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>51.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hare’s-ear mustard</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 6 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
