<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Barbara E. Goodson,Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Al-Shehbaz" date="unknown">descurainieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Webb &amp; Berthelot" date="unknown">DESCURAINIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hist. Nat. Îsles Canaries</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(2,3): 72. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe descurainieae;genus DESCURAINIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For François Descurain, 1658–1740, French botanist and apothecary]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Reichenbach" date="unknown">Huguenenia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Huguenenia;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name>name rejected</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Adanson" date="unknown">Sophia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sophia;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name>name rejected</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or perennials [shrubs, subshrubs]; not scapose; glabrous,
    glabrate, or sparsely to densely pubescent, trichomes usually short-stalked, dendritic, rarely
    also simple, sometimes mixed with unicellular, glandular, clavate papillae. Stems erect or
    prostrate, unbranched or branched basally and/or distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate
    or sessile; basal (often withered by flowering), rosulate, petiolate, blade (1–3-pinnate),
    margins entire or toothed; cauline petiolate or sessile, blade often similar to basal. Racemes
    (proximally sometimes bracteate), elongated or not in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate or
    erect, slender. Flowers: sepals erect to spreading, ovate to oblong or linear; petals usually
    obovate or oblanceolate, rarely oblong, (shorter to longer than sepals), claw obsolete or
    distinct, (apex obtuse); stamens tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers oblong to
    ovate, (apex obtuse); nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens, median glands
    present. Fruits siliques or silicles, sessile, usually linear, oblong, clavate, or fusiform,
    rarely ellipsoid or obovoid, smooth or torulose, terete; valves each often with distinct
    midvein, usually glabrous, rarely pubescent; replum rounded; septum complete or perforated
    (membranous, not veined or with 1–3 longitudinal veins); ovules 5–100 per ovary; style usually
    absent, rarely distinct; stigma capitate. Seeds uniseriate or biseriate, plump, wingless, oblong
    or ellipsoid; seed coat (minutely reticulate), usually mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons
    incumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, South America, Eurasia, n Africa, Atlantic Islands (Canary Islands).</description>
  <number>52.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Tansy mustard</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 45–47 (14 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Descurainia species are distributed in three major centers: North America (17
    species), South America (ca. 20 species), and the Canary Islands (7 species). Excluding D.
    sophioides, which extends into Siberia from arctic North America, three additional species are
    found outside those regions: D. kochii (Petri) O. E. Schulz (Caucasus, Turkey), D. sophia (a
    cosmopolitan weed of Eurasian origin), and D. tanacetifolia (Linnaeus) Prantl (Alps and the
    Iberian Peninsula).</discussion>
  <discussion>Descurainia is taxonomically difficult throughout most of the New World, especially
    the United States. Extensive morphological variation exists within numerous species and many
    wide-ranging and widely-overlapping taxa appear to intergrade endlessly. Inter- and
    infraspecific hybridization is probably extensive given the lack of reproductive barriers
    between the recently evolved New World species, the ready dispersibility of the mucilaginous
    seeds, and the weedy tendencies of the majority of taxa that readily occupy disturbed habitats.
    The frequent occurrence of hybrid populations, suggested by the intergrading morphology and
    widespread polyploidy, is supported by recent molecular evidence (B. E. Goodson 2007). A second
    factor contributing to the complexity of North American Descurainia is that the number of
    taxonomically reliable characters is somewhat limited, with a general lack of agreement among
    various authors on the characters to be emphasized for circumscription of taxa. A taxonomic
    nightmare has resulted from the recognition of numerous poorly defined species, subspecies, and
    varieties. Although an extensive molecular systematic study of the genus was recently conducted
    (Goodson), some relationships and species boundaries remain unclear. Because detailed
    population-level, morphological, cytological, and molecular studies of North American
    Descurainia are still needed, this treatment represents an early “pit stop” on the road to full
    understanding of the complexity in the genus.</discussion>
  <discussion>The keys and circumscriptions in both L. E. Detling (1939) and R. C. Rollins (1993)
    are unreliable for the identification of a given collection to an infraspecific taxon. In a
    genus where interspecific hybridization is so extensive, it is sometimes impossible to identify
    reliably every single specimen, especially if mature fruits are lacking. Unfortunately, most
    North American material in major herbaria consists of either specimens without mature fruits or
    unrecognized hybrids between various taxa. As a consequence, up to 60% of the holdings of
    Descurainia species in the major North American herbaria are misidentified. Because mature
    fruits are critical to proper identification, the following key relies primarily on fruiting
    material.</discussion>
  <discussion>Almost all taxonomists have used the presence versus absence of glandular papillae as
    an important character to subdivide a given complex into species, subspecies, varieties, or
    forms. Both glandular and eglandular forms sometimes occur within a given population of
    Descurainia incana, D. incisa, D. paradisa, D. pinnata, or D. sophioides. Some authors were
    inconsistent in according formal recognition to the glandular versus eglandular plants of a
    given species. For example, R. C. Rollins (1993) treated the glandular and eglandular forms of
    D. obtusa and D. paradisa, but not of D. incana and D. sophioides, as distinct subspecies; N. H.
    Holmgren (2005b) recognized such forms as varieties in D. paradisa but not D. incana. Although
    the presence versus absence of glands appears to be consistent within certain taxa, reliance on
    the use of glands as a diagnostic character should be applied with extreme caution.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 45-47 (14 in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bramwell, D. 1977. A revision of Descurainia Webb &amp; Berth.
      section Sisymbriodendron (Christ) O. E. Schulz in the Canary Islands. Bot. Macar. 4:
      31–53.</reference>
    <reference>Detling, L. E. 1939. A revision of the North American species of Descurainia. Amer.
      Midl. Naturalist 22: 481–520.</reference>
    <reference>Goodson, B. E. 2007. Molecular Systematics and Biogeography of Descurainia Webb
      &amp; Berthel. (Brassicaceae). Ph.D. dissertation. University of Texas.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits sparsely to densely pubescent at least when young.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials; fruiting pedicels 1.5–3 mm; fruits subappressed to rachises; styles
        sparsely</description>
      <determination>14. Descurainia torulosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Biennials; fruiting pedicels 6–31 mm; fruits not appressed to rachises; styles
        glabrous; ovules 16–64 per ovary; Arizona, California, Nevada, New Mexico.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seeds biseriate; ovules 48–64 per ovary; fruits 1–1.3 mm wide; fruiting
        pedicels</description>
      <determination>1. Descurainia adenophora</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seeds uniseriate; ovules 16–40 per ovary; fruits 0.7–1 mm wide; fruiting
        pedicels</description>
      <determination>9. Descurainia obtusa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits usually fusiform, obovate, clavate, or broadly ellipsoid, rarely broadly
        linear (wider distally).</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits usually clavate, rarely broadly linear (wider distally); seeds biseriate;
        ovules</description>
      <determination>11. Descurainia pinnata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits fusiform, obovate, or broadly ellipsoid (sometimes clavate in D. paradisa );
        seeds uniseriate (sometimes biseriate in D. paradisa ); ovules 4–12 per ovary; valves each
        with obscure midvein.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits long-acute basally and apically; styles (0.2–)0.3–0.6(–0.8) mm; stems
        (1.3–)</description>
      <determination>3. Descurainia californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits acute basally, obtuse apically; styles 0.05–0.3 mm; stems
        (1–)1.5–3.2(–4.1)</description>
      <determination>10. Descurainia paradisa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits linear (sometimes oblong in D. brevisiliqua ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials (short-lived); stems 0.1–0.15 dm; racemes not elongated in fruit;
        ovules</description>
      <determination>6. Descurainia kenheilii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals or biennials; stems (0.5–)0.9–12(–18) dm; racemes elongated considerably in
        fruit (sometimes slightly elongated in D. sophioides ); ovules 10–62 per ovary (6–12 in D.
        nelsonii ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits often strictly appressed to rachises; fruiting pedicels erect to
        erect-ascending</description>
      <determination>4. Descurainia incana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruits not appressed to rachises; fruiting pedicels horizontal, divaricate, or
        ascending.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades 2- or 3-pinnate; fruit septums appearing 2- or 3-veined</description>
      <determination>12. Descurainia sophia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades usually 1-pinnate (rarely 2-pinnate in D. sophioides ); fruit septums
        not veined.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants eglandular; fruits 3–8(–10) mm; petals 0.7–1.2 mm; seeds 0.5–0.8
        mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Biennials; stems 6–11 dm, unbranched; ovules 10–28 per ovary; seeds</description>
      <determination>2. Descurainia brevisiliqua</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals; stems (0.7–)0.9–3.2(–4.5) dm, usually branched at or near</description>
      <determination>8. Descurainia nelsonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants glandular or eglandular; fruits 8–30(–34) mm; petals 1.7–2.8 mm; seeds
        0.9–1.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers overtopped by developing fruits; ovules 30–62 per ovary</description>
      <determination>13. Descurainia sophioides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers not overtopped by developing fruits; ovules 14–32 per ovary.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants canescent or not; cauline leaf blades: distal segments oblong to lanceolate,
        or linear, margins dentate, denticulate or entire; fruits</description>
      <determination>5. Descurainia incisa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not canescent; cauline leaf blades: distal segments linear or oblong,
        margins entire; fruits straight or slightly curved</description>
      <determination>7. Descurainia longepedicellata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
