<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>54.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>TROPIDOCARPUM</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Hooker</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Icon. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: plate 43. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[Greek tropis , keel, and karpos , fruit, alluding to fruit shape]</etymology>
  <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Agallis</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Philippi</genus_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Twisselmannia</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Al-Shehbaz</genus_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Annuals; not scapose; pubescent or glabrous, trichomes simple, these mixed with smaller, short-stalked, Y-shaped, forked ones, rarely rays branched. Stems (usually several from base, rarely simple), usually ascending, decumbent, or prostrate, rarely erect, unbranched or branched [basally] distally, (slender). Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal (withered by fruiting), not rosulate, petiolate, blade margins pinnatifid or pinnatisect; cauline sessile or subsessile, blade margins pinnatifid. Racemes (several-flowered, bracteate throughout), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels erect, ascending, or divaricate, slender. Flowers: sepals erect to ascending, oblong, (glabrous or pubescent); petals yellow, sometimes with purple tinge, oblanceolate, obovate, or spatulate, (slightly longer than sepals), claw undifferentiated from blade; stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments sometimes slightly dilated basally; anthers ovate, (apex obtuse); nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits siliques or silicles, sessile, linear, oblong, or obdeltoid, smooth, strongly angustiseptate; valves [(2 or) 4 in T. capparideum, keeled], not veined, (thin-leathery throughout, or distally subwoody or thick-leathery and tuberculate-rugose), pubescent; replum rounded; septum complete or absent; ovules 4–70 per ovary; style distinct, (slender); stigma capitate. Seeds uniseriate or (in 4-valved fruits) 4-seriate, not winged, oblong; seed coat (reticulate), mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x = 8.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 4 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>California</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>c Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>South America (c Chile).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Tropidocarpum lanatum (Barnéoud) Al-Shehbaz &amp; R. A. Price is known from central Chile.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Al-Shehbaz, I. A. 2003c. A synopsis of Tropidocarpum (Brassicaceae). Novon 13: 392–395. Al-Shehbaz, I. A. and R. A. Price. 2001. The Chilean Agallis and Californian Tropidocarpum (Brassicaceae) are congeneric. Novon 11: 292–293.</reference>
    <reference>Robinson, B. L. 1896. The fruit of Tropidocarpum. Erythea 4: 108–119.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits obdeltoid, valves thick-leathery and tuberculate-rugose distally, puberulent, trichomes</statement>
      <determination>3. Tropidocarpum californicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits linear or oblong, valves thin-leathery and smooth distally, usually pubescent or puberulent, rarely glabrescent, trichomes retrorse; ovules 25–70 per ovary.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits narrowly linear, (25–)30–60(–70) × 1.5–2(–3) mm, length 13–46 times width;</statement>
      <determination>1. Tropidocarpum gracile</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits oblong, (5–)9–20 × (3–)4–5 mm, length (1.6–)2.8–5 times width; valves</statement>
      <determination>2. Tropidocarpum capparideum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
