<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">euclidieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="W. T. Aiton in W. Aiton and W. T. Aiton" date="unknown">EUCLIDIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. Aiton and W. T. Aiton, Hortus Kew.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 74. 1812</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe euclidieae;genus EUCLIDIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek eu- , well, and kleio , shut, alluding to indehiscent fruits]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals; not scapose; scabrous, trichomes stalked, 2-forked, submalpighiaceous, mixed with fewer, simple, and, rarely, 3-forked ones, usually different sizes. Stems erect or ascending, unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate, sessile, or subsessile; basal (often withered by flowering), not rosulate, petiolate, blade margins entire, dentate, or repand, rarely pinnatifid; cauline sessile or subsessile, blade similar to basal, margins entire, dentate, or repand. Racemes (corymbose), elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels erect, stout. Flowers: sepals ovate to oblong; petals white, narrowly spatulate, (slightly longer than sepals), claw slightly differentiated from blade (shorter than sepals, apex emarginate); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate, (apiculate); nectar glands (4), lateral, 1 on each side of lateral stamen. Fruits silicles (nutletlike), indehiscent, sessile, ovoid, subterete to slightly 4-angled; valves not veined, (thickened, woody), scabrous; replum strongly expanded laterally; septum complete, (thickened); ovules 2 per ovary, (subapical); style (persistent), obsolete or distinct; stigma capitate, 2-lobed (lobes not decurrent). Seeds aseriate, plump, not winged, oblong; seed coat (smooth), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent or obliquely so.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">w Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced also in Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: introduced; e Europe, c, w Asia; introduced also in Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; e Europe, c, w Asia; introduced also in Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>57.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
