<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">euclidieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Boissier" date="1854">STRIGOSELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Diagn. Pl. Orient.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(1): 22. 1854</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe euclidieae;genus STRIGOSELLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin strigosus , covered with short, bristly trichomes, and –ella , diminutive]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals; not scapose; pubescent [glabrous], trichomes simple and stalked, forked or dendritic. Stems erect or ascending, unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or subsessile; basal not rosulate, petiolate, blade margins entire, dentate, or pinnatifid; cauline petiolate or subsessile, blade margins usually entire or dentate, rarely sinuate [lobed]. Racemes (few- to several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels ascending or divaricate, stout [slender] (about equal to fruits). Flowers: sepals narrowly oblong [ovate], pubescent; petals pink or purple [rarely white], oblanceolate [spatulate, oblong], (longer than sepals), claw undifferentiated from blade, (apex obtuse or rounded); stamens tetradynamous, (erect); filaments not dilated basally [sometimes median 4 connate in 2 pairs]; anthers oblong [ovate], (apiculate or not); nectar glands (4), lateral, 1 on each side of lateral stamen, median glands absent. Fruits siliques, subsessile, linear, smooth [torulose], 4-angled [terete]; valves each with obscure [prominent] midvein, pubescent or glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 40–80 per ovary; style obsolete; stigma conical, 2-lobed (lobes connivent or connate, opposite replum). Seeds uniseriate, plump or slightly flattened, not winged, oblong [ovate]; seed coat (reticulate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Europe, c, w Asia, n Africa.</description>
  <number>58.</number>
  <discussion>Species 20 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Botschantzev, V. P. 1972b. The genus Strigosella Boiss. and its relation to the genus Malcolmia R. Br. (Cruciferae). Bot. Zhurn. (Moscow &amp; Leningrad) 57: 1033–1046.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
