<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Al-Shehbaz, Beilstein &amp; E. A. Kellogg" date="unknown">Eutremeae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eutrema</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">edwardsii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Chlor. Melvill.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9, plate A. 1823</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Eutremeae;genus Eutrema;species edwardsii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eutrema</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Turczaninow" date="unknown">edwardsii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="(Rollins) W. A. Weber" date="unknown">penlandii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eutrema;species edwardsii;subspecies penlandii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eutrema</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rollins" date="unknown">labradoricum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eutrema;species labradoricum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eutrema</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">penlandii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eutrema;species penlandii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Plants of Eutrema edwardsii from Alaska, northern Canada, and Greenland grow at elevations of 0–1900 m; those of Colorado, treated by R. C. Rollins (1993) as E. penlandii, grow at 3700–3900 m.</discussion>
  <discussion>An examination of collections of Eutrema edwardsii from its entire range amply demonstrates that it is a highly variable species that can easily accommodate E. penlandii. Although the latter is known from the high mountains of Park County (Colorado), its plants are indistinguishable from those of E. edwardsii from Greenland, and the higher latitudes in Alaska, British Columbia, Northwest Territories, Nunavut, and Yukon. In general, plants of E. edwardsii from lower latitudes tend to be far more robust than those of higher latitudes. R. C. Rollins (1993) indicated that E. penlandii is distinguished from E. edwardsii by having stems less than 10 (versus 10–45) cm, lingulate (versus obovate) petals, fruiting pedicels less that 4 (versus 5–10) mm, infructescence less than 5 (versus to 20) cm, and cordate (versus truncate or cuneate) basal leaves. In fact, the petals of E. penlandii are spatulate, just as those of most plants of E. edwardsii, and the basal leaves in E. penlandii (e.g., Penland 3909 and Weber 13315, both at GH) are cuneate. Furthermore, some plants from Greenland (e.g., Raup et al. 465, GH) are almost identical to those of E. penlandii, and they are only 3–8 cm with narrowly obovate petals, fruiting pedicels 2–4 mm, and infructescence 2–3 cm. Other examples of E. edwardsii that show some or all of the above aspects of E. penlandii could be cited. Weber treated E. penlandii as a subspecies of E. edwardsii, but the only difference I see between the two is geographic. Such distinction is unacceptable because the widely disjunct populations of E. edwardsii within Russia would have to be treated that way too.</discussion>
  <discussion>As Eutrema penlandii, E. edwardsii is in the Center for Plant Conservation’s National Collection of Endangered Plants.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
