<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>61.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>PENNELLIA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Nieuwland</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Midl. Naturalist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 224. 1918</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[For Francis Whittier Pennell, 1886–1952, American botanist]</etymology>
  <author>Sara Fuentes-Soriano</author>
  <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Heterothrix</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>(B. L. Robinson) Rydberg</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>34: 435. 1905,</place_in_publication>
      <other_info>based on Thelypodium Endlicher subgen. Heterothrix B. L. Robinson in A. Gray et al., Syn. Fl. N. Amer. 1(1,1): 178. 1895, not Müller Argoviensis 1860</other_info>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Lamprophragma</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>O. E. Schulz</genus_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Perennials; not scapose; pubescent or glabrous, trichomes simple, with stalked, forked or dendritic ones. Stems erect [ascending], often branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal (withered with age), rosulate, petiolate, blade margins entire, dentate to sinuate, or runcinate; cauline subsessile or sessile [shortly petiolate], blade margins entire [dentate to sinuate]. Racemes (several-flowered, sometimes secund, lax), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels erect, descending, ascending, or divaricate-ascending, slender, (glabrous). Flowers (usually actinomorphic, rarely zygomorphic, cup-shaped); sepals erect, oblong to ovate, lateral pair slightly to strongly saccate basally, (usually pubescent, rarely glabrous); petals white (lavender or purple apically), spatulate to oblanceolate, (± longer than sepals), claw undifferentiated from blade, (apex obtuse); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments dilated basally; anthers ovate to oblong, (apex obtuse); nectar glands confluent, subtending bases of stamens. Fruits siliques, sessile or shortly stipitate, linear, not torulose, straight or curved, terete or latiseptate; valves each with prominent or obscure midvein, glabrous or pubescent; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 40–250 per ovary; style distinct or obsolete; stigma capitate. Seeds uniseriate or biseriate, plump or flattened, winged or not, oblong to ovate; seed coat (reticulate-areolate), mucilaginous or not when wetted; cotyledons accumbent or incumbent. x = 8.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 8 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>sw United States</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>South America.</global_distribution>
  <references>
    <reference>Fuentes-Soriano, S. 2004. A taxonomic revision of Pennellia (Brassicaceae). Harvard Pap. Bot. 8: 173–202.</reference>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1980b. The genus Pennellia (Cruciferae) in North America. Contr. Gray Herb. 210: 5–21.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits strongly latiseptate, 2–2.5 mm wide; seeds 2.4–2.8 mm, winged (broadly); septums</statement>
      <determination>3. Pennellia tricornuta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruits terete or slightly latiseptate, 0.6–1.8 mm wide; seeds 0.7–1.3 mm, not winged; septums transparent; ovules 90–250 per ovary; cotyledons incumbent.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Racemes not secund; fruiting pedicels straight, erect or ascending; fruits (1.5–)2.2–5.8</statement>
      <determination>1. Pennellia micrantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Racemes secund; fruiting pedicels arcuate, reflexed; fruits 5–10 cm, latiseptate; ovules</statement>
      <determination>2. Pennellia longifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
