<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Prantl in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl" date="unknown">hesperideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">HESPERIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 663. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 297. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe hesperideae;genus HESPERIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hesperos , evening, alluding to time when flowers of some species are most fragrant]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants with caudex; not scapose; pubescent or glabrous, trichomes simple and/or forked, often mixed with unicellular glands on uniseriate stalks. Stems erect, unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate [sessile]; basal rosulate [not rosulate], blade margins entire, dentate, or pinnatifid; cauline similar to basal. Racemes (corymbose), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate or ascending [reflexed], slender or stout. Flowers: sepals oblong [linear], (sometimes connivent), lateral pair strongly saccate basally, (pubescent or glabrous); petals obovate [oblong], (much longer than sepals), claw distinctly differentiated from blade, (apex rounded [obtuse]); stamens strongly tetradynamous; filaments (erect), slender or dilated basally; anthers linear [oblong], (apex obtuse); nectar glands (2), lateral, annular or lunar. Fruits tardily dehiscent, sessile, linear, torulose; valves each with prominent midvein, glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 4–40 per ovary; style obsolete or distinct (relatively short); stigma conical (lobes prominent, connivent or distinct, decurrent). Seeds plump, not winged, oblong; seed coat (reticulate), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons incumbent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">c</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced also in South America (Argentina).</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced also in South America (Chile).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 25 (1 in the flora): introduced; se Europe, c, sw Asia, n Africa; introduced also in South America (Argentina, Chile).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 25 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; se Europe, c, sw Asia, n Africa; introduced also in South America (Argentina, Chile).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>62.</number>
  <discussion>Species 25 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Dvoák, F. 1966. A contribution to the study of the evolution of Hesperis series Matronales Cvl. emend. Dvoák. Feddes Repert. 73: 94–99. Dvoák, F. 1973. Infrageneric classification of Hesperis. Feddes Repert. 84: 259–272.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
