<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Webb &amp; Berthelot" date="unknown">Iberideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="W. T. Aiton" date="unknown">TEESDALIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. Aiton and W. T. Aiton, Hortus Kew.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 83. 1812</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Iberideae;genus TEESDALIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Robert Teesdale, 1740–1804, British botanist and gardener at Yorkshire]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals [perennials]; scapose; glabrous or sparsely pubescent. Stems (simple or few to several from base), erect or ascending, unbranched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal (persistent), rosulate, petiolate, blade margins usually lyrate-pinnatifid or pinnatisect, rarely entire or dentate; cauline (0–4), sessile, blade margins entire or dentate. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered). Fruiting pedicels divaricate, slender. Flowers (actinomorphic or zygomorphic); sepals ascending to spreading, ovate, glabrous; petals white, oblong or obovate, (equal to or longer than sepals, or lateral pair much larger), claw undifferentiated from blade, (apex obtuse); stamens (6) tetradynamous, or (4) equal; filaments dilated basally (appendaged); anthers ovate; nectar glands lateral, 1 on each side of lateral stamen, median glands absent. Fruits (often divaricate), sessile, broadly obcordate to suborbicular, slightly keeled, angustiseptate (strongly compressed), (apex notched); valves prominently veined, (apex narrowly winged), glabrous; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 4 per ovary; style absent or not; stigma capitate, entire. Seeds uniseriate, slightly compressed, not winged, broadly ovate; seed coat (rugulose), copiously mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw Asia (Middle East)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced also in South America (Chile)</description>
  <description type="distribution">n</description>
  <description type="distribution">c Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>64.</number>
  <discussion>Species 3 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Teesdalia conferta (Lagasca) O. Appel is known from Europe (Portugal, Spain). For a summary of the nomenclature of Teesdalia and references on its species introduced in North America, see I. A. Al-Shehbaz (1986).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Appel, O. 1998. The status of Teesdaliopsis and Teesdalia (Brassicaceae). Novon 8: 218–219.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers zygomorphic; stamens 6, tetradynamous; basal leaf blades: lateral lobes obtuse;</description>
      <determination>1. Teesdalia nudicaulis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers actinomorphic; stamens 4, equal; basal leaf blades: lateral lobes acute; styles</description>
      <determination>2. Teesdalia coronopifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
