<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">Brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Al-Shehbaz, Beilstein &amp; E. A. Kellogg" date="unknown">Noccaeeae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="F. K. Meyer" date="unknown">MICROTHLASPI</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Feddes Repert.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>84: 452. 1973</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Brassicaceae;tribe Noccaeeae;genus MICROTHLASPI;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek micro- , small, and genus Thlaspi ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals; not scapose; (glaucous). Stems erect or subdecumbent, unbranched or branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate, sessile, or subsessile; basal (withered by fruiting), loosely rosulate or not; petiolate [subsessile], blade margins entire or obscurely dentate; cauline blade (base cordate to amplexicaul), margins entire or repand. Racemes (several-flowered), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate, straight or recurved, slender. Flowers: sepals ovate or oblong, (margins membranous); petals white, oblong or spatulate, (sometimes slightly unequal), claw (short or) undifferentiated from blade, (apex rounded [obtuse]); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate, (apex obtuse); nectar glands (2 or 4), lateral, 1 on each side of lateral stamen (when 4). Fruits sessile, usually obcordate, rarely obovate, (apex emarginate), strongly angustiseptate; valves keeled, (winged around, much wider apically); replum rounded; septum complete, (not veined); ovules (4–)6–8(–10) per ovary; style obsolete or distinct, (included in apical notch of fruit); stigma capitate. Seeds plump, not winged, ovoid; seed coat (smooth), mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa.</description>
  <number>71.</number>
  <discussion>Species 4 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Koch, M. et al. 1998b. Molecular biogeography and evolution of the Microthlaspi perfoliatum s.l. polyploid complex (Brassicaceae): Chloroplast DNA and nuclear ribosomal DNA restriction site variation. Canad. J. Bot. 76: 382–396.</reference>
    <reference>Meyer, F. K. 2003. Kritische Revision der “Thlaspi”-Arten Europas, Afrikas und Vorderasiens. Spezieller Teil. III. Microthlaspi F. K. Mey. Häussknechtia 9: 3–59.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
