<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Burnett" date="unknown">brassicaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Al-Shehbaz" date="unknown">noccaeeae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Moench" date="1802">NOCCAEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Suppl. Meth.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>89. 1802</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family brassicaceae;tribe noccaeeae;genus NOCCAEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Domenico Nocca, 1758–1841, Italian clergyman, botanist, director of botanic garden at Pavia]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials or perennials; (stoloniferous or simple or several from caudex); not scapose; (often glaucous). Stems erect or decumbent, unbranched or branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal rosulate, petiolate, margins entire, denticulate, or dentate; cauline blade (base auriculate or subamplexicaul [sagittate]), margins entire or dentate. Racemes (corymbose, several-flowered), considerably elongated or congested in fruit. Fruiting pedicels horizontal or, rarely, ascending, slender. Flowers: sepals erect, oblong, or ovate [obovate]; petals white, pink, or purple, spatulate [obovate, oblanceolate, oblong, or, rarely, broadly linear], (longer than sepals), claw obscurely differentiated from blade, (apex obtuse or rounded); stamens slightly tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers ovate [oblong], (apex obtuse); nectar glands lateral, 2 and subtending stamens, or 4 and 1 on each side of stamen. Fruits sessile, obcordate, obovate, obdeltate, elliptical, or oblong, smooth, strongly angustiseptate, (winged or not winged apically); valves each obscurely to prominently veined, strongly keeled; replum rounded; septum complete; ovules 4–14[–24] per ovary; style included in, or much exceeding, apical notch; stigma capitate. Seeds plump or slightly compressed, not winged, ovoid [oblong]; seed coat (longitudinally, minutely reticulate to nearly smooth), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent. x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Mexico, South America (Patagonia), Europe, Asia, n Africa.</description>
  <number>72.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 80 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Previous North American accounts (e.g., E. B. Payson 1926; P. K. Holmgren 1971; R. C. Rollins 1993) treated species of Noccaea as members of Thlaspi. As discussed under the latter genus (see references there) and as shown by M. Koch and I. A. Al-Shehbaz (2004), Noccaea is definitely distinct from Thlaspi. Excellent comments on the biology, variability, and distribution of the North American taxa were given by Holmgren and are not repeated here.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Holmgren, P. K. 1971. A biosystematic study of North American Thlaspi montanum and its allies. Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 21(2): 1–106.</reference>
    <reference>Koch, M. and I. A. Al-Shehbaz. 2004. Taxonomic and phylogenetic evaluation of the American “Thlaspi” species: Identity and relationship to the Eurasian genus Noccaea (Brassicaceae). Syst. Bot. 29: 375–384.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals not flaring between blade and claw, 2–2.8(–3.6) mm; styles (0.2–)0.3–0.5(–0.6) mm;</description>
      <determination>3. Noccaea parviflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals often flaring between blade and claw, 3–13 mm; styles (0.3–)0.6–4.2 mm; sepals 1.5–5.3 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles (0.3–)0.6–1 mm; fruits not winged apically; petals 3–5 mm; arctic Alaska,</description>
      <determination>1. Noccaea arctica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles (0.4–)1.1–4.2 mm; fruits usually winged, rarely not winged apically; petals (3.4–)</description>
      <determination>2. Noccaea fendleri</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
