<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>73.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>DIMORPHOCARPA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Rollins</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Publ. Bussey Inst. Harvard Univ.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1979: 20, plates 3, 4. 1979</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <etymology>[Latin dimorphus , having two forms, and carpus , fruit, alluding to production of two fruit types in some species]</etymology>
  <common_name>Spectacle-pod</common_name>
  <author>Ihsan A. Al-Shehbaz</author>
  <description>Annuals, biennials, or, rarely, perennials; not scapose; densely pubescent throughout, trichomes usually subsessile and stellate, mixed with minutely stalked, dendritic ones, rarely unbranched. Stems erect [ascending], unbranched or branched proximally, branched distally. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate or sessile; basal not rosulate, petiolate, blade margins dentate, pinnatifid, or lobed; cauline sessile, subsessile, or shortly petiolate, blade (base not auriculate), margins entire or lobed. Racemes (corymbose), considerably elongated in fruit. Fruiting pedicels divaricate, sometimes ascending or slightly reflexed, slender. Flowers: sepals widely spreading to reflexed, oblong, (equal), lateral pair not saccate basally; petals (spreading), white or lavender, obovate (longer than sepals), claw well-differentiated from blade, (apex rounded); stamens (somewhat spreading), tetradynamous; filaments not dilated basally; anthers oblong [sagittate]; nectar glands distinct, lateral and median present; (gynophore to 0.5 mm). Fruits silicles, subsessile, breaking into two 1-seeded units at maturity, didymous, suborbicular, or broader than long, winged, strongly angustiseptate; valves keeled, enclosing seeds when falling off, not winged, narrowly winged, or margined, indurated around margin, glabrous or pubescent; replum concealed by valve margin; septum complete (ca. 0.1 mm wide); ovules 2 per ovary; style relatively short or obsolete, (terete or flattened); stigma conical, decurrently 2-lobed (appearing entire). Seeds aseriate, strongly flattened, not winged, broadly oblong to suborbicular; seed coat (smooth), not mucilaginous when wetted; cotyledons accumbent to obliquely incumbent. x = 9.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 4 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>sw United States</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Dimorphocarpa membranacea (Payson) Rollins is known from northern Mexico (San Luis Potosí, Tamaulipas).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1958. The genetic evaluation of a taxonomic character in Dithyrea (Cruciferae). Rhodora 60: 145–152.</reference>
    <reference>Rollins, R. C. 1979. Dithyrea and a related genus (Cruciferae). Publ. Bussey Inst. Harvard Univ. 1979: 3–32.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruit valves (7–)8–10 mm; petals (7–)8–10(–12) mm, claws not expanded basally; distal cauline leaves sessile, blades usually ovate to narrowly oblong, rarely lanceolate, bases</statement>
      <determination>1. Dimorphocarpa candicans</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Fruit valves 4–5.5(–6.5) mm; petals (3.5–)4–7(–8) mm, claws expanded basally; distal cauline leaves shortly petiolate or subsessile, blades linear to lanceolate, bases cuneate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Distal cauline blades: margins pinnately lobed; fruit valves nearly as long as wide,</statement>
      <determination>2. Dimorphocarpa pinnatifida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Distal cauline blades: margins usually entire, rarely dentate; fruit valves often longer</statement>
      <determination>3. Dimorphocarpa wislizeni</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
