<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">GROSSULARIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Pallas" date="unknown">diacanthum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Reise Russ. Reich.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 722, plate 1, fig. 2.  1776 (as diacantha),</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family GROSSULARIACEAE;genus Ribes;species diacanthum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants dioecious, 0.5–2 m.  Stems erect, stipitate-glandular, without nonglandular hairs; spines at nodes 2, 3–5 mm; prickles on internodes scattered.  Leaves: petiole 1–2 cm, glabrous; blade ovate to obovate, 3-lobed, cleft barely 1/8 to midrib, 1.5–3.5 cm, base cuneate to rounded, surfaces glabrous abaxially, strigillose adaxially, lobes rounded, margins deeply serrate, apex obtuse.  Inflorescences nodding, 10–15-flowered racemes, staminate 2–3 cm, pistillate 1–2 cm, axis glabrous, glandular, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels jointed, 2–4 mm, pubescent and stipitate-glandular; bracts lanceolate to ligulate, 4–6 mm, glabrous.  Flowers unisexual; hypanthium yellowish green, rotate, 1–1.5 mm, glabrous; sepals not overlapping, erect, greenish, ovate, 1.5–2 mm; petals widely separated, erect, greenish yellow, cuneate-orbiculate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 0.5–1 mm; nectary disc not seen; stamens nearly as long as petals; filaments linear, 0.2–0.5 mm, glabrous; anthers cream, dumbbell-shaped, 0.2 mm, apex with depressed callus, (pollen absent in pistillate flowers); ovary (absent in staminate flowers) glabrous; styles connate almost to stigmas, 0.5 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatable, red, globose to globose-ovoid, 5–10 mm, glabrous.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering May–Jun</description>
  <description type="morphology">Disturbed areas</description>
  <description type="morphology">400–500 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Man.</description>
  <description type="morphology">n Asia.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Ribes diacanthum was first seen as apparently naturalized in 1947 in oak woods on bluffs near the Experimental Farm, Brandon, Manitoba; collections were made in 1956 and 1959 and deposited in DAO and the Experimental Farm herbarium (G. A. Stevenson 1965).  Its current status in Manitoba is not known.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
