<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>1a.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Vaccinium</genus_name>
    <species_name>erythrocarpum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Michaux</species_authority>
    <subspecies_name>erythrocarpum</subspecies_name>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants crown-forming (some-times suckering or rhizomatous when injured); twigs of current season ± terete, smooth, hairy in lines.  Leaf blades green, elliptic or ovate to oblong-lanceolate, 40–70 × 15–30 mm, mem-branous, margins serrulate, abaxial surface glandular-hairy.  Inflorescence bracts caducous, 2, basal.  Pedicels nodding, to 1.5 cm, glabrous.  Flowers: calyx lobes to 1 mm, glabrous; corolla deeply reflexed, white, pink, or rarely red; filaments pilose.  Berries red, deep purple, or black, 6–15 mm diam., glabrous.  2n = 24.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering late spring–mid summer</phenology>
  <habitat>Wooded slopes, subalpine shrub lands, boggy areas, rocky slopes and thickets</habitat>
  <elevation>600–2000 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tenn.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>45b. Vaccinium   Linnaeus sect. Vaccinium</discussion>
  <description>Shrubs, procumbent to erect, (0.3–)1.2–4(–9) dm, rhizomatous.  Leaves deciduous.  Inflorescences axillary, racemes, 2–4-flowered, sometimes flowers solitary, ebracteate, from scaly bud on previous year’s wood.  Pedicels ± articulated with calyx tube.  Flowers: sepals 4–5; petals 4–5(–6), connate for 3/4 to nearly their entire lengths, corolla urceolate; stamens usually 8, included; anthers with awns, tubules ca. 1 mm.  Berries 4–5-locular.  Seeds ca. 8–15.</description>
  <discussion>Species 1: North America, Eurasia; circumboreal.</discussion>
  <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES">
    <reference>Warr, H. J.  1981.  Variation in Vaccinium uliginosum in Northeastern North America.  M.Sc. thesis.  Acadia University.   Young, S. B.  1970.  On the taxonomy and distribution of Vaccinium uliginosum.  Rhodora 72: 439–459.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>
