<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>9.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Gaylussacia</genus_name>
    <species_name>tomentosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>(A. Gray) Pursh ex Small</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>24: 443.  1897  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Hairy dangleberry</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Gaylussacia</genus_name>
    <species_name>frondosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Linnaeus) Torrey &amp; A. Gray</species_authority>
    <variety_name>tomentosa</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>A. Gray</variety_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. Gray et al., Syn. Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 19.  1878</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Decachaena</genus_name>
    <species_name>tomentosa</species_name>
    <species_authority>(A. Gray) Small</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 7.5–20 dm, forming small to extensive colonies (by rhizomes); branches spreading; twigs of current season pale green, densely hairy, sessile-glandular.  Leaves: petiole 2–3 mm; blade greenish white, glaucescent abaxially, dull green to yellowish green adaxially, ovate to oblong, 2.5–6 × 2–3 cm, subcoriaceous, base cuneate, margins entire, apex rounded to obtuse, surfaces densely short-hairy (longer hairs to ca. 0.2 mm), sessile-glandular abaxially.  Inflorescences drooping, 2–4-flowered, sometimes flowers solitary, bracteate, 1–2.5 cm, glabrous or pilose, sessile-glandular; bracts early-deciduous, leaflike, 5–6 mm, shorter than pedicels, densely hairy.  Pedicels 8–15(–20) mm, glabrous, sessile-glandular; bracteoles 1–2, 1–2.5 mm.  Flowers: sepals 5, 1–1.2 mm, glabrous or sparsely hairy, sessile-glandular; petals 5, corolla greenish white, campanulate-conic, 3–5 mm, lobes deltate, ca. 1 mm; filaments 0.5–1 mm, ciliate; anthers included (tips barely exserted), 2.5 mm, thecae not divergent distally; ovary glabrous.  Drupes juicy, sweet, dark blue, sometimes black, rarely white, glaucous, 5–8 mm diam., glabrous.  Seeds 1.5 mm.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering late spring</phenology>
  <habitat>Moist to wet pine flatwoods and savannas, margins of cypress-gum depressions, margins of blackwater floodplains, streamhead ecotones, sometimes in dry soils</habitat>
  <elevation>0–100 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ala.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>S.C.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Gaylussacia tomentosa is a coastal plain endemic that replaces G. frondosa from South Carolina south-ward.  The leaves and twigs are covered with dense, tawny hairs, unlike the relatively sparse, white hairs of G. frondosa.</discussion>
</treatment>
