<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Elizabeth Fortson Wells,Patrick E. Elvander†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">saxifragaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Voss" date="1899">DARMERA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gärtn. Zentralbl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 645.  1899  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family saxifragaceae;genus DARMERA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Karl Darmer, 1843–1918, German botanist and horticulturist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, not rhizomatous, not stoloniferous; caudex 1–5 cm diam., scaly.  Flowering stems (appearing before leaves), erect, leafless, 30–100(–150) cm, sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular to hispid.  Leaves in basal rosette; stipules present; petiole present, attachment to blade peltate, sparsely stipitate-glandular to glandular-hispid; blade orbiculate, peltate, cupped in center, 6–15-lobed, sinuses ± deep, ultimate margins irregularly serrate, apices of lobes acute, surfaces glabrous or scantily stipitate-glandular and hispid on veins abaxially, glabrous or scantily short stipitate-glandular adaxially; venation palmate.  Inflorescences ± flat-topped, compound cymes, arising from terminal bud in rosette, 60–75-flowered, usually ebracteate.  Flowers: hypanthium completely adnate to ovary, green to pinkish purple; sepals 5, greenish to pinkish purple; petals 5, white to pink; nectary tissue not seen or inconspicuous; stamens 10; filaments subulate; ovary superior, 2-locular, carpels connate proximally; placentation axile, appearing marginal; styles 2; stigmas 2.  Capsules folliclelike, 2-beaked.  Seeds dark brown, prismatic or angular, cellular-rugulose.  x = 17.</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Umbrella plant</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">Indian rhubarb</other_name>
  <discussion>Peltiphyllum Engler in H. G. A. Engler and K. Prantl, Nat. Pflanzenfam. 53[III,2a]: 61.  1891, not Peltophyllum Gardner 1843</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1: w United States.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
