<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>6.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>LITHOPHRAGMA</genus_name><genus_authority>(Nuttall) Torrey &amp; A. Gray</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Fl. N. Amer. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 583.  1840, name conserved  ,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Woodland-star </common_name><etymology>[Greek lithos, stone, and phragma, hedge or fence, alluding to rocky habitat; or an unsuccessful attempt to render Saxifraga in Greek]</etymology><author>Roy L. Taylor</author><discussion>Tellima R. Brown [unranked] Lithophragma Nuttall, J. Acad. Nat. Sci. Philadelphia 7: 26.  1834 (as Lithofragma); Pleurendotria Rafinesque, name rejected</discussion><description>Herbs, rhizomatous, not stoloniferous; caudex sometimes bearing bulbils.  Flowering stems erect, leafy, 8–85 cm, stipitate-glandular.  Leaves in basal rosette and cauline; cauline leaves (1–)2(–10), usually alternate (opposite in L. cymbalaria), unlobed, lobed, or palmately compound, sometimes with bulbils in axils; stipules present; petiole stipitate-glandular; blade rhombic or orbiculate to reniform, lobed, base cordate, hastate, rounded, ligulate, or cuneate, ultimate margins entire or toothed, apex obtuse or acute, surfaces often stipitate-glandular; venation palmate.  Inflorescences compact or lax racemes, arising from axillary buds in basal rosette, 2–12(–25)-flowered, sometimes flowers solitary, (flowers sometimes replaced by bulbils), bracteate.  Flowers: hypanthium partially adnate to proximal 1/2 to entire length of ovary, free from ovary 1–2 mm, green; sepals 5, green tinged with red; petals 5, white or pink; nectariferous tissue inconspicuous; stamens 10, (inserted on hypanthium, inner whorl attached proximal to point of petal insertion); filaments filiform; (anthers cordate); pistil 3-carpellate; ovary superior to 1/2 or almost completely inferior, 1-locular, carpels fully connate at ovaries; placentation parietal; styles 3; stigmas 3.  Capsules 3-beaked.  Seeds (50–200), usually dark brown, ovoid, smooth, wrinkled, or tuberculate.  x = 7.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 10 (10 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> w North America.</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference>Kuzoff, R. K., L. Hufford, and D. E. Soltis.  2001.  Structural homology and developmental transformations associated with ovary diversification in Lithophragma (Saxifragaceae).  Amer. J. Bot. 88: 196–205.</reference><reference>   Kuzoff, R. K., D. E. Soltis, L. Hufford, and P. S. Soltis.  1999.  Phylogenetic relationships within Lithophragma (Saxifragaceae): Hybridization, allopolyploidy, and ovary diversification.  Syst. Bot. 24: 598–615.</reference><reference>   Taylor, R. L.  1965.  The genus Lithophragma (Saxifragaceae).  Univ. Calif. Publ. Bot. 37: 1–122.</reference></references><key><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Leaves palmately compound, 3-foliolate; seeds spiny</statement><determination>1.   Lithophragma maximum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Leaves unlobed or lobed, or 3-foliolate; seeds smooth, wrinkled, tuberculate, or rough.</statement><next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2.</statement_id><statement>Stigma papillae in narrow subapical band; seeds smooth or wrinkled.</statement><next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3.</statement_id><statement>Leaf blades light green; cauline leaves 3-lobed, appearing pinnatifid; flowers persistent, slightly pendulous; racemes erect; petals 5–7-lobed; ovaries to</statement><determination>2.   Lithophragma tenellum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3.</statement_id><statement>Leaf blades dark green or reddish green; cauline leaves 3-foliolate or 3-lobed; flowers deciduous if unfertilized, horizontal; racemes often lax, nodding; petals 3-lobed; ovaries 1/2+ inferior.</statement><next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>4.</statement_id><statement>Hypanthia elongate-obconic, length 3–4 times diam.; petals pink; flowers fragrant</statement><determination>3.   Lithophragma trifoliatum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>4.</statement_id><statement>Hypanthia obconic to obconic-elongate, length 2 times diam.; petals usually white, sometimes pink; flowers not fragrant.</statement><next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>5.</statement_id><statement>Cauline leaves 3-foliolate; hypanthia obconic-elongate; petals white or pink, often with prominent venation, 3-lobed, obovate-rhombic, widely spreading, ultimate margins entire; ovaries 1/2+ inferior</statement><determination>4.   Lithophragma parviflorum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>5.</statement_id><statement>Cauline leaves 3-lobed; hypanthia obconic; petals white with obscure venation, usually shallowly 3-lobed, ovate-elliptic, not widely spreading, ultimate margins sometimes with extra tooth, (lobes acute); ovaries</statement><determination>5.   Lithophragma affine</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2.</statement_id><statement>Stigma papillae covering apical surface; seeds tuberculate, tubercles in 3–19 rows, blunt or spinelike.</statement><next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>6.</statement_id><statement>Cauline leaves opposite (1 pair); flowering stems simple; petals unlobed, without serrations at base, ultimate margins entire</statement><determination>6.   Lithophragma cymbalaria</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>6.</statement_id><statement>Cauline leaves alternate; flowering stems often branched; petals lobed or, if unlobed, margins sometimes with serrations at base.</statement><next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>7.</statement_id><statement>Hypanthia broadly campanulate; flowers pendulous, petals partly included, ovate-elliptic, ultimate margins lacerate; flowers ± sessile</statement><determination>7.   Lithophragma campanulatum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>7.</statement_id><statement>Hypanthia narrowly campanulate; flowers horizontal, petals completely exserted, obovate-pandurate, ovate-elliptic, or ovate and palmately 5-lobed, ultimate margins entire; flowers long-pedicellate.</statement><next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>8.</statement_id><statement>Hypanthia with truncate base; petals white, simple or 3–7-lobed; flowers not fragrant; racemes lax, nodding; cauline leaves 2–10; ovaries superior</statement><determination>8.   Lithophragma heterophyllum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>8.</statement_id><statement>Hypanthia with acute, obtuse, or hemispheric base; petals white or pink, unlobed, serrately 3–5-lobed, or 5-lobed; flowers sometimes fragrant; racemes erect; cauline leaves 2–4; ovaries to 1/2 inferior.</statement><next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>9.</statement_id><statement>Plants usually robust; leaves usually unlobed or 3–5-lobed; petals white, unlobed or 3–5-lobed with serrations at base; inflorescences 2(–3)-branched, 3–5(–25)-flowered racemes, flowers rarely replaced with bulbils</statement><determination>9.   Lithophragma bolanderi corymbose; flowers sometimes replaced with bulbils</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
