<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>6.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Lithophragma</genus_name>
    <species_name>cymbalaria</species_name>
    <species_authority>Torrey &amp; A. Gray</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 585.  1840  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Mission woodland star</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Tellima</genus_name>
    <species_name>cymbalaria</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Torrey &amp; A. Gray) Steudel</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants slender.  Flowering stems simple, 20–40 cm.  Leaves in basal rosette and cauline, basal weakly 3-lobed, cauline (2), opposite, (1 pair), deeply 3-lobed, reduced, similar to basal; stipules narrow, not decurrent on petiole, (margins fimbriate); petiole to 9 cm; blade dark green or reddish green, reniform, (base ligulate), surfaces sparsely hairy.  Inflorescences solitary flowers or 1–3, (lax), nodding, 2–5(–8)-flowered racemes, simple, (10–40 cm).  Pedicels 1.5–2 times longer than hypanthium.  Flowers persistent, fragrant, vertical; hypanthium turbinate, elongating in fruit, open at throat, (length 2 times diam.); sepals erect, becoming wide-spreading after anthesis, triangular; petals (exserted), widely spreading, white, ovate, narrowly clawed, unlobed, (bowl-shaped), 4–8 mm, ultimate margins entire; ovary 1/2 inferior; styles included in fruit; stigma papillae apical.  Seeds 0.4 mm, tuberculate (tubercles in 3–19 rows, blunt or spinelike).  2n = 14 + 1.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering Mar–Apr</phenology>
  <habitat>Shady oak-manzanita/arbutus woodland, mountainous regions, drainage courses</habitat>
  <elevation>0–2000 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Lithophragma cymbalaria is the only species of the genus with a single pair of opposite cauline leaves.  It shows a high degree of self-compatibility, with abundant seeds produced; it may produce abundant bulbils.  It is found from Stanislaus County to Santa Barbara County including the northern Channel Islands.</discussion>
</treatment>
