<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>7.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Lithophragma</genus_name>
    <species_name>campanulatum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Howell</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. N.W. Amer.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>200.  1898 (as campanulata)  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Siskiyou Mountain woodland star</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Lithophragma</genus_name>
    <species_name>laciniatum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Eastwood ex Small &amp; Rydberg</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants slender to robust.  Flowering stems often branched, 25–45 cm.  Leaves in basal rosette and cauline, basal 3-lobed, cauline (1–2), 3-lobed, reduced, more finely dissected than basal; stipules small, not decurrent on petiole, (margins raggedly fimbriate); petiole 4–8 cm; blade dark green or reddish green, orbiculate, (base rounded), surfaces moderately hairy.  Inflorescences 1–3, (lax), erect, 2–11-flowered racemes, sometimes branched, (10–25 cm).  Pedicels shorter than hypanthium, (flowers ± sessile).  Flowers persistent, fragrant, pendulous; hypanthium broadly campanulate, elongating slightly in fruit, throat not constricted, (length 2 times diam.); sepals erect in bud, widely spreading after anthesis, triangular; petals (partly included), spreading, white, ovate-elliptic, lamina tonguelike, narrowly clawed, palmately lobed, 3–7 mm, ultimate margins lacerate; ovary superior; styles well exserted in fruit; stigma papillae apical.  Seeds 0.6 mm, tuberculate (tubercles in 3–19 distinct rows, blunt).</description>
  <phenology>Flowering Apr–Jul</phenology>
  <habitat>Well-drained, moist, semishaded slopes with northern exposure, oak-coniferous woodlands</habitat>
  <elevation>100–2200 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Lithophragma campanulatum is known from the Siskiyou Mountains, adjacent Klamath and Cascade mountains, and adjacent Sierra Nevada in northern California and southern Oregon.</discussion>
</treatment>
