<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Elizabeth Fortson Wells,Patrick E. Elvander†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">SAXIFRAGACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="C. V. Morton" date="unknown">BENSONIELLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Leafl. W. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 181.  1965  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SAXIFRAGACEAE;genus BENSONIELLA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Gilbert Thereon Benson, 1896–1928, Stanford University botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, not rhizomatous, not stoloniferous; caudex slender, scaly.  Flowering stems erect or ascending, leafless, 19–45 cm, stipitate-glandular.  Leaves in basal rosette; stipules present; petiole long stipitate-glandular; blade orbiculate to cordate, 5–9-lobed, sinuses relatively shallow, base cordate, ultimate margins unevenly crenate, apex rounded, surfaces long stipitate-glandular along veins abaxially, sparsely long stipitate-glandular adaxially; venation palmate.  Inflorescences spikelike racemes, from axillary buds of basal rosette, 15–30-flowered, ebracteate.  Flowers slightly bilaterally symmetric, base gibbous on abaxial side; hypanthium 1/3 adnate to ovary proximally, free from ovary 0.5–0.8 mm, yellowish white to green; sepals 5, yellowish white to green; petals absent or 5, purple or pink; nectary tissue not seen or inconspicuous; stamens 5, opposite sepals; filaments filiform; ovary 1/3 inferior, 1-locular; placentation parietal; styles 2; stigmas 2.  Capsules 2-beaked.  Seeds dark brown, oblong to ellipsoid, smooth.  x = 7.</description>
  <number>7.</number>
  <discussion>Bensonia Abrams &amp; Bacigalupi, Contr. Dudley Herb. 1: 95, plate 5, fig. 1.  1929, not Buckman 1845 (fossil)</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1: w United States.</discussion>
  <discussion>Although the floral morphology of Bensoniella is quite distinctive, vegetative similarities suggest a connection with the otherwise equally distinctive genus Mitella.  Molecular data (D. E. Soltis et al. 1990), as well as karyotype analysis (Soltis 1988), clearly show a close relationship between the genera.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
