<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">saxifragaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">heuchera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Bartling" date="1838">parviflora</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Index Seminum (Göttingen)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1838: 4.  1838  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family saxifragaceae;genus heuchera;species parviflora</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs acaulescent; caudex branched or unbranched.  Flowering stems 9–45 cm, short to long stipitate-glandular, viscid.  Leaves: petiole usually long stipitate-glandular, some-times short stipitate-glandular; blade (often purple abaxially), reniform to orbiculate, shallowly 5–7-lobed, 3–13 cm, base cordate, lobes rounded, margins crenate, apex obtuse, surfaces short or long stipitate-glandular abaxially, short stipitate-glandular adaxially, viscid.  Inflorescences diffuse.  Flowers: hypanthium radially symmetric, free to 0.3 mm, white or pink, obconic, 1.2–3.2 mm, short or moderately long stipitate-glandular; sepals erect, green-tipped, equal, 0.5–1.3 mm, apex rounded; petals reflexed, white or pink, narrowly oblanceolate, unlobed, 1.5–3.5 mm, margins entire; stamens exserted 1.2–3.2 mm; styles exserted 1–3 mm, 1.5–4 mm, to 0.1 mm diam.  Capsules ovoid, 2–5.7 mm, (minutely stipitate-glandular or glabrous), beaks divergent, not papillose.  Seeds dark brown, ovoid, 0.4–0.6 mm, smooth.</description>
  <description type="morphology">United States.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora): United States.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>United States.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Little-flower alum-root</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The specific epithet, parviflora, is similar to that of another species, Heuchera parvifolia, but these two species are distinct and have different legitimate names.  The varieties of H. parviflora are not sympatric.  The species merits phylogenetic study.  The Blackfoot Indians applied a poultice of the pounded root to sores and swellings (D. E. Moerman 1998).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles and hypanthia sparsely to densely long stipitate-glandular; leaf blades sparsely to densely long stipitate-glandular abaxially, hairs 0.7–</description>
      <determination>3a.   Heuchera parviflora var. parviflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petioles and hypanthia densely short stipitate- glandular; leaf blades densely short stipitate-glandular abaxially, hairs to 0.6 mm</description>
      <determination>3b.   Heuchera parviflora var. puberula</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
