<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">saxifragaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">heuchera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas ex Lindley" date="1830">micrantha</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Edwards’s Bot. Reg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>15: plate 1302.  1830  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family saxifragaceae;genus heuchera;species micrantha</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs caulescent; caudex branched.  Flowering stems 6–57 cm, short to long stipitate-glandular or glabrous, viscid.  Leaves: petiole glabrous or sparsely to densely short to long stipitate-glandular; blade orbic-ulate to polygonal, shallowly to deeply 5–7(–9)-lobed, 2.5–10 cm, base cordate, lobes rounded, margins dentate, apex rounded or obtuse, surfaces glabrous or short to long stipitate-glandular, viscid.  Inflorescences diffuse.  Flowers: hypanthium radially symmetric, free to 1.5 mm, greenish white, often tinged with red, obconic to hemispheric, broadly turbinate, or campanulate, 1–4.9 mm, long stipitate-glandular, sometimes short stipitate-glandular proximally; sepals spreading to nearly erect, green- or red-tipped, equal, 0.5–1.8 mm, apex rounded to acute or mucronate; petals often coiled, white or pale pink, oblanceolate, (narrowly clawed), unlobed, 1.6–3.3 mm (2–3 times as long as sepals), margins entire; stamens exserted to 3 mm; styles exserted to 2.5 mm, 0.2–4.2 mm, to 0.1 mm diam.  Capsules ovoid, 3–8.5 mm, beaks divergent, not papillose.  Seeds black, broadly ellipsoid, (not curved), 0.5–0.8 mm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">w North America.</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Crevice alum-root</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 5 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The Skagit Indians rubbed pounded plants of Heuchera micrantha on hair to make it grow and applied it to cuts.  The Thompson Indians used a mashed poultice of this root mixed with Douglas fir pitch for wounds.  Chewed leaves and roots were spat on sores or wounds.  Infusions of roots were taken for liver trouble and sore throat.  Small, peeled, cleaned root pieces were chewed for mouth sores and gum boils (D. E. Moerman 1998).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades orbiculate to pentagonal, shallowly lobed</description>
      <determination>4a.   Heuchera micrantha var. micrantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades pentagonal or heptagonal, deeply lobed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences short stipitate-glandular; pet-ioles short stipitate-glandular or sparsely long stipitate-glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypanthia hemispheric, 1 times long as wide; petals 0.4–1.4 mm wide</description>
      <determination>4b.   Heuchera micrantha var. macropetala</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypanthia obconic, 1.4 times longer than wide; petals 0.2–0.6 mm wide</description>
      <determination>4c.   Heuchera micrantha var. erubescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences long stipitate-glandular; petioles short to long stipitate-glandular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypanthia long stipitate-glandular, sepal apex rounded to acute</description>
      <determination>4d.   Heuchera micrantha var. hartwegii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypanthia sparsely long stipitate-glandular, sepal apex acute to mucronate</description>
      <determination>4e.   Heuchera micrantha var. diversifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
