<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>9.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Heuchera</genus_name>
        <species_name>caroliniana</species_name>
        <species_authority>(Rosendahl, Butters &amp; Lakela) E. F. Wells</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Rhodora </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>81: 575. 1979 ,</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <common_name>Carolina alum-root</common_name>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
        <genus_name>Heuchera</genus_name>
        <species_name>americana</species_name>
        <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
        <variety_name>caroliniana</variety_name>
        <variety_authority>Rosendahl, Butters &amp; Lakela</variety_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>Minnesota Stud. Pl. Sci. </publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>2: 59. 1936</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Herbs acaulescent; caudex branched. Flowering stems leafy, 30–105 cm, short
        stipitate-glandular. Leaves: petiole glabrous or short stipitate-glandular; blade broadly
        ovate, shallowly 5-lobed, 3–10.5 cm, base cordate or nearly truncate, lobes rounded or
        ovate, margins dentate, apex acute or obtuse, surfaces glabrous or minutely
        stipitate-glandular on veins abaxially, glabrous or short stipitate-glandular adaxially.
        Inflorescences diffuse. Flowers: hypanthium weakly bilaterally symmetric, free 1.3–2.5 mm,
        green, subglobose, abruptly inflated distal to adnation to ovary, 2.8–4.5 mm, short
        stipitate-glandular; sepals erect, green-tipped, equal, 0.4–1.5 mm, apex rounded; petals
        erect, white or pink, broadly spatulate, unlobed, 0.6–1 mm, margins entire; stamens exserted
        0.2–1.5 mm; styles included from 1 mm to exserted 1.1 mm, 1–3.5 mm, to 0.1 mm diam; (stigmas
        from 0.5 mm included to 1.1 mm exserted). Capsules ovoid, 4–7 mm, beaks divergent, not
        papillose. Seeds dark brown, ellipsoid, 0.5–0.8 mm. 2n = 14.</description>
    <phenology>Flowering Apr–Jun</phenology>
    <habitat> Rich upland woods on base-saturated substrates, basic dikes and basic rock
        outcroppings</habitat>
    <elevation> 30–300 m</elevation>
    <us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution> Va.</us_distribution>
    <discussion>The geographic range of Heuchera caroliniana is contiguous with and appears to be a
        southern extension of that of H. pubescens. Heuchera americana var. americana occurs in
        counties adjacent to the range of H. caroliniana but they are sympatric only along the
        boundary; intergradation between the two is infrequent. Mixed populations of H. caroliniana
        and H. americana var. americana have not been seen.</discussion>
</treatment>
