<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">GROSSULARIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Richardson" date="unknown">hudsonianum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Franklin et al.,  Narr. Journey Polar Sea ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 734.  1823  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family GROSSULARIACEAE;genus Ribes;species hudsonianum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas" date="unknown">hudsonianum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Douglas) Janczewski" date="unknown">petiolare</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ribes;species hudsonianum;variety petiolare;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">petiolare</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ribes;species petiolare;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 0.5–2 m.  Stems erect or ascending (no short shoots), sparsely to densely glandular throughout with yellow, shiny, sessile, crystalline, round glands; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole (1–)2.7–9.5 cm, glabrous or hairy, with scattered, yellow, sessile, round glands; blade reniform to orbiculate, 3-lobed, 2 proximal segments less deeply and very unequally lobed (rarely equally 5-lobed), cleft usually less than 1/2 to midrib, 2–12(–13.3) cm, base deeply cordate, surfaces with yellow, sessile, round glands abaxially, otherwise glabrous or copiously hairy abaxially, sparsely hairy adaxially, lobes broadly deltate, margins coarsely bicrenate-dentate, apex acute.  Inflorescences ascending to spreading, 20–50-flowered racemes, 3–17 cm, axis thinly villous, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels jointed, 0.6–8(–11) mm, short-villous, short stipitate-glandular; bracts lanceolate to linear, 0.5–3 mm, pubescent.  Flowers: hypanthium white or green, saucer-shaped, widely flared, 0.6–1.5 mm, with sparse to dense, yellow, sessile glands and densely crisped-pubescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially; sepals not overlapping, widely spreading, white, triangular to ovate-lanceolate or oblong-elliptic, 3.4–7 mm; petals widely separated, erect to spreading, white or pinkish, oblong, becoming cuneate-flabelliform and obscurely 3-lobed distally, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 0.9–2 mm; nectary disc pale green, thin, partially covering ovary; stamens as long as petals; filaments linear, 1–1.1 mm, glabrous; anthers maroon, sometimes cream, oval, 0.4–1 mm, apex with small-holed callus, sessile- or stipitate-glandular; ovary sessile-glandular, stipitate-glandular, or sparsely hairy, rarely glabrous; styles connate 1/2+ their lengths, 2 mm, glabrous.  Berries bitter, not palatable, black, ± glaucous, subglobose, 5.5–12 mm, glabrous except for yellow, sessile glands.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering Apr–Aug</description>
  <description type="morphology">Stream banks, moist woods, thickets at edges of mountain meadows, treed bogs, swamps, shaded rock outcrops, deciduous, mixed, and coniferous forests on moist to wet organic and mineral soils</description>
  <description type="morphology">300–3300 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alta.</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Man.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Sask.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Yukon</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Colo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Idaho</description>
  <description type="morphology">Iowa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mich.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Minn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nev.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Utah</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wyo.</description>
  <number>7.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Wild</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">or northern or western black</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">or Hudson Bay</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">or stinking currant</other_name>
  <discussion>Plants of Ribes hudsonianum with leaf blades that are pubescent abaxially and mostly lack sessile glands, and have ovaries with sessile glands, have been recognized as var. hudsonianum; those with leaf blades that are shaggy-hairy abaxially and sessile-glandular, and have ovaries lacking such glands, have been named var. petiolare.  Variety hudsonianum has a more northern distribution; var. petiolare is western.  Where their ranges overlap, for instance in Saskatoon, pubescence density varies continuously and does not correlate with presence or absence of glands (V. L. Harms, pers. comm.).</discussion>
  <discussion>Ribes hudsonianum is a major host of blister rust; in early literature it is referred to as R. petiolare (E. P. Van Arsdel and B. W. Geils 2004).  It has a strong, sweetish, unpleasant odor, and bears its leaves on long shoots.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
