<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">saxifragaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">heuchera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rydberg in N. L. Britton et al." date="1905">abramsii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in N. L. Britton et al.,  N. Amer. Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>22: 109.  1905  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family saxifragaceae;genus heuchera;species abramsii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs subcaulescent; caudex branched.  Flowering stems 6–15 cm, short stipitate-glandular.  Leaves: petiole glabrous or short stipitate-glandular and scattered medium stipitate-glandular; blade ovate, deeply 5-lobed, 0.5–2 cm, base truncate or shallowly cordate, lobes rounded, margins dentate, apex obtuse, surfaces short stipitate-glandular abaxially, sparsely long stipitate-glandular adaxially.  Inflorescences dense.  Flowers: hypanthium strongly bilaterally symmetric, free 1.5–2 mm on adaxial side, reddish purple, cylindric, 4–5 mm, short stipitate-glandular proximally, medium stipitate-glandular distally; sepals spreading, green-tipped, unequal, 1.2–1.5 mm, apex obtuse or rounded; petals spreading, white, spatulate or oblanceolate, rarely linear, unlobed, 1.5–2.5 mm (equaling or longer than sepals), margins entire; stamens barely included to 1.5 mm exserted; styles exserted 1.5–2 mm, 2.5–3 mm, 0.1+ mm diam.  Capsules ovoid, 3.5–5 mm, beaks divergent, not papillose.  Seeds dark brown, ellipsoid, 0.6 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jul-Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rocky soil in red fir forest;</description>
  <description type="elevation">2800-3100 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.</description>
  <number>17.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">San Gabriel alum-root</other_name>
  <discussion>Heuchera abramsii occurs in the San Antonio Mountains and the eastern part of the San Gabriel Mountains, San Bernardino and Los Angeles counties.  It closely resembles H. brevistaminea, H. caespitosa, H. elegans, and H. pulchella.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
