<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">nigrum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 201.  1753  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species nigrum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 1–2 m.  Stems erect, glandular and puberulent or nearly glabrous; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 1–4 cm, pubescent, sometimes with longer setose hairs basally; blade reniform, 3–5-lobed, cleft nearly to midrib, 5–10 cm, base cordate, surfaces with shiny, resinous glands, lobes broadly ovate, margins irregularly serrate, apex acute.  Inflorescences pendent, 4–10-flowered racemes, 3–5 cm, axis pubescent, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels jointed, 2–10 mm, glabrous or finely pubescent to lanate; bracts ovate, 0.5–2 mm, pubescent.  Flowers: hypanthium green, cup-shaped or short-campanulate, 3–4 mm, densely pubescent or tomentose; sepals not overlapping, reflexed, greenish or pinkish abaxially, suffused with purple adaxially, oblong, 5–7 mm; petals nearly connivent, erect, white to reddish, bluntly deltate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 1.5–3 mm; nectary disc prominent, green or purplish, circular, covering ovary; stamens slightly longer than petals; filaments linear, 2–2.5 mm, glabrous with some glands; anthers white, sagittate, 1 mm, apex blunt; ovary pubescent, sessile-glandular; styles connate nearly to stigmas, 3 mm, very finely hairy.  Berries sweet-tasting, black, globose, 12–15 mm, glabrous with some sessile glands.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May-Jun.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Wet meadows, disturbed streamsides, anthropogenic habitats;</description>
  <description type="elevation">100-300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; N.B., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que.; Conn., Ill., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., N.H., N.J., N.Y., Ohio, Vt., Wis.; Eurasia.</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Garden black currant</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">gadellier noir</other_name>
  <discussion>Ribes nigrum is the source of the cultivated black currant.  It has a strong, unpleasant odor.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
