<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">saxifragaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">heuchera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Wheelock" date="1890">novamexicana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 200.  1890 (as nova-mexicana) ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family saxifragaceae;genus heuchera;species novamexicana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs acaulescent; caudex branched.  Flowering stems 30–50 cm, short or long stipitate-glandular.  Leaves: petiole glabrous or long stipitate-glandular; blade reniform or rounded-cordate, shallowly 5-lobed, 2–6 cm, base cordate, lobes rounded, margins dentate, apex obtuse, surfaces long stipitate-glandular on veins abaxially, glabrous or short stipitate-glandular adaxially.  Inflorescences dense.  Flowers: hypanthium radially symmetric, free 1–1.8 mm, cream or yellowish green, broadly campanulate, 3–5 mm, short stipitate-glandular; sepals erect or incurved, green-tipped, equal, 0.6–1.2 mm, apex ovate; petals usually erect, white, elliptic, (not clawed), unlobed, 0.5–1 mm, margins entire; stamens included 0.5 mm; (filaments erect or incurved distally, equaling and not concealed by anthers); styles included 0.5–1 mm, 0.5–1 mm, 0.1+ mm diam.  Capsules ovoid, 5.5–6.5 mm, beaks divergent, not papillose.  Seeds dark brown, asymmetrically ellipsoid or convex-fusiform, 0.5 mm.  2n = 14.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Jun.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shaded rocky ledges and outcrops;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1800-2200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ariz., N.Mex.</description>
  <number>28.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Range alum-root</other_name>
  <discussion>Heuchera novamexicana occurs in the mountains of Arizona and New Mexico.  Populations with glabrous petioles may be found in the Organ Mountains of New Mexico; elsewhere, long stipitate-glandular petioles are more common in the species.</discussion>
  <discussion>The Navajo Indians took a decoction of roots of Heuchera novamexicana for internal pain.  They applied a poultice of split roots to infected sores, swellings, and fractures, and used the plant as a panacea or “life medicine” (D. E. Moerman 1998).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
