<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>9.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>bracteosum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Douglas</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in W. J. Hooker,  Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 233.  1832  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Stink currant</common_name>
  <description>Plants 1–4 m.  Stems erect, with dense, yellowish, shiny, sessile, crystalline, round glands, sparsely pubescent throughout; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 2–10 cm, sparsely pubescent; blade ovate, deeply 5–7-lobed, cleft 1/2+ to midrib, (1.5–)2–10(–22) cm, base cordate, surfaces with yellow, dull, sessile glands and sparse hairs abaxially, with yellow, shiny, sessile glands and glabrous adaxially, lobes with main segments ovate-lanceolate, margins 1–2 times sharply serrate, apex acute, shallowly lobed.  Inflorescences ascending to erect, 20–50-flowered racemes, (10–)15–30 cm, axis sparsely pubescent, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels jointed, 5–12 mm, pubescent and glandular; bracts conspicuous, proximal ones ovate, lobed, distal ones narrowly oblong, unlobed, (3–)4–5 mm, sparsely glandular and pubescent.  Flowers: hypanthium green, saucer-shaped, widely flared, 0.5–1.5 mm, ± pubescent and sparsely glandular abaxially, glabrous adaxially; sepals nearly to somewhat overlapping, spreading, brownish purple to greenish or sometimes nearly white, ovate-lanceolate to oblong-lanceolate, 3–5 mm; petals widely separated, erect, white, cuneate-flabelliform, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 1 mm; nectary disc wine red, thick, lobed, covering and submerging ovary; stamens slightly longer than petals; filaments linear to slightly broader at base, 1 mm, glabrous; anthers white, transversely oblong-cordate, 0.5 mm, broader than long, apex shallowly notched; ovary somewhat hairy and densely sessile-glandular; styles connate 1/4–1/2 their lengths, 1 mm, glabrous or hairy.  Berries bland, black, subglobose, 8–10 mm, glandular.  2n = 16.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering Feb–Jun</phenology>
  <habitat>Stream banks, moist woods, floodplains, shorelines, thickets, avalanche tracks</habitat>
  <elevation>0–1700 m</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Ribes bracteosum occurs along the Pacific Coast from southeastern Alaska to northern California.  Its thin leaves have a sweetish, disagreeable odor and the conspicuous bracts bear acicular, mostly persistent processes near the base along the slightly winged, stipular margins.</discussion>
</treatment>
