<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Douglas E. Soltis,Walter S. Judd,Pamela S. Soltis,Patrick E. Elvander†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">saxifragaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey &amp; A. Gray" date="1840">TOLMIEA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 582.  1840, name conserved  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family saxifragaceae;genus TOLMIEA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For William F. Tolmie, 1812–1886, surgeon for Hudson’s Bay Company at Fort Vancouver]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, rhizomatous, not stoloniferous; rhizomes sometimes branched, scaly; caudex not cormlike, with persistent leaf bases.  Flowering stems erect, leafy, 2.5–70 cm, sparsely to moderately, short to long stipitate-glandular.  Leaves in basal rosette and cauline; cauline leaves reduced distally, vegetative shoots sometimes from axillary buds of cauline leaves; stipules present; petiole stipitate-glandular, (adventitious buds usually produced at apices of petioles of rosette and cauline leaves, sometimes forming plantlets); blade ovate, shallowly 5–9-lobed, base cordate, ultimate margins strongly to obscurely, irregularly serrate to nearly dentate, each tooth ending in glandular hair, apex acute (rarely obtuse), surfaces subglabrous to stipitate-glandular; venation palmate.  Inflorescences racemes, from axillary buds in rosette, 10–150-flowered, bracteate.  (Pedicels with subtending bracts.)  Flowers bilaterally symmetric; hypanthium adnate to ovary only at base for less than 1 mm (ovary appearing superior), free from ovary for 4–5 mm, greenish, ± split to base, (cylindric-funnelform); sepals (persistent), 5, green with variable development of red-purple stripes, (unequal, slightly gibbous at base, stipitate-glandular, 3 dorsal sepals ovate- to elliptic-triangular, apex obtuse to rounded-mucronate, 2 ventral-lateral sepals narrowly ovate-triangular to oblong-triangular, apex acute to acuminate); petals 4, (recurved), greenish to brown-purple, (± linear); nectariferous tissue proximal to stamens; stamens 3, (inserted at apex of hypanthium opposite dorsal sepals, slightly exserted); filaments filiform; ovary superior, 1-locular, (oblong, turbinate, apex 2-cleft, stipitate-glandular), carpels connate proximally; placentation parietal; styles 2; stigmas 2.  Capsules 2-beaked, (ovoid, turbinate).  Seeds brown to nearly black, subglobose, distinctly muricate.  x = 7.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw North America.</description>
  <number>11.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pig-a-back plant</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Although morphologically similar, as reviewed by D. E. Soltis et al. (2007), diploid and tetraploid Tolmiea each meets the criteria for all of the commonly used species concepts: they are reproductively isolated, so they are biological species; they are distinct evolutionary lineages, so the two cytotypes meet the expectations of the evolutionary species concept; each is monophyletic, so both can be considered phylogenetic (apomorphic) species; they are diagnosable on the basis of chromosome number and molecular characters, thus fitting the phylogenetic/diagnosability species concept; and morphological characters distinguish the two cytotypes (although these may be considered cryptic by some), hence they are taxonomic species.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Soltis, D. E.  1984b.  Autopolyploidy in Tolmiea menziesii (Saxifragaceae).  Amer. J. Bot. 71: 1171–1174.</reference>
    <reference>Soltis, D. E. and P. S. Soltis.  1988.  Electrophoretic evidence for tetrasomic inheritance in Tolmiea menziesii (Saxifragaceae).  Heredity 60: 375–382.</reference>
    <reference>Soltis, D. E. and P. S. Soltis.  1989.  Genetic consequences of autopolyploidy in Tolmiea (Saxifragaceae).  Evolution 43: 586–594.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves not or only slightly longer than wide, i.e., length-width quotient usually</description>
      <determination>1.   Tolmiea menziesii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves distinctly longer than wide, i.e., length-width quotient 0.8–1.4 (average 1, excluding length of basal lobes); plantlets on leaves sporadically produced</description>
      <determination>2.   Tolmiea diplomenziesii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
