<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>6.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Mitella</genus_name>
    <species_name>ovalis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 32.  1887  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Oval-leaf mitrewort</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Pectiantia</genus_name>
    <species_name>ovalis</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Greene) Rydberg</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants not stoloniferous or, rarely, stoloniferous.  Flowering stems 15–35(–40) cm.  Leaves: petiole 1.2–8(–11.3) cm, short stipitate-glandular and densely long stipitate-glandular, longer hairs spreading or retrorse, reddish brown; blade cordate-ovate to cordate-oblong, longer than wide, 2.7–7 × 1.5–5.4 cm, margins shallowly 5-, 7- or 9-lobed, doubly crenate-dentate or dentate, glabrous or irregularly ciliate, apex of terminal lobe acute to obtuse, surfaces sparsely short stipitate-glandular and long stipitate-glandular to sparsely long stipitate-glandular along primary veins abaxially, long stipitate-glandular adaxially; cauline leaves absent.  Inflorescences 1–3(–6), closely 20–60-flowered, 1(–2) flowers per node, not secund, 15–35(–40) cm, subglabrous or short stipitate-glandular and sparsely long  stipitate-glandular proximally, short stipitate-glandular and, rarely, long stipitate-glandular distally.  Pedicels 1–2 mm, short stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium shallowly saucer-shaped, 0.8–1 × 2–3.5 mm; sepals spreading to recurved, greenish, triangular, 0.7–1 × 0.9–1.9 mm; petals greenish yellow, 3–9-lobed, 1.5–2 mm, lobes linear, lateral lobes spreading; stamens 5, opposite sepals; filaments white, 0.1–0.3 mm; anthers 0.1–0.2 × 0.2–0.4 mm; ovary nearly completely inferior; styles divergent, flattened, 0.2–0.3 mm; stigmas 2-lobed.  Seeds reddish purple or blackish, 0.8–1.1 mm, pitted.  2n = 14.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering Mar–Jul</phenology>
  <habitat>Moist woods, stream margins, wet banks</habitat>
  <elevation>0–1500 m</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Mitella ovalis occurs from Vancouver Island and extreme southwest mainland of British Columbia south to Marin County, California.</discussion>
</treatment>
