<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Elizabeth Fortson Wells,Patrick E. Elvander†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">SAXIFRAGACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">BOLANDRA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 341.  1868  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SAXIFRAGACEAE;genus BOLANDRA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For Henry Nicholas Bolander, 1831–1897, physician and collector for California State Geological Survey]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, not rhizomatous or stoloniferous; caudex erect, slender, bearing bulbils at base.  Flowering stems erect to ascending, leafy, 10–40 cm, stipitate-glandular.  Leaves in basal rosette and cauline; cauline leaves conspicuous, reduced and bractlike distally; stipules present; petiole glabrous; blade reniform to orbiculate, 5–13-lobed, base cordate, ultimate margins irregularly serrate to crenate-dentate, apex obtuse to acute, surfaces glabrous; venation palmate.  Inflorescences compound, dichasial cymes, terminal from terminal bud in basal rosette, 5–18-flowered, bracteate.  Flowers: hypanthium free from ovary, greenish to purple; sepals 5, greenish to purple, (narrowly triangular to triangular-ovate); petals 5, greenish with purple margins or reddish purple to dark purple; nectary tissue not seen; stamens 5; filaments filiform; ovary nearly superior, 2-locular, ovaries connate 1/4–1/2 their lengths; placentation axile; styles 2; stigmas 2.  Capsules 2-beaked.  Seeds dark brown, prismatic (or angular) and fusiform, minutely tuberculate.  x = 7.</description>
  <description type="morphology">w United States.</description>
  <number>16.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Both the monograph by R. J. Gornall and B. A. Bohm (1985) and the molecular systematic work of D. E. Soltis et al. (1993) support a close relationship among Bolandra, Boykinia, and Suksdorfia.  Other genera that appear to be closely related to these are Jepsonia, Sullivantia, and Telesonix (Soltis et al.).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades deeply lobed, ultimate margins crenate-dentate; ovaries connate proximally</description>
      <determination>1.   Bolandra californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades shallowly lobed, ultimate margins serrate; ovaries connate proximally 1/4 their lengths; petals usually reddish purple to dark purple, 7–12(–14) mm</description>
      <determination>2.   Bolandra oregana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
