<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Douglas E. Soltis</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">SAXIFRAGACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey &amp; A. Gray" date="unknown">SULLIVANTIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. J. Sci. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>42: 22.  1842  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SAXIFRAGACEAE;genus SULLIVANTIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For William S. Sullivant, 1803–1873, American bryologist, who collected the type specimen in Ohio]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>17.</number>
  <discussion>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Perhaps the most noteworthy features of the distribution of Sullivantia species are their disjunct distributions and the restriction of most populations to unglaciated areas near Pleistocene glacial margins (D. E. Soltis 1991).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Rosendahl, C. O.  1927.  A revision of the genus Sullivantia.  Minnesota Stud. Pl. Sci. 1: 401–427.</reference>
    <reference>Soltis, D. E.  1980b.  Flavonoids of Sullivantia: Taxonomic implications at the generic level within the Saxifraginae.  Biochem. Syst. &amp; Ecol. 8: 149–151.</reference>
    <reference>Soltis, D. E.  1981.  Variation in hybrid fertility among the disjunct populations and species of Sullivantia (Saxifragaceae).  Canad. J. Bot. 59: 1174–1180.</reference>
    <reference>Soltis, D. E.  1982.  Allozymic variability in Sullivantia (Saxifragaceae).  Syst. Bot. 7: 26–34.</reference>
    <reference>Soltis, D. E.  1991.  A revision of Sullivantia (Saxifragaceae).  Brittonia 43: 27–53.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypanthia tubular-campanulate, portion distal to adnation to ovary not marked by conspicuous flaring; primary and higher-order inflorescence branches ascending relative to central axis; ovaries ca. 1/2 inferior; seeds usually tan, rarely red-brown, main body</description>
      <determination>1.   Sullivantia sullivantii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypanthia turbinate-campanulate, portion distal to adnation to ovary marked by conspicuous flaring; primary and higher-order inflorescence branches usually perpendicular to central axis; ovaries 4/5+ inferior; seeds dark red-brown, main body (excluding winged margins) 0.7–1 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants stoloniferous; petal blades suborbiculate; hypanthia widely turbinate- campanulate, sepals broader than long at apex</description>
      <determination>2.   Sullivantia oregana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not stoloniferous; petal blades ovate to ovate-lanceolate; hypanthia narrowly turbinate-campanulate, sepals not as broad as long at apex</description>
      <determination>3.   Sullivantia hapemanii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
