<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Wiggins" date="1929">canthariforme</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Dudley Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 101, plate 9.  1929 (as canthariformis)  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species canthariforme</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 1–2.5 m.  Stems erect, finely pubescent, stipitate-glandular; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 2.5–3.5 cm, pubescent; blade roundish, 3-lobed, shallowly cleft, 4–6 cm, base cordate, surfaces densely hairy abaxially, with wavy, long, soft hairs adaxially, lobes rounded, margins crenate, with gland-tipped teeth, apex rounded.  Inflorescences erect, spike- or headlike, 15–25-flowered racemes, 3–6 cm, axis densely stipitate-glandular, flowers crowded into distal 1/4–1/3.  Pedicels jointed, 1–2 mm, white-villous; bracts lanceolate, 2–4 mm, white-villous.  Flowers: hypanthium rose-purple, broadly urceolate, 0.5–1 mm, villous-pubescent with some gland-tipped hairs; sepals not to somewhat overlapping, spreading, rose-purple with darker veins, deltate-ovate, 2 mm; petals nearly connivent, erect, pale rose-purple, flabellate to spatulate-obovate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 1 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens nearly as long as petals; filaments linear, 0.5 mm, glabrous; anthers yellow, ovate, 0.2–0.3 mm, apex minutely apiculate; ovary white-villous with some stipitate glands; styles distinct to base, 1 mm, sparsely hairy proximally.  Berries palatability not known, purple, globose-ovoid, 5–6 mm, lanate- or glandular-hairy.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering Feb–Jun</description>
  <description type="morphology">Chaparral</description>
  <description type="morphology">300–1200 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <number>13.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Moreno currant</other_name>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
  <discussion>Ribes canthariforme is endemic to the Cuyamaca-Laguna Mountain region of San Diego County.  It has quite thick leaves.  Thirteen populations are known; nine of those are historic.  About 70 plants have been found in the remaining populations.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
