<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Elizabeth Fortson Wells,Patrick E. Elvander†</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">SAXIFRAGACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Small" date="unknown">SAXIFRAGOPSIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>23: 19, plate 257.  1896  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SAXIFRAGACEAE;genus SAXIFRAGOPSIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Genus Saxifraga and Greek opsis, resemblance]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs rhizomatous, not stoloniferous; rhizome woody, sometimes slightly elongated.  Flowering stems erect, leafless, 6–25 cm, stipitate-glandular, hairs unicellular.  Leaves in basal rosette and cauline; cauline leaves 1–2, reduced distally to sessile bracts; stipules barely expanded petiole bases; petiole jointed distally at attachment to blade, separating early from blade, sparsely stipitate-glandular; blade broadly obovate-cuneate, not lobed, base cuneate, ultimate margins coarsely 7–11-toothed distally, ciliate, apex acute to obtuse, surfaces glabrous or scantily stipitate-glandular; venation palmate.  Inflorescences compact thyrses, terminal from terminal bud in basal rosette, 27–90-flowered, bracteate.  Flowers: hypanthium adnate to ovary in proximal 1/2, free from ovary 0.2 mm, greenish; sepals 5, green; petals 5, white, unlobed; nectary tissue inconspicuous or absent; stamens 10; filaments filiform; ovary 1/2 inferior, 2-locular, carpels connate in proximal 1/4; placentation axile; styles 2, (distinct); stigmas 2.  Capsules 2-beaked.  Seeds brown, ovoid-prismatic, smooth or ribbed.  x = 7.</description>
  <number>21.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1: w United States.</discussion>
  <discussion>Features of Saxifragopsis that make it discordant within the relatively large and diverse genus Saxifraga include the thick, woody rhizome; early separation of the leaf blade from its joint with the petiole; unicellular, glandular trichomes; and beaklike form of the styles having no counterparts in Saxifraga, although that is where the single species of Saxifragopsis is most often placed (P. A. Munz 1968).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
