<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Eastwood" date="1902">indecorum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Calif. Acad. Sci., ser.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3, 2: 243, plate 23, fig. 3a, b.  1902  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species indecorum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants usually deciduous, 1.5–3 m.  Stems erect, densely pubescent and glandular; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 0.5–2.5 cm, with long, glandular hairs at base; blade roundish to pentangular, 3–5-lobed, cleft less than 1/4 to midrib, 1–4 cm, base cordate, surfaces white-tomentose abaxially, hairy and stipitate-glandular adaxially, lobes deltate, margins crenate, apex obtuse.  Inflorescences spreading, 10–25-flowered racemes, 2–5 cm, axis glandular-pubescent, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels jointed, 1–2 mm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular; bracts narrowly lanceolate, 2–4 mm, crisped-puberulent, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium greenish white, narrowly tubular-urceolate, 2.5–5 mm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular; sepals not overlapping, recurved, white, oblong to ovate, 1–2 mm; petals nearly connivent, erect, white, flabellate to spatulate-obovate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 0.5–1 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens nearly as long as petals; filaments broadened at base, ca. 0.2 mm, pubescent; anthers white, ovate, 0.5–0.8 mm, apex minutely apiculate; ovary tomentose, stipitate-glandular; styles connate nearly to stigmas, 3–4 mm, tomentose entire length.  Berries palatability not known, purple, globose, 6–7 mm, hairy, stipitate-glandular.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering Nov-Apr.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Chaparral, coastal sage scrub;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-2000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif.; Mexico (Baja California).</description>
  <number>14.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">White-flowered currant</other_name>
  <discussion>Ribes indecorum occurs from Santa Barbara County south into Baja California.  Its leaves are very rough to the touch and fragrant.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
