<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">saxifragaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">saxifraga</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">bronchialis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 400.  1753  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family saxifragaceae;genus saxifraga;species bronchialis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants mat-forming, (stems trailing), not stoloniferous, rhizomatous.  Leaves basal and cauline, (marcescent, crowded); petiole absent; blade (sometimes reddish), linear or linear-lanceolate to narrowly elliptic, unlobed, 3–15 mm, leathery, margins entire, stiffly, often hooked, white-ciliate, sometimes also glandular-ciliate, apex acute, white spinulose-mucronate (spine 1–1.5 mm), surfaces glabrous, sometimes adaxially sparsely sessile-glandular.  Inflorescences 2–15-flowered cymes or thyrses, sometimes solitary flowers, 5–20 cm, sparsely short stipitate-glandular; bracts sessile.  Flowers: sepals ± erect, (purplish), ovate to triangular, margins eciliate or sparsely glandular, surfaces glabrous or sparsely sessile-glandular; petals yellowish white, purple- or red- to yellow-spotted, oblong to elliptic, 3–7 mm, longer than sepals; ovary superior.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Eurasia; arctic and alpine areas.</description>
  <number>11.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Spotted saxifrage</other_name>
  <discussion>Subspecies 4 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The Saxifraga bronchialis complex, including S. cherlerioides, S. taylorii, S. tricuspidata, and S. vespertina, needs a thorough study.</discussion>
  <discussion>Saxifraga firma Litvinov ex Losina-Losinskaja has been cited for North America; the name belongs in synonymy of a Eurasian subspecies and appears to have been misapplied to North American specimens.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals yellow-spotted, distinctly clawed</description>
      <determination>11a.   Saxifraga bronchialis subsp. funstonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals yellow-spotted proximally, purple- or red-spotted distally, not clawed</description>
      <determination>11b.   Saxifraga bronchialis subsp. austromontana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
