<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>14.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Saxifraga</genus_name>
    <species_name>tricuspidata</species_name>
    <species_authority>Rotbøll</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Skr. Kiøbenhavnske Selsk. Laerd. Elsk.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 446.  1770 (as 3cuspidata)  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Prickly saxifrage</common_name>
  <common_name>saxifrage à trois dents</common_name>
  <description>Plants loosely mat-forming, (stems trailing), not stoloniferous, with elongate caudex or rhizomatous.  Leaves cauline, (marcescent, crowded proximally); petiole absent; blade (often reddish), linear to cuneate, 1–3-lobed or -toothed apically (distal cauline unlobed), rarely all unlobed, (lobes long spinose-mucronate), 5–20 mm, leathery, margins entire, softly glandular-ciliate, (nonsecreting hydathodes present adaxially), apex acute, long spinose-mucronate, surfaces glabrous.  Inflorescences 3–10-flowered cymes, 4–10(–24) cm, white to sparsely pink- to purple-tipped stipitate-glandular; bracts sessile.  Flowers: sepals erect to ascending, (sometimes purplish), triangular-ovate, margins ± glandular-ciliate, surfaces white to purple-tipped stipitate-glandular; petals white to cream, proximally to distally yellow-, orange-, and red-spotted, elliptic to ovate, 4–7 mm, much longer than sepals; ovary superior.  2n = 26.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering late spring–summer</phenology>
  <habitat>Open sandy, gravelly, or rocky sites, forest openings, grassy slopes, rocky ridges, stony tundra</habitat>
  <elevation>0–3000 m</elevation>
  <global_distribution>Greenland</global_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Alta.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Man.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr. (Labr.)</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nunavut</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Sask.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mich.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>The rare, entire-leaved form of Saxifraga tricuspidata can be confused with S. bronchialis; it has glandular-ciliate margins instead of stiffly hooked-ciliate ones.</discussion>
</treatment>
