<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>21.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Saxifraga</genus_name><species_name>rivularis</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 404.  1753,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants (delicate), loosely tufted or matted, (green to purple), stoloniferous, weakly rhizomatous, (with bulbils in axils of basal leaves).  Leaves basal and cauline; petiole ± flattened, 2–30(–50) mm; blade reniform, 3–5(–7)-lobed (lobes rounded, sometimes ± obtuse, distalmost unlobed), (2.6–)3.7–5.2(–7.4) mm, slightly fleshy, margins entire, eciliate or sparsely glandular-ciliate, without lime-secreting hydathodes (with nonsecreting hydathodes at lobe apices), apex acute, surfaces glabrous.  Inflorescences 2–3(–5)-flowered cymes, sometimes solitary flowers, (flowers pedicellate), 1.7–7 cm, glabrous or sparsely to ± densely tangled, pink-tipped stipitate-glandular; bracts (2–3), petiolate, (unlobed or 1–3-lobed, reduced).  Flowers (hypanthium U-shaped in longisection); sepals erect, (sometimes rusty brown), elliptic to ovate, margins eciliate or sparsely glandular-ciliate, glabrous or sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular; petals white, sometimes pink tinged, not spotted, oblong to elliptic, 2–6 mm, to 2–3 times length of sepals; ovary 1/2 inferior.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Subspecies 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> n North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> n Eurasia.</global_distribution><discussion>Some reports of Saxifraga sibirica Linnaeus from Canada are misidentifications of this species.</discussion><key><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Plants wholly green or purple only in inflorescences; hair crosswalls usually without color, rarely pale purple; inflorescences 2.7–7 cm, glabrous or sparsely stipitate-glandular; hypanthia sparsely short stipitate-glandular, hairs 0.1–0.3(–0.4) mm</statement><determination>21a.   Saxifraga rivularis subsp. rivularis</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Plants mostly purple (at least inflorescences); hair crosswalls purple; inflorescences 1.7–3 cm, sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular; hypanthia sparsely to densely long stipitate-glandular, hairs (0.2–)0.3–0.6(–1.1) mm</statement><determination>21b.   Saxifraga rivularis subsp. arctolitoralis</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
