<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Pursh" date="1813">viscosissimum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 163.  1813  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species viscosissimum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">viscosissimum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Janczewski) Janczewski" date="unknown">hallii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ribes;species viscosissimum;variety hallii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 1–2 m.  Stems erect to spreading, soft-pubescent, ± thickly stipitate-glandular, becoming glabrate; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole (0.8–)1–5(–10) cm, pubescent, sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular; blade suborbiculate to reniform, 3- or 5-lobed, cleft 1/4–1/3 to midrib, (1–)2.6–6.5(–8.5) cm, base deeply cordate, surfaces sparsely stipitate-glandular (otherwise nearly glabrous) to downy along veins, copiously soft-pubescent and glandular, lobes rounded, margins irregularly 1 or 2 times coarsely crenate-dentate, apex rounded to broadly acute.  Inflorescences erect to somewhat pendent, (3–)6–17-flowered racemes, 3–10 cm (shorter than leaves), axis copiously pubescent and stipitate-glandular, flowers clustered at end of peduncle.  Pedicels jointed, (2.7–)3.5–10(–12) mm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular; bracts lanceolate to oblanceolate, (5–)6–8.5(–12) mm, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium greenish, greenish yellow, or yellowish white, sometimes strongly pinkish or purplish tinged, campanulate to tubular-campanulate, (4.5–)7–8 mm, sparsely to densely hairy and stipitate-glandular abaxially, glabrous adaxially; sepals not overlapping, spreading at anthesis, becoming erect, whitish green, sometimes tinged with pink or purple, lanceolate-elliptic, (3.5–)4–7 mm; petals connivent, erect, white or cream, obovate-spatulate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 2.5–4 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens nearly as long as petals; filaments broadened at base, 1.2–3 mm, glabrous; anthers cream, oblong-oval, 1–1.8 mm, apex with cup-shaped gland; ovary glabrous or minutely hairy and strongly stipitate-glandular; styles connate nearly to stigmas, 6–9.5 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatable, dark bluish black, ovoid, (8–)10–15 mm, glabrous or ± hairy and stipitate-glandular.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering May–Aug</description>
  <description type="morphology">Along creeks, open to heavily timbered slopes, sagebrush</description>
  <description type="morphology">900–3100 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alta.</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Colo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Idaho</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nev.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Utah</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wyo.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering May-Aug. Along creeks, open to heavily timbered slopes, sagebrush; 900-3100 m; Alta., B.C.; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., Nev., Oreg., Utah, Wash., Wyo.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering May-Aug.</phenology>
      <habitat>Along creeks, open to heavily timbered slopes, sagebrush;</habitat>
      <elevation>900-3100 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Alta., B.C.; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Mont., Nev., Oreg., Utah, Wash., Wyo.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>16.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sticky or mountain currant</other_name>
  <discussion>All parts of Ribes viscosissimum are very fragrant.  Its leaves are thick and rough.  Plants with glabrous or sparsely stipitate-glandular ovaries have been recognized as var. hallii and are found only in California and Oregon.  Plants with strongly stipitate-glandular and softly pubescent ovaries are var. viscosissimum and are more widespread.  W. C. Martin and C. R. Hutchins (1980) indicated that R. viscosissimum is to be expected in New Mexico; no occurrence there has been confirmed.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
