<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas" date="1830">cereum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Hort. Soc. London</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 512.  1830,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species cereum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 0.2–2 m.  Stems spreading or arching to erect, puberulent, sparsely to copiously stipitate-glandular; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole (0.3–) 0.6–1.2(–2.8) cm, glabrous or finely to copiously pubescent; blade almost reniform to broadly cuneate-flabellate, 3–5(–7)-lobed, shallowly cleft, (0.5–) 1–2(–4) cm, base cordate to truncate, surfaces glabrous or copiously pubescent, sparsely stipitate-glandular to downy to conspicuously stipitate-glandular and sessile-glandular, particularly noticeable on margins, lobes rounded, margins coarsely crenate-dentate, apex obtuse.  Inflorescences pendent, solitary flowers or 2–8(–9)-flowered racemes, 1–3 cm, axis finely pubescent, ± sticky with short-stalked to subsessile glands, flowers tightly clustered at end of peduncle.  Pedicels jointed, (0.4–)1–2.2(–3.4) mm, puberulent; bracts flabellate or ovate to obovate, 3–7(–8.8) mm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium white to greenish white with pink tinge, or pinkish white, narrowly tubular, tube widest at base and near throat, 5–9(–9.4) mm, densely hairy and scattered stipitate-glandular abaxially, glabrous adaxially; sepals not overlapping, spreading-recurved, greenish white to white or faintly to strongly pinkish tinged, deltate-ovate, 1–3.2 mm; petals connivent, erect, white to pink, orbiculate or flabellate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 1–2.1 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens shorter than petals, (inserted below petals and completely included in hypanthium tube); filaments linear, 0.5–1.6 mm, glabrous; anthers pale cream-yellow to yellow, oval, 0.6–1.2 mm, apex with small, cup-shaped gland; ovary glabrous or hairy or sparsely to densely pubescent; styles connate nearly to stigmas, 7.5–11.5 mm, proximally hairy or glabrous.  Berries tasteless, dull to bright red or orange-red, ovoid, 5–12 mm, sparsely glandular to glandular.  2n = 16.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <number>17.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Ribes cereum has a notably spicy odor.  The bright green style, which becomes brown with age, is striking.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts truncate to broadly rounded apically; sepals pubescent and stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>17a.   Ribes cereum var. cereum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts acute apically; sepals glabrous or sparsely to densely pubescent, not stipitate-glandular</description>
      <determination>17b.   Ribes cereum var. colubrinum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
