<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Reid V. Moran</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">RHODIOLA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1035.  1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 457.  1754  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus RHODIOLA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek rhodon, rose, alluding to odor of rootstock in R. rosea]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial (dying back in winter to rootstock), not viviparous, 0.3–6 dm, glabrous [pubescent].  Stems a rootstock with apex mostly above ground, erect, spreading, or decumbent, commonly branching to form clumps, fleshy, with brown scalelike [or green] leaves; flowering stems from axils of brown scale-leaves on stout rootstock partly above ground.  Leaves persistent, cauline, alternate, sessile, subclasping basally; blade elliptic to ovate or oblanceolate to linear, obovate, or oblong, laminar (mostly to 1 mm thick), 0.5–5.5 cm, somewhat fleshy, base not spurred, margins entire or toothed; veins not conspicuous.  Inflorescences cymose or spikelike to subcapitate.  Flowers bisexual or unisexual, erect, 4–6-merous; sepals connate basally, all alike (unequal in R. rosea); petals erect or spreading, distinct, greenish, white, rose, dark red, or yellowish; calyx and corolla not circumscissile in fruit; nectaries quadrate to linear; stamens 2 times as many as sepals, epipetalous; filaments mostly adnate to corolla at base; pistils erect, nearly distinct; ovary base straight; styles 2+ times shorter than ovary.  Fruits erect.  Seeds oblanceoloid or pyriform, ribbed, finely cross-ribbed.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America, Eurasia; montane to arctic areas.</description>
  <number>6.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Roseroot</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 40 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>In Rhodiola, inflorescences are borne in axils of scale leaves on the rootstocks, which are partly above ground.  They are thinner and leafier than those of Hylotelephium.  This treatment largely follows R. T. Clausen (1975), except that he made Rhodiola a subgenus of Sedum.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences spikelike or subcapitate, 1–3.5 cm diam.; flowers bisexual; petals greenish or white to rose, 6–13 mm, longer than stamens; beaks of follicles erect</description>
      <determination>1.   Rhodiola rhodantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences corymbose cymes, to 8 cm diam.; flowers mostly unisexual (and plants mostly dioecious); petals yellow to greenish yellow and sometimes red at tips, or dark red and sometimes yellow basally and red apically, 1–5 mm, shorter than stamens; beaks of follicles spreading.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals mostly dark red, sometimes yellowish at base or yellow with apical 1/3 red, in staminate flowers 1.3–1.7 mm wide; leaf blades commonly bright green, sometimes glaucous</description>
      <determination>2.   Rhodiola integrifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals pale yellow to greenish yellow, sometimes red at tips, in staminate flowers 0.7–</description>
      <determination>3.   Rhodiola rosea</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
