<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Reid V. Moran</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Webb &amp; Berthelot" date="1840">AEONIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hist. Nat. Îles Canaries</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(2,1): 184, plates 28–35.  1840  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus AEONIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Dioscoridean name for A. arboreum]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs [perennial herbs], not viviparous, [1–]7–10[–20] dm, glabrous or pubescent.  Stems erect, branched [simple], woody or fleshy.  Leaves persistent, crowded in rosettes at ends of branches, alternate, sessile, not connate basally; blade oblong-lanceolate or obovate, laminar to terete, 3–15 cm, fleshy, base not spurred, margins ciliate; veins not conspicuous.  Inflorescences terminal cymes.  Pedicels present.  Flowers erect or spreading, [6–]7–12[–16]-merous; sepals connate basally, all alike; petals spreading or erect, distinct or nearly so, cream or bright yellow; calyx and corolla not circumscissile in fruit; nectaries mostly rectangular; stamens 2 times as many as sepals; filaments adnate on corolla base; pistils erect, distinct or nearly so; ovary base rounded; styles 2+ times shorter than ovary.  Fruits erect.  Seeds ellipsoidal, ribbed, finely cross-ribbed.  x = 18.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced, California; Asia (Yemen), Africa, Atlantic Islands (especially Canary Islands).</description>
  <number>7.</number>
  <discussion>Species 31 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Aeonium and the other polymerous-flowered Macaronesian Crassulaceae were formerly included in the polymerous-flowered Sempervivum.  From studies in DNA and molecular systematics, T. H. M. Mes (1995) concluded that Aeonium and these related genera probably evolved from North African Sedum-like ancestors and are only more distantly related to Sempervivum.  He thought that the wide range of growth-forms in Aeonium, including the woody habit, is derived from herbaceous ancestors.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Liu, H. Y.  1989.  Systematics of Aeonium (Crassulaceae).  Taichung.  [Natl. Mus. Nat. Sci. [Taiwan], Special Publ. 3.]</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rosette leaves 50–75, blade bright green, 5–9(–15) cm, 1.5–3 mm thick; petals 9–11, spreading, bright yellow</description>
      <determination>1.   Aeonium arboreum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rosette leaves 15–25, blade gray-green, 3–6 cm, 2–5 mm thick; petals 7–9, erect, cream</description>
      <determination>2.   Aeonium haworthii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
