<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Grauer" date="1784">glandulosum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pl. Minus Cogn.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2.  1784  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species glandulosum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 0.5–1 m.  Stems reclining or sprawling to ± strongly ascending, sparingly pubescent and glandular, sometimes gla-brescent; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 3–7 cm; glabrous or sparsely glandular; blade pentangular, 5–7-lobed, cleft nearly to midrib, 3–8 cm, base cordate, surfaces glabrous or pubescent along veins abaxially, lobes deltate, margins serrate or 2 times serrate, apex acute.  Inflorescences erect or ascending, 6–15-flowered racemes, 3–5 cm, axis stipitate-glandular, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels jointed, 2–7 mm, pubescent and stipitate-glandular; bracts linear, 1–2 mm, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium greenish white, deeply saucer-shaped, 0.7–1 mm, glabrous or sparsely hairy, sometimes stipitate-glandular; sepals not overlapping, spreading, white to pink, oblong-obovate from rounded sinuses, 1.5–2.5 mm; petals widely separated, erect, pinkish, cuneate to flabellate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 0.5–1.5 mm; nectary disc prominent, yellowish, flat, not angled, covering most of ovary; stamens as long as or slightly longer than petals; filaments linear, 1.5 mm, glabrous; anthers cream or dark pink, ovate, 0.3–0.5 mm, apex shallowly notched; ovary glandular-bristly; styles connate 1/4 their lengths, 1.5 mm, glabrous, with few glands at base.  Berries palatable or unpalatable, dark red, ovoid, 6–8 mm, glandular-bristly.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering May-Jun.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Conifer and conifer-hardwood swamps, wet woods, spruce-fir forests, montane thickets, krummholz, seeps, boulder fields, clearings, roadsides;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-2100 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., N.S., Nunavut, Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask., Yukon; Alaska, Conn., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., Tenn., Vt., Va., W.Va., Wis.</description>
  <number>19.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Skunk currant</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">gadellier glanduleux</other_name>
  <discussion>Ribes glandulosum herbage has a skunklike odor.  The glands are dark pink atop stalks as long as 1 mm.  The flowers have stamens with pinkish filaments.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
