<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Howell" date="1895">acerifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Erythea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 34.  1895  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species acerifolium</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 0.5–1 m.  Stems spreading to erect, finely puberulent, often thickly sprinkled with small, nearly sessile to rather strongly stipitate glands; spines at nodes absent; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 2–5.5 cm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular; blade orbiculate, lobed into 3 main and 2 smaller segments, cleft 1/2 to midrib, 3–8 cm, base deeply cordate, surfaces puberulent and stipitate-glandular abaxially, glabrous adaxially, lobes ovate-deltate, margins 2 times crenate-serrate, apex acute.  Inflorescences pendent, 7–15-flowered racemes, 3–5 cm, axis crisped-puberulent, stipitate-glandular, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels jointed, 2–8 mm, crisped-puberulent, stipitate-glandular; bracts lanceolate, 6–8 mm, crisped-puberulent, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium greenish white with pinkish tinge, shallowly bowl-shaped, 1–1.5 mm, crisped-puberulent, stipitate-glandular; sepals nearly overlapping, spreading, tips usually recurved, pinkish or white streaked with pink, broadly oblong-ovate to nearly deltate-obovate, 2–3 mm; petals very slightly connate or distinct, spreading with sepals, rose-red, obovate-cuneate, (inwardly pouched and nearly keeled in center), 1–1.5 mm; nectary disc greenish or cream, raised, angled, covering ovary; stamens nearly as long as petals; filaments oblong, 1 mm, glabrous; anthers cream, oval, 0.2–0.3 mm, apex acute; ovary finely crisped-puberulent; styles connate 3/4 their lengths, 0.7–1 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatability not known, gray-black, spheric, to 10 mm, slightly pubescent, sparsely glandular.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering Jun–Aug</description>
  <description type="morphology">Montane to alpine stream banks, meadow thickets, open ridges</description>
  <description type="morphology">900–2200 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Idaho</description>
  <description type="morphology">Oreg.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering Jun-Aug. Montane to alpine stream banks, meadow thickets, open ridges; 900-2200 m; B.C.; Idaho, Oreg., Wash.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering Jun-Aug.</phenology>
      <habitat>Montane to alpine stream banks, meadow thickets, open ridges;</habitat>
      <elevation>900-2200 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>B.C.; Idaho, Oreg., Wash.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>22.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Maple-leaved currant</other_name>
  <discussion>Ribes acerifolium K. Koch (1869), which was believed to block the use of R. acerifolium Howell, was not validly published.  Consequently, the name R. howellii Greene, proposed as a substitute name, is superfluous; it appears in many floras and on many herbarium specimens.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
