<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Britton &amp; Rose" date="1903">dudleya</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Nuttall) Britton &amp; Rose" date="1903">pulverulenta</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>New N. Amer. Crassul.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13.  1903  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus dudleya;species pulverulenta</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Echeveria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Nuttall" date="unknown">pulverulenta</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Torrey and A. Gray, Fl. N. Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 560.  1840</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Echeveria;species pulverulenta;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Caudices (becoming decumbent), simple, to 50 × 4–10 cm, (densely covered proximally with old leaves), axillary branches absent.  Leaves: rosettes solitary, not in clumps, 30–80-leaved, 25–60 cm diam.; blade chalky white, oblong to oblong-oblanceolate, widest at base or in distal 1/3, 8–25(–30) × 3–10[–13] cm, 3–10 mm thick, base 3–8 cm wide, apex acuminate to cuspidate, surfaces puberulent, chalky.  Inflorescences: cyme mostly densely 2–5-branched, obpyramidal to cylindric; branches twisted at base (flowers on underside), simple or 1 times bifurcate; cincinni 2–5, (in age straight and spreading to erect), 10–30-flowered, circinate, 10–50 cm; floral shoots 30–100[–150] × 0.5–2 cm; leaves 20–70, spreading to deflexed, (becoming red), cordate-ovate to suborbiculate, 20–50 × 15–30 mm, apex acuminate.  Pedicels pendent or declined, in age sharply bending near middle to bring fruits ± erect, 10–35 mm.  Flowers: calyx 5–9 × 5–8 mm; petals connate 6–10 mm, red, 11–19 × 2–4.5 mm, apex acute to obtuse, tips erect; pistils connivent, erect.  Unripe follicles erect.  2n = 34.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering early summer</description>
  <description type="morphology">Coastal side of mountains, cliffs and dry hillsides</description>
  <description type="morphology">0–1500 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Calif.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico (Baja California).</description>
  <description type="morphology">Stems underground, tuberous corms, mostly unbranched distally, ovoid to oblong, sometimes irregular.  Leaves mostly withering by anthesis; petiole often strongly narrowed; blade terete or laminar, turgid except at very thin, broadened base.  Cymes: branches commonly 2–3, simple; cincinni not or scarcely circinate.  Pedicels absent or erect, to 3 mm.  Flowers: petals ascending to spreading from near middle, corolla widely open; pistils erect to ascending or mostly widely spreading, separated in flower, somewhat gibbous in fruit.</description>
  <description type="morphology">sw California</description>
  <description type="morphology">nw Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering early summer. Coastal side of mountains, cliffs and dry hillsides; 0-1500 m; Calif.; Mexico (Baja California).</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering early summer.</phenology>
      <habitat>Coastal side of mountains, cliffs and dry hillsides;</habitat>
      <elevation>0-1500 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Calif.; Mexico (Baja California).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>21.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Chalk dudleya</other_name>
  <discussion>Dudleya pulverulenta is one of the largest and most distinctive species of the genus, easily recognized from a distance, even without flowers.  All parts of the flowering shoot often are farinose.  It has the widest range of any dudleya, over 1000 kilometers, from Monterey County to the Sierra San Borja in north-central Baja California.  It is a beautiful plant, much admired but less easily grown than some others.</discussion>
  <discussion>Hummingbirds often visit Dudleya pulverulenta, hovering beneath the pendent flowers and thrusting their bills up into them for nectar.  The species shows a syndrome of traits that K. A. Grant and V. Grant (1968) found in hummingbird-pollinated plants of western North America: open inflorescence; pendent flowers on long, slender pedicels; long red corolla with long tube; and (as shown by G. A. Levin and T. W. Mulroy 1985) high nectar yield.  Although hummingbirds also visit other species of the genus, this one seems especially adapted to them as pollinators, having, for example, about the longest corolla, with the longest tube, and the highest nectar output.  While most other dudleyas have flowers erect along the adaxial side of the cincinnal branch, here the young branch twists at the base, putting the flowers on the abaxial or outer side, where they are declined or pendent.  After flowering, each pedicel bends sharply to bring the fruit erect, as it is in other species.  This syndrome is nearly unique to D. pulverulenta and the related D. anthonyi, of northern Baja California, although variously approached in forms of the related and intergrading D. arizonica.</discussion>
  <discussion>10c. Dudleya   Britton &amp; Rose subg. Hasseanthus   (Rose) Moran, Leafl. W. Bot. 7: 110.  1953</discussion>
  <discussion>Hasseanthus Rose in N. L. Britton and J. N. Rose, New N. Amer. Crassul., 37.  1903</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 6 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The underground corms of subg. Hasseanthus, and the leaves that wither in spring, seem clear adaptations to drought.  Also, the plants are reduced in size and in lifespan.  M. Dodero (1996) found that in the greenhouse the smaller ones could flower in five months from seed.  From morphological and allozyme data, he concluded that the group is monophyletic, seeming close to Dudleya attenuata, the species of subg. Stylophyllum with the most-reduced leaves and inflorescence.  He suggested that by paedomorphosis the underground caudex (“corm”) probably evolved from the tuberous caudex he noted in Dudleya seedlings, which furthermore tend to be drought-deciduous, and that the leaves became smaller, with narrower and thinner petioles, as in the series from D. multicaulis through D. variegata and D. blochmaniae to D. brevifolia.  Thus he found the adult leaves of D. brevifolia like the first seedling leaves of these other species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Although in subg. Dudleya and Stylophyllum the leaves rarely become detached and take root, M. Dodero (1996) found that in subg. Hasseanthus they more often do.  The leaves readily root at the base and quickly form new plants, most easily in those species with narrower leaf bases.  Where wild plants were browsed by rabbits and rodents, he sometimes found detached leaves rooting.  In the greenhouse, with species having smaller leaves, he even saw new rosettes formed in January and flowering by April.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Clausen, R. T., R. V. Moran, and C. H. Uhl.  1945.  The taxonomy and cytology of Hasseanthus.  Desert Pl. Life 17: 69–83.</reference>
    <reference>Dodero, M. 1996. Phylogenetic Analysis of Dudleya Subgenus Hasseanthus (Crassulaceae), Using Morphological and Allozyme Data. M.S. thesis. San Diego State University.</reference>
    <reference>Moran, R. V.  1951b.  Notes on Hasseanthus, II.  Desert Pl. Life 22: 99–105.</reference>
    <reference>Moran, R. V. 1950. Notes on Hasseanthus, I. Desert Pl. Life 22: 76–82.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rosette leaf blades linear, 5–15 cm, base scarcely narrowed into petiole, apex narrowly acute; petals bright yellow (fading pale yellow), often red-lineolate on keel, connate 1–2 mm</description>
      <determination>22.   Dudleya multicaulis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rosette leaf blades linear-oblanceolate or oblanceolate, clavate-oblanceolate to spatulate, or ovate to orbiculate or reniform, 0.2–7 cm, base narrowed to petiole to 1/3 as wide as blade, apex acute or subacute to rounded or obtuse; petals white or yellow, connate 0.5–2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals bright yellow (fading whitish); flowers mostly odorless</description>
      <determination>23.   Dudleya variegata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals white; flowers with musky sweet odor.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals erect or spreading, 7–14 × 3.5–5.5 mm; rosette leaf blades 3–15(–25) mm wide, base 4–12 mm wide</description>
      <determination>25.   Dudleya nesiotica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Petals spreading from near middle, 5–10 × 2–3.5 mm; rosette leaf blades 2–8 mm wide, base 1–4 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corms subglobose to oblong, 0.7–3.5 cm × 5–20 mm; rosette leaf blades oblanceolate or clavate-oblanceolate; inflorescence shoot leaf blades 0.5–2.5 cm × 3–10 mm</description>
      <determination>24.   Dudleya blochmaniae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corms elongate, 1.5–3.5 cm × 1–6 mm; rosette leaf blades ovate to orbiculate or reniform; inflorescence shoot leaf blades 0.2–1 cm × 2.5–8 mm</description>
      <determination>26.   Dudleya brevifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
