<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. Gray" date="1858">nevii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Amer. Acad. Arts, n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 373.  1858,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species nevii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, tufted, glabrous.  Stems decumbent, branched, bearing terminal rosettes (primary rosettes usually 1 cm diam.).  Leaves alternate, spreading, petiolate; blade green or grayish green, not glaucous, narrowly rhombic-elliptic, oblanceolate, or spatulate, sub-terete, 6–11 × 2.5–3.2 mm, base with simple, short spur, not scarious, apex rounded, (surfaces papillose marginally).  Flowering shoots erect or pendent, simple, 6–8.5 cm; leaf blades narrowly elliptic or linear, (8.5–18 × 0.7–5.4 mm), base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences cymes, 5–30-flowered, 3-branched; branches not recurved, sometimes dichotomously forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels absent or to 0.5 mm.  Flowers 4-merous; sepals spreading, slightly connate basally, green, linear or linear-lanceolate, unequal, 3–8.5 × 0.5–2 mm, apex obtuse; petals spreading, distinct, white, lanceolate, carinate, 3.5–7 mm, apex acute; filaments white; anthers red; nectar scales white, subquadrate or square.  Carpels stellate in fruit, distinct, brown.  2n = 12.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering spring</description>
  <description type="morphology">On living mats of mosses and lichens on rocks of quartzite and gneiss, crevices and ledges of cliffs, sometimes talus</description>
  <description type="morphology">1000 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ala.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ga.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tenn.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Sedum nevii has conspicuous lips along the adaxial suture of mature follicles.  R. T. Clausen (1975) considered it to be closely related to S. glaucophyllum and possibly conspecific with it; S. nevii has narrower leaves and is not glaucous.  Flavonoid chemistry and seed coat morphology support recognizing S. nevii and S. glaucophyllum as separate species (P. J. Calie 1981).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
