<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sedum</genus_name><species_name>glaucophyllum</species_name><species_authority>R. T. Clausen</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Cact. Succ. J. (Los Angeles) </publication_title><place_in_publication>18: 60, fig. 40.  1946,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, perennial, cespitose, glabrous.  Stems creeping, much-branched, forming terminal rosettes on branches (primary rosettes usually 1–2.7 cm diam.).  Leaves alternate, spreading to ascending, petiolate; blade pale green or blue-green, usually glaucous, oblanceolate to spatulate, laminar, (6–)10–18 × 1–4.5 mm, base petiolelike, with simple, short spur, not scarious, apex obtuse, (surfaces papillose).  Flowering shoots erect, simple, 3.5–17.5 cm; leaf blades narrowly oblong to linear, base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences cymes, 5–30-flowered, 3-branched; branches erect or only slightly recurved, sometimes forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels absent.  Flowers 4-merous; sepals divergent, distinct, green, linear-lanceolate, unequal, 3.6–6.3 × 0.9–1.6 mm, apex obtuse, (papillose); petals spreading, distinct, white, lanceolate, minutely hooded, 4–9 mm, apex acuminate; filaments white; anthers dark red to almost purple; nectar scales white, subquadrate.  Carpels widely divergent in fruit, slightly connate basally, brown.  2n = 28, 44, 45–49.</description><phenology>Flowering late spring–mid summer</phenology><habitat>  Usually shaded cliffs, crest of cliffs, rocky slopes, on limestone, shale, sandstone, granite, hornblende gabbro, schist, and gneiss rocks</habitat><elevation> 50–1200 m</elevation><us_distribution> Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution> W.Va.</us_distribution><discussion>Sedum glaucophyllum is known only from the central and southern Appalachian Mountains.  According to A. S. Weakley (2007), reports from Georgia are based on confusion with S. nevii.</discussion></treatment>
