<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>8.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Sedum</genus_name>
    <species_name>wrightii</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(5): 76.  1852,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Herbs, perennial, tufted, glabrous.  Stems erect or decumbent, branched from base, bearing shoots with rosettes axillary to proximal leaves.  Leaves (immediately deciduous), alternate, erect to spreading, sessile; blade green or yellow-green, not glaucous, elliptic or oblanceolate-oblong, terete, 5–12 × 3–5 mm, base not spurred, not scarious, apex widely rounded, (surfaces minutely papillose marginally).  Flowering shoots erect, simple, 6–15 cm; leaf blades elliptic or oblanceolate-oblong, base not spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences cymes, 2–30-flowered, or flowers solitary, monochasially 1–2-branched; branches erect or recurved, sometimes forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels to 3.7 mm.  Flowers (with pungent, musky scent unique to this species), 4–7-merous; sepals divergent or erect, distinct, green, elliptic or lanceolate-oblong, unequal, 4–9 × 3.5 mm, apex acute to apiculate; petals erect in proximal 1/3, curved outward sharply 2/3 from base (distal 1/3 divergent), distinct, white, oblanceolate-oblong, not carinate, 5–9 mm, apex abruptly acute with mucronate appendage; filaments white; anthers red or yellow; nectar scales yellow, stipitate-reniform.  Carpels erect in fruit, connate basally, pale brown.  2n = 24, 30–33, 48, 49, 61–77, 72, 96, 120, 144.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 3 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>sc United States</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Variety densiflorum (R. T. Clausen) H. Ohba occurs in northern Mexico.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades of flowering shoots 10+ mm; sepals</statement>
      <determination>8a.   Sedum wrightii var. wrightii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades of flowering shoots 6–9 mm; sepals ca. 4 mm; petals 5–6 mm</statement>
      <determination>8b.   Sedum wrightii var. priscum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
