<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>7.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sedum</genus_name><species_name>cockerellii</species_name><species_authority>Britton</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in N. L. Britton and J. N. Rose,  New N. Amer. Crassul., </publication_title><place_in_publication>41.  1903,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Cockerellia</genus_name><species_name>cockerellii</species_name><species_authority>(Britton) Á. Löve &amp; D. Löve</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, perennial, tufted, glabrous.  Stems rootstocks, erect, rarely branched, (smooth or papillose), bearing erect shoots and axillary rosettes.  Leaves alternate, spreading to ascending, sessile; blade green or yellow-green, sometimes glaucous, obovate or oblong-spatulate, laminar, 9.5–15 × 1.5–3.5 mm, base spurred, not scarious, apex rounded to obtuse, (surfaces papillose).  Flowering shoots erect, simple, 5–10 cm, (sometimes papillose distally); leaf blades oblanceolate-elliptic, oblanceolate-oblong, or spatulate, base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences 3-parted cymes, (4–)10–27-flowered, 1–3-branched, sometimes monochasially; branches ± arched, spreading, or sometimes recurved, sometimes forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels 1–3.5 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect to spreading, distinct basally, yellow-green to yellow, lanceolate-linear or clavate-oblong, unequal, 4.5–12 × 1.4–2.6 mm, apex acute or obtuse, (papillose); petals erect, curving upward distally, distinct, rarely slightly connate, white streaked with pink, lanceolate-elliptic, not carinate, 5–8 mm, apex obtuse, with minute mucronate appendage; filaments white; anthers purple or brown; nectar scales yellow or creamy white, square.  Carpels erect in fruit, distinct, pale brown.  2n = 28, 30, 32, (34), 58, 64.</description><phenology>Flowering late summer–early autumn</phenology><habitat>  Pine forests in high mountains, shallow soils, usually in shade</habitat><elevation> 1600–3200 m</elevation><us_distribution> Ariz.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Mex.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><discussion>Mature carpels of Sedum cockerellii have conspicuous, divergent beaks.</discussion></treatment>
