<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint" date="unknown">CRASSULACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey" date="unknown">lanceolatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Lyceum Nat. Hist. New York</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 205.  1827,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CRASSULACEAE;genus Sedum;species lanceolatum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, tufted, glabrous.  Stems rootstocks, decumbent and ascending, branched, (sometimes papillose), bearing terminal rosettes and above ground shoots.  Leaves (not easily detached), alternate, spreading-erect to erect or ascending, sessile; blade dull gray-green or bluish green, green, or reddish green, often glaucous, lanceolate, elliptic-lanceolate, or elliptic-ovate, subterete, 4.2–13 × 1.5–3.5 mm, base very short-spurred, base of withered blade at times becoming scarious, apex obtuse or obtusely apiculate, (surfaces papillose).  Flowering shoots erect, simple or branched, 3–18 cm; leaf blades elliptic-lanceolate, base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences cymes, 5–25-flowered, (1–)3(–6)-branched; branches ascending, spreading to erect, or recurved, forked; bracts similar to leaves.  Pedicels absent or to 3 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect, connate basally, pale green to yellow-green, ovate or lanceolate, equal, 2–5 × 1–2 mm, apex acute or, rarely, obtuse, (often papillose); petals widely spreading from suberect base, distinct, canary to golden yellow, lanceolate, elliptic-lanceolate, or linear-lanceolate, canaliculate, 6–9.2 mm, apex acute to acuminate with minute mucronate appendage; filaments yellow; anthers yellow, sometimes suffused with red; nectar scales deep yellow to yellow-green, obovately square.  Carpels erect in fruit, basally connate, brown.  2n = 16.</description>
  <description type="morphology">w</description>
  <description type="morphology">wc North America.</description>
  <number>9.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Sedum lanceolatum forms offsets in the axils of rosette leaves.  The mature carpels have divergent beaks and narrow lips along the adaxial suture.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rosette leaf blades 4.2–9 × 1.5–2.5 mm</description>
      <determination>9a.   Sedum lanceolatum var. lanceolatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rosette leaf blades 8–13 × 3–3.5 mm</description>
      <determination>9b.   Sedum lanceolatum var. nesioticum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
