<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Pursh" date="1813">stenopetalum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 324.  1813,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species stenopetalum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Amerosedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Pursh) Á. Löve &amp; D. Löve" date="unknown">stenopetalum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Amerosedum;species stenopetalum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual, biennial, or weakly perennial, tufted or not, glabrous.  Stems decumbent, branched, bearing terminal rosettes.  Leaves alternate, spreading to erect, sessile; blade green, not glaucous, linear to elliptic-oblong (subulate when dry), subterete, 4.3–13.8 × 1.4–2.7 mm, base (persistent), spurred (spur simple, small), scarious, apex acute, (surfaces sometimes papillose marginally).  Flowering shoots erect, branched, 10–43 cm; leaf blades linear, base with scarious spurs; offsets rosettes, produced from axils of leaves and bracts.  Inflorescences solitary flowers or cymes, 9–15(–25)-flowered, mostly 3-branched; branches slightly recurved, not forked; bracts linear-lanceolate, smaller than leaves, base spurred.  Pedicels absent or to 0.5 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect, distinct, pale green or yellow-green, lanceolate or ovate, equal, 2–3.7 × 0.9–1.7 mm, apex acute or long-acuminate; petals stellately spreading, distinct, deep yellow with green to brown dorsal keel to almost white, lanceolate or elliptic, slightly carinate, 5.4–8 mm, apex obtuse, acute, or long-acuminate, sometimes with aristate appendage; filaments yellow; anthers yellow; nectar scales greenish yellow or yellowish white, reniform-subquadrate or square.  Carpels divergent in fruit, shortly connate, pale green, yellow-green, or brown.  2n = 50–54, 58, 62–70, 63–64.</description>
  <description type="morphology">w North America.</description>
  <number>12.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Mature follicles of Sedum stenopetalum are finely papillose, with prominent lips along the adaxial suture.  Petal number can range from three to eight.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades linear; inflorescences 9–25-flowered cymes</description>
      <determination>12a.   Sedum stenopetalum var. stenopetalum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic-oblong; inflorescences solitary flowers</description>
      <determination>12b.   Sedum stenopetalum var. monanthum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
