<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey &amp; E. James ex Eaton" date="1829">nuttallii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Man. Bot. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 388.  1829  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species nuttallii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual, not tufted, glabrous.  Stems erect or decumbent, simple or branched, not bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, widely divergent, sessile; blade pale or bluish green, not glaucous, narrowly lanceolate-elliptic or oblong, subterete to, rarely, globular, 3–6 × 1.5–2 mm, base short-spurred, not scarious, apex obtuse.  Flowering shoots erect, simple or branched, 2.5–11 cm; leaf blades lanceolate-elliptic or oblong, base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences cymes, 20–60(–100)-flowered, 1–3-branched; branches ± erect to spreading, sometimes slightly recurved, usually not forked, sometimes 1–2-forked; bracts similar to leaves.  Pedicels absent or to 1 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect, distinct, yellow-green, lanceolate or lanceolate-oblong, unequal, 0.6–3 × 0.4–1.5 mm, (base short-spurred), apex acute; petals spreading, distinct, yellow, elliptic-oblong, slightly cucullate, 2–4 mm, apex mucronate; filaments yellow; anthers yellow; nectar scales yellow or translucent, stipitate-reniform, subquadrate, or obovate.  Carpels widely spreading in fruit, connate basally, straw-yellow.  2n = 20.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering spring–summer</description>
  <description type="morphology">Open areas, shallow soil, commonly over granite or sandstone</description>
  <description type="morphology">200–400 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ark.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Kans.</description>
  <description type="morphology">La.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Okla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tex.</description>
  <number>17.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Yellow stonecrop</other_name>
  <discussion>Until recently, Sedum nuttallii was thought to have been published first in 1833 (not 1829), a year after S. nuttallianum Rafinesque; consequently the latter name has been applied incorrectly to this species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
