<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Fröderström" date="1936">nanifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Acta Horti Gothob.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10(app.): 96, figs. 736–746, plate 61.  1936,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species nanifolium</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hemsley" date="unknown">parvum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="(Fröderström) R. T. Clausen" date="unknown">nanifolium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sedum;species parvum;subspecies nanifolium;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, mat-forming, glabrous.  Stems procumbent, becoming erect, (reddish-shiny proximally), long-branched, not bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, (densely set), erect to slightly spreading, sessile; blade green with prominent red dots, not glaucous, sometimes waxy, orbiculate to broadly obovate, semiterete, 2.5–3.5(–5) × 2–2.5 mm, base not spurred, not scarious, apex rounded to acute.  Flowering shoots erect, simple or branched, 2–4 cm; leaf blades orbiculate to broadly ovate, base not spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences subscorpioid cymes, 10–20-flowered, simple to 2-branched; branches erect to spreading or recurved, sometimes forked; bracts oblong, ca. 3 mm, base broadly spurred.  Pedicels absent.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals suberect, distinct basally, greenish, sometimes with reddish striations, subovate, unequal, 2–2.5 × 0.1–1.6 mm, apex obtuse, (papillose); petals erect to spreading, distinct, yellow with prominent, short, longitudinal red stripes, lanceolate, carinate, 4.5–5 mm, apex subobtuse, narrowly mucronate; filaments whitish or pale yellow; anthers yellow; nectar scales inconspicuous.  Carpels spreading in fruit, distinct, tan or brown with reddish striations.  2n = 52, 53, 104.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late spring-early winter.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Limestone gravel or outcrops in various vegetation;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1300-2000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.; Mexico (Chihuahua, Coahuila, Nuevo León).</description>
  <number>18.</number>
  <discussion>Sedum nanifolium is found in the Del Norte Mountains of Brewster County.  The long-branched (to 20 cm), reddish-shiny stems are distinctive; see discussion under 19. S. robertsianum.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
