<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>27.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>velutinum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Calif. Acad. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 83.  1885  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Desert gooseberry</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Grossularia</genus_name>
    <species_name>velutina</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Greene) Coville &amp; Britton</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>gooddingii</species_name>
    <species_authority>M. Peck</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>velutinum</species_name>
    <variety_name>glanduliferum</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(A. Heller) Jepson</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>velutinum</species_name>
    <variety_name>gooddingii</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(M. Peck) C. L. Hitchcock</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 0.5–2 m.  Stems spread-ing, (densely and intricately branched), glabrous or copiously pubescent when young; spines at nodes 1–3, 5–20 mm; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 0.2–1.5(–3.3) cm, pilose and glandular or stipitate-glandular; blade nearly orbiculate to cordate or reniform, 3–5-lobed, cleft 1/3–1/2(–3/4) to midrib, 0.5–2 cm, base broadly truncate to cordate, surfaces glabrous or finely pubescent and slightly glandular-puberulent, lobes cuneate, margins entire or 2–3-toothed, apex rounded.  Inflorescences spreading, solitary flowers or 2(–3)-flowered racemes, 0.5–1 cm (much shorter than leaves), axis pubescent, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels not jointed, 1–3(–4) mm, glabrous, pubescent, or glandular-pubescent; bracts lanceolate-ovate, 1–2 mm, pubescent.  Flowers: hypanthium whitish or yellowish, sometimes pink tinged, tubular to slightly campanulate, 1–2.5(–2.8) mm, glabrous, pubescent, or stipitate-glandular and pubescent abaxially, glabrous adaxially, becoming indurate; sepals not overlapping, spreading to nearly erect, yellow to pinkish, oblong, 1–2 mm; petals nearly connivent, erect, white or yellowish, elliptic-oblanceolate or oblong-obovate to spatulate, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 1.5–2.5 mm; nectary disc greenish or cream, raised, roundish, covering much of ovary; stamens nearly as long as petals; filaments linear, 0.6–1.1 mm, glabrous; anthers pale yellow to light violet, oval, 0.5–1.2 mm, apex blunt or with punctate notch; ovary usually densely crisped-puberulent and stipitate-glandular, rarely glabrous; styles completely connate, 3 mm, glabrous or finely pubescent.  Berries palatable, yellow, becoming purple or dark reddish, globose, 4–9.5 mm, glabrous, sparsely to densely pubescent, or sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular pubescent.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering Mar–Jun</phenology>
  <habitat>Sagebrush scrub, pinyon-juniper woodland, yellow pine forests</habitat>
  <elevation>300–3500 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Utah</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>The leaves of Ribes velutinum are thick and leathery.</discussion>
</treatment>
