<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>26.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Ribes</genus_name><species_name>binominatum</species_name><species_authority>A. Heller</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Cat. N. Amer. Pl., ed. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2, 5.  1900  ,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Trailing gooseberry</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Ribes</genus_name><species_name>montanum</species_name><species_authority>Howell</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. N.W. Amer., </publication_title><place_in_publication>210.  1898,</place_in_publication><other_info>not Philippi 1859</other_info></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Grossularia</genus_name><species_name>binominata</species_name><species_authority>(A. Heller) Coville &amp; Britton</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 0.1–1 m.  Stems spreading to prostrate, pubescent; spines at nodes 3, 5–20 mm; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 2–5 cm, puberulent to villous and stipitate-glandular; blade suborbiculate, 3–5-lobed, deeply cleft, 2–5 cm, base cordate, surfaces pubescent, not stipitate-glandular, lobes broadly cuneate, sides mostly straight, margins dentate-crenate, apex rounded.  Inflorescences pendent, solitary flowers or 2–3-flowered racemes, 1–4 cm (much shorter than leaves), axis hairy, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels not jointed, 1–2 mm, bristly; bracts lanceolate-ovate, 1.5–3 mm, puberulent.  Flowers: hypanthium green, broadly campanulate, 2–3(–4) mm, pubescent; sepals not overlapping, reflexed, greenish white to green with red margins, lanceolate, 4–6 mm; petals nearly connivent, erect, white to pink, oblong, flat or shallowly concave abaxially, 2–3 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens longer than petals; filaments slightly expanded at base, 2–4 mm, glabrous; anthers reddish brown, oval, 0.2–0.5 mm, apex blunt; ovary densely bristly and glandular; styles connate 1/2 their lengths, 2–4 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatability not known, yellow-green, ovoid, 8–10 mm, prickles yellow, nonglandular, stout, developing into spines, hairs glandular or eglandular.</description><phenology>Flowering Apr–Jul</phenology><habitat>  Montane and subalpine forests</habitat><conservation> of conservation concern</conservation><elevation> 1000–2600 m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Oreg.</us_distribution><discussion>Ribes binominatum occurs at relatively high elevations in the Coast Ranges of northern California and the Klamath Mountains of central and southern Oregon.</discussion></treatment>
