<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1755">hispanicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cent. Pl. I,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12.  1755  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species hispanicum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual, tufted, glabrous or scattered glandular-hairy.  Stems erect or ascending, simple or much-branched, (glandular-hairy), not bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, ascending, sessile; blade green, sometimes glaucous, linear to oblong, semiterete or ± laminar, 4–20 × 1–2 mm, base not spurred, not scarious, apex obtuse, (surfaces usually glabrous or, rarely, glandular-hairy).  Flowering shoots spreading or erect, simple, 5–15 cm, (glabrous or with scattered glandular hairs); leaf blades linear to oblong, base not spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences lax to ± dense cymes, 2–8-flowered or flowers solitary, 2–4-branched; branches not recurved, not forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels to 0.5 mm.  Flowers 5–9-merous; sepals erect, connate basally, green, broadly triangular, equal, ca. 2 × 1 mm, apex acute, (glandular-pubescent); petals spreading, distinct, white with pinkish midvein, lanceolate, not carinate, 4–5(–7) mm, apex narrowly acuminate; filaments white; anthers dark purple; nectar scales white, spatulate-quadrate.  Carpels stellate-spreading in fruit, connate basally, white or pale pink.  2n = 40.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring-summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rocks and waste places;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-1000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Ont., Que.; Mass., Mich., N.Y., Utah, Vt.; s, c Europe (Balkan Peninsula, Caucasus region); sw Asia (n Iran, Lebanon, Palestine, Turkey).</description>
  <number>21.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Orpin d’Espagne</other_name>
  <discussion>Sedum hispanicum has been naturalized in North America since 1880; it is sometimes cultivated.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
