<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>22.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Sedum</genus_name>
    <species_name>album</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 432.  1753,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Herbs, perennial, laxly cespitose, minutely puberulent, papillose.  Stems creeping and short-ascending, much-branched, (densely glandular-pubescent basally), not bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, patent or appressed, sessile; blade green, often reddish, not glaucous, linear to ovate, subterete but adaxial surface somewhat flattened, 4–20(–25) × 1–20 mm, base scarcely spurred, not scarious, apex obtuse or rounded, (surfaces glabrous or sparsely hairy).  Flowering shoots erect, simple or branched, 5–18(–30) cm, (glabrous or sparsely hairy); leaf blades linear to ovate, base scarcely spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences paniculate cymes, 15–50+-flowered, 3–5-branched; branches reflexed, forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels 3–5 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect, connate basally, green, ovate to triangular, equal, 0.5–1.5 × 0.2–0.5 mm, apex acute, (glabrous or sparsely and minutely puberulent); petals spreading, distinct, white or rarely pink, lanceolate, not carinate, 2–4.5 mm, apex subacute; filaments white; anthers red; nectar scales white or yellow, spatulate.  Carpels erect in fruit, distinct, whitish.  2n = 34, 51, 68, 85, 102, 136.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering summer–fall</phenology>
  <habitat>Calcareous rock ledges, gravelly flat areas, ruderal areas</habitat>
  <elevation>60–1400 m</elevation>
  <introduced>introduced</introduced>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.B.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ind.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mich.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.J.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ohio</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Pa.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Utah</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Sedum album was first reported as naturalized in the United States in 1934.</discussion>
</treatment>
