<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>23.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Sedum</genus_name>
    <species_name>annuum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 432.  1753,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Etiosedum</genus_name>
    <species_name>annuum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Linnaeus) Á. Löve &amp; D. Löve</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Herbs, annual, tufted, glabrous.  Stems erect, simple or branched, not forming rosettes.  Leaves alternate, spreading-erect, sessile; blade pea green, not glaucous, linear-oblong or oblong-elliptic, terete or subterete, ca. 6 × 2 mm, base not spurred, not scarious, apex obtuse, (surfaces papillose).  Flowering shoots erect, simple, 3–15 cm; leaf blades linear-oblong or obovate-elliptic, base not spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences corymbiform cymes, 3–15-flowered, 2–3-branched; branches not recurved, not forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels absent or to 1 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals spreading, distinct, green, lanceolate, unequal, 1.5–2.5 × 0.5–1 mm, apex acute; petals divergent in distal 1/2 from erect base, distinct, yellow, narrowly lanceolate, slightly carinate, 3–5 mm, apex acute; filaments yellowish or greenish; anthers yellow; nectar scales yellow, oblong.  Carpels stellately spreading in fruit, distinct, light brown or yellow.  2n = 22.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering summer</phenology>
  <habitat>Sunny rocks, stony ground</habitat>
  <elevation>0–2000 m</elevation>
  <introduced>introduced</introduced>
  <global_distribution>Greenland</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Sedum annuum is similar to S. nuttallii; the latter has spurred sepals and smaller petals, nectaries, and follicles (R. T. Clausen 1975).</discussion>
</treatment>
