<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>25.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sedum</genus_name><species_name>sexangulare</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 432.  1753,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, perennial, laxly cespitose, mat-forming, glabrous.  Stems ascending, branched, (stolonif-erous), not bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, (densely imbricate on nonflowering shoots), usually in 6 rows (fewer on flowering shoots), ascending, sessile; blade bright green, not glaucous, linear, subterete to terete, 3–6 × 0.8–2 mm, base spurred, not scarious, apex obtuse.  Flowering shoots erect, simple or branched, 6–15 cm; leaf blades linear, base spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences moderately lax cymes, 5–25-flowered, (1–)2–3(–4)-branched; branches spreading, sometimes forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels to 0.5 mm.  Flowers 5(–6)-merous; sepals erect, distinct, yellowish green, linear-elliptic, unequal, 0.8–1 × 0.4–0.5 mm, apex obtuse; petals spreading, distinct, bright yellow, lanceolate, not carinate, 3–4 mm, apex acute or acuminate; filaments yellow; anthers yellow; nectar scales yellow, square.  Carpels divergent in fruit, distinct, dark brown.  2n = 74, 111, 148, 185.</description><phenology>Flowering late spring–summer</phenology><habitat>  Roadsides, waste places</habitat><elevation> 0–500 m</elevation><introduced> introduced</introduced><ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Conn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ill.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ind.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mass.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mich.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.H.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ohio</us_distribution><us_distribution> Vt.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Europe.</global_distribution><discussion>Sedum sexangulare was first reported as naturalized in the United States in 1942.  The mature carpels have narrow brown lips along the adaxial suture.</discussion></treatment>
