<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rose in N. L. Britton et al." date="1905">havardii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in N. L. Britton et al.,  N. Amer. Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>22: 74.  1905 (as havardi),</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species havardii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs or subshrubs, perennial, not tufted, glabrous.  Stems procumbent, creeping, or spreading, with ascending or erect branches, (tuberculate), not bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, (imbricate to subim-bricate), erect to spreading, sessile; blade bright green, sometimes glaucous, suboblong to ovate, somewhat flattened to terete, 4–9 × 1–2 mm, base widened, short-spurred, not scarious, apex obtuse, (surfaces smooth or papillose).  Flowering shoots erect, simple, 1–5 cm, (papillose); leaf blades elliptic, base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences 3-parted cymes, 2–10-flowered or flowers solitary, simple or monochasially 1-branched; branches erect to slightly recurved, not forked; bracts similar to leaves, sometimes imbricate.  Pedicels absent or to 1.5 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect to suberect, distinct basally, green to pinkish, linear or lanceolate, slightly unequal, 3–5 × 0.2–1 mm, apex obtuse; petals spreading, distinct basally, white, suboblong, not carinate, 5–6.5 mm, apex obtuse, shortly mucronate; filaments white to pale pink; anthers red or purplish; nectar scales whitish to pale pink, oblong, (retuse).  Carpels divergent or stellately spreading in fruit, distinct, red to purple or stramineous with  reddish to  purplish striations.  2n = ca. 36–50, 68–72.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering spring–fall</description>
  <description type="morphology">Igneous rock outcrops or talus in oak-pinyon woodlands and chaparral</description>
  <description type="morphology">1500–2500 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Tex.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico (Coahuila).</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
