<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="S. Watson" date="1885">stelliforme</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20: 365.  1885,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species stelliforme</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Raymond-Hamet" date="unknown">topsentii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Sedum;species topsentii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, somewhat tufted, glabrous.  Stems root-stocks and erect shoots, branched proximally, sometimes bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, spreading to ascending, sessile; blade blue-green, not glaucous, linear-oblanceolate, terete to subterete, 4–9(–15) × 1–2 mm, base broadly spurred, not scarious, apex obtuse.  Flowering shoots erect or ascending, simple or branched, 1–4(–9) cm, (with small glistening patches); leaf blades linear-oblanceolate, base truncate or spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences compact, 3-parted cymes, (5–)10–25-flowered, monochasially branched; branches erect to spreading or recurved, rarely forked; bracts suboblong, base truncate or spurred.  Pedicels absent.  Flowers 5–6-merous; sepals erect to spreading, distinct, blue-green, linear to narrowly oblong, unequal, ca. 2–4(–6) × 0.7–1.5 mm, apex obtuse; petals spreading, distinct, white tinged with purple, oblong, somewhat carinate, 4–7 mm, apex acute or broadly mucronate; filaments white; anthers purplish; nectar scales dark pink, spatulate.  Carpels stellately spreading in fruit, distinct, stramineous.  2n = 19, 22, 24, 44, 52.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering mid summer</description>
  <description type="morphology">Grassland, moist areas, moist cliffs in conifer forests</description>
  <description type="morphology">300–3000 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ariz.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Colo.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Mex.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico (Chihuahua, Durango).</description>
  <number>28.</number>
  <discussion>Sedum stelliforme has glistening patches on the flowering branches and sepals.  It is found in southern Colorado, Graham, Greenlee, and Apache counties in Arizona, the Zuni Mountains and Fort Wingate in New Mexico, and on the Mexican Plateau.  More information is needed to determine whether S. topsentii should be separated from S. stelliforme.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
