<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. de Candolle" date="1847">praealtum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mém. Soc. Phys. Genève</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 445.  1847,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species praealtum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, glabrous.  Stems erect, pendulous, or prostrate, much-branched, not bearing basal rosettes.  Leaves alternate, spreading, sessile; blade green tinged with red, not glaucous, elliptic-oblanceolate, laminar, 40–80 × 13–25 mm, base not spurred, not scarious, apex rounded.  Flowering shoots (axillary), ascending, usually simple, sometimes branched, 10–50 cm; leaf blades elliptic-oblanceolate, base not spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences elongated paniculate cymes, 50–300+-flowered, 3–25-branched; branches not recurved, forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels absent or to 1 mm.  Flowers (4–)5(–6)-merous; sepals erect, usually distinct, green, ovate, lanceolate, or elliptic-oblong, unequal, 1.5–9.6 × 1–3.2 mm, apex obtuse; petals widely spreading, distinct or slightly connate basally, yellow, lanceolate, carinate, ca. 7.5 mm, apex acute or obtuse, mucronate; filaments yellow; anthers yellow; nectar scales yellowish or translucent, subquadrate or reniform.  Carpels widely divergent in fruit, distinct, brown.  2n = 68.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late winter.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Cliffs;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-100 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Calif.; c Mexico; Central America (Guatemala); introduced also in Europe (Italy), Australia.</description>
  <number>29.</number>
  <discussion>The first record of Sedum praealtum cultivated in the United States is from 1930.  It is native in the trans-Mexican volcanic belt.  It was reported from Ventura County in 1948 and has naturalized in the vicinity of Santa Cruz in Santa Cruz County.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
