<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>35.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sedum</genus_name><species_name>laxum</species_name><species_authority>(Britton) A. Berger</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler et al.,  Nat. Pflanzenfam. ed. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2, 18a: 451.  1930,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Gormania</genus_name><species_name>laxa</species_name><species_authority>Britton</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in N. L. Britton and J. N. Rose, New N. Amer. Crassul., </publication_title><place_in_publication>29.  1903</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, perennial, cespitose or not, glabrous.  Stems root-stocks, ascending, much-branched, bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, erect to spreading, sessile; blade green, glaucous or not, not pruinose, oblanceolate, spatulate, or obovate, subterete or somewhat flattened, 10–50 × (4.5–)6–33 mm, base not spurred, not scarious, apex truncate to rounded or obtuse, emarginate or barely notched.  Flowering shoots erect or decumbent, simple or branched, 4–30(–40) cm; leaf blades oblanceolate, spatulate, obovate, or suborbiculate, base not spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences elongate, paniculate cymes, 12–80-flowered, monochasially 3+-branched; branches not recurved, 2-forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels 0.6–6.3 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect, (closely appressed to corolla tube), slightly connate basally, pale green, ovate or lanceolate, equal, (2–)2.6–5.1 × 2 mm, apex acute or subacute, (rarely obtuse in var. flavidum); petals basally erect, divergent in distal 1/2, connate basally, pink, pinkish white, or white to yellowish white, lanceolate-oblong, oblanceolate-oblong, or elliptic-oblong, not carinate, 4–11 mm, apex obtuse, shortly mucronate or aristate; filaments white, greenish white, or pink; anthers red, reddish purple, red-brown, or yellow; nectar scales white, yellow, or pink, reniform or transversely oblong.  Carpels erect in fruit, distinct, brown.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 5 (5 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> w United States.</global_distribution><discussion>Sedum laxum is unusual in forming offsets in axils of rosette leaves rather than on a rootstock or creeping stem.</discussion><key><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Flowering shoot leaf bases clasping stems</statement><determination>35d.   Sedum laxum var. heckneri</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Flowering shoot leaf bases not clasping stems.</statement><next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2.</statement_id><statement>Petals pale yellow or white with pink mid- veins; sepal apices obtuse</statement><determination>35c.   Sedum laxum var. flavidum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2.</statement_id><statement>Petals pink or white; sepal apices acute.</statement><next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3.</statement_id><statement>Flowering shoot leaf blades suborbiculate</statement><determination>35b.   Sedum laxum var. eastwoodiae</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3.</statement_id><statement>Flowering shoot leaf blades spatulate to oblanceolate.</statement><next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>4.</statement_id><statement>Leaf blades 9–17 mm wide</statement><determination>35a.   Sedum laxum var. laxum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>4.</statement_id><statement>Leaf blades 17–33 mm wide</statement><determination>35e.   Sedum laxum var. latifolium</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
