<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="R. T. Clausen" date="1975">oblanceolatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sedum N. Amer.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>404, figs. 113, 114.  1975,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species oblanceolatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, cespitose, glabrous.  Stems rootstocks, erect, branched from base, bearing rosettes.  Leaves alternate, erect, sessile; blade green, appearing whitish because of pruinose covering, margins green, not white, strongly pruinose, not glaucous, narrowly obovate, laminar, 7–38 × 5–9 mm, base spurred, not scarious, apex usually obtuse to truncate, sometimes emarginate.  Flowering shoots erect, simple, 6–15 cm; leaf blades oblanceolate-oblong, base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences dense, paniculate cymes, 30–60-flowered, 7–9-branched; branches not recurved, somewhat forked; bracts similar to leaves, smaller.  Pedicels 3–5 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect, connate basally, green, appearing blue-green, glaucous, lanceolate-oblong, equal, 4–7 × 1.5–3.2 mm, apex acute, (papillose); petals erect, connate basally, creamy white, oblong, not carinate, 8.5–11.5 mm, apex acute, mucronate; filaments white, becoming reddish; anthers yellow; nectar scales yellow, transversely oblong.  Carpels erect in fruit, connate basally, brown.  2n = 30.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Rocky slopes, in crevices, edges of rocks;</description>
  <description type="elevation">400-1600 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Calif., Oreg.</description>
  <number>36.</number>
  <discussion>Sedum oblanceolatum is restricted to the upper Klamath and Applegate river basins in Jackson County, Oregon, and Siskiyou County, California.  Represented by relatively few individual plants, it occurs on a wide range of substrates including phyllite-schist, schist, metavolcanics, metasedimentary, as well as ultramafics like serpentine, soapstone, and peridotite.  It is of conservation concern in California.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
