<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>40.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Sedum</genus_name><species_name>oreganum</species_name><species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in J. Torrey and A. Gray,  Fl. N. Amer. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 559.  1840,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Gormania</genus_name><species_name>oregana</species_name><species_authority>(Nuttall) Britton</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, perennial, multi-stemmed from base, glabrous.  Stems rootstocks and decumbent branches, (stout), bearing terminal rosettes.  Leaves alternate, spreading, sessile; blade lustrous light green, not glaucous, spatulate or cuneate, laminar (thickest near apex), 7–12 × 4.4–9 mm, base short-spurred, not scarious, apex broadly rounded or truncate.  Flowering shoots erect, simple or branched, 8–13 cm; leaf blades spatulate or cuneate, base short-spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences dense corymbs, 5–10-flowered, 3-branched; branches spreading to erect, primary branch dichotomously forked; bracts spatulate or oblanceolate, 5–8 mm, base spurred.  Pedicels absent or 0.4–3+ mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals erect, connate basally, green, ovate-lanceolate, equal, ca. 3.5 × 2 mm, apex acuminate or acute; petals erect or erect basally and divergent distally, connate basally, yellow, narrowly lanceolate, carinate, ca. 10.5 mm, apex aristate; filaments yellowish or greenish; anthers yellow; nectar scales yellow, subquadrate to spatulate or oblong.  Carpels erect in fruit, connate basally, light brown or yellow.  2n = 24.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> w North America.</global_distribution><key><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Nectar scales subquadrate to spatulate, 0.4–0.5 mm; carpels 4.7–5.1 mm</statement><determination>40a.   Sedum oreganum var. oreganum</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1.</statement_id><statement>Nectar scales oblong, 0.5 mm; carpels 3.7–4.5 mm</statement><determination>40b.   Sedum oreganum var. tenue</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
