<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">sedum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hooker" date="1832">spathulifolium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 227.  1832,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus sedum;species spathulifolium</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, mat-forming, glabrous.  Stems rhizomatous, procumbent or creeping, much-branched, bearing terminal rosettes.  Leaves alternate, spreading, petiolate; blade green, often glaucous or pruinose, spatulate, terete to laminar, 7–19 × 4.5–10 mm, base not spurred, not scarious, apex rounded or truncate, submucronate, (surfaces papillose marginally).  Flowering shoots erect, simple, 3–14 cm; leaf blades spatulate-oblong or elliptic-oblong, base not spurred; offsets not formed.  Inflorescences cymes, ca. 30-flowered, ca. 3-branched; branches not recurved, forked; bracts oblong-spatulate or linear, ca. 3 cm, base not spurred.  Pedicels 2–8 mm.  Flowers 5-merous; sepals spreading to erect, connate basally, green or yellow-green, glaucous or pruinose, lanceolate, linear-lanceolate, oblong-ovate, or obovate, equal, ca. 2.5 × 1.5 mm, apex acute or obtuse; petals widely spreading from short, erect base, distinct or slightly connate basally, yellow, linear to oblanceolate, not carinate, 4.5–9 mm, apex acute; filaments yellow; anthers yellow; nectar scales yellow, reniform or nearly square.  Carpels divergent in fruit, connate basally, brown.  2n = 30.</description>
  <description type="morphology">w North America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora): w North America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>w North America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>41.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The mature carpels of Sedum spathulifolium have five ribs and prominent lips along the adaxial suture.  The flowers are sweetly fragrant.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Primary rosettes 2.5–3.7 cm diam.; leaf blades not pruinose, glaucous or not, 1.4–2.1 mm thick; flowers 1.2–1.6 cm diam.</description>
      <determination>41a.   Sedum spathulifolium var. spathulifolium</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Primary rosettes 1.5–2.1 cm diam.; leaf blades pruinose, not glaucous, 2.1–2.5 mm thick; flowers 1–1.2 cm diam.</description>
      <determination>41b.   Sedum spathulifolium var. pruinosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
