<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Reid V. Moran</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="J. Saint-Hilaire" date="unknown">crassulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rose" date="1911">GRAPTOPETALUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. U.S. Natl. Herb.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 296, fig. 55, plate 52.  1911  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family crassulaceae;genus GRAPTOPETALUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek graptos, marked, and petalon, leaf, alluding to petals]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs [or shrubs], perennial, not viviparous, 2.5–3.5 dm, glabrous or papillose.  Stems erect, branched or unbranched, succulent; floral stems annual, axillary, overtopping rosette, with scattered smaller leaves.  Leaves persistent, in dense, basal rosettes, alternate, sessile, subclasping [narrowed] basally; blade cuneate- or rhombic-oblanceolate or -obovate, laminar or semiterete, 2–10 cm, succulent, base not spurred, margins entire; with [1] several veins entering margins.  Inflorescences lateral, flat or paniculate cymes.  Pedicels present.  Flowers (fetid), erect, 5–8-merous; sepals distinct, ± alike in size; petals spreading or slightly reflexed from middle, connate basally, [mostly] pale yellow irregularly dotted and red-banded in distal 1/2; calyx and corolla not circumscissile in fruit; nectaries flabellate; stamens [as many] 2 times as many as sepals; filaments adnate to corolla base, (becoming reflexed); pistils erect, connate basally; ovary base narrowed; styles 2+ times shorter than ovaries.  Fruits mostly erect.  Seeds narrowly ovoid, finely grooved, papillose.  x = 30–35.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Arizona</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico.</description>
  <number>17.</number>
  <discussion>Species 15 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>From cytological studies (C. H. Uhl 1970, 1992), Graptopetalum belongs to a large comparium with Echeveria, Lenophyllum, Villadia, and others, but not including Dudleya.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Rosas, R. et al. 2004. Phylogenetic relationships and morphological patterns in Graptopetalum (Crassulaceae). Brittonia 56: 185–194. Acevedo-</reference>
    <reference>Uhl, C. H.  1970.  Chromosomes of Graptopetalum and Thompsonella.  Amer. J. Bot. 57: 1115–1121.</reference>
    <reference>Rosas, R. et al. 2004b. A molecular phylogenetic study of Graptopetalum (Crassulaceae) based on ETS, ITS, rfpl16, and trnL-F nucleotide sequences. Amer. J. Bot. 91: 1099–1104.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rosettes solitary or multiple, 7–16 cm diam.; leaf blades smooth, apex scarcely apiculate; flowering fall–winter; corollas 19–28 mm diam.; flowers mostly 5-merous; inflorescences paniculate cymes</description>
      <determination>1.   Graptopetalum bartramii cences mostly flat cymes</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
