<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Richard P. Wunderlin,R. David Whetstone</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">sapotaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Adanson" date="1763">MANILKARA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fam. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 166, 574.  1763, name conserved  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family sapotaceae;genus MANILKARA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Malabar Manil, from Portuguese Manilhas Insulas (Manila, Philippines), and kara, edible fruit]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees.  Stems not armed, tomentose or glabrous.  Leaves persistent, alternate; stipules present or absent; petiole present; blade: base rounded to cuneate, apex retuse to acuminate, surfaces hairy or glabrous.  Inflorescences fascicles or solitary flowers.  Flowers: sepals 6 in 2 whorls of 3, outer valvate, darker, abaxially densely hairy; petals 6[–9], white or yellow, glabrous or sparsely hairy, lobes undivided, shorter than or exceeding corolla tube; stamens 6[–12], distinct [basally connate with staminodes]; staminodes [absent or 1–]6[–12], alternate with stamens, erect or incurved, petaloid, triangular-lanceolate, glabrous or hairy; pistil 5–12[–14]-carpellate; ovary 5–12[–14]-locular, glabrous or hairy; placentation axile or basiventral.  Berries brown [yellow-green, orange, red, black, or purple], ellipsoid or depressed-globose to subglobose, glabrous.  Seeds [1–]2–10, brown, laterally compressed; hilum linear; embryo vertical; endosperm present.  x = [12,] 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Florida; Mexico, West Indies, Central America, South America, Asia, Africa, Indian Ocean Islands (Madagascar), Pacific Islands.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Balata tree</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">bully</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">bullet</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">purgio</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">quinilla</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sapodilla</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 65 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Species of Manilkara are used as sources of latex for nonelastic rubber.  The wood is dense and hard, useful for bridge pilings (fresh water), wheel spokes, posts, railroad ties, etc.  Seed extracts have been used as antihelminthics and in ophthalmics.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades: apex acute to acuminate (often folded on pressed specimens); corolla tubes equaling or exceeding lobes; fruits 35–80 mm; fruiting pedicels slightly enlarged distally</description>
      <determination>1.   Manilkara zapota</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades: apex retuse (older leaves often split on pressed specimens); corolla tubes shorter than lobes; fruits 25–40 mm; fruiting pedicels conspicuously enlarged distally</description>
      <determination>2.   Manilkara jaimiqui</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
