<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Gürke" date="unknown">ebenaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">diospyros</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Blume" date="1826">maritima</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bijdr. Fl. Ned. Ind.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13: 669.  1826  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ebenaceae;genus diospyros;species maritima</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, to 12 m.  Bark dark brown to black, smooth and flaking.  Leaves persistent; petiole 0.5–1 cm; blade dark green and glossy adaxially, elliptic-lanceolate to elliptic-oblong or slightly obovate, 7–15(–17) × 3–6(–8) cm, thick, apex obtuse, abaxial surface glabrous (or sparsely pubescent when young), with 2 basilaminar glands.  Inflorescences solitary flowers or 2–3-flowered cymes, borne on twigs of current season.  Flowers 1.5–1.8 cm; sepals 4; petals 4; stamens 16; anthers dehiscent along their entire length; pistillate flowers with 8 staminodes; styles 4, connate for most of their lengths; ovary pubescent.  Berries yellow to orange or black, not glaucous, depressed-globose, (1.5–)2–3 cm diam., glabrous (except at apex).  Seeds brown, ellipsoid, ca. 1.5 cm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering intermittently year-round; fruiting year-round.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Disturbed ground near shores;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-10 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Fla.; e Asia (including Japan); w Pacific Islands; Australia.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Malay persimmon</other_name>
  <discussion>A common tree of coastal forests throughout the tropical western Pacific, Diospyros maritima is climatically well suited to seasonally dry southern Florida, with its salt-laden air, where it rarely escapes from cultivation.  Although uncommon at present, it has the potential to become an established strand species, like Terminalia catappa Linnaeus or Casuarina equisetifolia Linnaeus.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
