<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Anita F. Cholewa</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="D. Don" date="unknown">THEOPHRASTACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family THEOPHRASTACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <other_name type="common_name">Theophrasta Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 7, species ca. 100 (3 genera, 6 species in the flora): widespread, mainly neotropical with Samolus cosmopolitan.</discussion>
  <discussion>Theophrastaceae are of little economic importance; some species of Jacquinia are used to make tropical fish poisons; fruits of the tropical Clavija Ruiz &amp; Pavón are edible.  All genera apparently are pollinated by insects (bees, flies, midges), with nectar and pollen as rewards (B. Ståhl and M. Källersjö 2004).</discussion>
  <discussion>Theophrastaceae are closely related to Myrsinaceae (often included by some in the latter) and Primulaceae, and are considered less advanced than either.  Samolus had been included in Primulaceae; the semi-inferior ovary, along with staminodal anatomy and mostly Southern Hemisphere distribution, made it an anomaly in that family.  M. Källersjö et al. (2000) have shown that Samolus is a sister taxon to Theophrastaceae and should be included in that family (as done here) or placed in a monotypic Samolaceae (B. Ståhl &amp; Källersjö 2004).  See further discussion under Primulaceae.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennial herbs; fruits capsular</description>
      <determination>3.   Samolus, p. 254</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees; fruits baccate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Young branches puberulous, hairs relatively short, uniseriate; corollas yellow or orange; seeds flattened, partially covered by placental tissue</description>
      <determination>1.   Bonellia, p. 252</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Young branches lepidote, hairs irregularly branched, thick-walled; corollas white or cream; seeds subglobose, completely covered by placental tissue</description>
      <determination>2.   Jacquinia, p. 253</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
