<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>35.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Ribes</genus_name><species_name>thacherianum</species_name><species_authority>(Jepson) Munz</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Aliso </publication_title><place_in_publication>4: 92.  1958  ,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Santa Cruz Island gooseberry</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Ribes</genus_name><species_name>menziesii</species_name><species_authority>Pursh</species_authority><variety_name>thacherianum</variety_name><variety_authority>Jepson</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. Calif. </publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 156.  1936</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 1–2.5 m.  Stems erect, densely white soft-pubescent; spines at nodes absent or 1–3, 4–8 mm; prickles on internodes scattered, glandular and eglan-dular.  Leaves: petiole 1–2 cm, copiously white-pilose; blade oblong to roundish, shallowly 5-lobed, cleft 1/4–1/3 to midrib, 2–3 cm, base truncate, surfaces soft-pubescent abaxially, subglabrous adaxially, lobes rounded, margins coarsely crenate-dentate, apex rounded to acute.  Inflorescences pendent, solitary flowers or 2-flowered racemes, 2–4 cm, axis white-pilose.  Pedicels not jointed, 6–8 mm, pilose; bracts broadly lanceolate, 2–3 mm, white-pilose.  Flowers: hypanthium pinkish, narrowly tubular, 4–5 mm (1/2 as long as sepals), white-pilose, not glandular; sepals not overlapping, erect, pinkish, lanceolate, 9–10 mm; petals connivent, erect, white, oblong, inrolled, 4–6 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens 1.3 times as long as petals; filaments linear, 4–6 mm, glabrous; anthers white, lanceolate, somewhat sagittate, 3 mm, apex apiculate; ovary pilose, not glandular; styles connate nearly 3/4 their lengths, 9–11 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatability not known, purple, subglobose, 7 mm, pilose-hairy with nonglandular spines.</description><phenology>Flowering Nov–Jul</phenology><habitat>  Ravines in pine forests</habitat><elevation> 0–700 m</elevation><us_distribution> Calif.</us_distribution><discussion>Ribes thacherianum is known only from Santa Cruz Island, Santa Barbara County.  The indehiscent part of the anther is short and dark.</discussion></treatment>
