<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>7.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Douglasia</genus_name>
    <species_name>montana</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 371.  1868  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Rocky Mountain dwarf primrose</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Douglasia</genus_name>
    <species_name>biflora</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Nelson</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Douglasia</genus_name>
    <species_name>montana</species_name>
    <variety_name>biflora</variety_name>
    <variety_authority>(A. Nelson) R. Knuth</variety_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants loosely cespitose cushions with branched caudex.  Stems prostrate to ascending with marcescent, imbricate, gray to light brown leaves.  Leaves spreading to erect, thin; blade linear-subulate, 4–10 × 0.5 mm, margins entire, ciliolate, hairs simple, apex acute, surfaces glabrous.  Scapes 5–20 mm, elongating little in fruit, densely hairy, hairs branched and stellate.  Inflorescences 1–2-flowered, ebracteate or bracteate; bracts 1–3, subulate, 2–3 × 0.5 mm, hairy, hairs simple or forked.  Pedicels present, 0.5–10 mm.  Flowers: calyx 4–8 × 3–5 mm, glabrous or slightly hairy, hairs branched and stellate; corolla rose-pink, limb 6–10 mm diam., lobes 3–5 × 1–2 mm, margins erose or entire.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering early–mid summer</phenology>
  <habitat>Foothills, open ridges, scree slopes</habitat>
  <elevation>1000–3500 m</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>Alta.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wyo.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Specimens of Douglasia montana from Wyoming tend to have two flowers per inflorescence (once recognized as var. biflora); those from the northern part of the range tend to have only one.  Because both one- and two-flowered inflorescences occur together on individual plants throughout the range, and no other morphological differences separate the forms, the varietal distinction is not recognized here.</discussion>
  <discussion>In Alberta, Douglasia montana is known only from Waterton Lakes National Park near the Montana border.</discussion>
</treatment>
