<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Batsch ex Borkhausen" date="unknown">primulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">dodecatheon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Chamisso &amp; Schlechtendal" date="1826">frigidum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 222. 1826 ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family primulaceae;genus dodecatheon;species frigidum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Primula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Chamisso &amp; Schlechtendal) Mast &amp; Reveal" date="unknown">frigida</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Primula;species frigida;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants (4–)8–30(–40) cm; scape glandular-puberulent. Caudices obvious at anthesis,
        often horizontal and elongated, slender to stout, (often woody); roots reddish; bulblets
        absent. Leaves (2–)3.5–12(–19) × 0.7–2.5(–4.5) cm; petiole slightly winged or slender (at
        least basally); blade ovate to oval, rarely oblong to spatulate, base slightly to obviously
        decurrent onto stem, abruptly tapering to petiole, margins subentire to crenate-dentate,
        surfaces minutely glandular-puberulent or glabrous. Inflorescences 2–7-flowered; bracts
        narrowly lanceolate, 3–8 mm, glandular-puberulent. Pedicels 0.5–2.5(–3) cm,
        glandular-puberulent. Flowers: calyx green to dark green, sometimes speckled with reddish
        purple, 4–7 mm, glandular-puberulent, tube 1.5–3 mm, lobes 5, (2–)2.5–4 mm; corolla tube
        yellow or rarely white with or sometimes without maroon, thick, wavy ring, lobes 5, pink or
        magenta to lavender, rarely white, (5–)8–15(–20) mm; filaments distinct or slightly connate,
        maroon, 0.2–0.8 mm; anthers (3–)4–6 mm; pollen sacs usually maroon, sometimes pale purple
        and speckled with maroon, connective black, smooth; stigma not enlarged compared to style.
        Capsules reddish brown to purplish, operculate, cylindric-ovoid, 6–12 × 3–4.5(–5) mm,
        glabrous or slightly glandular-puberulent apically; walls thin, pliable. Seeds without
        membrane along edges. 2n = 44.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Moist to boggy depressions, flats and rocky, often calcareous slopes, stream banks, lake shores, outcrops and screes mainly in meadows, low dunes, sparse conifer woodland, willow and heath tundra communities near melting snow or on permafrost;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-1700(-1900) m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">B.C., N.W.T., Sask., Yukon; Alaska; e Asia (Russian Far East).</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Western arctic shootingstar</other_name>
  <discussion>Dodecatheon frigidum is the northernmost species in the genus. It is found from
        northern British Columbia, southern Northwest Territories (Mackenzie District), and
        northwestern Saskatchewan, and Yukon (including its northern islands), and most of Alaska
        except near the immediate southern coast and Aleutian Islands. The species is disjunct onto
        the Chukotsk Peninsula in the Russian Far East. The elongated, usually woody, nearly
        horizontal caudex is diagnostic.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
