<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Batsch ex Borkhausen" date="unknown">PRIMULACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Dodecatheon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="L. F. Henderson" date="unknown">poeticum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>32: 27.  1930  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family PRIMULACEAE;genus Dodecatheon;species poeticum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Primula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(L. F. Henderson) Mast &amp; Reveal" date="unknown">poetica</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Primula;species poetica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>14.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Poet’s shootingstar</other_name>
  <discussion>Dodecatheon poeticum grows mainly in the Columbia River gorge and on the eastern edge of the Cascade Range in Washington, and in Oregon.  Nearby one can find D. conjugens var. conjugens and D. pulchellum var. cusickii, features of which (the rugose connective of the former, the glandular condition of the latter) are combined in D. poeticum.  The distinct filaments of var. conjugens readily distinguish that taxon from D. poeticum; distinction between D. poeticum and D. pulchellum var. cusickii is difficult.  The former has maroon pollen sacs; var. cusickii has yellow ones.  Plants with all of the features of D. poeticum rarely have the smooth connective typical of D. pulchellum.  H. J. Thompson (1953) suggested that D. poeticum (a tetraploid) might be the product of an allopolyploid involving var. cusickii and D. hendersonii (both diploids).</discussion>
  <discussion>The leaves of Dodecatheon poeticum are occasionally slightly toothed and relatively broad (e.g., K. L. Chambers 2080, OSC) and resemble the leaves of D. dentatum, a species that flowers in the Gorge typically after D. poeticum.  Rootstocks with bulblets are rarely seen on herbarium specimens.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
