<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>39.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>lobbii</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. Naturalist</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 274.  1876  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Gummy gooseberry</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Grossularia</genus_name>
    <species_name>lobbii</species_name>
    <species_authority>(A. Gray) Coville &amp; Britton</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 0.5–1(–1.5) m.  Stems erect or spreading, finely pubescent, not bristly; spines at nodes usually 3, 7–12 mm; prickles on internodes absent or sparse.  Leaves: petiole 1–4 cm, glandular-pubescent; blade round-ovate, 3–5-lobed, cleft less than 1/2 to midrib, 1.5–2.5 cm, base shallowly cordate, surfaces paler and usually pubescent and glandular abaxially, sparsely pubescent adaxially, lobes rounded, shallowly cleft, margins crenate-dentate, apex rounded.  Inflorescences pendent, solitary flowers or 2-flowered racemes, 4–6 cm, axis stipitate-glandular.  Pedicels not jointed, 3–4 mm, densely stipitate-glandular; bracts broadly ovate, 2–3 mm, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium greenish with strong reddish tinge abaxially, narrowly campanulate, 3.5–5.5 mm, sparsely pilose; sepals not overlapping, reflexed, bright red, narrowly oblong, 10–13 mm; petals connivent, erect, white or pinkish, broadly flabelliform but usually inrolled on edges, 4–5(–7) mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens 2 times as long as petals; filaments linear, 8–14 mm, glabrous; anthers purple or red, oval, 1.2–2 mm, apex rounded; ovary glandular; styles connate 2/5–3/5 their lengths, 8–14 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatable, reddish brown, globose-ellipsoid, 10–15(–20) mm, coarsely setose-glandular, not prickly.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering Apr–Jun</phenology>
  <habitat>Montane and subalpine forests</habitat>
  <elevation>100–2200 m</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Ribes lobbii occurs in mountains from southwestern British Columbia to northwestern California.  It is unusual in having anthers that are warty or capitate-papillate with red glands abaxially.</discussion>
</treatment>
