<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>20.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Primula</genus_name><species_name>veris</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title> Sp. Pl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 142.  1753  ,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Cowslip primrose</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Primula</genus_name><species_name>officinalis</species_name><species_authority>(Linnaeus) Hill</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants 8–30 cm, herbaceous; rhizomes thick, short; rosettes sometimes clumped, vegetative parts efarinose but often pubescent.  Leaves not aromatic, indistinctly or abruptly petiolate; petiole winged; blade with deep reticulate veins abaxially, ovate to ovate-oblong, 5–20 × 2–6 cm, thin, membranaceous in age, margins coarsely toothed, apex acute to obtuse, surfaces pubescent, hairs simple.  Inflorescences 5–16-flowered; involucral bracts plane, unequal.  Pedicels erect to drooping, moderately thick, 3–20 mm, length 1–3 times bracts, flexuous.  Flowers heterostylous; calyx pale green, broadly campanulate, 0.8–2 cm; corolla yellow, with orange spots at base of lobes, tube 8–20 mm, length to 1 times calyx, eglandular, limb 8–28 mm diam., lobes 8–14 mm, apex slightly emarginate to distinctly notched.  Capsules ovoid, length to 1 times calyx.  Seeds without flanged edges, minutely vesiculate.  2n = 22 (Europe).</description><phenology>Flowering spring</phenology><habitat>  Meadows and pastures, persisting around old gardens and homesteads, apparently substantially spreading and naturalized</habitat><elevation> 0–1000 m</elevation><introduced> introduced</introduced><ca_distribution> B.C.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.B.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> N.S.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Ont.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution> Que.</ca_distribution><us_distribution> Conn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Maine</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mass.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mich.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Y.</us_distribution><global_distribution> Europe.</global_distribution><discussion>Primula veris shows exceptional morphological variation in Europe, with multiple specific and infraspecific names.  It is a popular garden plant both here and in Europe; horticultural varieties abound and are almost certainly represented among the records from North America.</discussion></treatment>
