<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>40.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>marshallii</species_name>
    <species_authority>Greene</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 31.  1887  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Marshall’s or Hupa gooseberry</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Grossularia</genus_name>
    <species_name>marshallii</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Greene) Coville &amp; Britton</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 1–2 m.  Stems arched, puberulent; spines at nodes 3, 5–10 mm; prickles on internodes absent.  Leaves: petiole 1–4 cm, villous, pubescent, or glabrous; blade round-ovate, 3–5-lobed, cleft less than 1/2 to midrib, 2.5–3.5 cm, base shallowly cordate, surfaces sparsely pubescent, with nonglandular and stipitate-glandular hairs on veins and margins, lobes cuneate-rounded, margins with 2–5 rounded teeth, apex rounded to broadly acute.  Inflorescences pendent, solitary flowers or 2–3-flowered racemes, 2–3 cm, axis pubescent, stipitate-glandular.  Pedicels not jointed, 2–3 mm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular; bracts broadly ovate, 2–3 mm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium green or tinged with purple, campanulate (± as long as wide), 2–4 mm, pubescent; sepals not overlapping, strongly reflexed, purple or rust-red, long-triangular, 10–15 mm; petals connivent, erect, bright yellow, oblong-deltate-spatulate, strongly concave abaxially, 5–6 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens nearly 2.5 times as long as petals; filaments linear, 10–15 mm, glabrous; anthers cream, oval, 1–2 mm, apex rounded; ovary villous with weak, glandless bristles; styles connate nearly to stigmas, 10–15 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatability not known, dark red, oblong, 10–20 mm, prickles nonglandular, hairs sparse, appressed.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering May–Jul</phenology>
  <habitat>Subalpine and upper montane coniferous forests</habitat>
  <elevation>1200–2200 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Ribes marshallii occurs in the Coast Ranges of northernmost California and in the Klamath Mountains in Josephine County, Oregon.</discussion>
</treatment>
