<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>41.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>sericeum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Eastwood</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Calif. Acad. Sci., ser.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3, 2: 246, plate 24, fig. 9a–f.  1902  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Santa Lucia gooseberry</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Grossularia</genus_name>
    <species_name>sericea</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Eastwood) Coville &amp; Britton</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants 1–2 m.  Stems erect, densely hairy, bristly, bristles often gland-tipped; spines at nodes 3, 6–12 mm; prickles on internodes dense, often gland-tipped.  Leaves: petiole 0.5–1.5 cm, pubescent, stipitate-glandular; blade round-ovate, 3–5-lobed, cleft nearly 1/3 to midrib, 1–3.5 cm, base shallowly cordate, surfaces villous, stipitate-glandular, lobes cuneate-rounded, margins with 2–5 rounded teeth, apex rounded.  Inflorescences pendent, solitary flowers or 2–3-flowered racemes, 3.5–4.5 cm, axis stipitate-glandular and pilose.  Pedicels not jointed, 5–10 mm, pilose, stipitate-glandular; bracts lanceolate, 1–2 mm, pilose, stipitate-glandular.  Flowers: hypanthium green, conic to campanulate, 3–4 mm, sericeous; sepals not overlapping, strongly reflexed, greenish red, long-triangular, 6–8 mm; petals connivent, erect, white, oblong-deltate-spatulate, strongly concave abaxially, 4–6 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens 2 times as long as petals; filaments linear, 1–1.3 mm, glabrous; anthers cream, oblong, 1.5–1.8 mm, apex blunt or rounded; ovary pubescent, copiously glandular-bristly; styles connate 3/4 their lengths, 15 mm, glabrous.  Berries palatability not known, purple, globose, 15–25 mm, glandular-bristly.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering Apr–May</phenology>
  <habitat>Streamsides</habitat>
  <elevation>0–800 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Ribes sericeum is known primarily from the Santa Lucia Mountains; a disjunct population occurs north of Figueroa Mountain in Santa Barbara County.</discussion>
</treatment>
