<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">MYRSINACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ardisia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Thunberg" date="unknown">elliptica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Nov. Gen. Pl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>119.  1798  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family MYRSINACEAE;genus Ardisia;species elliptica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, not stoloniferous, 1–2 m; branchlets conspicuously black punctate-lineate, glabrous.  Leaves: petiole 5–10 mm, glabrous; blade oblanceolate or obovate, 6–12(–16) × 3–5(–7) cm, margins entire, revolute, (without vascularized nodules), apex obtuse or acute, surfaces glabrous.  Inflorescences lateral or subterminal, on basally thickened lateral branches, subumbels or umbels, 5+-flowered.  Pedicels erect, ca. 1–2 cm, glabrous.  Flowers: sepals 5, broadly ovate, ca. 1 mm, margins subentire, (minutely ciliate), apex rounded, densely black-punctate, glabrous; petals 5, pink or white, broadly ovate, 6–8 mm, margins entire, (hyaline, scarious), apex long-acuminate, densely punctate, glabrous; stamens subequaling petals; anthers linear-lanceolate, transversely septate-lobed, apex apiculate, punctate abaxially; ovary pellucid-punctate, glabrous; ovules 5+, multiseriate.  Drupes red or purplish black, subglobose, ca. 8 mm diam., minutely punctate.  2n = 48.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering Feb–Apr; fruiting Sep–Nov</description>
  <description type="morphology">Roadsides, scrub, near villages, edges of fields, along coasts</description>
  <description type="morphology">0–20 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Fla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">pantropical.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Shoebutton ardisia</other_name>
  <discussion>The names Ardisia solanacea Roxburgh and A. polycephala Wight have been misapplied to specimens of A. elliptica, which escapes from cultivation and is invasive.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
