<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="de Candolle" date="unknown">grossulariaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rydberg" date="1900">inerme</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. New York Bot. Gard.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 202.  1900,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family grossulariaceae;genus ribes;species inerme</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Grossularia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Rydberg) Coville &amp; Britton" date="unknown">inermis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Grossularia;species inermis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Ribes</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Douglas" date="unknown">divaricatum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Rydberg) McMinn" date="unknown">inerme</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ribes;species divaricatum;variety inerme;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 1–3 m.  Stems erect to sprawling, glabrous or sparsely retrorse-bristly when young and with black, sessile glands; spines at nodes sometimes absent or 1(–3), 1–8(–12) mm; prickles on internodes usually absent.  Leaves: petiole (0.4–)1–5.5 cm, tomentose to pilose, with few longer, slender, stipitate-glandular hairs; blade broadly ovate or pentagonal, 3–5-lobed, cleft nearly 1/2 to midrib, sometimes lateral lobes again less deeply cut into larger distal and smaller proximal segments, 1.5–8 cm, base rounded to broadly cordate, surfaces glabrous, sparsely pubescent, or pilose-villous, usually ciliate, lobes acutish or oblong-rounded, margins deeply crenate-serrate or coarsely round-toothed, apex acute or rounded.  Inflorescences pendent, solitary flowers or 2–5-flowered racemes, 1.5–3.5 cm, axis glabrous, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels not jointed, (1.5–)2.3–5.5(–8) mm, glabrous; bracts ovate, 1–3 mm, glandular-ciliolate.  Flowers: hypanthium green or greenish white, narrowly tubular to tubular-campanulate, 1.5–3.5 mm, glabrous or densely pilose to arachnoid-pubescent adaxially; sepals not overlapping, spreading to curved-reflexed (extended in fruit), white or greenish to purplish or reddish margined or tinged, oblong or oblong-lanceolate to narrowly lanceolate, 2.5–5 mm; petals connivent, erect, whitish or pinkish, broadly cuneate-obovate or cuneate-flabellate to cuneate or oblong, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 1–2.3 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens nearly 2 times as long as petals; filaments linear, 1.8–3.1 mm, mostly glabrous; anthers cream, ovate, 0.6–1.1 mm, apex with cup-shaped gland; ovary glabrous; styles connate 1/3–3/4 their lengths, 4.5–7 mm, proximally pilose-villous to middle or throughout.  Berries palatable, greenish or reddish purple to gray-black, nearly globose or globose, 7–11 mm, glabrous.  2n = 16.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America.</description>
  <number>44.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Ribes inerme has strikingly pilose-villous styles that are sometimes green proximally and reddish distally, with the stigmas sometimes dark green.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals glabrous; leaf blades glabrous (except for soft ciliation) or sparsely pubescent; peduncles</description>
      <determination>44a.   Ribes inerme var. inerme</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Sepals pilose; leaf blades pilose-villous; peduncles</description>
      <determination>44b.   Ribes inerme var. klamathense</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
