<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Desfontaines" date="unknown">symplocaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Jacquin" date="1760">SYMPLOCOS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Syst. Pl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 24.  1760  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family symplocaceae;genus SYMPLOCOS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek symplokos, connected, twisted, entwined, evidently alluding to connation of stamens and their adnation to petals in type species, S. martinicensis Jacquin]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, glabrous or hairy (hairs simple, 1-celled, with transverse septa); new vegetative growth from axillary and/or pseudoterminal buds.  Branches smooth at maturity, glabrous or white- or rufous-pubescent.  Leaves often sweet tasting; blade with marginal teeth usually glandular, apex acute to acuminate, midvein abaxially prominent, adaxially raised, prominent, or impressed [rarely flat].  Flowers fragrant; sepals imbricate; petals imbricate, white or yellow [pink, reddish, or lavender]; filaments glabrous [hairy]; anthers rotund-ovate to spheric.  Drupes usually blue, sometimes orange to brown [white], crowned by persistent calyx; endocarp 1[–5]-celled.  x = 11.</description>
  <description type="morphology">e</description>
  <description type="morphology">s United States</description>
  <description type="morphology">West Indies (Antilles)</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America (Argentina, Brazil)</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America (Argentina, Brazil) Asia (China, India, Japan)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pacific Islands (Fiji)</description>
  <description type="morphology">Australia</description>
  <description type="morphology">temperate</description>
  <description type="morphology">tropical</description>
  <description type="morphology">and subtropical areas.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 318 (2 in the flora): e, s United States, West Indies (Antilles), South America (Argentina, Brazil), Asia (China, India, Japan), Pacific Islands (Fiji), Australia; temperate, tropical, and subtropical areas.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 318 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>e, s United States, West Indies (Antilles), South America (Argentina, Brazil), Asia (China, India, Japan), Pacific Islands (Fiji), Australia; temperate, tropical, and subtropical areas.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sweetleaf</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 318 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>1 Leaf midveins impressed adaxially, blade margins closely serrate, serrulate, or dentate; inflorescences paniculate, usually internodal; flowers appearing with leaves; corolla lobes</discussion>
  <discussion>2.5–5 mm; styles 2–4 mm; drupes bright blue to bluish black 1.   Symplocos paniculata</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf midveins raised to prominent adaxially, blade margins usually obscurely crenulate-serrulate, teeth remote, sometimes nearly entire; inflorescences fasciculate, axillary; flowers appearing before leaves; corolla lobes 6–8 mm; styles 5–6 mm; drupes dark orange to brown</description>
      <determination>2.   Symplocos tinctoria</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
