<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">DIAPENSIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family DIAPENSIACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <other_name type="common_name">Diapensia Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 5, species 14 (4 genera, 6 species in the flora): North America, Europe, Asia.</discussion>
  <discussion>In addition to the four genera treated here, one other genus completes the family: Berneuxia Decaisne, with one species in the Sino-Himalayan Mountains.  Diapensia lapponica and its sister D. obovata, as a pair, are circumboreal in distribution; all of the other species of the family are narrowly distributed.  A phylogenetic analysis based on morphology and molecular data from four genes (K. Rönblom and A. A. Anderberg 2002) indicated that Galax is sister to all other genera; Pyxidanthera is sister to the remaining genera at the next higher node; relationships among Berneuxia, Diapensia, and Shortia are unresolved.  In this interpretation, the “inverted-eucamptodromous” venation pattern shared by Diapensia and Pyxidanthera (H. T. Murphy and J. W. Hardin 1976) was perhaps developed in parallel.</discussion>
  <discussion>Leaves of Diapensia, Galax, and some Shortia species become reddish to purplish or orange-bronze (anthocyanic) in the fall and winter.  The colored leaves of Galax are gathered in the fall for the florist trade.  Leaves of all genera of Diapensiaceae sequester large amounts of aluminum (L. Schultz, pers. comm.), an unusual characteristic for temperate plants.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Doonan, S.  1993.  The Diapensia family.  Bull. Amer. Rock Gard. Soc. 51: 97–106.</reference>
    <reference>Qin, H. N. and B. M. Bartholomew.  2005.  Diapensiaceae.  In: Wu Z. and P. H. Raven, eds.  1994+.  Flora of China.  11+ vols.  Beijing and St. Louis.  Vol. 14, pp. 235–237.   Rönblom, K. and A. A. Anderberg.  2002.  Phylogeny of Diapensiaceae based on molecular data and morphology.  Syst. Bot. 27: 383–395.</reference>
    <reference>Scott, P. J.  2004.  Diapensiaceae.  In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds.  1990+.  The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants.  9+ vols.  Berlin etc.  Vol. 6, pp. 117–121.</reference>
    <reference>Scott, P. J. and R. T. Day.  1983.  Diapensiaceae: A review of the taxonomy.  Taxon 32: 417–423.</reference>
    <reference>Wood, C. E. Jr. and R. B. Channell.  1959.  The Empetraceae and Diapensiaceae of the southeastern United States.  J. Arnold Arbor. 40: 161–171.</reference>
    <reference>Xi, Y. Z. and Tang Y. C.  1990.  Pollen morphology and phylogenetic relationships in the Diapensiaceae.  Cathaya 2: 89–112.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades subpalmately veined; inflorescences compact racemes; corollas 3.5–8 mm; anthers 1-locular, transversely dehiscent</description>
      <determination>1.   Galax, p. 333</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades pinnately veined or appearing 1-veined; inflorescences solitary flowers; corollas 14–25 mm or 2–10 mm; anthers 2-locular, transversely or longitudinally dehiscent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Herbs, scapose; stems unbranched, erect; leaves basal, 30–80 mm, blade orbiculate to elliptic-orbiculate or ovate-oblong to ovate, pinnately veined; corollas 14–25 mm; anthers longitudinally dehiscent; staminodes present</description>
      <determination>2.   Shortia, p. 334</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, caulescent; stems branched, mostly prostrate to decumbent; leaves cauline, 2–15 mm, blade lanceolate or narrowly oblanceolate to ovate, ovate-lanceolate, obovate, narrowly spatulate, or slightly falcate, appearing 1-veined; corollas 2–10 mm; anthers transversely or longitudinally dehiscent; staminodes absent or vestigial.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves often densely congested, alternate, blade apex minutely apiculate; inflorescences sessile; anthers transversely dehiscent</description>
      <determination>3.   Pyxidanthera, p. 336</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves densely imbricate or in compact whorls, blade apex acute or obtuse (not apiculate); inflorescences pedicellate to subsessile; anthers longitudinally dehiscent</description>
      <determination>4.   Diapensia, p. 337</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
