<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>2.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>SHORTIA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Torrey &amp; A. Gray</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. J. Sci. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>42: 48.  1842, name conserved  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Oconee bells</common_name>
  <common_name>little coltsfoot</common_name>
  <etymology>[For Charles Wilkens Short, 1794–1863, Kentucky botanist]</etymology>
  <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
  <description>Herbs, colonial, scapose, rhizomatous; rhizome slender, scale-leaved, lignescent.  Stems erect, unbranched.  Leaves basal, rosulate from rhizome buds, 30–80 mm; petiole present; blade orbiculate to elliptic-orbiculate, ovate-oblong, or ovate, margins coarsely crenate-serrate, apex emarginate to truncate, surfaces glabrous, pinnately veined.  Scapes bracteate, elongating after flowering.  Inflorescences solitary flowers.  Flowers: sepals distinct; petals connate in proximal 1/4–1/2, corolla campanulate to funnelform, 15–25 mm, lobes white to rose-purple, margins obtusely toothed to laciniate or fringed; anthers 2-locular, without basal spurs, longitudinally dehiscent; filaments adnate to corolla tube; staminodes present.  x = 6.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 6 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>se United States</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>The Asian species of Shortia occur in Japan (three endemic), Taiwan and the Ryukyus (one endemic), and Yunnan Province, China (one endemic).</discussion>
  <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES">
    <reference>Barnes, P. G.  1990.  A summary of the genus Shortia.  Plantsman 12: 23–34.</reference>
    <reference>Davies, P. A.  1952.  Geographical variation in Shortia galacifolia.  Rhodora 54: 121–124.</reference>
    <reference>Davies, P. A.  1955.  Distribution and abundance of Shortia galacifolia.  Rhodora 57: 189–201.</reference>
    <reference>Hatley, J. R.  1977.  An Analysis of Variation in Shortia galacifolia.  M.S. thesis.  North Carolina State University.   Vivian, V. E.  1967.  Shortia galacifolia, its life history and microclimate requirements.  Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 94: 369–387.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>
