<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">diapensiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="1803">pyxidanthera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="1803">barbulata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 152, plate 17.  1803  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family diapensiaceae;genus pyxidanthera;species barbulata</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems commonly elongate and creeping, sometimes compact and short-creeping or not creeping, glabrous or sparsely hairy; internodes usually 1+ mm.  Leaf blades narrowly oblance-olate to lanceolate, 3.5–7(–10) mm, herbaceous, those of fertile shoots ciliate along proximal margins, adaxial surface usually white-pilose on proximal 1/5–1/3.  Flowers: calyx pinkish; corolla lobes 3–5 mm.  2n = 12.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering Mar–May</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pine savannas and barrens (commonly with Pinus rigida, sometimes with Quercus marilandica and Q)</description>
  <description type="morphology">10–200 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.J.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">S.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Va.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering Mar-May. Pine savannas and barrens (commonly with Pinus rigida, sometimes with Quercus marilandica and Q. ilicifolia), pine flatwoods, pocosin margins, streamhead ecotones, edges of sandhill seepage bogs (with Pinus serotina and P. palustris, usually with Aristida stricta and Vaccinium crassifolium), depressions, primarily mesic to hydric sites, wet sands and peaty sands, sometimes submesic sands, usually with permanently or seasonally high water table, often with Sphagnum; 10-200 m; N.J., N.Y., N.C., S.C., Va.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering Mar-May.</phenology>
      <habitat>Pine savannas and barrens (commonly with Pinus rigida, sometimes with Quercus marilandica and Q. ilicifolia), pine flatwoods, pocosin margins, streamhead ecotones, edges of sandhill seepage bogs (with Pinus serotina and P. palustris, usually with Aristida stricta and Vaccinium crassifolium), depressions, primarily mesic to hydric sites, wet sands and peaty sands, sometimes submesic sands, usually with permanently or seasonally high water table, often with Sphagnum;</habitat>
      <elevation>10-200 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>N.J., N.Y., N.C., S.C., Va.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Common pyxie-moss</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">big pyxie</other_name>
  <discussion>There are no current or historical records of Pyxidanthera barbulata from Delaware or Maryland, where habitats exist that seem comparable to those where the species occurs north and south.</discussion>
  <discussion>Pyxidanthera barbulata is in the Center for Plant Conservation’s National Collection of Endangered Plants.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
