<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">DIAPENSIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pyxidanthera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Wells" date="unknown">brevifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>44: 238, plate 9.  1929  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family DIAPENSIACEAE;genus Pyxidanthera;species brevifolia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pyxidanthera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">barbulata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(Wells) H. E. Ahles" date="unknown">brevifolia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pyxidanthera;species barbulata;variety brevifolia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sandhills or Wells’s pyxie-moss</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">little pyxie</other_name>
  <discussion>Pyxidanthera brevifolia is known only from a six-county area in the sandhills of North Carolina and South Carolina, where it is sympatric with P. barbulata.  It occurs in xeric sites upslope; P. barbulata occurs in moist sites (seepage areas or streamhead ecotones).  R. B. Primack and R. Wyatt (1975) concluded that recognition of only a single taxon is justified, based on a study of seven populations in the area where the two taxa are sympatric; they found that variation in leaf length and corolla lobe length is “clinal and associated with differences in soil moisture retaining capacity and other environmental parameters.”  Recent intensive surveys in this area (Nature Conservancy 1993), in contrast, indicate that putative morphological intermediates are primarily phenotypic responses of P. brevifolia to shading by leaf litter and of P. barbulata to disturbance and/or canopy removal.  The two taxa are morphologically and ecologically distinct, and ecologically intermediate sites usually are rarely occupied by Pyxidanthera.  The sharp divide in habitat apparently provides reproductive isolation, and the taxa are appropriately recognized at specific rank.  The key features consistently separate them, essentially returning to distinctions made by A. E. Radford et al. (1968).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
