<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Guy L. Nesom</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Lindley" date="unknown">diapensiaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">DIAPENSIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 141.  1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 69.  1754  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family diapensiaceae;genus DIAPENSIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek dia-, composed, and pente, five, alluding to sepal, petal, and stamen numbers]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, forming tussocks, cushions, domes, or mats, caulescent, taprooted.  Stems mostly prostrate to decumbent, branched; branches procumbent or decumbent to erect.  Leaves cauline, mostly opposite or compactly whorled, densely imbricate or crowded, 3–15 mm; petiole present or absent; blade oblong-lanceolate to narrowly spatulate, obovate, or spatulate-elliptic, slightly falcate, margins entire, apex acute or obtuse, surfaces glabrous, appearing 1-veined, sometimes with 1–2, indistinct, lateral veins.  Inflorescences solitary flowers, pedicellate to subsessile, immediately subtended by 2–3 bracts.  Pedicels ebracteate, elongating after anthesis.  Flowers: sepals distinct or connate proximally; petals connate in proximal 1/2, corolla cupulate to campanulate, 7–10 mm, lobes white to cream or pinkish tinged to rose, margins entire; anthers 2-locular, without basal spurs, longitudinally dehiscent; filaments adnate to corolla tube; staminodes absent or vestigial.  x = 6.</description>
  <description type="morphology">North America</description>
  <description type="morphology">n Europe</description>
  <description type="morphology">Asia.</description>
  <number>4.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Pincushion plant</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 5 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The three temperate species of Diapensia are endemic to the Sino-Himalayan Mountains.  They differ as a group from the two boreal species by their production of vestigial staminodes (see F. Ludlow 1976).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Evans, W. E.  1927.  A revision of the genus Diapensia with special reference to the Sino-Himalayan species.  Notes Roy. Bot. Gard. Edinburgh 15: 209–236.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants forming tussocks; branches not adventitiously rooted; leaf blades oblong-oblanceolate to narrowly spatulate, 7–15 × 1.3–2.3 mm, margins with narrow hyaline flange proximally</description>
      <determination>1.   Diapensia lapponica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants usually forming mats or low mounds or cushions; branches adventitiously rooted; leaf blades obovate to spatulate-elliptic, 3–8(–12) × 1.5–2.2(–3) mm, margins sometimes with narrow hyaline flange</description>
      <determination>2.   Diapensia obovata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
