<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>T. Lawrence Mellichamp</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">sarraceniaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Torrey" date="1853">DARLINGTONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6(4): 4, plate 12.  1853, name conserved  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family sarraceniaceae;genus DARLINGTONIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For William Darlington, 1782–1863, Philadelphia botanist]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs colonial, stoloniferous; rhizomes horizontal.  Pitchers persistent, erect, monomorphic, twisted through 90–270°, yellowish green, often suffused with red, distally enlarging into globose head, firm, surfaces glabrous; orifice round, facing ground, not covered by hood; hood arising adaxially on rim of orifice, pendulous, fishtail-shaped, flattened or slightly twisted, 2-lobed, lobes widely divergent laterally from pitcher axis, yellowish green to reddish, base narrowed to neck, apex acute to rounded.  Phyllodia absent.  Scapes 1, slightly longer to much longer than pitchers; bracts usually 9, alternate along scape, clasping, erect or spreading, lanceolate, apex acute.  Flowers odorless; sepals persistent, lance-ovate to oblanceolate, margins entire, apex acute; petals deciduous, touching, forming curtain surrounding stamens and pistil, pendulous, ovate, each notched beyond middle (distally) so that indentations of adjacent petals align forming 5 holes in corolla, margins entire, apex acuminate; stamens 15, distinct; filaments uniform in length; anthers basifixed; ovary turbinate, shallowly 10-lobed, apex depressed; style terminal, arising from depressed apex of ovary, terminating in 5 radially diverging, filiform arms covered with stigmatic cells laterally.  Capsules obconic, finely tuberculate, acropetally dehiscent.  Seeds ca. 1000, long-clavate, not keeled, long-papillate.  x = 15.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw North America.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">California pitcher plant</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cobra-lily or</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">plant</other_name>
  <discussion>Chrysamphora Greene</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1: nw North America.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>DeBuhr, L. E.  1973.  Distribution and Reproductive Biology of Darlingtonia californica.  M.S. thesis.  Claremont Graduate School.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
