<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">SARRACENIACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Sarracenia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">psittacina</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 311 (as psyttacina)</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>2: [341].  1803  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family SARRACENIACEAE;genus Sarracenia;species psittacina;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Parrot pitcher plant</other_name>
  <discussion>Sarracenia psittacina is usually the latest-flowering species of the genus.  It is distinguished by basal rosettes of radiating pitchers often resting flat against the ground.  Sometimes, the clumps mound up or form mats, produced from the intermingling of multiple growing points.  It can grow in some of the wettest habitats, often submerged under water for periods—perhaps trapping aquatic invertebrates.  The pitchers can be overlooked in dense vegetation, the presence of the plants indicated only by their flowering scapes emerging through the matted grass.  It occurs on the coastal plain from eastern Georgia to extreme northeastern Florida, west to southwestern Georgia across the Florida panhandle to southern Alabama, southern Mississippi, and barely into southeastern Louisiana.  A form bearing pitchers to 40 cm long may be found in the wetter parts of the Okefenokee Swamp of southeastern Georgia, along with S. minor var. okefenokeensis.</discussion>
  <discussion>Sarracenia psittacina is unusual in that the proximal 1/2 of the pitchers are lined internally with a meshwork of retrorse hairs, to 4 mm, that force prey ever deeper into the trapping tubes.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
