<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Klotzsch" date="unknown">clethraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">CLETHRA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 396.  1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5. 188.  1754  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family clethraceae;genus CLETHRA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek klethra, alder, alluding to resemblance of leaves of certain species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants sometimes spreading by root suckers.  Leaves spirally arranged, often seemingly verticillate at ends of twigs; blade not coriaceous, margins revolute, surfaces glabrous or tomentose abaxially, glabrous or with sparse, short-stellate hairs, especially when young, adaxially, venation pinnate.  Inflorescences borne on new growth, racemes solitary or in clusters of 2–4, bracteate.  Pedicels ridged and somewhat flattened laterally, 1-bracteate basally.  Flowers fragrant; sepals imbricate in bud; petals spreading at anthesis, weakly 5-ridged, apex obtuse; filaments adnate to corolla basally, straight or S-shaped, elongate, glabrous or hairy; anthers reflexed in bud, erect at anthesis, obsagittate, base attenuate, papillose, thecae divergent distally; style straight.  Capsules globose, sutures thin.  Seeds strongly flattened, slightly winged; testa thin.  x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">s, e North America, Mexico, Central America, South America, e Asia, Atlantic Islands (Madeira).</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sweet pepperbush</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 65 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades: apex acuminate, margins toothed, proximalmost tooth averaging 2.4 cm distal to base; bracts longer than flowers; filaments glabrous or with scattered, simple hairs</description>
      <determination>1.   Clethra acuminata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades: apex obtuse to acute, margins toothed, proximalmost tooth averaging 3.4 cm distal to base; bracts shorter than flowers; filaments glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Young shoots and abaxial surface of new leaves sparsely hairy, adaxial surface glabrous; petioles 2.5–3.5(–6) cm; styles 6–7 mm, hairy in proximal 1/2, hairs simple, straight; filaments 0.2–0.3(–0.4) mm wide</description>
      <determination>2.   Clethra alnifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Young shoots and abaxial surface of new leaves woolly-tomentose, adaxial surface sparsely hairy; petioles 0.5–1(–1.5) cm; styles 3.5–5 mm, hairy; filaments 0.4–0.5(–0.7) mm wide</description>
      <determination>3.   Clethra tomentosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
