<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Craig C. Freeman</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Salisbury ex Gray" date="1821">MONESES</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Nat. Arr. Brit. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 396, 403.  1821  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus MONESES</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek monos, one, single, and hesis, delight, alluding to attractive, solitary flower]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, chlorophyllous, autotrophic.  Stems erect, glabrous or papillose distally.  Leaves cauline, sometimes appearing basal, alternate or pseudoverticillate in 1–4 whorls; petiole present; blade not maculate, broadly elliptic to orbiculate, subcoriaceous, margins crenate-serrate to serrate, plane, surfaces glabrous.  Inflorescences solitary flowers, not lax in bud or flower, erect in fruit; peduncular bracts present or absent.  Pedicels absent.  Flowers radially symmetric, spreading or nodding; sepals 5, connate proximally, often obscurely so, calyx lobes ovate to narrowly ovate; petals 5, distinct, creamy white, without basal tubercles, corolla rotate to broadly campanulate; intrastaminal nectary disc absent; stamens 10, included; filaments broad proximally, gradually narrowed medially, slender distally, glabrous; anthers oblong, without awns, with tubules, dehiscent by 2 round pores; pistil 5-carpellate; ovary imperfectly 5-locular; placentation intruded-parietal; style (exserted), straight, expanded distally; stigma 5-lobed, without subtending ring of hairs.  Fruits capsular, erect, dehiscence loculicidal, no cobwebby tissue exposed by splitting valves at dehiscence.  Seeds ca. 1000, fusiform, winged.  x = 11, 12, 13, 16.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Woodnymph</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">single delight</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">one-flowered wintergreen</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">monésès uniflore</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 1: North America, Eurasia; circumboreal.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
