<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>3.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>CHIMAPHILA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Pursh</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 279, 300.  1813  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Prince’s-plume</common_name>
  <common_name>chimaphile</common_name>
  <etymology>[Greek cheima, winter, and philia, love, alluding to evergreen habit]</etymology>
  <author>Craig C. Freeman</author>
  <description>Subshrubs, chlorophyllous, autotrophic.  Stems erect, rarely decumbent, glabrous or papillose to hispidulous, especially distally.  Leaves cauline, alternate or pseudoverticillate in 2–5(–6) whorls; petiole present; blade maculate or not, lanceolate, elliptic-lanceolate, ovate-lanceolate, oblong-lanceolate, ovate, lanceolate-oblong, oblanceolate, elliptic, or spatulate, coriaceous, margins entire, serrulate, serrate, or crenate-serrate, revolute, surfaces glabrous or papillose.  Inflorescences corymbs or subumbels, rarely solitary flowers, not lax in bud or flower, erect in fruit, (symmetric); peduncular bracts absent; inflorescence bracts adnate to pedicels, sometimes scarcely so.  Pedicels erect in fruit, (glabrous or papillose to hispidulous); bracteoles absent.  Flowers radially symmetric, nodding or spreading; sepals 5, connate proximally, often obscurely so, calyx lobes ovate, broadly ovate, or suborbiculate; petals 5, distinct, white, pink, or rose, often tinged violet, without basal tubercles, (surfaces glabrous), corolla rotate to crateriform or broadly crateriform; intrastaminal nectary disc present; stamens 10, included; filaments broad proximally, abruptly narrowed medially, slender distally, dilated basal portions ciliate or villous to densely villous; anthers oblong, without awns, with tubules, dehiscent by 2 crescent-shaped to round pores; pistil 5-carpellate; ovary imperfectly 5-locular; placentation intruded-parietal; style (included), straight, expanded distally; stigma entire or obscurely 5-ridged, without subtending ring of hairs.  Fruits capsular, erect, dehiscence loculicidal, no cobwebby tissue exposed by splitting valves at dehiscence.  Seeds ca. 1000, fusiform, winged.  x = 13.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 5 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>West Indies (Hispaniola)</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Eurasia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Ethnobotanical studies have documented a wide variety of drug and food uses of Chimaphila among more than two dozen tribes of Native Americans (D. E. Moerman 1998; K. Sheth et al. 1967).</discussion>
  <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES">
    <reference>Standley, L. A., S. S.-H. Kim, and I. M. Hjersted.  1988.  Reproductive biology of two sympatric species of Chimaphila.  Rhodora 90: 233–244.</reference>
    <reference>Takahashi, Hiroshi.  1986b.  Pollen polyads and their variation in Chimaphila (Pyrolaceae).  Grana 25: 161–169.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence bracts broadly ovate to broadly obovate; inflorescences 1–3-flowered; calyx lobes (3–)5–6.5 mm; stigmas 1.6–2.2(–2.8) mm wide</statement>
      <determination>2.   Chimaphila menziesii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence bracts acicular to linear-lanceolate; inflorescences (1–)2–7-flowered; calyx lobes 1–4.1 mm; stigmas 2–4 mm wide.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades maculate; dilated basal portions of filaments densely villous</statement>
      <determination>1.   Chimaphila maculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades not maculate; dilated basal portions of filaments ciliate</statement>
      <determination>3.   Chimaphila umbellata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
