<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>49.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Ribes</genus_name>
    <species_name>oxyacanthoides</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 201.  1753  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Canadian gooseberry</common_name>
  <description>Plants 0.3–2 m.  Stems erect or spreading, strongly puberulent, pubescence often intermixed with glandular hairs, becoming glabrate; spines at nodes 1–3 (–7), 2.2–13 mm; prickles on internodes absent or sparse to dense.  Leaves: petiole (0.4–)1–4 cm, finely and softly pubescent, sparsely to densely pubescent, or pilose, and glandular-puberulent or glabrous, sometimes abaxially more glandular, or glabrous; blade roundish to reniform, 3–5(–7)-lobed, cleft 1/2 to midrib, (0.7–)1.5–4 cm, base truncate to cordate, surfaces abaxially pilose to villous, sometimes glabrate or glabrous, stipitate- and sessile-glandular, lobes oblong, oblong-cuneate, or cuneate-rounded, margins irregularly crenate-dentate into prominent, unequal teeth, apex rounded to broadly acute.  Inflorescences spreading, solitary flowers or 2–3(–4)-flowered racemes, 2–3 cm, axis glabrous or stipitate-glandular and puberulent to pilose, flowers evenly spaced.  Pedicels not jointed, 1–6 mm, glabrous or villous stipitate-glandular and puberulent to pilose; bracts broadly ovate-deltate, 1–2 mm (much shorter than leaves), finely glandular-ciliate.  Flowers: hypan-thium green or greenish white to white or pinkish, narrowly tubular or campanulate to rotate, 1.4–5.5(–6.6) mm, glabrous abaxially, villous-pubescent adaxially; sepals not overlapping, spreading to somewhat reflexed, greenish white or greenish yellow, sometimes pinkish or purplish with slightly reddish tinge, broadly to narrowly oblong-ovate or elliptic-obovate, 1–6 mm; petals connivent, becoming separated, erect, white or pinkish, oblong-oblanceolate or obovate to oblong-obovate, flabelliform-reniform, or obovate-rhombic, not conspicuously revolute or inrolled, 1–3.5 mm; nectary disc not prominent; stamens as long as or only slightly longer than petals; filaments slightly expanded at base, 0.5–3.5 mm, glabrous; anthers cream, oblong-oval, 0.6–1.3 mm, apex rounded; ovary glabrous; styles connate 1/3–3/4 their lengths, 2.5–8(–9) mm, pilose in proximal 1/2.  Berries palatable, reddish, greenish purple, or deep purplish black, globose, 7–16 mm, glabrous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 5 (5 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Styles 2.5–3.3 mm; hypanthia 1.4–3 mm; sepals</statement>
      <determination>49b.   Ribes oxyacanthoides var. hendersonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Styles 5.5–9 mm; hypanthia 1.5–6.6 mm; sepals 2.5–6 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Sepals finely pilose</statement>
      <determination>49e.   Ribes oxyacanthoides var. cognatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Sepals glabrous or with scattered hairs.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Peduncles 6–15 mm</statement>
      <determination>49c.   Ribes oxyacanthoides var. irriguum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Peduncles 2–6 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades densely pilose abaxially, base truncate or subcordate; sepal apices rounded</statement>
      <determination>49a.   Ribes oxyacanthoides var. oxyacanthoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaf blades finely pubescent abaxially, base deeply cordate; sepal apices truncate</statement>
      <determination>49d.   Ribes oxyacanthoides var. setosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
