<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>1.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Pleuricospora</genus_name>
    <species_name>fimbriolata</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 369.  1868  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Fringed pinesap</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Pleuricospora</genus_name>
    <species_name>longipetala</species_name>
    <species_authority>Howell</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Inflorescences 6–10 cm; bracts cream, 8–15 × 4–8 mm.  Flowers: sepals 5–8 × 2–4 cm; petals oblong, 8–10 × 4–6 cm, base slightly saccate, apex fimbriate; stamens 0.8–1.1 cm; anthers erect at anthesis, cream, 3–4 mm; ovary 3–5 × 4–5 mm, glabrous; style 1.5–2.5 × 2 mm; stigma apex lobed.  Berries 1 cm diam.  Seeds 0.2–0.5 mm diam.  2n = 52.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering late spring–summer</phenology>
  <habitat>Moist, coniferous or mixed-deciduous forests</habitat>
  <elevation>100–1800 m</elevation>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>b. Ericaceae   Jussieu subfam. Arbutoideae   Niedenzu, Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 11: 135.  1889</discussion>
  <author>Gordon C. Tucker</author>
  <discussion>Arbuteae Meisner</discussion>
  <description>Shrubs or trees, multicellular hairs present or, sometimes, absent (Comarostaphylis); bark smooth, not furrowed, often flaky, sometimes shredding.  Stems erect or prostrate.  Leaves persistent (deciduous in Arctous), usually alternate, sometimes opposite or whorled (Ornithostaphylos), rarely opposite (Xylococcus); petiole usually present, sometimes absent (Arctostaphylos); blade plane, abaxial groove absent.  Inflorescences terminal, panicles or racemes; perulae absent; bracts much shorter than sepals; bracteoles 2 or absent (Arctostaphylos, Arctous).  Flowers pendulous; sepals (4–)5; petals (4–)5, connate, corolla deciduous, usually urceolate, sometimes cylindric, conic, or globose, lobes much shorter than tube; intrastaminal nectary disc present; stamens (8–)10; anthers dehiscent by slits or pores; ovary 2–10-locular; placentation axile; style straight.  Fruits drupaceous (baccate in Arbutus), (pulp mealy or juicy), indehiscent; pyrenes 1–5, often connate into stonelike endocarp.  Seeds 1–10, usually distinct, sometimes connate, globose (sometimes 3-sided), not winged.</description>
  <discussion>Genera 6, species 91 or 92 (6 genera, 70 species in the flora): North America, Mexico, Central America, Europe, n Africa, n Atlantic Islands (Canary Islands); most species endemic to western North America.</discussion>
  <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCE">
    <reference>Hileman, L. C., M. C. Vasey, and V. T. Parker.  2001.  Phylogeny and biogeography of the Arbutoideae (Ericaceae): Implications for the Madrean-Tethyan hypothesis.  Syst. Bot. 26: 131–143.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>
