<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>George M. Diggs Jr.</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Zuccarini" date="1837">COMAROSTAPHYLIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Abh. Math.-Phys. Cl. Königl. Bayer. Akad. Wiss.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 331.  1837  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus COMAROSTAPHYLIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek komaros, arbutus, and staphyle, cluster of grapes, alluding to resemblance of fruit clusters to those of Arbutus unedo]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, burled, (capable of sprouting after fire); bark gray to reddish, peeling to shredding [flaking, exfoliating, sometimes in patches].  Stems usually erect to spreading, rarely trailing or mat-forming, branching, glabrous or densely hairy.  Leaves persistent [rarely facultatively drought-deciduous], bifacial; blade narrowly ovate to ovate or elliptic to obovate or broadly ovate, coriaceous, margins usually serrate to serrulate, rarely subentire, plane or revolute, abaxial surface usually densely gray-tomentose, rarely subglabrous, adaxial (green, shining), usually glabrous, sometimes hairy along midvein.  Inflorescences racemes [panicles], solitary or clustered, 5–30-flowered.  Flowers bisexual; sepals (drying) persistent, (4–)5, distinct or slightly connate, narrowly triangular to subulate or nearly acicular; petals (4–)5, (imbricate), connate for 3/4+ their lengths, white [greenish white, pale yellow, pink, or red], corolla cylindric to nearly globose; stamens 10, included; filaments dilated near base; anthers with 2 dorsal awns, dehiscent by 2 slits 1/4–1/2 as long as anthers; ovary 5-locular, (papillate); stigma slightly capitate.  Drupes red [nearly black to dark purple], globose, juicy, warty, granular, or papillate (with multicellular papillae radiating ± perpendicularly outward); pyrenes 5, connate into solid, thick-walled, stonelike, globose endocarp.  Seeds 5, connate.  x = 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">California, Mexico, Central America.</description>
  <number>14.</number>
  <discussion>Arctostaphylos Adanson sect. Comarostaphylis (Zuccarini) A. Gray; Arctostaphylos subg. Comarostaphylis (Zuccarini) A. Gray</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 10 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Diggs, G. M.  1987.  Numerical systematics of Comarostaphylis (Arbuteae, Ericaceae).  Syst. Bot. 12: 586–600.</reference>
    <reference>Diggs, G. M.  1995.  Comarostaphylis.  In: Organization for Flora Neotropica.  1968+.  Flora Neotropica.  98+ nos.  New York.  No. 66, pp. 146–193.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
