<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gordon C. Tucker,Wayne J. Elisens</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ERICACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cassiope</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Pallas) D. Don" date="unknown">lycopodioides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Edinburgh New Philos. J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 158.  1834,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ERICACEAE;genus Cassiope;species lycopodioides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Andromeda</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Pallas" date="unknown">lycopodioides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Ross.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1(2): 55, plate 73, fig. 1.  1789</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Andromeda;species lycopodioides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cassiope</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">lycopodioides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="subspecies" authority="Calder &amp; Roy L. Taylor" date="unknown">cristapilosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cassiope;species lycopodioides;subspecies cristapilosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems prostrate to weakly ascending, forming loose mats, hairy.  Leaves not or somewhat imbricate, closely appressed to stem, not strongly 4-ranked; blade linear-lanceolate, abaxial groove absent, 2–3 × 0.5–1.2 mm, margins conspicuously scarious, curled hairs present at leaf tips (at least on young leaves), abaxial base and adaxial surface hairy.  Flowers: sepals 1.5–2 mm, margins hyaline; petals connate for ca. 1/2 their lengths, tips recurved, corolla white, campanulate, 6–8 mm; stamens to 3 mm.  Capsules ca. 3 mm.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering Jun–Aug</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alpine rocky slopes and crevices</description>
  <description type="morphology">100–2000 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">B.C.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Alaska</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wash.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, shrubs, or trees, multicellular hairs present; bark smooth or furrowed, not flaky (peeling or shredding in Menziesia).  Stems erect to decumbent, sprawling, creeping, trailing, prostrate, or procumbent.  Leaves deciduous or persistent, usually alternate, sometimes opposite, whorled, or spirally arranged; petiole usually present; blade plane or acicular, abaxial groove present or absent.  Inflorescences axillary or terminal, fascicles, racemes, panicles, capitula, cymes, umbels, corymbs, spikes, or solitary flowers; perulae present or absent; bracts much shorter than sepals (sometimes absent).  Flowers bisexual or unisexual, erect or pendulous, usually radially or bilaterally symmetric; sepals (2–)4–5(–7); petals absent or (2–)4–5(–7), connate or distinct, corolla deciduous or persistent, campanulate, salverform, rotate, saucer-shaped, funnelform, cylindric, or urceolate, (with pockets holding anthers until they open in some Kalmia), lobes shorter than tube; intrastaminal nectary disc present; stamens (2–)5–10; anthers dehiscent by lateral pores or slits; ovary (2–)5–10-locular; placentation axile (parietal distally in Epigaea); style straight or declinate (curved in Elliottia).  Fruits capsular, dehiscence usually septicidal, sometimes loculicidal or septifragal, or drupaceous, (dry to fleshy), indehiscent.  Seeds 2–300, distinct, obovoid, ovoid, or ellipsoid to oblong, linear, fusiform, or planoconvex, winged or not.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <discussion>Subspecies cristapilosa was based on a collection from the Queen Charlotte Islands, British Columbia.  The only distinction that the authors drew between it and subsp. lycopodioides was that subsp. cristapilosa has one to three crisped apical hairs on the leaves.  Their claim that subsp. lycopodioides has entirely glabrous leaves is not supported.  All specimens of Cassiope lycopodioides that I have seen have curled hairs on the leaf apices of at least the young leaves.  The hairs appear to be fugacious.  However, subsp. cristapilosa does differ from subsp. lycopodioides in several features.  It lacks the hyaline leaf margin as well as the adaxial surface and abaxial leaf base pubescence.  In addition, the stems are thicker, and the pedicels and corollas are longer.  This insular material warrants further investigation.</discussion>
  <discussion>d. Ericaceae   Jussieu subfam. Ericoideae Link, Handbuch 1: 602.  1829(as Ericeae)</discussion>
  <discussion>Empetraceae Hooker &amp; Lindley</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera 18, species ca. 1850 (14 genera, 58 species in the flora): North America, Mexico, West Indies (Cuba), Central America, s South America, Europe, Asia, Africa, Atlantic Islands, Australia; especially diverse in western Europe and southern Africa.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bohm, B. A., S. W. Brim, R. J. Hebda, and P. F. Stevens.  1978.  Generic limits in the tribe Cladothamneae (Ericaceae) and its position in the Rhododendroideae.  J. Arnold Arbor.  59: 311–341.</reference>
    <reference>Copeland, H. F.  1943.  A study, anatomical and taxonomic, of the genera of Rhododendroideae.  Amer. Midl. Naturalist 30: 533–625.</reference>
    <reference>Hebda, R. J. and C. C. Chinnappa.  1980.  Cytological evidence for generic limits in tribe Cladothamneae.  Canad. J. Bot. 58: 1119–1120.</reference>
    <reference>Kron, K. A.  1997.  Phylogenetic relationships of Rhododendroideae (Ericaceae).  Amer. J. Bot. 84: 973–980.</reference>
    <reference>Kron, K. A. and W. S. Judd.  1990.  Phylogenetic relationships within the Rhodoreae (Ericaceae) with specific comments on the placement of Ledum.  Syst. Bot. 15: 57–68.</reference>
    <reference>Kron, K. A. and J. M. King.  1996.  Cladistic relationships of Kalmia, Leiophyllum, and Loiseleuria (Phyllodoceae, Ericaceae) based on rbcL and nrITS data.  Syst. Bot. 21: 17–29.</reference>
    <reference>Metheny, D. 1991. Hardy Heather Species, and Some Related Plants. Seaside, Oreg.</reference>
    <reference>Mikolajski, A. 1997. Heathers. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Small, D. and A. Small. 2001. Handy Guide to Heathers, ed. 3. Ipswich.</reference>
    <reference>Underhill, T. L. 1971. Heaths and Heathers: Calluna, Daboecia and Erica. Newton Abbot.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
