<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Therorhodion</genus_name><species_name>camtschaticum</species_name><species_authority>(Pallas) Small</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in N. L. Britton et al.,  N. Amer. Fl. </publication_title><place_in_publication>29: 45.  1914  ,</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Kamchatka rhododendron</common_name><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Rhododendron</genus_name><species_name>camtschaticum</species_name><species_authority>Pallas</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. Ross. </publication_title><place_in_publication>1(1): 48, plate 33 [as kamtschaticum].  1784</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Shrubs usually to 2 dm.  Stems multicellular, eglandular-hairy (hairs unbranched), sometimes also stipitate-glandular-hairy, glabrate with age.  Leaves often clustered toward distal portions of shoots; blade elliptic to obovate, 1–4.5(–6) × 0.7–2.4 cm, thin, margins ciliate (hairs eglandular), plane, apex rounded to obtuse or acute, mucronate, surfaces usually eglandular-hairy, sometimes sparsely glandular-hairy.  Floral bud scales (and leaflike inflorescence bracts) eglandular-hairy, sometimes also stipitate-glandular-hairy.  Inflorescences 2–3-flowered, sometimes flowers solitary; axis elongate.  Pedicels 1–4.7 cm, eglandular- and/or stipitate-glandular-hairy; bracteoles 2, green, smaller than leaves.  Flowers opening after shoot development, appearing to terminate leafy shoots due to their leaflike bracts; calyx lobes 8–21 mm, eglandular- and/or stipitate-glandular-hairy; corolla purple to, rarely, white, upper 3 lobes with darker spots, 19–32 mm, margins ciliolate, unicellular-hairy on outer surface, tube ± absent due to slit between lower 2 lobes, lobes 12–26 mm; stamens unicellular-hairy proximally.  Capsules 6–11 mm, unicellular-hairy.  2n = 24, 26.</description><phenology>Flowering summer</phenology><habitat>  Arctic and alpine tundra and heathlands, meadows, and subalpine woods</habitat><elevation> 0–1500 m</elevation><us_distribution> Alaska</us_distribution><global_distribution> e Asia (Japan, Russian Far East).</global_distribution><discussion>Therorhodion camtschaticum is found in the coastal and southern insular regions.</discussion></treatment>
