<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>5.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Rhododendron</genus_name>
    <species_name>lapponicum</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Linnaeus) Wahlenberg</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Lapp.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>104.  1812  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Lapland rose-bay</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Azalea</genus_name>
    <species_name>lapponica</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 151.  1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Shrubs, to 0.5(–0.7) m, rhizomatous.  Stems prostrate to erect; bark ± smooth to vertically furrowed, shredding; twigs with straw-colored to ferruginous, multicellular, broad-rimmed, peltate scales and unicellular-hairy.  Leaves persistent; petiole with broad-rimmed, glandular-peltate scales; blade oblong-elliptic to elliptic, ovate, or obovate, 0.4–2(–2.5) × 0.2–0.7(–0.9) cm, coriaceous, margins entire, plane to revolute, with broad-rimmed scales, apex obtuse to rounded or mucronate, surfaces with conspicuous, straw-colored or golden to ferruginous, broad-rimmed, glandular-peltate scales and unicellular-hairy abaxially.  Floral bud scales ferruginous-lepidote, sometimes also unicellular-hairy abaxially, margins ± ciliate, unicellular and multicellular, elongate eglandular-hairy.  Inflorescences fasciculate racemes, 3–6-flowered; bracts similar to bud scales.  Pedicels 2.5–14 mm, with ferruginous scales and often unicellular-hairy.  Flowers opening before development of leaves, erect to horizontal, fragrant; calyx lobes 0.5–2 mm, with ferruginous scales and unicellular-hairy, margins ciliate, unicellular and multicellular eglandular-hairy; corolla rose to purple, sometimes white, without blotch, broadly funnelform, (6.5–)7.5–14(–15) mm, glabrous on outer surface, petals connate (for 3/4+ their lengths), lobes 4.5–8.5 mm, tube gradually expanding into lobes, 1.5–6.5 mm; stamens 5–10, slightly exserted, ± unequal, 7–13 mm; filaments glabrous or proximally unicellular-hairy.  Capsules borne on erect pedicels, 4–7 × 2–3 mm, with ferruginous, peltate scales and unicellular-hairy.  Seeds without distinct tails; testa closely appressed.  2n = 26, 52.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering spring–summer</phenology>
  <habitat>Arctic and alpine tundra, rocky barrens and heaths or thickets, raised beach ridges, sandy stream banks</habitat>
  <elevation>0–1900 m</elevation>
  <global_distribution>Greenland</global_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Alta.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Man.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.W.T.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>N.S.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Nunavut</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
  <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.H.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Wis.</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Europe (Russia, Scandinavia)</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Asia (Siberia).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Rhododendron lapponicum is known to hybridize with R. tomentosum in Greenland, producing R. ×vanhoeffenii Abromeit.</discussion>
</treatment>
