<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>7.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Rhododendron</genus_name>
    <species_name>maximum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 392.  1753  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Rosebay</common_name>
  <common_name>great laurel</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Rhododendron</genus_name>
    <species_name>ashleyi</species_name>
    <species_authority>Coker</species_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Shrubs or trees, to 10 m, sometimes rhizomatous.  Stems: bark smooth to vertically furrowed, shredding; twigs multicellular stipitate-glandular-hairy and eglandular-hairy (hairs basally branched, crisped/matted), glabrate in age.  Leaves persistent; petiole multicellular-hairy (hairs ± branched), often glabrescent; blade oblong to obovate or elliptic, (6–)9–20(–31) × (1.5–)2–5(–8) cm (length/width ratio 2.4–8), thick, coriaceous, margins entire, revolute to ± plane, glabrous or sparsely hairy (hairs branched), apex acuminate to sometimes acute, surfaces scattered stipitate-glandular-hairy and eglandular-hairy (hairs forming dense mat, basally branched, crisped, abaxially becoming sticky and matted, forming ± scaly or continuous, pale, shellaclike coating, smooth to slightly roughened, hairs ± deciduous adaxially).  Floral bud scales stipitate-glandular-hairy, eglandular-hairy (hairs ferruginous, crisped), and short unicellular-hairy abaxially, margins hairy (hairs branched, long-celled).  Inflorescences 10–25-flowered; bracts similar to bud scales.  Pedicels 17–60 mm, multicellular stipitate-glandular-hairy.  Flowers opening after development of leaves (of flowering shoots), erect to horizontal, not or only slightly fragrant; calyx lobes 2–6 mm, stipitate-glandular-hairy; corolla white to pink, rarely deep pink to purple, with yellowish green spots on upper lobe, campanulate, 20–36 mm, scattered stipitate-glandular-hairy on outer surface, petals connate, lobes 10–23 mm, tube gradually expanding into lobes, 7–16 mm; stamens 10, included, ± unequal, 14–26 mm; (ovary stipitate-glandular-hairy).  Capsules borne on erect pedicels, 8–20 × 4–6.5 mm, stipitate-glandular-hairy.  Seeds without distinct tails, flattened portion of testa well developed at each end; testa expanded, dorsiventrally flattened, loose.  2n = 26.</description>
  <phenology>Flowering summer</phenology>
  <habitat>Stream banks, mesic woods</habitat>
  <elevation>0–1900 m</elevation>
  <us_distribution>Ala.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Conn.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ky.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Maine</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Md.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Mass.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.H.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.J.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Ohio</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Pa.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>R.I.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>S.C.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Tenn.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Vt.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution>
  <us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution>
  <discussion>Individuals of Rhododendron maximum are beautiful, cold-hardy shrubs and are frequently cultivated as ornamentals.  Hybrids with R. catawbiense occur.  This species has been attributed in standard floras to eastern Canada but not confirmed there by specimens.</discussion>
</treatment>
