<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">rhododendron</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Torrey in New York State" date="1841">canadense</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in New York State,  Rep. Geol. Surv.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>151.  1841  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus rhododendron;species canadense</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Rhodora</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">canadensis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 1: 561.  1762</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Rhodora;species canadensis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs, to 1 m, rhizomatous.  Stems: bark ± smooth to slightly shredding; twigs sparsely  multicellular eglandular- and shorter stipitate-glandular-hairy (hairs unbranched), also unicellular-hairy.  Leaves deciduous; petiole multicellular eglandular- and stipitate-glandular-hairy and unicellular-hairy; blade elliptic to oblong or obovate, 1–8.3 × 0.4–3 cm, thin, membranous to chartaceous, margins entire, usually ± revolute, sometimes plane, eglandular- and unicellular-hairy, apex acute to rounded, abaxial surface eglandular- and stipitate-glandular-hairy, also unicellular-hairy, (± glaucous), adaxial surface scattered eglandular- and stipitate-glandular-hairy, also unicellular-hairy.  Floral bud scales unicellular-hairy abaxially, and often stipitate-glandular- and eglandular-hairy, margins unicellular-hairy.  Inflorescences sometimes fasciculate, 3–9-flowered; bracts similar to bud scales.  Pedicels 3–10 mm, (usually glaucous), usually sparsely stipitate-glandular-hairy, and sometimes also densely unicellular-hairy.  Flowers appearing before or, sometimes, with leaves, erect to horizontal, fragrant; calyx lobes 0.4–1.5 mm, often scattered stipitate-glandular-hairy, sometimes also unicellular-hairy, margins glandular- and/or eglandular-ciliate; corolla rose-purple to pink, rarely white, unspotted or red-spotted on upper 3 lobes, irregularly shaped, clearly 2-lipped due to very extensive connation of 3 upper lobes contrasting with 2 elongate, widely divergent lower lobes, 12–22 mm, glabrous or, sometimes, sparsely stipitate-glandular-hairy on outer surface, petals connate, upper lobe 3–8 mm, lateral lobes 12–22 mm (closely connate with upper lobe), lower lobes 12–22 mm, tube absent due to deep division between 2 lower lobes and between lateral and lower lobes; stamens 10, exserted, ± unequal, 9–20 mm.  Capsules borne on erect pedicels, 0.7–1.7 × 0.3–0.6 mm, multicellular stipitate-glandular- and eglandular-hairy and densely unicellular-hairy.  Seeds with flattened tails; testa tightly appressed.  2n = 52.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering spring</description>
  <description type="morphology">Moist to dry, coniferous or mixed conifer-deciduous forests, thickets, open rocky areas, lake margins, bogs, swamps</description>
  <description type="morphology">0–1900 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.B.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.S.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ont.</description>
  <description type="morphology">P.E.I.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Conn.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Maine</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mass.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.H.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.J.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Pa.</description>
  <description type="morphology">R.I.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Vt.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering spring. Moist to dry, coniferous or mixed conifer-deciduous forests, thickets, open rocky areas, lake margins, bogs, swamps; 0-1900 m; N.B., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que.; Conn., Maine, Mass., N.H., N.J., N.Y., Pa., R.I., Vt.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering spring.</phenology>
      <habitat>Moist to dry, coniferous or mixed conifer-deciduous forests, thickets, open rocky areas, lake margins, bogs, swamps;</habitat>
      <elevation>0-1900 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>N.B., Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.), N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que.; Conn., Maine, Mass., N.H., N.J., N.Y., Pa., R.I., Vt.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>10.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Rhodora</other_name>
  <discussion>Rhododendron canadense is distinctive and is most closely related to R. vaseyi; together they constitute sect. Rhodora (Linnaeus) G. Don (W. S. Judd and K. A. Kron 1995).  Rhododendron canadense is sometimes cultivated for its showy flowers.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
