<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">rhododendron</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Small) Rehder in L. H. Bailey" date="1917">austrinum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in L. H. Bailey,  Stand. Cycl. Hort.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 3571.  1917  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus rhododendron;species austrinum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Azalea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Small" date="unknown">austrina</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. S.E. U.S. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 1356.  1913</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Azalea;species austrina;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, to 3(–5) m, usually not rhizomatous.  Stems: bark smooth to vertically furrowed, shredding; twigs conspicuously multicellular stipitate-glandular-hairy, otherwise ± moderately to densely unicellular-hairy.  Leaves deciduous; petiole multicellular stipitate-glandular-hairy and unicellular-hairy; blade ovate to obovate, 3–11 × 1.5–4.5 cm, thin, membranous, margins entire, plane, ciliate, eglandular- and stipitate-glandular-hairy, apex acute to obtuse, often mucronate, abaxial surface ± moderately unicellular-hairy, adaxial surface sparsely scattered stipitate-glandular-hairy, otherwise ± moderately unicellular-hairy, rarely glabrescent.  Floral bud scales densely to moderately unicellular-hairy abaxially, margins unicellular-ciliate, also partly glandular-serrate.  Inflorescences 9–24-flowered; bracts similar to bud scales.  Pedicels 5–17 mm, stipitate-glandular-hairy, otherwise ± densely unicellular-hairy.  Flowers opening before or with leaves, erect to horizontal, slightly or not fragrant; calyx lobes 0.5–2.5 mm, scattered stipitate-glandular-hairy, otherwise unicellular-hairy, margins long stipitate-glandular-hairy; corolla yellow to orange, with usually red or orange-red tube, with indistinct, darker yellow, orange, or red blotch on upper lobe, funnelform, 25–45 mm, scattered stipitate-glandular-hairy, otherwise ± moderately unicellular-hairy on outer surface, petals connate, lobes 9–20 mm, tube ± gradually expanded into lobes, 15–25 mm (longer than lobes); stamens 5, much exserted, ± unequal, 52–77 mm.  Capsules borne on erect pedicels, 14–26 × 3–5.5 mm, sparsely to densely stipitate-glandular-hairy, otherwise moderately to densely unicellular-hairy.  Seeds without distinct tails, flattened portion of testa well developed at each end; testa expanded, dorsiventrally flattened, ± loose.  2n = 26.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering spring</description>
  <description type="morphology">Wooded slopes, bluffs or lowlands along streams</description>
  <description type="morphology">0–100 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ala.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Fla.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Ga.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Miss.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering spring. Wooded slopes, bluffs or lowlands along streams; 0-100 m; Ala., Fla., Ga., Miss.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering spring.</phenology>
      <habitat>Wooded slopes, bluffs or lowlands along streams;</habitat>
      <elevation>0-100 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Ala., Fla., Ga., Miss.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>14.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Florida azalea</other_name>
  <discussion>Rhododendron austrinum is most closely related to R. luteum Sweet of eastern Europe, Turkey, and the Caucasus region and to R. occidentale (K. A. Kron 1993).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
