<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">rhododendron</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Michaux) Sweet" date="1830">canescens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Hort. Brit. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 343.  1830  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus rhododendron;species canescens</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Azalea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">canescens</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 150.  1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Azalea;species canescens;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Azalea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Small" date="unknown">candida</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Azalea;species candida;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, to 6 m, usually not rhizomatous.  Stems: bark smooth to vertically furrowed, shredding; twigs scattered, multicellular eglandular- and/or stipitate-glandular-hairy (hairs unbranched), otherwise moderately to densely unicellular-hairy.  Leaves deciduous; petiole usually multicellular eglandular- or stipitate-glandular-hairy, also unicellular-hairy; blade ovate to obovate, 2.5–10(–13) × 1.2–3(–4) cm, thin, membranous to chartaceous, margins entire, rarely minutely serrulate, plane, inconspicuously ciliate, eglandular-hairy (hairs appressed to margins), apex acute to obtuse, often mucronate, abaxial surface densely to sparsely unicellular-hairy, sometimes glabrous or glabrate, often also scattered eglandular-hairy, adaxial surface usually scattered eglandular-hairy, otherwise sparsely unicellular-hairy, sometimes glabrous.  Floral bud scales ± densely unicellular-hairy abaxially, margins usually unicellular-ciliate.  Inflorescences 6–19-flowered; bracts similar to bud scales.  Pedicels 4–17 mm, usually eglandular-hairy, rarely stipitate-glandular- and/or eglandular-hairy, otherwise sparsely to densely unicellular-hairy.  Flowers opening before or with leaves, erect to horizontal, fragrant (usually musky-scented); calyx lobes 0.5–4 mm, surfaces and margins scattered stipitate-glandular- and/or eglandular-hairy, otherwise usually densely unicellular-hairy; corolla deep pink to white with pink tube, without blotch on upper lobe, funnelform, 23–46 mm, scattered, multicellular stipitate-glandular-hairy (hairs not forming distinct lines), otherwise sparsely to densely unicellular-hairy on outer surface, petals connate, lobes 7–20 mm, tube ± gradually expanded into lobes, 13–27 mm (equaling or longer than lobes); stamens 5, much exserted, ± unequal, 31–64 mm.  Capsules borne on erect pedicels, 12–33 × 3–6.5 mm, usually sparsely to moderately eglandular-hairy, otherwise ± densely unicellular-hairy.  Seeds without distinct tails, flattened portion of testa well developed at each end; testa expanded, dorsiventrally flattened, ± loose.  2n = 26.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Moist to dry woods, pocosins, swamps and savannas, often along streams;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0-500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Ark., Fla., Ga., Ill., Ky., La., Miss., N.C., Okla., S.C., Tenn., Tex.</description>
  <number>19.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Piedmont or southern pinxterbloom azalea</other_name>
  <discussion>Rhododendron canescens is most similar to R. prinophyllum and R. periclymenoides, although these three species do not constitute a clade (K. A. Kron 1993); they occasionally hybridize where their habitats and ranges overlap.  In addition, putative hybrids with R. alabamense, R. atlanticum, R. austrinum, R. flammeum, R. periclymenoides, and R. calendulaceum are known.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
