<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">rhododendron</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kron &amp; Creel" date="1999">eastmanii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9: 377, figs. 1, 2.  1999  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus rhododendron;species eastmanii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, to 5 m, not rhizomatous.  Stems: bark smooth to vertically furrowed, shredding; twigs unicellular and multicellular eglandular-hairy and unicellular-hairy.  Leaves deciduous; petiole densely unicellular-hairy and sparsely to densely multicellular eglandular-hairy; blade ovate or obovate to elliptic, 4.3–7.1 × 1.8–2.9 cm, membranous, margins entire, plane, ciliate, multicellular eglandular-hairy, apex acute to obtuse, mucronate, surfaces sparsely scattered, multicellular eglandular-hairy, abaxial surface moderately to densely unicellular-hairy and multicellular eglandular-hairy, midvein densely unicellular-hairy and multicellular eglandular-hairy, secondary veins sometimes multicellular eglandular-hairy, adaxial surface sparsely to densely unicellular-hairy, midvein densely unicellular-hairy.  Floral bud scales glabrous abaxially, margins unicellular-ciliate near apex, glandular along proximal 2/3.  Inflorescences 5–9 flowered; bracts similar to bud scales.  Pedicels 5–11 mm, densely unicellular-hairy and sparsely to densely multicellular eglandular-hairy, sometimes multicellular glandular-hairy.  Flowers opening after leaves have expanded, erect to horizontal, strongly fragrant (fresh during mid day); calyx lobes 0.5–1 mm (often varying in length on same flower), margins setose, multicellular eglandular-hairy, abaxial surface sparsely to densely unicellular-hairy and multicellular eglandular-hairy, sometimes sparsely multicellular, weakly glandular-hairy; corolla white, lobes pink tinged on newly opened flowers, with yellow to orange blotch on upper lobe (style white), funnelform, 24–50 mm, outer surface densely unicellular-hairy and sparsely to densely multicellular stipitate-glandular-hairy (glands usually weakly developed), inner surface densely unicellular-hairy, petals connate, upper lobe 9–17 mm, lateral lobes 11–25 mm, tube gradually expanding into lobes, 13–25 mm (equaling or much longer than lobes); stamens 5, exserted, ± unequal, 45–67 mm.  Capsules borne on erect pedicels, 12–19 × 4–8 mm, sparsely to densely unicellular-hairy and multicellular eglandular-hairy.  Seeds without distinct tails, flattened portion of testa  well developed at each end; testa expanded, dorsiventrally flattened, ± loose.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering late spring–early summer</description>
  <description type="morphology">Forests on north-facing slopes near limestone</description>
  <description type="morphology">30–200 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">S.C.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering late spring-early summer. Forests on north-facing slopes near limestone; 30-200 m; S.C.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering late spring-early summer.</phenology>
      <habitat>Forests on north-facing slopes near limestone;</habitat>
      <elevation>30-200 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>S.C.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>25.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">May white azalea</other_name>
  <discussion>Older collections of Rhododendron eastmanii were typically referred to R. alabamense, which flowers early in the spring before the leaves have expanded, and has inflorescence bud scales are unicellular-ciliate; in R. eastmanii the bud scale margins are glandular.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
