<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>34.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>HARRIMANELLA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Coville</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Wash. Acad. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 570, figs. 62, 66.  1901  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Moss heather</common_name>
  <etymology>[For Edward H. Harriman, 1848–1909, American financier and patron of science]</etymology>
  <author>Gary D. Wallace</author>
  <description>Subshrubs small; branches prostrate, spreading, or ascending, mat-forming.  Leaves densely crowded on stems; petiole very short, leaving small pegs on stem when leaves fall off; blade linear-oblong to subulate, margins entire or erose, surfaces glabrous.  Pedicels nodding in flower, erect in fruit, slender; bracteoles absent.  Flowers: sepals distinct or connate basally, ovate to oblong-ovate; petals connate ca. 1/2 their lengths, white or tinged with pink, apex blunt; stamens not exserted; filaments swollen at base; anthers inverted at anthesis, with awns; ovary globose to ovoid; style ovoid or conic; stigma simple.  Capsules borne on erect pedicels, globose to ovoid, dehiscent basipetally.  x = 16.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Asia.</global_distribution>
  <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCE">
    <reference>Stevens, P. F.  1970.  Calluna, Cassiope and Harrimanella: A taxonomic and evolutionary problem.  New Phytol. 69: 1131–1148.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves divergent, blade linear-oblong, apex obtuse to broadly acute; pedicels barely exceeding leaves at anthesis; capsules 4–5 mm diam.</statement>
      <determination>1.   Harrimanella stelleriana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves loosely appressed, blade linear to subulate, apex acute; pedicels 3+ times longer than leaves at anthesis; capsules 2–3.5 mm diam.</statement>
      <determination>2.   Harrimanella hypnoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
