<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Gordon C. Tucker</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Coville" date="1901">harrimanella</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Coville" date="1901">hypnoides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Wash. Acad. Sci.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 575.  1901,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus harrimanella;species hypnoides</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Andromeda</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">hypnoides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 393.  1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Andromeda;species hypnoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cassiope</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) D. Don" date="unknown">hypnoides</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cassiope;species hypnoides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems forming loose mats; branches lax, tips barely, if at all ascending.  Leaves loosely appressed; blade linear to subulate, 2–3 × 0.5–0.8 mm, (ciliolate), apex acute.  Pedicels (deep red), 0.7–1.5 cm, 3+ times longer than leaves at anthesis.  Flowers erect; sepals ovate, ca. 2 mm; corolla white, ca. 4 × 3 mm, lobes distinct for ca. 1/2 their lengths, tips not recurved; stamens to 1.5 mm.  Capsules 2–3.5 mm diam.  2n = 32, 48.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Flowering Jul–Aug</description>
  <description type="morphology">Damp, sheltered places in tundra at lower elevations, and in alpine or subalpine meadows, often in damp soil where snow drifts form</description>
  <description type="morphology">50–1900 m</description>
  <description type="morphology">Greenland</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nfld. and Labr.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.W.T.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Nunavut</description>
  <description type="morphology">Que.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Maine</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.H.</description>
  <description type="morphology">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="morphology">n Europe.</description>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs, shrubs, vines, or trees, usually multicellular-hairy (margins of leaves usually glandular-hairy), or sometimes absent (Andromeda); bark smooth or furrowed, not flaky.  Stems erect, arching, spreading, creeping, or procumbent.  Leaves deciduous or persistent, alternate, sometimes pseudoverticillate (Pieris); petiole usually present, sometimes absent (some species of Vaccinium); blade plane, abaxial groove absent.  Inflorescences usually axillary, sometimes terminal, usually panicles or racemes, sometimes corymbs or fascicles, sometimes solitary flowers, (borne on leafy twigs, except Zenobia on leafless twigs); perulae absent; bracts much shorter than sepals (sometimes absent).  Flowers pendulous; perianth and androecium hypogynous or epigynous (Gaylussacia, Vaccinium); sepals (4–)5[–8]; petals 4–5(–6), connate (rarely distinct or nearly so in some species of Vaccinium), corolla deciduous, campanulate, cylindric, or urceolate, lobes usually much shorter (sometimes longer) than tube; intrastaminal nectary disc absent or present; stamens 8–10[–16]; anthers dehiscent by terminal pores or short slits; ovary 5- or 10-locular; placentation axile; style straight.  Fruits capsular, dehiscence loculicidal, or baccate or drupaceous, indehiscent.  Seeds 2–300, distinct, ovoid or obovoid to ellipsoid, lanceoloid, or conic, to angular or wedge- or crescent-shaped, usually not winged, sometimes slightly winged or tailed.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering Jul-Aug. Damp, sheltered places in tundra at lower elevations, and in alpine or subalpine meadows, often in damp soil where snow drifts form; 50-1900 m; Greenland; Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., Nunavut, Que.; Maine, N.H., N.Y.; n Europe.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering Jul-Aug.</phenology>
      <habitat>Damp, sheltered places in tundra at lower elevations, and in alpine or subalpine meadows, often in damp soil where snow drifts form;</habitat>
      <elevation>50-1900 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Greenland; Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., Nunavut, Que.; Maine, N.H., N.Y.; n Europe.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>2.</number>
  <discussion>Harrimanella hypnoides has not been collected in New York state in more than a century and is presumed extirpated there.</discussion>
  <discussion>f. Ericaceae   Jussieu subfam. Vaccinioideae   Arnott in M. Napier, Encycl. Brit. ed. 7, 5: 118.  1832 (as Vaccinieae)</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera 46, species ca. 1600 (12 genera, 58 species in the flora): nearly worldwide, especially arctic, temperate, and alpine areas, also very diverse in neotropical cloud forests.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kron, K. A., W. S. Judd, and D. M. Crayn.  1999.  Phylogenetic analyses of Andromedeae (Ericaceae subfam. Vaccinioideae).  Amer. J. Bot. 86: 1290–1300.</reference>
    <reference>Lems, K.  1964.  Evolutionary studies in the Ericaceae.  II.  Leaf anatomy as a phylogenetic index in the Andromedeae.  Bot. Gaz. 125: 178–186.</reference>
    <reference>Lens, F. et al.  2004.  Comparative wood anatomy of the blueberry tribe (Vaccineae, Ericaceae s.l.).  Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 91: 566–592.</reference>
    <reference>Middleton, D. J.  1991.  Taxonomic studies in the Gaultheria group of genera of the tribe Andromedeae (Ericaceae).  Edinburgh J. Bot. 48: 283–306.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
