<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Walter S. Judd</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="D. Don ex G. Don" date="1834">AGARISTA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Hist.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 788, 837.  1834  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus AGARISTA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek mythological daughter of Clisthenes, alluding to beauty of flowers]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees.  Stems erect; twigs glabrous.  Leaves persistent; blade ovate, coriaceous, margins entire or serrate, plane, surfaces often multicellular, long-stalked stipitate-glandular-hairy, otherwise unicellular-hairy on midvein [covering abaxial surface]; venation reticulodromous (reticulum rather dense and with all orders ± equally prominent).  Inflorescences axillary [terminal] racemes [panicles], 10–20-flowered, (produced just before flowering).  Pedicels: bracteoles 2, near base to ± midpoint.  Flowers: sepals 5, slightly connate, deltate; petals 5, connate for most of their lengths, white [red], corolla cylindric [urceolate], lobes short; stamens 10, included; filaments geniculate, flattened, hairy, without spurs; anthers without awns, dehiscent by elliptic pores; pistil 5-carpellate; ovary 5-locular; stigma (slightly exserted), truncate to capitate, obscurely lobed, (minutely papillose).  Fruits capsular, subglobose to short-ovoid, (with unthickened sutures), dry.  Seeds 120–250, narrowly oblong to pyramidal or angular-obovoid; testa cells elongate.  x = 12.</description>
  <description type="morphology">se United States</description>
  <description type="morphology">Mexico</description>
  <description type="morphology">Central America</description>
  <description type="morphology">South America</description>
  <description type="morphology">Africa</description>
  <description type="morphology">Indian Ocean Islands (including Madagascar).</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 31 (1 in the flora): se United States, Mexico, Central America, South America, Africa, Indian Ocean Islands (including Madagascar).</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 31 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>se United States, Mexico, Central America, South America, Africa, Indian Ocean Islands (including Madagascar).</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>37.</number>
  <discussion>Agauria (de Candolle) Bentham &amp; Hooker f.; Leucothoë D. Don subg. Agarista (D. Don ex G. Don) Drude</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 31 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Judd, W. S.  1984.  A taxonomic revision of the American species of Agarista (Ericaceae).  J. Arnold Arbor. 65: 255–342.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
