<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Walter S. Judd</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ericaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Nuttall" date="1818">LYONIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. N. Amer. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 266.  1818, name conserved  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ericaceae;genus LYONIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[For John Lyon, 1765–1814, Scottish-born, early American botanist and explorer of southern Appalachians]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs or trees, (sometimes with woody burl, resprouting after fire).  Stems erect to arching; twigs hairy, sometimes glabrescent (sometimes also lepidote).  Leaves deciduous or persistent; blade elliptic, obovate, or ovate, membranous to coriaceous, margins entire, undulate, or serrulate [irregularly serrate], plane or revolute, surfaces multicellular, peltate-scaled or short-stalked stipitate-glandular-hairy, often unicellular-hairy on major veins or abaxial surface; venation brochidodromous (or reticulodromous).  Inflorescences axillary fascicles, panicles, or racemes, (2–)5–8(–12)-flowered, sometimes flowers solitary, (produced just before flowering).  Pedicels: bracteoles 2, at or near base.  Flowers: sepals usually [4–]5[–8], slightly connate, ovate-deltate to lanceolate; petals usually [4–]5[–8], connate nearly their entire lengths, white to red, corolla cylindric to urceolate, lobes much shorter than tube, (sparsely stipitate-glandular-hairy or peltate-scaled); stamens usually [8–]10[–16], included; filaments geniculate, flattened, roughened or hairy, with or without spurs; anthers without awns, dehiscent by elliptic pores; pistil usually [4–]5[–8]-carpellate; ovary [4–]5[–8]-locular; (style slightly longer than stamens); stigma capitate-truncate.  Fruits capsular, globose to ovoid or ellipsoid, dry, (with [4–]5[–8] pale, decidedly thickened, whitish sutures).  Seeds ca. 100–300, ellipsoidal, narrowly oblong, obovoid to angular-obovoid or narrowly conic, (sometimes tailed); testa cells elongate.  x = 12.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e United States, Mexico, West Indies, e Asia.</description>
  <number>38.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Maleberry</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">staggerbush</other_name>
  <discussion>Arsenococcus Small; Desmothamnus Small; Neopieris Britton</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 36 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Judd, W. S.  1981.  A monograph of Lyonia (Ericaceae).  J. Arnold Arbor. 62: 63–209, 315–436.</reference>
    <reference>Judd, W. S.  1995.  Lyonia.  In: Organization for Flora Neotropica.  1968+.  Flora Neotropica.  98+ nos.  New York.  No. 66, pp. 222–294.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Abaxial surface of leaf blades, pedicels, and calyx lepidote.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate branchlets spreading, flowers nearly always restricted to previous year’s branches; leaves not conspicuously reduced toward branch tips, blade margins usually revolute distally, sometimes strongly so, major veins usually depressed; shrubs or trees to 6(–12) m</description>
      <determination>4.   Lyonia ferruginea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ultimate branchlets rigidly ascending, flowers frequent on current year’s branchlets (some flowers also borne on branches of previous year); leaves conspicuously reduced toward branch tips, blade margins at most slightly revolute distally, major veins not depressed; shrubs to 1.5(–3) m</description>
      <determination>5.   Lyonia fruticosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Abaxial surface of leaf blades, pedicels, and calyx nearly glabrous or hairy, not lepidote.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades scattered, multicellular long-headed-hairy abaxially, margins serrulate; corollas urceolate, 2–4(–4.5) mm; calyx lobes 0.5–1.5 mm</description>
      <determination>1.   Lyonia ligustrina</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades scattered, multicellular short-headed-hairy abaxially, margins entire; corollas cylindric, 5–14 mm; calyx lobes 2–9.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves persistent, blade rigidly coriaceous, intramarginal vein present; corollas usually pink, sometimes red or white, 2–5 mm wide, base swollen; filaments roughened; capsules ovoid to ovoid-globose</description>
      <determination>2.   Lyonia lucida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves deciduous, blade membranous, intramarginal vein absent; corollas usually white, rarely pink, 4.5–9 mm wide, base not swollen; filaments long-hairy, especially near base; capsules ovoid</description>
      <determination>3.   Lyonia mariana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
