<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Dorothy M. Fabijan</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">ERICACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Moench" date="unknown">CHAMAEDAPHNE</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Methodus,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>457.  1794, name conserved  ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family ERICACEAE;genus CHAMAEDAPHNE;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chamai, dwarf, and daphne, laurel, alluding to low habit and persistent leaves]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs.  Stems erect, ascending or spreading; twigs hairy, lepidote.  Leaves persistent; blade usually oblong to elliptic, rarely obovate, coriaceous, margins entire or denticulate-crenulate, plane, abaxial surface glabrous, silvery, stramineous or brownish lepidote-scaled (splitting in age); venation reticulodromous.  Inflorescences terminal, (leafy) racemes, (flowers secund), 8–20-flowered, (from buds produced in previous season).  Flowers: sepals 5, distinct, ovate to broadly triangular; petals 5, connate ca. 3/4 their lengths, white, corolla cylindric to urceolate-cylindric, slightly narrowed at throat, lobes much shorter than tube, (glabrous); stamens 10, included; filaments ± straight, flattened, subulate, abruptly narrowed at base, papillate, glabrous, without spurs; anther with 2 awns (awns erect, tubular, as long as body), dehiscent by terminal or subterminal pore; pistil 5-carpellate; ovary 5-locular; (style enlarged just distal to ovary); stigma slightly expanded, truncate.  Fruits capsular, depressed-globose, dry-dehiscent, (with unthickened sutures).  Seeds 35–50, wedge-shaped, flattened, (without wings); testa reticulate, (cells isodiametric).  x = 11.</description>
  <number>41.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Leatherleaf</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">dwarf cassandra</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cassandre caliculé</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">faux bleuets</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">petit-daphné</other_name>
  <discussion>Cassandra D. Don</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1: North America, Eurasia.</discussion>
  <discussion>Chamaedaphne has been included in other genera of subfamily Vaccinioideae (Andromeda, Lyonia) and more recently has been placed in tribe Gaultherieae (K. A. Kron et al. 2002).  Its leaf anatomy differs from that of other genera in having venation transitional between pleuroplastic and basiplastic types, denser venation, and thin vein endings (K. Lems 1964).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
