<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>42.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>LEUCOTHOË</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>D. Don</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Edinburgh New Philos. J.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 159. 1834 ,</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <common_name>Hobblebush</common_name>
  <common_name>sweetbells</common_name>
  <common_name>dog-laurel</common_name>
  <common_name>fetterbush</common_name>
  <common_name>dog-hobble</common_name>
  <etymology>[Greek name for a princess of Babylon]</etymology>
  <author>Gordon C. Tucker</author>
  <description>Shrubs. Stems erect or spreading, glabrous or sparsely short-hairy, glabrescent;
        branches without silvery scales. Leaves persistent; blade oblong, lanceolate, oblanceolate,
        or elliptic, coriaceous, margins entire or spinulose-serrulate, plane, surfaces not
        glaucous, without silvery scales, glabrous or hairy abaxially; venation reticulodromous.
        Inflorescences axillary, fascicled or solitary racemes, (not leafy), 8–60-flowered,
        (produced on previous year’s wood); (bracteoles 2, medial or proximal, partly covering
        pedicel). Flowers: sepals 5, slightly connate, lanceolate-ovate to broadly ovate; petals 5,
        connate nearly their entire lengths, white, corolla cylindric to urceolate, lobes much
        shorter than tube; stamens 8(–10), included; filaments straight, flattened, glabrous or
        hairy, without spurs; anthers with or without 2 awns proximal to anther-filament junction,
        dehiscent through terminal pores; pistil 5-carpellate; ovary pseudo 10-locular; (style
        scarcely longer than stamens); stigma 5-lobed, capitate to peltate. Fruits capsular,
        subglobose, dry. Seeds ca. 60–120, ellipsoid, oblong, or angular, flattened or wedge-shaped;
        testa smooth and shiny, reticulate, or papillose. x = 11.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 5 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>e</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>w United States</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia.</global_distribution>
  <references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES">
    <reference>Ingram, J. W. 1961. Studies in the cultivated Ericaceae, I. Leucothoë. Baileya 9:
            57–66.</reference>
    <reference>Ingram, J. W. 1979. Leucothoë revisited (Ericaceae). Baileya 20:
            141–145.</reference>
    <reference>Melvin, N. C. 1981. Additional comments on Leucothoë (Ericaceae). Baileya 21:
            127–130.</reference>
    <reference>Sleumer, H. 1959. Studien über die Gattung Leucothoë D. Don. Bot. Jahrb. Syst.
            78: 435–480.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Filaments glabrous; racemes fascicled; w United States</statement>
      <determination>3. Leucothoë davisiae</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Filaments spreading-hairy and/or papillate; racemes fascicled or solitary; se
                United States.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Sepals broadly ovate, apex obtuse or rounded; racemes 2–4(–5) cm</statement>
      <determination>1. Leucothoë axillaris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Sepals lance-ovate, apex acute or subacute; racemes 4–10 cm</statement>
      <determination>2. Leucothoë fontanesiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
