<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David J. Keil</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">mutisieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="P. Browne" date="1756">TRIXIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Civ. Nat. Hist. Jamaica,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>312, plate 33, fig. 1. 1756</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe mutisieae;genus TRIXIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek trixos , 3-fold, describing the 3-cleft corolla]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Shrubs [herbs], 20–300+ cm (often rhizomatous, stems hairy, hairs gland-tipped and glandless). Leaves cauline; sessile or petiolate; blades elliptic, lanceolate, linear, or linear-lanceolate, bases cuneate, margins dentate or entire, faces (at least abaxial) usually glandular and ± strigose. Heads quasi-radiate (see florets), borne singly or in corymbiform or paniculiform arrays. Involucres ± cylindric, 12–15 mm (subtended by calyculi of 3–7 spreading or ascending bractlets). Phyllaries (reflexed in fruit) in 1–2 series, linear (± keeled), apices acute. Receptacles flat, smooth, hairy, epaleate. Florets 4–25[–60], bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow (aging white), zygomorphic (2-lipped; outer lip liguliform, lobes 3, lance-deltate, inner lip smaller, lobes ± filiform, recurved); anther basal appendages entire, apical appendages oblong, acute; style branches relatively short, apices truncate-penicillate. Cypselae subcylindric to fusiform, often ± beaked, ribs 5, faces glandular-hairy; pappi of 60–80+ dull white [tawny], finely barbed bristles. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Threefold</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 65 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Anderson, C. E. 1972. A monograph of the Mexican and Central American species of Trixis (Compositae). Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 22(3): 1–68.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually ascending, almost parallel with stems, stomates on both faces, induments: abaxial faces glandular and sparsely strigose (sometimes only on veins), adaxial faces glandular and strigose to pilose; papilla-like double hairs of cypselae producing mucilage when wetted</description>
      <determination>1. Trixis californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves usually spreading, stomates on abaxial faces, induments: margins and, sometimes, abaxial midveins with glandless and glandular hairs, otherwise glabrous; papilla-like double hairs of cypselae not producing mucilage when wetted</description>
      <determination>2. Trixis inula</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
