<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>40.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Cirsium</genus_name>
    <species_name>occidentale</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Nuttall) Jepson</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. W. Calif.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>509. 1901</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cynareae;genus Cirsium;species occidentale;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <common_name>Western thistle</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carduus</genus_name>
    <species_name>occidentalis</species_name>
    <species_authority>Nuttall</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Trans. Amer. Philos. Soc., n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 418. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Biennials, 5–400 cm; taproots. Stems usually 1, thinly to densely gray- or white-tomentose, sometimes ± glabrate; branches few–many, usually from above mid or near base in compact, moundlike dwarf plants, ascending to spreading. Leaves: blades oblong–elliptic to oblanceolate, 6–40 × 1.5–10+ cm, shallowly to deeply pinnatifid, lobes usually rigidly spreading, undivided or with 1–2 pairs of coarse teeth or lobes, main spines 5–15 mm, both faces gray- to white-tomentose, sometimes ± glabrate or adaxial faces green, thinly arachnoid-tomentose; basal sometimes present at flowering, petiolate or sessile and bases tapered, spiny-winged; principal cauline much reduced distally, sessile, bases decurrent or not, as spiny wings; distal much reduced, linear, ± bractlike. Heads 1–many in loose to tight clusters (barely raised above rosette in dwarf plants). Peduncles 1–30 cm. Involucres ovoid to spheric, 1.5–5 × 1.5–8 cm, arachnoid to ± loosely tomentose, often adjacent phyllaries connected by conspicuous arachnoid trichomes, sometimes glabrous or glabrate. Phyllaries in 7–10 series, subequal to strongly imbricate, green or stramineous to purple-tinged, linear to narrowly lanceolate, abaxial faces without glutinous ridge; outer and mid bodies appressed, entire, apices deflexed to spreading or ascending, short-triangular to elongate, linear-acicular, spines spreading to reflexed, 1–10+ mm; apices of inner erect, often flexuous, flat. Corollas white to lavender, pink, rose-purple, or red, 18–40 mm, tubes 8–18 mm, throats 5–7 mm, lobes 5–10 mm; style tips 4–5 mm. Cypselae ± brown, 5–6 mm, apical collars not differentiated; pappi 15–30 mm.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 7 (7 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>w United States.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants compact, rounded, moundlike; heads usually not much elevated above leaves</statement>
      <determination>40c. Cirsium occidentale var. compactum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants usually erect; principal heads usually conspicuously pedunculate.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Corollas white to light purple or rose</statement>
      <determination>40d. Cirsium occidentale var. californicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Corollas deep purple to bright pink or red.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants densely white-tomentose; phyllaries persistently white-tomentose (except spines); outer phyllaries usually very long, spreading to reflexed</statement>
      <determination>40g. Cirsium occidentale var. candidissimum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants variably tomentose, sometimes ± glabrate; phyllaries ± arachnoid to floccose-tomentose, sometimes green and glabrate; outer phyllaries short to long, ascending to spreading or reflexed.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres usually about as long as wide or wider than long; phyllaries densely and persistently arachnoid with fine trichomes connecting tips of adjacent phyllaries.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary apices ± imbricate, the proximal usually shorter than medial and distal, lanceolate to linear-acicular, 0.5–15 mm; co- rollas bright purple</statement>
      <determination>40a. Cirsium occidentalevar. occidentale</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllary apices subequal, all long- acicular, 1.5–3 cm; corollas light to deep reddish purple</statement>
      <determination>40b. Cirsium occidentale var. coulteri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Involucres usually longer than wide; phyllaries tomentose or glabrate, sparingly or not arachnoid with fine trichomes connecting tips of adjacent phyllaries.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Corollas 20–24 mm, deep reddish purple; s Santa Lucia Mountains of San Luis Obispo County, California</statement>
      <determination>40e. Cirsium occidentale var. lucianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <statement>Corollas 23–35 mm, bright pink to red; widespread</statement>
      <determination>40f. Cirsium occidentale</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

