<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="unknown">Cynareae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cirsium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(A. Gray) Petrak" date="unknown">arizonicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Tidsskr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>31: 68. 1911</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cynareae;genus Cirsium;species arizonicum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Cnicus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">arizonicus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10: 44. 1874</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Cnicus;species arizonicus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>43.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Arizona thistle</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 5 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The Cirsium arizonicum complex is widely distributed from the Sierra Nevada, White Mountains, and New York Mountains of eastern California across the mountains of the southern Great Basin and Colorado Plateau to the mountains of eastern Colorado, Arizona, and New Mexico. This group of plants comprises a series of intergrading races with intricately overlapping patterns of variation. For plants that I am treating as C. arizonicum (in the broad sense), F. Petrak (1917) recognized three species, one with a variety and two subspecies plus his unstated type subspecies and variety. R. J. Moore and C. Frankton (1974b) revised the complex, recognizing six species, three of them newly described, for the plants I treat as C. arizonicum plus C. turneri, which I do not include in C. arizonicum. P. L. Barlow-Irick (2002), in a work focused on statistical analyses of variation patterns, recognized six species also, but circumscribed very differently from those of Moore and Frankton. Two of the species proposed by Barlow-Irick have not been formally described.</discussion>
  <discussion>I have wrestled with how to treat these plants since beginning my research for this treatment. After careful consideration of the complex patterns of variation among members of the C. arizonicum complex, I acknowledged the futility of trying to distinguish more than one species. Any character combinations that I or others have attempted to use to distinguish species break down hopelessly when enough specimens are examined. Instead I have chosen to recognize that in this complex, as in several others, the plants in question are a work of evolution in progress. Cirsium arizonicum is a rapidly evolving, only partially differentiated assemblage of races that have not reached the level of stability that is usually associated with the concept of species. Certainly there is much variation within the group that deserves a level of taxonomic recognition, or at least should be mentioned, but I think it much more prudent to recognize varieties–entities that may be expected to freely intergrade–rather than species. The geographic area where these plants occur, the highlands of the American Southwest, has had a turbulent history in the Quaternary with major shifts in climate, vegetation, and elevational zonation accompanying the vicissitudes of glacial and interglacial episodes. The complicated patterns of variation in C. arizonicum reflect both that history and the geographic and topographic complexity of the region.</discussion>
  <discussion>Heads of Cirsium arizonicum are visited by hummingbirds as well as a variety of insects (P. L. Barlow-Irick 2002). Hummingbirds are the most common visitors, but hummingbirds and bees are both apparently effective pollinators in C. arizonicum.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Barlow-Irick, P. L. 2002. Biosystematic Analysis of the Cirsium arizonicum Complex of the Southwestern United States. Ph.D. dissertation. University of New Mexico. Moore, R. J. and C. Frankton. 1974b. The Cirsium arizonicum complex of the southwestern United States. Canad. J. Bot. 52: 543–551.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corollas bright red or reddish pink.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves glabrous on both faces</description>
      <determination>43b. Cirsium arizonicum var. rothrockii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ± tomentose, at least on the abaxial faces</description>
      <determination>43a. Cirsium arizonicum var. arizonicum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Corollas lavender to reddish purple.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and abaxial leaf midveins villous to tomentose with septate trichomes; leaves conspicuously decurrent; leaves deeply divided, lobes many, narrow, closely spaced, each tipped by a very slender spine 5–12 mm; northeastern Arizona and northwestern New Mexico</description>
      <determination>43d. Cirsium arizonicum var. chellyense</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems and abaxial leaf midveins glabrous to tomentose with fine, non-septate trichomes; septate trichomes usually absent; leaf divisions various.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Principal marginal leaf spines 3–10 mm; New Mexico, northeastern Arizona, southeastern Utah, and southwestern Colorado</description>
      <determination>43c. Cirsium arizonicum var. bipinnatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Principal marginal leaf spines 5–30 mm; southeastern California and southwestern</description>
      <determination>43e. Cirsium arizonicum var. tenuisectum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
