<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>5.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>ADENOCAULON</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Hooker</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Misc.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 19, plate 15. 1829</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Mutisieae;genus ADENOCAULON;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <etymology>[Greek aden , gland, and kaulos , stem]</etymology>
  <author>David J. Keil</author>
  <description>Perennials (perhaps flowering first year, usually rhizomatous), (10–)30–60(–100+) cm
    (aerial stems usually proximally tomentose and distally stipitate-glandular). Leaves basal and
    cauline; petiolate (proximal) or sessile (distal); blades ovate to ± triangular [suborbiculate],
    bases mostly truncate to cordate or hastate, margins coarsely dentate or lobulate to denticulate
    or entire, abaxial faces tomentose, adaxial faces glabrate (distalmost leaves often linear or
    scalelike). Heads disciform, borne in open paniculiform arrays. Involucres cuplike to
    saucer-shaped (inconspicuous), 4–8+ mm diam. Phyllaries in 1–2 series, ovate to oblong, ± equal
    (reflexed in fruit), apices obtuse. Receptacles convex, smooth, glabrous, epaleate. Florets:
    outer 3–7 florets pistillate, corollas white or ochroleucous, obscurely zygomorphic (± 2-lipped;
    staminodes 4–5, minute; style branches relatively short); inner 2–10 florets functionally
    staminate, corollas white or ochroleucous, actinomorphic (lobes 5); anther basal appendages
    (relatively short) entire, apical appendages narrowly triangular; style branches none (apices of
    styles obtuse to acute). Cypselae clavate to obovoid, not beaked, ± ribbed, faces distally
    stipitate-glandular; pappi 0. x = 23.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 5 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>s South America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Adenocaulon is well adapted for animal dispersal. The prominent glandular hairs on the
    cypselae are very sticky and cling readily to fabrics, fur, and feathers. The intercontinental
    disjunctions within the range of Adenocaulon are probably a result of dispersal of cypselae on
    the feathers of birds. Bird dispersal may also account for the intracontinental disjunctions of
    A. bicolor (in the Pacific Northwest, the Black Hills, and the northern Great Lakes region). An
    alternate hypothesis for the disjunctions of A. bicolor is a former transcontinental periglacial
    distribution that was broken apart by Holocene climatic changes.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bittmann, M. 1990. Die Gattung Adenocaulon (Compositae): I. Morphologie. Candollea
      45: 389–420.</reference>
    <reference>Bittmann, M. 1990b. Die Gattung Adenocaulon (Compositae): II. Ökologie, Verbreitung
      und Systematik. Candollea 45: 493–518.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>

