<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>15</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>SAUSSUREA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>de Candolle</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Mus. Natl. Hist. Nat.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>16: 156, 196, plates 10–13. 1810</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cynareae;genus SAUSSUREA;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <etymology>[For Nicolas Théodore (1767–1845) and Horace Bénédict (1740–1799) de Saussure, Swiss naturalists]</etymology>
  <conserved_name>name conserved</conserved_name>
  <common_name>Saw-wort</common_name>
  <author>David J. Keil</author>
  <description>Perennials, 5–120+ cm; herbage tomentose or glabrescent, not spiny. Stems erect or ascending, simple or branched. Leaves basal or cauline (sometimes cauline only), sessile or petiolate; blade margins entire or dentate to pinnately lobed, faces glabrous to densely tomentose, glandular or eglandular. Heads discoid, borne singly or in corymbiform arrays. Involucres ovoid to campanulate or ± turbinate. Phyllaries many in 3–5(–10+) series, subequal to strongly unequal, appressed or not, ovate to lanceolate, margins entire, toothed, or lobed, apices obtuse or acute, appendaged or not, not spine-tipped. Receptacles flat or convex, epaleate, smooth, usually subulate-scaly, sometimes bristly or naked. Florets 10–20; corollas white to blue or purple, tubes slender, abruptly expanded to throats, lobes linear; anther bases short-tailed, apical appendages linear, acute; style branches: fused portions with minutely hairy subterminal nodes, distinct portions oblong to linear, short-papillate. Cypselae oblong, ± angled, cylindric or 4–5-angled, ribs (when present) smooth or roughened, apices entire, glabrous or minutely glandular, attachment scars basal; pappi usually of 2 series, outer of readily falling, short bristles, inner persistent or falling as unit, of basally connate, usually longer, plumose bristles. x = 13, 14, 16, 17, 18, 19?.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 300–400 (6 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Eurasia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>1 in Australia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Saussurea is a notoriously difficult, largely Asiatic genus with species boundaries often indistinct.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Lipschitz, S. J. 1979. Rod Saussurea DC. (Asteraceae). Leningrad.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Outer and mid phyllaries with toothed or lobed appendages</statement>
      <determination>6. Saussurea amara</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Outer and mid phyllaries entire, without appendages.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Proximal leaves ovate to lanceolate, usually more than 30 mm wide, bases broadly obtuse to truncate or cordate; plants 30–120 cm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaves usually more than 20, finely to ± coarsely serrate or dentate; s Alaska and Yukon to California, Idaho, and Montana</statement>
      <determination>1. Saussurea americana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Cauline leaves usually 15 or fewer, coarsely laciniate-dentate; nw Alaska</statement>
      <determination>2. Sausserea triangulata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Proximal leaves linear to elliptic, 2–25 mm wide, bases acute to acuminate; plants 3–40 cm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries subequal, linear to lanceolate; receptacles naked</statement>
      <determination>4. Saussurea nuda</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <statement>Phyllaries strongly unequal, the outer ovate to lanceolate, conspicuously shorter than inner; receptacles scaly.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Tips of outer and mid phyllaries acute; Alaska and nw Canada</statement>
      <determination>3. Saussurea angustifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <statement>Tips of outer and mid phyllaries ± rounded; Rocky Mountains</statement>
      <determination>5. Saussurea weberi</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

