<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David J. Keil</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">cardueae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ARCTIUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 816. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 357. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe cardueae;genus ARCTIUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek arktion , from arktos , bear, perhaps alluding to rough involucre]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials or (monocarpic) perennials, 50–300 cm; herbage not spiny. Stems erect, openly branched, branches ascending. Leaves basal and cauline; long-petiolate; gradually smaller distally; blade margins entire or dentate (pinnately lobed or dissected), faces abaxially resin-gland-dotted, adaxially often tomentose. Heads discoid, in leafy-bracted racemiform to paniculiform or corymbiform arrays. (Peduncles 0 or 1–9 cm.) Involucres spheric to ovoid. Phyllaries many in 9–17 series, outer and mid narrowly linear, bases appressed, margins entire, apices stiffly radiating, hooked-spiny tipped, inner linear, ascending or erect, straight tipped. Receptacles ± flat, epaleate, bearing subulate scales. Florets (5–)20–40+; corollas pink to ± purple, glabrous or glandular-puberulent, tubes elongate, throats campanulate, lobes narrowly triangular, ± equal; anther bases tailed, apical appendages ovate, obtuse to acute; style branches: fused portions distally hairy-ringed, distinct portions oblong, acute or obtuse. Cypselae obovoid, ± compressed, rough or ribbed, glabrous, attachment scars basal; pappi falling, of many bristles in 2–4 series. x = 18.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">widely introduced worldwide.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 10 (3 in the flora): introduced; Eurasia, n Africa, widely introduced worldwide.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 10 (3 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; Eurasia, n Africa, widely introduced worldwide.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>16.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Burdock</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">clotbur</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">bardane</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 10 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>At maturity the dry heads of Arctium species are readily caducous with the enclosed cypselae, and the hooked phyllary tips cling easily to fur or fabrics. Animal dispersal is a major factor in the spread of burdock species across North America. The burs are a major problem when they become entangled in the wool of sheep and fur of dogs and other animals.</discussion>
  <discussion>Published chromosome reports for Arctium other than n = 18 are probably in error because of difficulty in interpretation of somatic chromosomes (R. J. Moore and C. Frankton 1974).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Arènes, J. 1950. Monographie du genre Arctium L. Bull. Jard. Bot. État Bruxelles 29: 67–156.</reference>
    <reference>Duistermaat, H. 1996. Monograph of Arctium L. (Asteraceae). Gorteria, suppl. 3: 1–143.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually sessile to short-pedunculate in racemiform or paniculiform clusters</description>
      <determination>3. Arctium minus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually long-pedunculate in corymbiform clusters.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucre 2.5–4 cm diam.; phyllary apices glabrous or loosely cobwebby; corollas glabrous</description>
      <determination>1. Arctium lappa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucre 1.5–2.5 mm diam.; phyllary apices densely cobwebby; corollas minutely glandular-puberulent</description>
      <determination>2. Arctium tomentosum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
