<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="unknown">Cynareae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Arctium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Hill) Bernhardi" date="unknown">minus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Verz.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>154. 1800</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cynareae;genus Arctium;species minus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lappa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hill" date="unknown">minor</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Veg. Syst.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 28. 1762</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lappa;species minor;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>3.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Common or lesser burdock</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">petite bardane</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">cibourroche</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">chou bourache</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">bourrier</other_name>
  <discussion>Arctium minus has been reported from Delaware and Texas; I have not seen specimens.</discussion>
  <discussion>Arctium minus is a complex species with many variants that have been recognized at ranks ranging from forma to species (J. Arènes 1950). Some North American workers (e.g., R. J. Moore and C. Frankton 1974) have often distinguished plants with involucres more than 3 cm diameter that equal or overtop the corollas as A. nemorosum. Arènes treated those plants as a subspecies of A. minus. Arctium nemorosum was recognized as a species distinct from A. minus (H. Duistermaat 1996), with a different and more restricted circumscription than that used by North American workers. Although most of the characters that Duistermaat used to separate those A. nemorosum from A. minus overlap extensively, the consistently wider mid phyllaries of A. nemorosum (1.7–2.5 mm wide versus 0.6–1.6 mm in A. minus) supposedly distinguish the species. None of the North American specimens examined in preparation of this treatment had the wide phyllaries of A. nemorosum in the sense of Duistermaat, who stated that she had seen no material of this taxon from the American continent. Some American authors have taken up the name Arctium vulgare in place of A. nemorosum and applied A. vulgare (dubbed woodland burdock) to the larger-headed North American plants. Duistermaat considers A. vulgare to be a synonym of A. lappa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
