<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David J. Keil</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">cardueae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cassini" date="1818">MANTISALCA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Sci. Soc. Philom. Paris</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1818: 142. 1818</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe cardueae;genus MANTISALCA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Anagram of specific epithet salmantica ]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials or perennials, 50–100 cm, herbage not spiny. Stems erect, branched. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate (basal) or sessile (cauline); blade margins ± lobed (proximal) or dentate or lobed (distal), sparsely hirsute (basal and proximal cauline) or glabrous (distal cauline). Heads radiant, borne singly. Involucres ovoid to spheric, 10–15 mm diam. Phyllaries many in 6–8 series, unequal, appressed, ovate, margins entire, apices obtuse to acute, narrowly membranous fringed, each with a short deciduous spine. Receptacles flat, epaleate, long-bristly. Florets many; outer neuter, corollas expanded and ± raylike, ± bilateral, staminodes present; inner fertile, corollas purple (rarely white), radial, tubes very slender, throats narrowly funnelform, lobes linear; anther bases tailed, apical appendages oblong; style branches: fused portions with minutely hairy nodes, distinct portions minute. Cypselae ± barrel-shaped, ± compressed, with elaiosomes ribbed, transversely roughened, apices without prominent collars, smooth, faces glabrous, basal attachment scars oblique or lateral; pappi of several series, outer of stiff, scabrous bristles, inner a single abaxial scale. x = 9, 10, 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mediterranean region.</description>
  <number>19.</number>
  <discussion>Species 4 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
