<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">Mutisieae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Phys. Chim. Hist. Nat. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>88: 199. 1819</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe Mutisieae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, perennials, subshrubs, or shrubs (sometimes clambering) [trees, vines].
    Leaves basal and/or cauline; alternate [opposite]; petiolate or sessile; margins entire,
    dentate, pinnately lobed, or pinnatifid [pinnately compound, spiny, tipped with tendrils]. Heads
    homogamous (discoid in Gochnatia, Hecastocleis; quasi-discoid, -radiate, or -liguliflorous in
    Acourtia, Trixis) or heterogamous (disciform in Adenocaulon, disciform or quasi-radiate or
    -liguliflorous in Chaptalia and Leibnitzia; sometimes cleistogamous in Chaptalia and
    Leibnitzia); borne singly (sometimes on scapiform stems) or in corymbiform, paniculiform, or
    racemiform arrays (aggregated in second-order heads, florets 1–3 per individual head in
    Hecastocleis). Calyculi usually 0 (of 3–7 bractlets in Trixis; second-order heads subtended by
    leaflike bracts in Hecastocleis). Phyllaries persistent or tardily falling, in 1–5+ series,
    distinct or connate, unequal to subequal, usually ± herbaceous, margins and apices seldom
    notably scarious. Receptacles flat to convex, epaleate [paleate] (usually ± foveolate to
    alveolate, margins of sockets sometimes ± membranous). Florets of 1, 2, or 3+ kinds in a head
    (some not readily assignable to usual ray- and disc-floret categories, ± 3 combinations in the
    flora): (1) all florets bisexual and fertile, corollas actinomorphic (Gochnatia, Hecastocleis)
    or zygomorphic (often 2-lipped; Acourtia, Trixis); (2) outer florets pistillate and inner
    bisexual, corollas actinomorphic (Adenocaulon); and (3) outer florets pistillate, corollas
    usually zygomorphic (raylike or liguliform to 2-lipped), sometimes lacking limbs (reduced to
    tubes), inner florets bisexual or functionally staminate, corollas zygomorphic (2-lipped) or
    actinomorphic (Chaptalia, Leibnitzia); anther bases ± tailed, apical appendages ovate or
    lanceolate to linear [none]; styles (bisexual, fertile florets) abaxially glabrous or papillate
    to hairy, branches ± linear, adaxially stigmatic in 2 lines from bases nearly to apices (±
    continuous around apices in Adenocaulon), apices rounded or truncate, appendages essentially
    none. Cypselae ± monomorphic within heads, usually cylindric, clavate, fusiform, or turbinate,
    sometimes ± beaked, bodies smooth or ribbed (glabrous, glabrate, sericeous, or velutinous;
    sometimes distally stipitate-glandular, Adenocaulon); pappi 0 or persistent, of smooth or
    barbellulate to plumose bristles or subulate to setiform and plumose scales.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (Hawaii)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>187a.</number>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 76, species ca. 1000 (7 genera, 14 species in the
    flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Mutisieae as traditionally circumscribed is now considered to be polyphyletic.
    Molecular work has shown that Barnadesia and its allies, a South American group formerly placed
    in Mutisieae, constitute the basal clade of the family; they are now treated as a distinct
    subfamily, Barnadesioideae (K. Bremer and R. K. Jansen 1992). Similarly, J. L. Panero and V. A.
    Funk (2002) segregated two additional subfamilies from Mutisieae (based on Gochnatia and on
    Hecastocleis). Mutisieae in the broad sense are centered in the New World tropics and subtropics
    and are relatively poorly represented elsewhere.</discussion>
  <discussion>Gerbera jamesonii Bolus ex Hooker f. (Transvaal Daisy; perennials, leaves in basal
    rosettes, petioles 10–20+ cm, blades usually pinnately lobed, 12–25+ cm, abaxially lanate,
    peduncles scapiform, to 50+ cm, ray corollas red to orange, pink, or yellow, laminae 2–3+ cm)
    has been noted as established in Florida (http://www.plantatlas.usf.edu).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hansen, H. V. 1990. Phylogenetic studies in the Gerbera-complex (Compositae, tribe
      Mutisieae, subtribe Mutisiinae). Nordic J. Bot. 9: 469–485.</reference>
    <reference>Kim, H. G., D. J. Lookerman, and R. K. Jansen. 2002. Systematic implications of ndhF
      sequence variation in the Mutisieae (Asteraceae). Syst. Bot. 27: 598–609.</reference>
    <reference>Simpson, B. B. and C. E. Anderson. 1978. Mutisieae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds.
      1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Ser. 2, part 10, pp. 1–13.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves: abaxial faces glabrous or with scattered, straight, sometimes glandular,
        hairs and/or double hairs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades narrowly linear-lanceolate (spiny near bases, ± thickened at margins);
        corollas actinomorphic; style-branch apices rounded</description>
      <determination>1. Hecastocleis, p. 71</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves broadly lanceolate or ovate (sometimes linear-lanceolate in Trixis ; not
        spiny at bases or thickened at margins); corollas 2-lipped; style-branch apices
        truncate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials (caudices brown-woolly); corollas pink, lavender, or white</description>
      <determination>2. Acourtia, p. 72</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Shrubs; corollas yellow</description>
      <determination>3. Trixis, p. 75</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves: abaxial faces usually tomentose, tomentulose, or covered with dense wool
        (thinly gray-tomentose in Leibnitzia ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Shrubs or subshrubs; leaves (stiff): adaxial faces dark green; corollas
        actinomorphic (heads discoid)</description>
      <determination>4. Gochnatia, p. 76</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials; leaves (soft): adaxial faces light green; corollas actinomorphic (heads
        discoid or disciform) or actinomorphic and zygomorphic (heads disciform or
        quasi-radiate).</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades triangular to broadly triangular, bases cordate to hastate; heads in
        paniculiform arrays; corollas of inner florets actinomorphic</description>
      <determination>5. Adenocaulon, p. 77</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades elliptic to obovate, bases cuneate; heads borne singly; corollas of
        inner florets zygomorphic (2-lipped) or nearly actinomorphic.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads chasmogamous (produced well after rosette leaves); cypselae glabrous or
        pubescent (hairs relatively short, apices rounded or apiculate)</description>
      <determination>6. Chaptalia, p. 78</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads chasmogamous (early spring, before and concurrently with first rosette
        leaves) or cleistogamous (produced after rosette leaves); cypselae strigose to hispid (hairs
        relatively long, apices sharp-pointed)</description>
      <determination>7. Leibnitzia, p. 80</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
