<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">cardueae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">centaurea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Lamarck in J. Lamarck et al." date="1785">diffusa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Lamarck et al., Encycl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 675. 1785</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe cardueae;genus centaurea;species diffusa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Acosta</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Lamarck) Soják" date="unknown">diffusa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Acosta;species diffusa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals or perennials, 20–80 cm. Stems 1–several, much-branched throughout, puberulent and ± gray tomentose. Leaves hispidulous and ± short-tomentose; basal and proximal cauline petiolate, often absent at anthesis, blades 10–20 cm, margins bipinnately dissected into narrow lobes; mid cauline sessile, bipinnately dissected; distal much smaller, entire or pinnately lobed. Heads disciform, in open paniculiform arrays. Involucres narrowly ovoid or cylindric, 10–13 × 3–5 mm. Principal phyllaries: bodies pale green, ovate to lanceolate, glabrous or finely tomentose, with a few prominent parallel veins, margins and erect appendages fringed with slender stramineous spines, each phyllary tipped by spine 1–3 mm. Inner phyllaries lanceolate, ± acute, appendage lacerate or spine-tipped. Florets 25–35; corollas cream white (rarely pink or pale purple), those of sterile florets 12–13 mm, slender, inconspicuous, those of fertile florets 12–13 mm. Cypselae dark brown, ca. 2–3 mm; pappi 0 or less than 0.5 mm, only rudimentary. 2n = 18, 36.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer (Jun–Aug).</description>
  <description type="habitat">Disturbed sites in grasslands, woodlands, open coniferous forests;</description>
  <description type="elevation">100–2200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Alta., B.C., Ont., Que., Sask., Yukon; Ariz., Calif., Colo., Conn., Idaho, Ill., Ind., Iowa, Ky., Mass., Mich., Mo., Mont., Nebr., Nev., N.H., N.J., N.Mex., Oreg., R.I., Tenn., Utah, Wash., Wyo.; Europe.</description>
  <number>12.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Diffuse or tumble or white knapweed</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">centaurée diffuse</other_name>
  <discussion>Centaurea diffusa is native to southeastern Europe and casually adventive in central and western Europe.</discussion>
  <discussion>Centaurea diffusa readily hybridizes with C. stoebe subsp. micranthos and is often confused with their fertile hybrid (C. ×psammogena G. Gáyer); the latter can be recognized by its cypselae bearing pappi and having conspicuously radiant heads. Morphologically the hybrids are extremely variable; they may be intermediate or may closely resemble one or the other of the parents. Conspicuously radiant heads and pappi are always present; appendages of the phyllaries are brown to black, or rarely stramineous; spines are absent or short and 2n = 18. Centaurea ×psammogena is known from waste places, roadsides, railway tracks; 50–2500 m; B.C., Ont., Que.; Colo., Mass., Mich., Mo., N.C., Oreg., Tenn., Wash. It may occur spontaneously where the ranges of the parent species overlap; they may also be distributed separately. In mixed stands it replaces C. diffusa by introgression. Hybrids are often misidentified as C. diffusa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
