<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="unknown">Cynareae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Centaurea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Willdenow" date="unknown">sulphurea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>930. 1809</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cynareae;genus Centaurea;species sulphurea;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>20.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sicilian star-thistle</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sulphur-colored Sicilian thistle</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sulphur knapweed</other_name>
  <discussion>Centaurea sulphurea is considered to be a noxious weed by the state of California.</discussion>
  <discussion>Excluded species:</discussion>
  <discussion>Centaurea bovina. J. T. Kartesz and C. A. Meacham (1999) listed C. bovina Velenovský from Massachusetts, referencing Rhodora 1924, perhaps based on collections reported as C. diffusa from Norfolk County (C. H. Knowlton and W. Deane 1924). Knowlton and Deane made no mention of C. bovina. According to J. Dostál (1976), C. bovina differs from C. diffusa in having smaller involucres (6–7 mm versus 7–10 mm; 3.5 mm versus 4–5 mm diameter), and purple versus pink flowers). Examination of one of the Norfolk County collections (Churchill s.n., MIN) revealed no differences from C. diffusa.</discussion>
  <discussion>According to R. Angelo (pers. comm.), “The Kartesz citation is puzzling. This taxon [C. bovina] is not cited in the 1924 volume of Rhodora or anywhere in the first 50 years of Rhodora according to the index for that volume and our 50 year index (which is quite comprehensive).</discussion>
  <discussion>“Also, there are no specimens identified as this taxon in the New England Botanical Club (NEBC) herbarium or from Massachusetts in the Harvard University Herbaria collections. We also looked for re-identifications in the other taxa in Centaurea in the NEBC and found no specimens that were earlier identified as C. bovina.</discussion>
  <discussion>“The Vascular Plants of Massachusetts[...] (1999) of [B. A.] Sorrie and [P.] Somers does not list this taxon, nor does the Flora of the Northeast[...] (1999) by [D. W.] Magee and [H. E.] Ahles.”</discussion>
  <discussion>Centaurea paniculata. According to our herbarium studies, reports of C. paniculata Linnaeus (Jersey knapweed) from North America are apparently referable to C. stoebe subsp. micranthos. Centaurea paniculata is quite similar to C. stoebe in habit; it differs clearly by its narrowly ovoid or cylindric heads.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
