<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">Vernonieae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Phys. Chim. Hist. Nat. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>88: 203. 1819</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe Vernonieae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, perennials, or shrubs [trees or lianas] (sap rarely milky).
    Leaves usually cauline, sometimes basal or basal and cauline; alternate (rarely subopposite
    distally) [opposite]; usually petiolate, sometimes sessile (or petioles winged); margins usually
    ± dentate, sometimes entire [lobed or dissected]. Heads homogamous (discoid, pseudo-radiant or
    -liguliflorous in Stokesia), usually in corymbiform, paniculiform, or scorpioid arrays,
    sometimes borne singly or in glomerules [aggregated in second-order heads]. Calyculi 0.
    Phyllaries usually persistent [readily falling], in 2–8+ series, distinct, unequal, herbaceous
    to chartaceous, margins and/or apices sometimes scarious. Receptacles flat to convex, usually
    epaleate (often foveolate, sometimes setose). Ray florets 0 (corollas of peripheral florets
    enlarged, zygomorphic, ± raylike in Stokesia). Disc florets bisexual, fertile; corollas white,
    ochroleucous, or pink to cyanic [yellow]; anther bases ± sagittate [tailed], apical appendages
    ovate to lanceolate; styles abaxially hirsutulous (at least distally), branches lance-linear to
    ± lanceolate, adaxially continuously stigmatic from bases nearly to apices, apices acute,
    appendages essentially none. Cypselae ± monomorphic within heads, columnar to clavate, fusiform,
    or prismatic, sometimes compressed, not beaked, bodies smooth, nerved, or ribbed (glabrous or
    hirsutulous to strigillose, sometimes resin-gland-dotted as well); pappi usually persistent,
    usually in 2 series (outer series of shorter, stouter bristles or narrow scales, inner of
    longer, usually barbellate bristles), sometimes in 1 series (bristles or scales, scales often
    aristate).</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly tropics and warm-temperate regions of New World and Old
    World.</description>
  <number>187d.</number>
  <discussion>Genera 100–140, species ca. 1300 (6 genera, 25 species in the
    flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Most members of Vernonieae are herbs, subshrubs, or shrubs (Vernonia arborea
    Buchanan-Hamilton of tropical Asia may form trees to 33 m). They are characterized by discoid
    heads of bisexual florets with purple to pink or white corollas, calcarate anthers, attenuate,
    abaxially hirsutulous style branches stigmatic ± uniformly (rather than in two lines or bands)
    nearly to their tips, and pollen grains with regular, polygonal, patterns of ± spiny to smooth
    ridges. Centers of species concentration for the tribe are found in Africa, Madagascar, South
    America, and Antilles. In the flora, most species are found in the eastern and southern states
    of the United States. The plants are often associated with open, prairie or savanna-like
    areas.</discussion>
  <discussion>Treating clades recognized by J. L. Panero and V. A. Funk (2002) as corresponding to
    tribes, Vernonieae is sister to Liabeae (none in the flora) and is included with Arctotideae
    (introduced), Cichorieae, and Gundelieae (none in the flora) within Cichorioideae.</discussion>
  <discussion>Historically, 80% or so of the species in the tribe were included in Vernonia. H.
    Robinson (1999) has argued for resurrections and recircumscriptions of some old genera and
    recognition of some “new” genera, resulting in a Vernonia of ca. 20 species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Stokesia laevis and some Vernonia species are grown as ornamentals. Some Vernonia
    species have been used medicinally in folk remedies and some may be locally troublesome as weeds
    (e.g., V. baldwinii).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Robinson, H. 1999. Generic and subtribal classification of American Vernonieae.
      Smithsonian Contr. Bot. 89.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads pseudo-radiant (corollas of peripheral, bisexual florets enlarged,
        zygomorphic); margins of phyllaries (at least the outer), pectinately
        spinose-toothed</description>
      <determination>28. Stokesia , p. 201</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads ± discoid; margins of phyllaries not pectinately spinose-toothed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads sessile, borne in congested clusters; florets (1–)4(–5) in each
        head.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads (1–)10–40 per cluster, each cluster subtended by (2–)3 ± deltate bracts;
        pappi of 5(–6) 1-aristate scales (look closely for squamiform, gradually to abruptly
        tapering base of each arista), no scales tipped with plicate aristae</description>
      <determination>29. Elephantopus , p. 202</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads 1–5+ per cluster, each cluster subtended by 1–2 lanceolate to spatulate or
        linear bracts; pappi of 6–10 ± laciniate to aristate scales, 2(–3+) of aristate scales each
        with awnlike arista plicate (2-folded) distally</description>
      <determination>30. Pseudelephantopus , p. 204</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads mostly pedunculate, not borne in congested clusters; florets 9–100+ in each
        head.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals (perhaps persisting); cypselae not ribbed</description>
      <determination>31. Cyanthillium , p. 204</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials or functionally annuals; cypselae 8–10-ribbed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads each subtended by 3–8+, ± foliaceous bracts; pappi caducous</description>
      <determination>32. Centratherum , p. 206</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads not each subtended by foliaceous bracts; pappi persistent</description>
      <determination>33. Vernonia , p. 206</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
