<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>32.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>CENTRATHERUM</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Centratherum Cassini</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Sci. Soc. Philom. Paris</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1817: 31. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in F. Cuvier, Dict. Sci. Nat. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 7: 383. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Vernonieae;genus CENTRATHERUM;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <etymology>[Latin centrum , center, and atherum , prickle or awn, perhaps alluding to spine-tipped middle phyllaries of original species]</etymology>
  <common_name>Larkdaisy</common_name>
  <author>John L. Strother</author>
  <description>Perennials (or functionally annuals), 1–3(–8+) dm (stems sometimes rooting at proximal nodes). Leaves cauline; sessile or petiolate, petioles ± winged; blades ovate to obovate, lanceolate, or linear, bases ± cuneate, margins toothed, apices acute, abaxial faces usually ± hirtellous to strigillose or tomentose, sometimes nearly glabrous, adaxial faces sparsely scabrellous or glabrate, both usually resin-gland-dotted. Heads discoid (pedunculate, each subtended by 3–8+, ± foliaceous bracts), borne singly. Involucres ± hemispheric, 6–12(–18+) mm diam. Phyllaries 24–50+ in 4–8+ series, each proximally firm, distally ± scarious, the outer ovate to deltate or lanceolate, inner oblong to lanceolate, margins entire, tips rounded to acute, usually apiculate to seta-tipped or attenuate-spinose, abaxial faces glabrous or sparsely strigillose to tomentose and usually ± resin-gland-dotted distally. Florets 30–50(–100+); corollas usually lavender to purplish (rarely white), tubes longer than funnelform throats, lobes 5, lance-linear, ± equal. Cypselae ± columnar to plumply clavate, 8–10-ribbed, glabrous, often resin-gland-dotted; pappi caducous, of 20–40 lance-linear to subulate scales. x = 16.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 2–4 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <us_distribution>Florida</us_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Neotropics</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Pacific Islands (Philippines)</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Australia.</global_distribution>
  <references>
    <reference>Gleason, H. A. 1922. Centratherum. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora…. 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 33, pp. 49–50.</reference>
    <reference>Kirkman, L. K. 1981. Taxonomic revision of Centratherum and Phyllocephalum (Compositae: Vernonieae). Rhodora 83: 1–24.</reference>
  </references>
</treatment>

