<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Beryl B. Simpson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Mutisieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">HECASTOCLEIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Proc. Amer. Acad. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>17: 220. 1882</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Mutisieae;genus HECASTOCLEIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hecastos, each, and cleios , to shut up, alluding to one floret enclosed in each involucre]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs or shrubs, 40–80(–150+) cm (usually with tufts of hairs in axils of leaves). Leaves cauline; sessile; blades linear, bases cuneate, margins entire or proximally spiny, faces tomentulose, glabrescent. Heads discoid, clustered in second-order heads (each cluster 15–25 mm diam. and subtended by ovate to orbiculate, prickly-margined bracts). Involucres (each enclosing 1 floret) cylindric to fusiform, 10 mm. Phyllaries in 2–3 series, ovate to lanceolate or linear, unequal, apices acute to cuspidate. Receptacles flat, smooth, glabrous, epaleate. Florets 1, bisexual, fertile; corollas reddish purple to greenish white, actinomorphic (lobes 5, lance-linear, glabrous); anther basal appendages slightly fimbriate, apical appendages lanceolate, acute; style branches relatively stout (0.1–0.5 mm), apices rounded (abaxial faces papillose to pilose). Cypselae ± terete (± 4 mm), not beaked, obscurely 4–5-nerved, faces glabrescent, not glandular-hairy; pappi of 6 unequal, lanceolate or multitoothed scales (sometimes ± coalescent and forming lacerate crowns). x = 8.</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw United States.</description>
  <number>1.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Williams, M. J. 1977. Hecastocleis shockleyi A. Gray. Mentzelia 3: 18.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
