<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="1806">cichorieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="F. H. Wiggers" date="1780">taraxacum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="de Candolle in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle" date="1838">latilobum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in A. P. de Candolle and A. L. P. P. de Candolle, Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7: 146. 1838</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe cichorieae;genus taraxacum;species latilobum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants 9–75 cm; taproots seldom branched. Stems 1–7+, erect to ascending, ± purplish, glabrate, sometimes ± sparsely villous distally. Leaves 10+, erect to patent; petioles ± narrowly winged; blades broadly oblance-olate to narrowly obovate (often runcinate), 15–47.5 × 2.5–9 cm, bases attenuate, margins usually shallowly lobed to sometimes lacerate (mostly proximally), lobes retrorse or straight, broadly deltate to triangular, sometimes antrorsely curved apically, acute to acuminate, teeth 5–7 on lobes and in sinuses, irregular, triangular or sometimes lanceolate, terminals broader than laterals, apices obtuse to bluntly short-caudate or -acuminate (rarely acute), faces glabrous or glabrate to sparsely pilose or villous. Calyculi of ca. 18 , reflexed to recurved, ovate to broadly lanceolate bractlets in 3 series, 8–11 × 2–5 mm, margins narrowly scarious, sometimes proximally more widely so, apices acuminate, hornless, ± scarious-erose, tips often purplish and blackish. Involucres dark green, often purplish-tinged, campanulate, (13–)15–23 mm. Phyllaries 14–18 in 2 series, lanceolate to linear (outer) or ovate to lance-ovate (inner), 1.2–4 mm wide, scarious, narrowly (outer, distal part of inner) or widely (proximal part of inner), apices long-acuminate, hornless, scarious, erose, hyaline, purplish-grayish. Florets ca. 150; corollas yellow (outer dark gray striped abaxially, also purplish), 13–17 × 1–1.3 mm. Cypselae olive-tan to tan, bodies oblanceoloid, 2.8–3.8 mm, cones terete, 0.9–1 mm, beaks slender, 8–12 mm, ribs 5, wide (with 2–3 rows of tubercles or spines), faces proximally tuberculate, muricate in distal 1/3–1/2, distalmost spines sometimes very sharp, fused in pairs and flattened; pappi white to creamy, 6.5–7 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology">jul</description>
  <description type="phenology">aug</description>
  <description type="habitat">seaside calcareous slopes and grassy taluses or clifftops</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–30 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Nfld. and Labr. (Nfld.)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Que.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Maine.</description>
  <number>2.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Large-lobed dandelion</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">pissenlit à lobes larges</other_name>
  <discussion>Taraxacum latilobum is known only from the Gulf of St. Lawrence and adjacent areas.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
