<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="unknown">Cichorieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Zinn" date="unknown">HELMINTHOTHECA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Cat. Pl. Hort. Gott.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>430. 1757</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cichorieae;genus HELMINTHOTHECA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek helminthos , worm, and Latin theca , case or container; allusion unclear, perhaps to shapes of cypselae]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals or biennials, 10–100+ cm; taprooted. Stems usually 1, erect, branched distally or throughout, hirsute to hispid or setose (hair tips 2–4-hooked). Leaves basal and cauline; basal ± petiolate, distal sessile; blades elliptic, lanceolate, oblanceolate, oblong, or ovate, margins usually dentate to pinnately lobed (faces hirsute to hispid, hair tips 2–4-hooked). Heads borne singly or in loose, corymbiform arrays. Peduncles (terminal and axillary) not inflated distally, seldom bracteate. Calyculi of (3–)5, cordate or ovate to lance-ovate, foliaceous bracts. Involucres ovoid to urceolate, 9–12+ mm diam. (larger in fruit). Phyllaries (5–)8–13+ in 1 series, lance-linear to linear, subequal, margins little, if at all, scarious, apices acuminate. Receptacles flat, pitted, glabrous, epaleate. Florets 30–60+; corollas yellow (often reddish abaxially). Cypselae (dimorphic): outer whitish, bodies gibbous, ribs 5–10, beaks about equaling bodies, fragile, faces hirtellous to pilosulous adaxially; inner reddish brown, bodies ± compressed-ellipsoid to fusiform, beaks about equaling or longer than bodies, fragile, faces transversely rugulose to muricate, otherwise glabrous; pappi persistent, of 10–15+, whitish, subequal, barbellate or plumose, subulate to setiform (basally connate) scales in 1–2 series. x = 5.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">widely introduced.</description>
  <number>55.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Oxtongue</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 4 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Lack, H. W. 1975. A note on Helminthotheca Zinn (Compositae). Taxon 24: 111–112.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
