<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>61.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>CALYCOSERIS</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>A. Gray</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Smithsonian Contr. Knowl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5(6): 104, plate 14. 1853</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cichorieae;genus CALYCOSERIS;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <etymology>[Greek kalyx , cup, and seris , chicory, alluding to shallow cups on apices of cypselae]</etymology>
  <common_name>Tack-stem</common_name>
  <author>L. D. Gottlieb</author>
  <description>Annuals, 5–30 cm; taprooted. Stems 1–3, erect or ascending, branched from bases; distal stems, branches, and involucres conspicuously dotted with short, stipitate, flat-topped glands that resemble tacks. Leaves basal and cauline; alternate; sessile; basal blades pinnately lobed (lobes narrow, linear, often delicate, spreading, margins entire, smooth); distal reduced to linear, entire bracts. Heads borne singly or in open, cymiform arrays. Peduncles (1–3 cm) not inflated, not bracteate. Calyculi of 8–16, reflexed, unequal bractlets (lengths to 1/2 phyllaries). Involucres campanulate, 5–12+ mm diam. Phyllaries 12–20 in 1 series, linear-lanceolate, equal, margins scarious, apices acute. Receptacles flat, smooth, bristly, epaleate (each floret subtended by 1 fine, capillary bristle). Florets ca. 25; corollas white or yellow (showy). Cypselae tan to brown, fusiform, beaked, ribs 5, separated by longitudinal grooves, faces glabrous or scabridulous; pappi (borne on denticulate cups at beak tips) falling (together), of 50–60+, white, basally connate, smooth bristles 5–8(–9) mm in 1 series. x = 7.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>sw United States</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>nw Mexico.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Ligules yellow; tack-shaped glands red- or purple-tipped; cypselae deeply grooved between ribs, faces not rugulose</statement>
      <determination>1. Calycoseris parryi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Ligules white; tack-shaped glands straw-colored; cypselae shallowly grooved between ribs, faces weakly cross-rugulose</statement>
      <determination>2. Calycoseris wrightii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

