<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>1.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Agoseris</genus_name>
    <species_name>glauca</species_name>
    <species_authority>(Pursh) Rafinesque</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Herb. Raf.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>39. 1833</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cichorieae;genus Agoseris;species glauca;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <common_name>Prairie agoseris</common_name>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Troximon</genus_name>
    <species_name>glaucum</species_name>
    <species_authority>Pursh</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Amer. Sept.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 505. 1813</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Stems 0. Leaves erect to decumbent; petioles rarely purplish, petiole margins glabrous or pubescent, not usually ciliate; blades lanceolate to oblanceolate, 2–46 cm, margins usually entire, sometimes dentate, rarely lobed or lacerate, lobes 2–3 pairs or irregularly arranged, lanceolate, spreading, lobules 0, faces glabrous and glaucous or sparsely villous to tomentose. Peduncles not notably elongating after flowering, 5–60(–90) cm in fruit, glabrous or glabrate, or apically puberulent to lanate, sometimes stipitate-glandular. Involucres obconic to hemispheric, 1–3 cm in fruit. Phyllaries in 2–3 series, green or medially rosy purple, often with purple-black spots, midstripe, and/or tips, subequal to unequal, margins glabrous or ± hairy, not usually ciliate, faces glabrous or tomentose, sometimes stipitate-glandular or eglandular; outer erect or spreading, apices adaxially glabrous or hirsuto-villous; inner erect, not notably elongating in fruit. Receptacles epaleate or paleate. Florets 15–150; corollas yellow, tubes 4–18 mm, ligules 6–24 × 2–5 mm; anthers 3–7 mm. Cypselae 7–15 mm, bodies fusiform to narrowly conic, 5–9 mm, tapered to stout beaks 1–4 mm, lengths mostly less than 1/2 times bodies; ribs flattened to ridged, glabrous, or distally scabrous; pappi in 2–3 series, 8–18 mm. 2n = 18, 36</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>w North America.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Receptacles epaleate; leaf blades usually glabrous and glaucous, rarely sparsely hairy; peduncles (distally, and phyllaries) usually glabrous, some- times puberulent, eglandular</statement>
      <determination>1a. Agoseris glaucavar. glauca</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Receptacles usually ± paleate; leaf blades usually puberulent to densely villous, sometimes glabrous; peduncles (distally, and phyllaries) usually villous to lanate or tomentose, sometimes glabrous, often stipitate-glandular</statement>
      <determination>1b. Agoseris glaucavar. dasycephala</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

