<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>David J. Bogler</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Lamarck &amp; de Candolle" date="1806">cichorieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Lessing" date="1832">PINAROPAPPUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Gen. Compos.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>143. 1832</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe cichorieae;genus PINAROPAPPUS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pinaro, dirty, squalid, and pappos , pappus, alluding to color of pappi]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, 3–40 cm; taprooted (taproots deep, woody) or rhizomatous. Stems 1–20+, erect or ascending, simple or branched proximally, ± scapiform, glabrous. Leaves basal and cauline; petiolate; basal blades linear to lanceolate, margins entire, toothed, or pinnately lobed (faces glabrous); cauline foliaceous or reduced to minute bracts distally. Heads borne singly. Peduncles not inflated distally, sometimes bracteate. Calyculi 0. Involucres cylindric to campanulate, 3–20 mm diam. Phyllaries 18–22 in 3–5 series, ovate to lanceolate, unequal, margins scarious, apices acute. Receptacles slightly convex, slightly pitted, glabrous, paleate (paleae scarious, acuminate). Florets (10–)20–40(–60); corollas pink, purple, lavender, or nearly white. Cypselae golden or yellowish brown, cylindric or fusiform, tapered to slender beaks, ribs 5–6, rounded, obscure, scabrous or hispidulous; pappi persistent, of 15–60, distinct, tawny or yellowish brown, unequal, barbellulate bristles in 1 series.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 7–10 (2 in the flora): North America, Mexico, Central America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 7–10 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Mexico, Central America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>81.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Rocklettuce</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 7–10 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Plants of Pinaropappus are recognized by the glabrous leaves in dense rosettes, scapiform stems, graduated phyllaries, and pale lavender and whitish corollas. They are commonly found in dry, rocky, limestone habitats; some species are cliff-dwellers.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 3–7 cm (forming dense clumps and mats); involucres cylindric, 8–10 × 3–5 mm; phyllaries purplish, margins white, apices purplish to dull brown (necrotic)</description>
      <determination>1. Pinaropappus parvus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 10–30 cm (forming individual rosettes or clumps); involucres campanulate, 10–15 × 12–20 mm; phyllaries pale green, margins pink, apices dark brown</description>
      <determination>2. Pinaropappus roseus</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
