<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">cardueae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">cirsium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="1803">horridulum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 90. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe cardueae;genus cirsium;species horridulum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Biennials or perennials, (± fleshy), 15–250 cm; stout taproots and a fascicle of fleshy lateral roots, often perennating by root sprouts. Stems 1–several, usually erect, often stout, glabrous to densely tomentose; branches 0–many, spreading to ascending, short, stout. Leaves: blades linear to oblanceolate or oblong-elliptic, 10–40 × 2–10 cm, unlobed and spiny-dentate to deeply pinnatifid, lobes spiny-dentate or coarsely lobed, main spines stout, 5–30 mm, abaxial faces subglabrous to loosely tomentose, adaxial glabrous to ± densely villous with septate trichomes; basal present at flowering, spiny winged-petiolate, bases often tapered; principal cauline sessile, well distributed, often not much reduced distally, bases often ± auriculate-clasping; distal cauline often spinier than the proximal. Heads 1–20 in subcapitate to corymbiform arrays (each closely subtended by an involucre-like ring of spiny-margined bracts). Peduncles 0–5 cm. Involucres hemispheric to campanulate, 3–5 × 3–8 cm. Phyllaries in 5–9 series, subequal to imbricate, light green to stramineous, lanceolate to linear, distally often with reddish margins, abaxial faces without glutinous ridge, often ± thinly tomentose, often scabridulous in submarginal bands; outer and middle appressed-ascending, bodies usually reddish-tinged, margins setulose-ciliolate, apices acuminate, spines 1–2 mm, weak; apices of inner straight, flat. Corollas white to yellow, pink, purple, or red, 30–47 mm, tubes 11–30 mm, throats 6–10 mm, lobes 7–10 mm; style tips 3–5 mm. Cypselae straw-colored to tan, 4–6 mm, apical collars weakly differentiated; pappi 25–35 mm. 2n = 32, 33, 34, 35.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Varieties 4 (3 in the flora): e United States, Mexico.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Varieties 4 (3 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>e United States, Mexico.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>11.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Bristly or horrid or yellow or bull thistle</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 4 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Although several variants have been given taxonomic recognition as species, these seem at most races. Flower color varies greatly, sometimes within populations and sometimes on a populational or regional basis. Herbarium specimens are sometimes difficult to assign to variety.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems densely tomentose; involucres ± densely tomentose</description>
      <determination>11a. Cirsium horridulum var. horridulum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems glabrous or sparsely tomentose; involucres glabrous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves shallowly to deeply pinnatifid, main spines 10–30 mm</description>
      <determination>11b. Cirsium horridulum var. megacanthum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves spinose-dentate to shallowly pinnatifid, main spines mostly 5–10 mm</description>
      <determination>11c. Cirsium horridulum var. vittatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
