<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini ex Lecoq &amp; Juillet" date="1831">Gnaphalieae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Dict. Rais. Term. Bot.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>296. 1831</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe Gnaphalieae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, perennials, subshrubs, or shrubs (often ± woolly annuals 1–10 cm). Leaves
    basal and/or cauline; usually alternate, rarely opposite; petiolate or sessile (bases often
    decurrent onto stems); blade margins usually entire, rarely denticulate (often revolute or
    involute, faces often tomentose or woolly and/or glandular-pubescent). Heads usually
    heterogamous (usually disciform, rarely “quasi-radiate”), sometimes homogamous (discoid,
    sometimes pistillate or functionally staminate), usually borne in corymbiform, paniculiform, or
    racemiform arrays, sometimes in glomerules, sometimes aggregated into second-order heads, rarely
    borne singly. Calyculi 0. Phyllaries sometimes 0 (apparent phyllaries interpreted as outer
    receptacular paleae), usually persistent (often wholly or partially white or brightly colored,
    sometimes woolly, at least proximally and/or medially), usually (12–30+) in 3–10+ series,
    distinct, and unequal, sometimes in 1–2 series, distinct and subequal to equal, medially
    herbaceous to membranous or scarious, margins and/or apices usually notably scarious.
    Receptacles usually flat to convex, sometimes conic to ± columnar, usually epaleate, sometimes
    paleate (paleae sometimes enfolding pistillate florets). Ray florets usually 0 (sometimes
    peripheral florets pistillate and corollas ± zygomorphic and bearing a ± flat limb and
    interpreted by some as ray florets). Peripheral (pistillate) florets (often 100+ in disciform
    heads) in 1–3+ series; corollas (usually present) yellow or purplish to whitish, sometimes
    red-tipped (actinomorphic and filiform). Disc (inner) florets (sometimes 1–10, usually more)
    bisexual or functionally staminate; corollas yellow or purplish, sometimes red-tipped, usually
    actinomorphic, lobes usually (4–)5, usually ± deltate, rarely lance-ovate to lanceolate; anther
    bases usually ± tailed [not tailed], apical appendages mostly ovate to lance-ovate or linear
    (usually flat); styles abaxially glabrous or (mostly distally) papillate, branches ± linear,
    adaxially stigmatic in 2 lines from bases to apices, apices truncate or truncate-penicillate,
    appendages essentially none. Cypselae usually monomorphic within heads, mostly ovoid to obovoid
    and compressed or obcompressed, not beaked or apically attenuate, bodies smooth or ± papillate
    or muriculate, often 2-, 3-, or 5-ribbed (glabrous or hairy, seldom glandular, sometimes with
    myxogenic hairs or papillae); pappi (rarely 0) persistent or readily falling, usually of
    barbellulate, sometimes plumose bristles, sometimes of scales (scales often aristate), sometimes
    combinations of bristles and scales.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide, with centers of concentration in southern Africa and Australia; in both Old World and New World, the greater numbers of genera and species in the southern hemisphere.</description>
  <number>187g.</number>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 187, species ca. 1240 (19 genera, 111 species in the
    flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Traditionally, taxa included here in Gnaphalieae have been treated in Inuleae within
    Gnaphaliinae (cf. A. A. Anderberg 1991; K. Bremer 1994). Gnaphalieae include everlastings and
    helichrysums, which have brightly colored, persistent phyllaries and are much used in dried
    floral arangements, and other ornamentals, e.g., species or cultivars from Anaphalis,
    Antennaria, and Leontopodium (edelweiss). Some species of Facelis, Gamochaeta, Gnaphalium,
    Helichrysum, and Pseudognaphalium are widespread as weeds.</discussion>
  <discussion>Phyllaries in most Gnaphalieae are usually more or less herbaceous to more or less
    cartilaginous medially and/or proximally and membranous to scarious laterally and distally. The
    herbaceous to cartilagionous area of a phyllary is usually somewhat thicker than the rest and
    such areas are called stereomes. Stereomes may be more or less divided or not and may be more or
    less glandular or not. The membranous to scarious portion of a phyllary distal to the stereome
    is sometimes called a lamina (not to be confused with corolla laminae of other groups). The
    phyllaries, or laminae are often colored and may be more or less opaque or more or less
    hyaline.</discussion>
  <discussion>Surfaces of cypselae of Gnaphalieae may be smooth, longitudinally ridged, or papillate
    (with minute bumps or projections from one or both ends of each epidermal cell; see A. A.
    Anderberg 1991). In addition, the cypselae may be glabrous or may bear myxogenic (producing
    mucilage when wetted) or non-myxogenic “twin-hairs.” The twin-hairs may be relatively long and
    form sericeous to strigillose induments. Very short, globose to clavate twin-hairs (lengths
    equaling or not much greater than diameters) are characteristic of some taxa and have sometimes
    been called “papillae” in descriptions of members of Gnaphalieae. Cypselae with such very short
    twin-hairs are described here as minutely hairy and the hairs are referred to as
    papilliform.</discussion>
  <discussion>Stuartina hamata Philipson, a member of Gnaphalieae, was collected near a wool mill in
    South Carolina in 1957 (G. L. Nesom 2004c). It is native to Australia and may be characterized
    as annuals, prostrate, mostly 6–12 cm across, ± woolly, leaves cauline (crowded near heads),
    petioles basally dilated, blades suborbiculate, heads ca. 3 mm (borne in glomerules), phyllaries
    ovate to lanceolate, inner uncinate, florets 5 (outer 4 pistillate, inner bisexual), cypselae
    0.8–1 mm, epappose.</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera 97–105 below (genera following second lead 3 in key to genera, members of
    Filagininae in a narrow sense) have exceptionally small heads and florets (even for composites)
    and are closely similar in expressions of some characters. Together, as found in the flora, they
    may be characterized as:</discussion>
  <discussion>Annuals, taprooted, usually arachnoid-sericeous to lanuginose throughout, sometimes
    glabrescent proximally on stems and/or on adaxial faces of leaves. Leaves usually sessile,
    sometimes obscurely petiolate (usually gradually larger and more crowded distally, sometimes
    again smaller among heads, where referred to as capitular leaves); blades 1-nerved, bases
    usually ± cuneate, sometimes rounded, margins entire. Heads disciform. Involucres absent,
    vestigial, or inconspicuous, often simulated by leaves or paleae. Phyllaries 0, vestigial, or
    1–6. Receptacles paleate (at least peripherally), usually glabrous among paleae (bristly in
    Hesperevax). Florets pistillate, functionally staminate (usually referred to as staminate), or
    bisexual; corollas whitish, usually distally yellowish, reddish, brownish, or
    purplish.</discussion>
  <discussion>Leaves of Filagininae that immediately subtend heads and/or glomerules are here called
    capitular leaves. Flowering branches may also immediately subtend heads or glomerules; if so,
    capitular leaves collectively subtend such branches and their heads/glomerules, and
    heads/glomerules appear to be sessile in forks of pseudo-dichotomies or -polytomies. Sometimes
    capitular leaves subtend only glomerules and not individual heads and individual heads may be
    difficult to distinguish within glomerules.</discussion>
  <discussion>Paleae subtend all or at least some florets in members of Filagininae. They are
    referred to as bisexual, pistillate, or staminate paleae depending on sorts of florets
    subtended. Pistillate paleae persistent or shed with cypselae, usually incurved over inner
    (bisexual or functionally staminate) florets at flowering; margins usually thinner, ± scarious,
    forming wings (sometimes gradually and obscurely so); wings recurved to erect to incurved or
    inflexed; abaxial faces usually ± lanuginose to sericeous, sometimes glabrate or glabrous;
    apices rounded or obtuse to acuminate or aristate. Bisexual and/or staminate paleae usually
    persistent, sometimes falling in fruit, sometimes 0 (most Filago, Logfia, and Micropus, all
    Psilocarphus; then simulated by pistillate paleae), usually erect at flowering, incurved, erect,
    or spreading in fruit, sometimes enlarging as cypselae mature (then adaxially lanuginose to
    sericeous), shorter than or surpassing pistillate paleae; bodies ± ovate or lanceolate to
    spatulate (saccate in Micropsis); margins rarely forming wings; abaxial faces lanuginose to
    sericeous or nearly glabrous; apices usually entire, sometimes 2–3-fid, sometimes aristate to
    spinose (uncinate in Ancistrocarphus filagineus).</discussion>
  <discussion>Corolla scars on cypselae of Filagininae may be offset adaxially to subapical or ±
    median positions and may be diagnostic for certain taxa (corolla attachments usually appear to
    be apical before ovaries mature).</discussion>
  <discussion>All or outer pistillate florets of Filagininae lack pappi. Inner pistillate, bisexual,
    and staminate florets have pappi 0 or of 1–28+, whitish, fragile (easily broken or detached) or
    readily falling, ± barbellate to barbellulate or smooth (sometimes smooth only distally)
    bristles in 1 series. At bases of bristles, barbs are sometimes notably longer and finer,
    sometimes wavy or curled, and more patent than antrorse and may interweave, resulting in
    proximal coherence of adjacent bristles (e.g., in Logfia); cohering bristles may be shed in
    groups or complete rings and separate subsequently.</discussion>
  <discussion>In descriptions of Filagininae, median refers to areas or positions about midway
    between a base and corresponding apex, and medial refers to areas or positions ± centered
    between opposing lateral edges.</discussion>
  <discussion>As noted by A. Cronquist (1950) for Psilocarphus, the wings or apices of pistillate
    paleae of Filagininae are incurved during flowering, guide styles over bisexual or functionally
    staminate florets, and, likely, enforce nearly obligate within-head geitonogamy. Reproductive
    isolation created by this self-pollinating syndrome may allow interspecific or intergeneric
    hybrids, when fertile, to persist and become independently reproducing species among their
    parental taxa (J. D. Morefield 1992, 1992b).</discussion>
  <discussion>Birds harvest shoots of Logfia, Micropus, Psilocarphus, and Stylocline species,
    presumably for nesting materials (neststraw is common name for Stylocline) and may be
    significant in shorter-distance dispersal of some taxa. The light, fluffy paleae enclosing
    epappose cypselae of the same genera aid in wind dispersal, as suggested by A. Cronquist
    (1950).</discussion>
  <discussion>Different species and genera of Filagininae often grow together and are frequently
    mixedand/or misidentified on herbarium sheets. Young or stunted plants often will not fit keys
    and descriptions; whenever practicable in attempting identifications of members of Filagininae,
    use well-developed plants with at least some heads in fruit. Some diagnostic characters require
    careful evaluation of structures within heads, usually with magnification; for example, anther
    tips and corolla lobes may be similar in color and shape and may be difficult to
    distinguish.</discussion>
  <discussion>Good illustrations of most North American Filagininae may be found in L. Abrams and R.
    S. Ferris (1923–1960, vol. 4), G. Beauverd (1913), or J. C. Hickman (1993).</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 187, species ca. 1240 (19 genera, 111 species in the flora)</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Anderberg, A. A. 1991. Taxonomy and phylogeny of the tribe
      Gnaphalieae (Asteraceae). Opera Bot. 104: 1–195.</reference>
    <reference>Drury, D. G. 1970. A fresh approach to the classification of the genus Gnaphalium
      with particular reference to the species present in New Zealand (Inuleae–Compositae). New
      Zealand J. Bot. 9: 157–185.</reference>
    <reference>Hilliard, O. M. and B. L. Burtt. 1981. Some generic concepts in
      Compositae–Gnaphaliinae. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 82: 181–232.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually discoid (unisexual or nearly so, staminate or pistillate; plants
        unisexual or nearly so; predominantly pistillate heads rarely with 1–9 central, functionally
        staminate florets; predominantly staminate heads rarely with 1–4+ peripheral, pistillate
        florets; involucres mostly 6–10 mm).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants (0.2–)4–25(–70) cm; basal leaves usually present at flowering (withering
        before in A. geyeri ); pappus bristles (at least pistillate) usually basally connate or
        coherent</description>
      <determination>87. Antennaria , p. 388</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants mostly 20–80(–120+) cm; basal leaves usually withering before flowering;
        pappus bristles distinct or basally connate</description>
      <determination>90. Anaphalis , p. 426</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually disciform (plants not unisexual; heads mostly alike, each with 4–200+
        pistillate and 1–200+ bisexual or functionally staminate florets; heads rarely discoid in
        Xerochrysum , which has involucres 10–30 mm and brightly colored phyllaries in 3–8+
        series).</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, perennials, or subshrubs; receptacles epaleate; cypselae all
        pappose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate florets fewer than bisexual.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Subshrubs; heads in glomerules in corymbiform arrays; involucres campanu- late, 4–8
        mm</description>
      <determination>89. Helichrysum , p. 425</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or perennials; heads borne singly or 2–3 in loose, corymbi-
        form arrays; involucres ± hemispheric, 10–30 mm</description>
      <determination>91. Xerochrysum , p. 427</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate florets more numerous than bisexual.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals; pappi persistent; pappus bristles ± plumose</description>
      <determination>96. Facelis , p. 442</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or perennials; pappi readily falling; pappus bristles
        barbellate to barbellulate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads in spiciform or subcapitate arrays or in glomerules in continuous or
        interrupted, usually spiciform, sometimes paniculiform, arrays (terminal glomerules in
        depauperate plants); cypselae ± papillate (papillae or papilliform hairs myxogenic) or
        strigillose (hairs not myxogenic); pappus bristles basally connate, falling readily (in
        groups or rings; distinct in Omalotheca supina ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals or short-lived perennials; phyllaries in 3–7 series; pistillate florets
        50–130+; cypselae ± papillate (papillae or papilliform hairs myxogenic)</description>
      <determination>93. Gamochaeta , p. 431</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials; phyllaries in 2–3 series; pistillate florets 35–70+; cypselae
        strigillose (hairs not myxogenic)</description>
      <determination>94. Omalotheca , p. 438</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads usually in ± capitate clusters (subtended by leafy bracts) or corymbiform or
        paniculiform (often bracteate) arrays; cypselae usually glabrous or minutely hairy or
        papillate (papillae or papilliform hairs not myxogenic), sometimes minutely roughened and/or
        with 4–6 longitudinal ridges; pappus bristles distinct (falling separately) or basally
        coherent (falling in groups or rings).</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres narrowly campanulate to cylindric; phyllaries mostly stramineous to
        brownish, sometimes purplish to pinkish (hyaline, stereomes not glandular)</description>
      <determination>95. Euchiton , p. 440</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucres narrowly to broadly campanulate to cylindric; phyllaries white, rosy,
        tawny, or brown (opaque or hyaline, stereomes usually glandular).</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals, (1–)3–30 cm; heads usually in ± capitate clusters (in axils of leaves or
        bracts), sometimes in spiciform glomerules; cypselae usually glabrous, sometimes minutely
        hairy or papillate (hairs or papillae not myxogenic)</description>
      <determination>92. Gnaphalium , p. 428</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, or perennials, (4–)15–150(–200) cm; heads usually in glomerules
        in corymbiform or paniculiform arrays, sometimes in terminal clusters; cypselae usually
        smooth, sometimes papillate-roughened and/or with 4–6 longitudinal ridges, usually glabrous
        (papilliform hairs in P. luteoalbum )</description>
      <determination>88. Pseudognaphalium , p. 415</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals; receptacles ± paleate (all or at least the outermost florets each
        subtended by a palea); cypselae (all or at least the outermost) epappose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bisexual florets (1–)2–10(–11), pappi of (11–)13–28+ bristles visible in heads;
        functionally staminate florets 0.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Receptacles fungiform to obovoid (heights 0.4–1.6 times diams.); most pistillate
        paleae ± saccate, each ± enclosing a floret, apices blunt; innermost paleae spreading in
        fruit; cypselae dimorphic (outer longer than inner)</description>
      <determination>97. Logfia , p. 443</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Receptacles cylindric to clavate (heights 5–15 times diams.); most pistillate
        paleae open to ± folded (at most each enfolding, not enclosing a floret; apices acuminate to
        aristate); innermost paleae erect to ascending in fruit; cypselae mono- morphic (outer ±
        equaling inner)</description>
      <determination>98. Filago , p. 447</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bisexual florets 0 or 2–7, pappi 0; functionally staminate florets 0 or 2–12, pappi
        0 or of 1–10(–13) bristles hidden in heads.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate paleae open most of lengths, flat or concave to loosely folded (not
        enclosing florets); pappi 0.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bisexual paleae saccate, each enclosing a floret, apices 2-fid or 3-fid; cypselae
        (at least outer) strigose; coastal Texas</description>
      <determination>103. Micropsis , p. 463</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bisexual or staminate paleae flat to concave, not enclosing florets, apices entire;
        cypselae glabrous; central and western North America.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Receptacles glabrous; pistillate paleae falling (all or the inner together);
        staminate (or bisexual) paleae: bodies ± spatulate (apices scarcely enlarged); central North
        America</description>
      <determination>102. Diaperia , p. 460</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Receptacles bristly; pistillate paleae persistent; staminate paleae: bodies obovate
        (apices enlarged); California and Oregon</description>
      <determination>105. Hesperevax , p. 467</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate paleae saccate most of lengths (each enclosing a floret, outermost
        rarely open); pappi 0 or of 1–10(–13) bristles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate paleae 5(–7), ± spreading proximally, enlarged in fruit (apices incurved
        to uncinate); pistillate paleae with 3, ± parallel (prominent) nerves; cypselae: corolla
        scars apical</description>
      <determination>104. Ancistrocarphus , p. 465</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate paleae 0 or 1–4, erect, not enlarged in fruit (apices erect); pistillate
        paleae with 5+, reticulate (and prominent) or ± parallel (and obscure) nerves; cypselae:
        corolla scars subapical to ± median.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves mostly opposite; phyllaries 0; pistillate paleae (nerves reticulate,
        prominent): wings inflexed (and ± lateral); staminate paleae 0; pappi 0</description>
      <determination>101. Psilocarphus , p. 456</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Cauline leaves mostly alternate; phyllaries 0 or 1–6; pistillate paleae (nerves
        parallel, obscure): wings ± erect (or subapical); staminate paleae 1–4 and/or staminate
        pappi of (0–)1–10(–13) bristles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate paleae (obcompressed to terete, not galeate): wings ± erect (and
        apical); receptacles cylindric to clavate (heights 2.8–8 times diams.); phyl- laries 0 or
        1–4 (similar to paleae); cypselae: corolla scars subapical</description>
      <determination>99. Stylocline , p. 450</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate paleae (compressed, galeate): wings ± erect (and lateral) or inflexed
        (and subapical); receptacles depressed-spheric to obovoid (heights 0.5–1.8 times diams.);
        phyllaries 4–6 (unlike paleae); cypselae: corolla scars ± lateral</description>
      <determination>100. Micropus , p. 454</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
