<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini ex Lecoq &amp; Juillet" date="1831">gnaphalieae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Gaertner" date="1791">antennaria</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Greene" date="1898">rosea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Pittonia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 281. 1898</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe gnaphalieae;genus antennaria;species rosea</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Gynoecious (staminate plants uncommon). Plants 4–30 cm. Stolons 1–7 cm. Basal leaves 1-nerved, 8–40 × 2–10 mm, spatulate, oblanceolate, or cuneate, tips mucronate, faces usually gray-pubescent, adaxial sometimes green-glabrous. Cauline leaves linear, 6–36 mm, usually not flagged (apices acute to subulate or with lanceolate flags). Heads 3–20 in corymbiform arrays. Involucres: staminate unknown; pistillate 4–10 mm. Phyllaries distally brown, cream, gray, green, pink, red, white, or yellow (apices acute or erose-obtuse). Corollas: staminate unknown; pistillate 2.5–6 mm. Cypselae 0.7–1.8 mm, glabrous or papillate; pappi: staminate unknown; pistillate 3.5–6.5 mm. 2n = 42, 56, (70).</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Rosy pussytoes</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">antennaire rosée</other_name>
  <discussion>Subspecies 4 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Antennaria rosea is the most widespread Antennaria of North America, occurring in dry to moist habitats from near sea level to the alpine zone. The A. rosea polyploid agamic complex is one of the more morphologically diverse complexes of North American Antennaria. It occurs from the western cordillera of North America from southern California, Arizona, and New Mexico north to subarctic Alaska and east to Greenland and, disjunctly, in the Canadian maritime provinces, eastern Quebec, and immediately north of and adjacent to Lake Superior (R. J. Bayer et al. 1991). Antennaria chilensis (including A. chilensis var. magellanica) is a Patagonian endemic that morphologically fits within the circumscription of A. rosea and may well be an amphitropical disjunct member of the complex.</discussion>
  <discussion>Antennaria rosea is taxonomically confusing; it includes agamospermous microspecies that have been recognized as distinct taxonomic species. Morphometric and isozyme analyses have demonstrated that the primary source of morphologic variability in the complex derives from six sexually reproducing progenitors, A. aromatica, A. corymbosa, A. pulchella, A. microphylla, A. racemosa, and A. umbrinella (R. J. Bayer 1989b, 1990b, 1990c). Additionally, three other sexually reproducing species, A. marginata, A. suffrutescens, and A. rosulata, may have contributed to the genetic complexity of the A. rosea complex (Bayer 1990b). Here, four reasonably distinct subspecies are recognized within the complex.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves 20–40 mm; phyllaries distally usually green, pink, red or white, seldom brown</description>
      <determination>27d. Antennaria rosea subsp. rosea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves 8–20 mm; phyllaries distally brown, cream, gray, green, pink, red, white, or yellow.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate: involucres 4–6.5 mm, corollas 2.5–4, pappi 3.5–5; cauline leaves 6–20 mm (tips subulate); phyllaries usually distally brown, sometimes cream, gray, or yellow</description>
      <determination>27b. Antennaria rosea subsp. confinis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate: involucres 6.5–10 mm, corollas 3.5–6 mm, pappi 5–6.5 mm; cauline leaves 6–19 or 9–26 mm (tips sometimes with flat, lanceolate scarious appendages); phyllaries distally brown, green, pink, red, or white.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 19–30 cm; cauline leaves 9–26 mm (proximalmost usually 19+ mm); heads usu- ally 6–12</description>
      <determination>27a. Antennaria rosea subsp. arida</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants 4–17 cm; cauline leaves 6–19 mm (proximalmost usually less than 19 mm); heads usually 3–5</description>
      <determination>27c. Antennaria rosea subsp. pulvinata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
