<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>24.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Cirsium</genus_name>
    <species_name>ochrocentrum</species_name>
    <species_authority>A. Gray</species_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Mem. Amer. Acad. Arts, n. s.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 110. 1849</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Cynareae;genus Cirsium;species ochrocentrum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <description>Perennials, 30–90 cm; crown sprouts or runner roots producing adventitious buds. Stems 1–20+, erect or ascending, densely gray-tomentose with non-septate trichomes; branches 0 or few, usually in distal 1/2, ascending. Leaves: blades oblong to narrowly elliptic, 10–30 × 2–8 cm, strongly undulate, margins coarsely dentate or shallowly to deeply pinnatifid with 8–15 pairs of lobes 0.5–2 cm, often revolute, lobes ± triangular, closely spaced, spreading, spinose-dentate and cleft into 2–5 spine-tipped divisions, main spines 5–20 mm, yellowish, abaxial faces densely white-tomentose, adaxial thinly gray-tomentose; basal usually present at flowering, winged-petiolate; principal cauline sessile, progressively reduced distally, bases ± auriculate to long-decurrent as spiny wings; distal cauline usually much reduced, less lobed. Heads 1–few, in leafy, ± corymbiform arrays. Peduncles 0–4 cm. Involucres ovoid to hemispheric or broadly campanulate, 2.5–4.5 × 2.5–4.5 cm in first-formed heads, often smaller in later ones, loosely arachnoid on phyllary margins or glabrate. Phyllaries in 5–10 series, imbricate, ovate (outer) to linear-lanceolate (inner), margins entire, abaxial faces with narrow glutinous ridge; outer and middle appressed, spines spreading, 3–12 mm; apices of inner often flexuous, expanded and flat, scabrid-margined, sometimes erose, spineless. Corollas white or pale lavender to purple, pink, or red, 25–45 mm, tubes 8–25 mm, throats 6–17 mm, lobes 6–15 mm; style tips 2–8 mm. Cypselae light brown, sometimes with lighter or darker streaks, 6–9 mm, apical collars colored like the body, narrow; pappi (white or tawny), 20–40 mm, usually noticeably shorter than corolla. 2n = 30, 31, 32, 34.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>w United States</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Mexico.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems densely leafy, nodes crowded; leaves often long- decurrent; corollas white or pale lavender to purple</statement>
      <determination>24a. Cirsium ochrocentrumvar. ochrocentrum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Stems leafy, nodes usually well separated; distal cauline leaves clasping, or if decurrent spiny wing usually less than 1 cm; corollas red, pink, or reddish purple (rarely white)</statement>
      <determination>24b. Cirsium ochrocentrum var. martinii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>

