<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="(Cassini ex Dumortier) Anderberg" date="1989">plucheeae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cassini" date="1817">pluchea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="G. L. Nesom" date="1989">yucatanensis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>67: 160. 1989</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe plucheeae;genus pluchea;species yucatanensis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Perennials, 20–60 cm; probably fibrous-rooted. Stems ± stipitate- or sessile-glandular, otherwise glabrous. Leaves sessile; blades (leathery, slightly succulent, shiny) oblong-obovate to oblong-oblanceolate or broadly lance-olate, 3–5 × (0.6–)1.5–2 cm (bases subclasping and sub-auriculate), margins serrulate, faces ± stipitate- or sessile-glandular, otherwise glabrous or distalmost minutely puberulent. Heads in corymbiform arrays. Involucres turbinate to campanulate, 5–6 × 4–5 mm. Phyllaries pink to lavender or cream, proximally stipitate- or sessile-glandular, distally densely stipitate-glandular (outermost ovate-lanceolate, lengths usually 1 times inner, rarely only 0.5 times inner). Corollas pink to lavender or cream or pinkish to rosy. Pappi persistent, bristles distinct.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late May–Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Low woods;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–10 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Ala., Miss.; Mexico; Central America (Belize).</description>
  <number>8.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Yucatan camphorweed</other_name>
  <discussion>Pluchea yucatanensis apparently is native along the Gulf and Caribbean coasts of Mexico and Central America, most commonly on the Yucatan Peninsula and in Belize. In the United States, it is known from collections made from 1896 to 1969 in coastal Alabama and Mississippi; it appears to be naturalized in the flora.</discussion>
  <discussion>Pluchea yucatanensis is similar in habit and general appearance to P. foetida and P. baccharis and has been identified as both; the rosy tinted phyllaries and florets are more similar to those of P. baccharis. The glabrous, slightly thickened, shiny leaves and glabrous phyllaries are recognition traits for the species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
