<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Linda E. Watson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Anthemideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">CLADANTHUS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bull. Sci. Soc. Philom. Paris</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1816: 199. 1816</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Anthemideae;genus CLADANTHUS;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Derivation not given; possibly Greek klados , branch, and anthos , flower, alluding to branching of stems at bases of sessile heads in original species]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="(Cassini) Cassini" date="unknown">Ormenis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Ormenis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals [perennials, subshrubs], 10–60+ cm (usually aromatic). Stems usually 1, usually erect [prostrate], branched [immediately proximal to sessile, terminal heads], puberulent or villous to arachnose (hairs basifixed), glabrescent. Leaves mostly cauline; alternate; petiolate (proximal) or sessile (distal); blades obovate or spatulate to oblong or linear, 1–2(–3)-pinnately lobed (ultimate lobes ± linear to filiform), ultimate margins entire or dentate, faces villous to arachnose, glabrescent. Heads radiate, borne singly or in lax, corymbiform arrays. Involucres hemispheric or broader, 5–8[–12+] mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 16–24+ in 2–3+ series, lance-linear or lanceolate to oblong or obovate, subequal, margins and apices (hyaline) scarious (apices ± dilated, rounded, abaxial faces ± villous or arachnose, glabrescent). Receptacles hemispheric to narrowly columnar or conic, paleate; paleae ± folded (carinate, each with central, red-brown resin duct). Ray florets 12–18+, neuter or styliferous and sterile; corollas orange, yellow, or white with yellow bases, laminae ± oblong (spreading to reflexed, ± marcescent). Disc florets 40–150[–200+], bisexual, fertile; corollas orange or yellow, tubes ± cylindric (bases saccate, each obliquely spurred, adaxially clasping distal 0.5+ of cypsela), throats campanulate to funnelform, lobes 5, deltate (apices minutely crested or dilated). Cypselae ± obovoid (apices oblique), weakly flattened (stylopodia sublateral), ribs or nerves (weak): 2 lateral, 1 adaxial, faces finely striate, glabrous [hairy] (pericarps with myxogenic cells in longitudinal rows, without resin sacs); pappi 0. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">s Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced also in South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">elsewhere in Old World.</description>
  <number>114.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 5 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Oberprieler, C. and R. Vogt. 2002. Cladanthus. In: Med Checklist notulae, 21. Willdenowia 32: 195. 208.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
