<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Linda E. Watson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">anthemideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Miller" date="1754">CHAMAEMELUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gard. Dict. Abr. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4, vol. 1. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe anthemideae;genus CHAMAEMELUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chamae- , on the ground, lowly, creeping, and melon , orchard, alluding to common habitat]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals or perennials, 5–20(–35+) cm, (aromatic). Stems usually 1, erect, ascending, or prostrate, usually branched, glabrous or glabrate, puberulent, or villous to strigoso-sericeous (hairs basifixed). Leaves mostly cauline (at flowering); alternate; petiolate or sessile; blades oblong, ovate, elliptic, or spatulate, 1–3-pinnately lobed (ultimate lobes narrowly spatulate to linear or filiform, apices apiculate), ultimate margins entire, faces glabrous or glabrate, puberulent, or villous to strigoso-sericeous. Heads radiate or discoid, borne singly or in lax corymbiform arrays. Involucres hemispheric or broader, 6–10 mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 22–45+ in 3–4+ series (sometimes reflexed in fruit), mostly ovate to oblong, unequal, margins and apices (colorless, brownish, or greenish) scarious. Receptacles hemispheric to conic, paleate; paleae weakly navicular to ± flat (medially chartaceous, margins scarious, apices rounded). Ray florets 0 or 12–21+, pistillate and fertile or styliferous and sterile; corollas white, laminae oblong (often marcescent, reflexed in fruit). Disc florets 100–200+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow, tubes ± cylindric (somewhat dilated, bases saccate, weakly clasping apices of cypselae), throats funnelform, lobes 5, deltate. Cypselae ± obovoid, weakly obcompressed, ribs or nerves (weak): 2 lateral, 1 adaxial, faces finely striate, glabrous (pericarps with myxogenic cells in longitudinal rows, without resin sacs); pappi 0. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">s</description>
  <description type="distribution">w Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">n Africa.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 2 (2 in the flora): introduced; s, w Europe, n Africa.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; s, w Europe, n Africa.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>115.</number>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals; stems erect or ascending, glabrous or puberulent; margins and apices of phyllaries brownish</description>
      <determination>1. Chamaemelum fuscatum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perennials; stems mostly prostrate (much branched, often forming mats), ± strigoso-sericeous to villous; margins and apices of phyllaries greenish or lacking pigment</description>
      <determination>2. Chamaemelum nobile</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
