<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>116.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>SANTOLINA</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 842. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 365. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Anthemideae;genus SANTOLINA;</taxon_hierarchy>
  <etymology>[Latin sanctus , holy, and linum , flax; ancient name for a species of the genus]</etymology>
  <author>Linda E. Watson</author>
  <description>Subshrubs, [5–]10–60 cm (sometimes ± rhizomatous; aromatic). Stems usually 1, ± erect [decumbent to ascending], branched mostly from bases [± throughout], often tomentose to lanate, sometimes glabrate or glabrous [sericeous] (hairs mostly medifixed) and gland-dotted. Leaves cauline [mostly basal]; alternate; petiolate or sessile; blades narrowly oblong or spatulate to linear, usually 1-pinnately lobed (lobes usually crowded and overall effect ± vermiform), ultimate margins entire or ± crenate, faces usually arachnose or tomentose to lanate, sometimes glabrate or glabrous [sericeous]. Heads discoid, borne singly (pedunculate). Involucres campanulate to hemispheric or broader, [3–]6–10[–12+] mm diam. Phyllaries persistent (soon indurate), 18–45+ in 3(–5+) series, distinct, lanceolate to elliptic (usually carinate), unequal, margins and apices (usually light to dark brown, sometimes purple) scarious (abaxial faces glabrous or ± arachnose, glabrescent). Receptacles convex to hemispheric, paleate; paleae ± lanceolate, ± navicular (each with central resin duct). Ray florets 0. Disc florets mostly 60–250+, bisexual, fertile; corollas pale to bright or deep yellow [whitish], tubes often compressed (± winged and/or saccate, ± clasping apices of cypselae), throats ± funnelform, lobes 5, lance-ovate. Cypselae obconic to obovoid, sometimes slightly obcompressed, 3–5-angled, faces glabrous (pericarps sometimes with myxogenic cells, without resin sacs); pappi 0. x = 9.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 8–12+ (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <introduced>introduced;</introduced>
  <global_distribution>s Europe</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Africa.</global_distribution>
</treatment>

