<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Leila M. Shultz</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">Asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="unknown">Anthemideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">ARTEMISIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 845. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 367. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Asteraceae;tribe Anthemideae;genus ARTEMISIA;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek Artemis, goddess of the hunt and namesake of Artemisia, Queen of
    Anatolia]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>119.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Felon-herb</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">mugwort</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sagebrush</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">sailor’s-tobacco</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">wormwood</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">armoise</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">herbe Saint-Jean</other_name>
  <discussion>species ca. 350–500 (50 in the flora)</discussion>
  <discussion>As circumscribed here, there are five subgenera in Artemisia; four are represented in
    the flora area.</discussion>
  <discussion>Etymologies of the common names used for Artemisia species provide glimpses of their
    uses and demonstrate the rich diversity within the genus. The common name ‘mugwort’ is from the
    Old English mucgwyrt, mucg meaning ‘midge,’ and refers to the use of Old World herbaceous
    species in repelling flies and midges. Artemisia was called Motherwort in nineteenth century
    Maine (as an indication of the high esteem for this otherwise rather pedestrian plant), and in
    the herbal by R. Banckes (1525): “This herb helpeth a woman to conceyve a chylde, and clenseth
    the mother, and maketh a woman to have her flowers.” Early settlers in North America brought
    European plants of A. dracunculus, A. vulgaris, A. absinthium, and A. abrotanum into their herb
    gardens for seasoning and medicinal uses; they would also have learned about aboriginal uses of
    Artemisia species native to North America, uses that included fertility rites (sagebrush in
    western North America) and antihelminthics (wormwoods of grasslands and mountain habitats).
    Immigrants used A. annua (sweet Annie) in potpourris and later recognized its utility as an
    anti-malarial drug, a use that was well known in oriental medicine. ‘Bulwand’ is the local name
    used for herbaceous wormwoods in Scotland, and ‘green-ginger’ and ‘Sailor’s tobacco’ are local
    names in England (T. Coffey 1993). Use of the names ‘sagewort’ and ‘sagebrush’ in North America
    arise from the familiar aroma of culinary sage, Salvia officinalis (Lamiaceae). Because true
    sages (Salvia) and sagewort/sagebrushes (Artemisia) are in separate families, the chemical
    similarities are an example of convergent evolution. The intense aroma and bitter taste of the
    plants from terpenoids and sesquiterpene lactones discourages herbivory and undoubtedly has
    contributed to the remarkable evolutionary success (measured by abundance as well as diversity)
    of species in this genus.</discussion>
  <discussion>Members of Artemisia are wind-pollinated and their heads and florets are exceptionally
    small (even for composites) and, consequently, difficult to examine and assess. Nevertheless,
    the sexual constitution of floral heads is important in recognition of subgenera. Plant habits
    and ornamentations of receptacles have also figured in arriving at subgeneric circumscriptions;
    additional characteristics are enumerated in the descriptions.</discussion>
  <discussion>Artemisia has a well-deserved reputation for being taxonomically difficult. The number
    of subgenera varies from four to five in modern treatments, and the number of taxa recognized at
    the species or subspecific levels varies between 250 and 500 (K. Bremer and C. J. Humphries
    1993; H. M. Hall and F. E. Clements 1923; Y. R. Ling 1982, 1995; P. P. Poljakov 1961; M. Torrell
    et al. 1999). In this treatment, I recognize four native subgenera; subg. Seriphidium is endemic
    to Asia. In the flora area, the greatest diversity occurs in subg. Artemisia. Subgenus
    Absinthium can be segregated on the basis of hairs on the receptacle; it may be not
    phylogenetically distinct (L. E. Watson et al. 2002; J. Valles and E. D. McArthur 2001).
    Subgenus Dracunculus is clearly distinguished by molecular differences, and subg. Tridentatae is
    well defined with the exception of A. pygmaea.</discussion>
  <discussion>This treatment is based on extensive fieldwork, review of recent research, and
    examination of thousands of specimens; taxonomic circumscriptions remain controversial.
    Molecular analyses have helped define subgenera but have not clarified relationships between
    closely related species. The morphologic characters useful in distinguishing species tend to be
    variable and are often hard to assess (i.e., the sexuality of microscopic florets). Users of the
    keys will meet with frustrations; descriptions of subgenera and illustrations will help in
    defining the major groupings of species.</discussion>
  <discussion>The subgenera are arranged in approximate phylogenetic order; species are arranged
    alphabetically within the subgenera. Molecular studies define subg. Dracunculus as a major clade
    that is ancestral to the majority of Artemisia. The subgenera Absinthium, Tridentatae, and
    Artemisia can be classified as clades; they are weakly supported by molecular
    evidence.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hall, H. M. and F. E. Clements. 1923. The phylogenetic method in taxonomy: The North America species of Artemisia, Chrysothamnus, and Atriplex. Publ. Carnegie Inst. Wash. 326.</reference>
    <reference>Ling, Y. R. 1995. The New World Artemisia L. In: D. J. N. Hind et al., eds. 1995.
      Advances in Compositae Systematics. Kew. Pp. 225–281.</reference>
    <reference>Torrell, M., N. Garcia-Jacas, A. Susanna, and J. Valles. 1999. Phylogeny in Artemisia
      (Asteraceae, Anthemideae) inferred from nuclear ribosomal DNA (ITS) sequences. Taxon 48:
      721–736.</reference>
    <reference>Valles, J. and E. D. McArthur. 2001. Artemisia systematics and phylogeny:
      Cytogenetic and molecular insights. In: E. D. McArthur and D. J. Fairbanks, comps. 2001.
      Shrubland Ecosystem Genetics and Biodiversity: Proceedings: Provo, UT, June 13–15, 2000.
      Ogden. Pp. 67–74.</reference>
    <reference>Ling, Y. R. 1982. On the system of the genus Artemisia L. and the relationship with its allies. Bull. Bot. Lab. N. E. Forest. Inst., Harbin 2: 1–60.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Shrubs; leaves in lateral fascicles (on vegetative shoots); heads discoid (except
        in A. bigelovii with, rarely, 1–2 raylike florets): florets bisexual (corollas 5-lobed);
        receptacles glabrous</description>
      <determination>119b. Artemisia subg. Tridentatae, p. 509</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Annuals, biennials, perennials, or subshrubs (shrubs in A. filifolia, A.
        californica , and A. nesiotica ); leaves not in fascicles; heads usually disciform, rarely
        discoid; receptacles glabrous or villous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Disc florets functionally staminate (not setting fruits), corollas
        subglobose</description>
      <determination>119a. Artemisia subg. Dracunculus, p. 505</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Disc florets usually bisexual and fertile (sometimes functionally staminate in A.
        packardiae in subg. Artemisia ), corollas funnelform.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Receptacles villous</description>
      <determination>119c. Artemisia subg. Absinthium, p. 518</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Receptacles glabrous (paleate in A. palmeri )</description>
      <determination>119d. Artemisia subg. Artemisia, p. 520</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
