<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Linda E. Watson</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">anthemideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">ANTHEMIS</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 893. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Gen. Pl. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5, 381. 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe anthemideae;genus ANTHEMIS</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek anthemon , flower]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals (biennials) [perennials, subshrubs], mostly 5–90 cm (often aromatic). Stems 1–5+, erect to decumbent, usually branched, strigillose or strigoso-sericeous to villous (hairs medifixed), glabrescent [glabrous or sericeous to lanate]. Leaves mostly cauline; alternate; petiolate or sessile; blades ± obovate to spatulate, 1–3-pinnately lobed, ultimate margins dentate to lobed, faces glabrous or strigillose to villous [glabrous or sericeous to lanate]. Heads radiate [discoid], borne singly or in lax, corymbiform arrays (peduncles sometimes clavate and/or curved in fruit). Involucres obconic to hemispheric or broader, 5–13[–20] mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, mostly 21–35+ in 3–5 series, distinct, deltate to lanceolate, oblong, or elliptic, unequal, margins and apices (hyaline and colorless or brownish [black]) scarious. Receptacles hemispheric to narrowly conic, paleate (wholly or only distally); paleae ± flat, scarious to indurate (subulate or elliptic to obovate with mucronate to acuminate-spinose tips). Ray florets [0 or 2–]5–20[–30+], pistillate and fertile or styliferous and sterile; corollas usually white, rarely yellow or pink, laminae mostly oblong (tubes sometimes hairy). Disc florets (60–)100–300+, bisexual, fertile; corollas usually yellow, rarely pink, tubes ± cylindric (usually proximally dilated, ± spongy in fruit, sometimes hairy, not saccate), throats funnelform, lobes 5, ± triangular (abaxially minutely crested). Cypselae obovoid to obconic or turbinate (circular or 4-angled in cross section), ribs usually 9–10 (0) and smooth or tuberculate, faces glabrous (pericarps with myxogenic cells); pappi 0 or coroniform. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Europe</description>
  <description type="distribution">sw Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">n</description>
  <description type="distribution">e Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced in s Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands (New Zealand)</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 175 (2 in the flora): introduced; Europe, sw Asia, n, e Africa; introduced in s Africa, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 175 (2 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced; Europe, sw Asia, n, e Africa; introduced in s Africa, Pacific Islands (New Zealand), Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>122.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Chamomile</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 175 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Anthemis secundiramea Bivona-Bernardi, a European species, was collected once in Virginia; it differs from A. arvensis in having peduncles to 8 cm and ribs on cypselae ± tuberculate.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Oberprieler, C. 2001. Phylogenetic relationships in Anthemis L. (Compositae, Anthemideae) based on nrDNA ITS sequence variation. Taxon 50: 745–762.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched mostly proximally; receptacles paleate throughout, paleae lanceolate to oblanceolate, weakly navicular (± carinate, tips acuminate-spinose); cypselae: ribs smooth or weakly tuberculate</description>
      <determination>1. Anthemis arvensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stems branched mostly distally or ± throughout; receptacles paleate distally, paleae subulate to acerose; cypselae: ribs ± tuberculate</description>
      <determination>2. Anthemis cotula</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
