<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">anthemideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Webb ex Schultz-Bipontinus in P. B. Webb and S. Berthelot" date="1844">ARGYRANTHEMUM</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in P. B. Webb and S. Berthelot, Hist. Nat. Îles Canaries</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3(2,75): 245, 258. 1844</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe anthemideae;genus ARGYRANTHEMUM</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek argyros , silver, and anthemon , flower; allusion unclear]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Subshrubs or shrubs, 10–80+[–150] cm. Stems usually 1, procumbent to erect, usually branched, glabrous [hairy]. Leaves mostly cauline; alternate; petiolate or sessile; blades ± obovate [oblong to lanceolate or linear] (bases sometimes ± clasping), [0](1–)2–3-pinnately lobed (lobes cuneate to linear), ultimate margins dentate [entire], faces glabrous [hairy]. Heads radiate [discoid], borne singly or in open, corymbiform arrays. Involucres hemispheric or broader, [6–]10–18[–22+] mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 28–45+ in 3–4 series, distinct, oblanceolate or ovate to lance-deltate or lanceolate (not keeled abaxially), unequal, margins and apices (stramineous to brown) scarious (tips of inner often ± dilated). Receptacles convex to conic, epaleate. Ray florets 12–35+, pistillate, fertile; corollas usually white, sometimes yellow or pink, laminae ± ovate to linear. Disc florets [50–]80–150+, bisexual, fertile; corollas yellow [red, purple], tubes ± cylindric (not basally dilated, ± gland-dotted), throats campanulate, lobes 5, deltate (without resin sacs). Cypselae dimorphic: outer (ray) 3-angled, each angle usually ± winged (wings not spine-tipped); inner (disc) compressed-prismatic (± quadrate, sometimes 2 angles winged, wings not spine-tipped); all ± ribbed or nerved, faces usually glabrous, sometimes gland-dotted between ribs (pericarps without myxogenic cells or resin sacs; embryo sac development bisporic); pappi 0 (cypselar wall tissue sometimes produced as teeth, crowns, or oblique tubes similar in texture to cypselar wings). x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Atlantic Ocean Islands (Macaronesia).</description>
  <number>131.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Marguerite</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 24 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Humphries, C. J. 1976. A revision of the Macaronesian genus Argyranthemum Webb ex Schultz Bip. (Compositae–Anthemideae). Bull. Brit. Mus. (Nat. Hist.), Bot. 5: 147–240.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
