<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>John L. Strother</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Martinov" date="unknown">asteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="tribe" authority="Cassini" date="1819">anthemideae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Cassini in F. Cuvier" date="1826">ISMELIA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in F. Cuvier, Dict. Sci. Nat. ed.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2, 41: 40. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family asteraceae;tribe anthemideae;genus ISMELIA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Etymology unknown]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Annuals, 10–30(–50+) cm. Stems 1, erect, usually branched distally, glabrous or sparsely hairy (hairs basifixed). Leaves mostly cauline; alternate; petiolate or sessile; blades obovate to oblong (bases sometimes clasping), usually 2-pinnately lobed, ultimate margins usually dentate, rarely entire, faces glabrous. Heads radiate, borne singly or in 2s or 3s. Involucres hemispheric or broader, 12–25+ mm diam. Phyllaries persistent, 20–30+ in 2–3 series, distinct, ovate or obovate to lance-deltate or lanceolate (± carinate), unequal, margins and apices scarious (tips of inner often ± dilated). Receptacles convex to conic, epaleate. Ray florets 13–21+, pistillate, fertile; corollas proximally white or red to purple, distally yellow or white, laminae ± linear. Disc florets 80–150+, bisexual, fertile; corollas proximally ochroleucous, distally red to purple, tubes cylindric (stipitate-glandular or gland-dotted), throats funnelform, lobes 5, deltate. Cypselae dimorphic: outer 3-angled (each angle ± winged, wings not spine-tipped); inner compressed, adaxial angles ± winged (wings not spine-tipped); ribs 0, faces glabrous (pericarps without myxogenic cells or resin sacs); pappi 0. x = 9.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; n Africa; widely adventive elsewhere.</description>
  <number>132.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
