<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>
      <title>FNA V25</title>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <number>62</number>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <rank>species</rank>
    <name_authority_date>Muhlenbergia rigens (Benth.) Hitchc. </name_authority_date>
  </taxon_identification>
  <common_names>DEERGRASS</common_names>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; cespitose, not rhizomatous. Culms (35)50-150 cm tall, to 5 mm thick near the base, stiffly erect, not rooting at the lower nodes; internodes glabrous. Sheaths longer than the internodes, smooth or scabridulous, rounded dorsally, bases somewhat flat and chartaceous; ligules 0.5-2(3) mm, firm, truncate, usually ciliolate; blades 10-50 cm long, 1.5-6 mm wide, flat or involute, stiff, glabrous abaxially, scabrous adaxially. Panicles 15-60 cm long, 0.5-1.2 cm wide, spikelike, dense, grayish-green, often interrupted below; primary branches 0.2-4 cm, appressed; pedicels 0.2-3 mm, hispidulous, strongly divergent. Spikelets 2.4-4 mm. Glumes subequal, 1.8-3.2 mm, almost as long as the florets, scabrous to scabridulous, 1-veined, usually acute or obtuse, occasionally acuminate or notched, occasionally mucronate, mucros to 0.6 mm; lemmas 2.4-4 mm, lanceolate, pubescent on the calluses, lower 1/6 of the margins, and midveins, hairs to 0.4 mm, apices scabrous, acute or obtuse, unawned, rarely mucronate, mucros to 1 mm; paleas 2.3-3.8 mm, lanceolate, acute; anthers 1.3-1.8 mm, yellow to purple. Caryopses 1.8-2.2 mm, fusiform, brownish. 2n = 40.</description>
  <discussion>Muhlenbergia rigens grows in sandy washes, gravelly canyon bottoms, rocky drainages, and moist, sandy slopes, often along small streams, at elevations of 90-2500 m. Its geographic range extends to central Mexico. It is available commercially as an ornamental. Muhlenbergia rigens is similar to M. dubia, but dif¬fers in having tighter, spikelike panicles, shorter ligules, yellow or purplish anthers, and shorter lemmas.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
