<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment>
  <meta>
    <source>
      <title>FNA V25</title>
      <author>J.K. Wipff</author>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <number>25.02</number>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <rank>genus</rank>
    <name_authority_date>ANTHENANTIA P. Beauv.</name_authority_date>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; rhizomatous. Culms 60-120 cm, stiffly erect, clustered. Sheaths open; ligules 0.1-0.3 mm, membranous, ciliate; blades flat, stiff, upper blades much reduced. Inflorescences terminal, simple panicles with elongate rachises; branches ascending to erect, not spikelike, lower branches usually with 8 or more spikelets; disarticulation beneath the glumes. Spikelets 3-4 mm, laterally compressed neither subtended by bristles nor sunken into the rachis, elliptic, obovoid, hirsute, unawned, with 2 florets. Lower glumes absent; upper glumes as long as the spikelets, obovate, densely hirsute, 5-veined; lower florets sterile or staminate; lower lemmas densely hirsute, similar to the upper glumes; lower paleas present or absent; upper lemmas and upper paleas cartilaginous, glabrous, dark brown, separating slightly at maturity, exposing the caryopses, lemmas 3-veined, margins flat, hyaline, 0.5-1 mm wide, paleas 2-veined. x = 10. </description>
  <discussion>Anthenantia is a genus of two species, both of which are endemic to the southeastern United States. It is very similar to Leptocoryphium Nees, a monotypic genus that extends from Mexico to Argentina, but differs in having laterally, rather than dorsally, compressed spikelets.
Anthenantia is the etymologically correct version of the three alternative spellings used by Palisot de Beauvois (Clayton and Renvoize 1986).
</discussion>
  <references>Clayton, W.D. and S.A. Renvoize. 1986. Genera Graminum: Grasses of the World. Kew Bull., Addit. Ser. 13. Her Majesty's Stationery Office, London, England. 389 pp.</references>
  <key>
    <key_body>
1. Junction of the sheath and blade not evident abaxially, the sheath and blades in line with each other; blades 2-5 mm wide, the margins scabrous; leaves 30-60 cm long .....1. A. rufa
1. Junction of the sheath and blade evident, the blades not in line with the sheaths; blades 5-10 mm wide, the margins papillose-hispid; leaves mostly less than 30 mm long  .....2. A. villosa

    </key_body>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
