<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Peter W. Ball,A. A. Reznicek,David F. Murray</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;</taxon_hierarchy>
    
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, cespitose or not, rhizomatous or not, stoloniferous or not. Roots fibrous, principally adventitious. Stems (culms) usually trigonous, occasionally terete, rarely compressed, usually solid, rarely hollow or septate. Leaves basal and/or cauline, alternate, usually 3-ranked, rarely 2-ranked or multi-ranked, bases forming cylindric sheaths enclosing stem, margins usually fused; junction of sheaths and blades often with adaxial flaps of tissue or fringes of hair (ligules); blades frequently absent from some basal leaves, rarely from cauline leaves, when present divergent or ascending, flat, folded, plicate, rolled, or terete, linear, venation parallel. Primary inflorescences (spikelets) a shortened axis; glumaceous bracts (scales) 1–many, spirally arranged, sometimes 2-ranked, usually appressed or ascending; scales usually all fertile, each subtending a single flower, sometimes proximal and/or distal scales empty; lateral spikes often with basal, usually empty, usually 2-keeled scale (prophyll); occasionally prophyll subtending and enclosing rachilla, bearing 1 pistillate, sometimes (0–)3 staminate flowers and empty scales (Carex, Cymophyllus, and Kobresia). Secondary inflorescences panicles, often modified to corymb, pseudoumbel, cyme (anthela), raceme, spike, or capitulum (head), rarely single spike, usually subtended by foliaceous or, less frequently, glumaceous bracts; secondary inflorescences sometimes simulating spikelets (Carex, Cymophyllus, and Kobresia). Flowers hypogynous, bisexual in most genera, unisexual in Scleria, Carex, Cymophyllus, and Kobresia; perianth absent or with (1–)3–6(–30) bristles and/or scales, usually falling off with fruit; stamens usually (1–)3, rarely more, usually distinct; anthers basifixed; pistils 1, 2–3(–4)-carpellate, fused, locule 1; style undivided or branches 2–3(–4); stigma sometimes papillate. Fruits achenes, usually trigonous or biconvex; pericarps thin (except in Scleria). Seeds 1; testa thin, free from pericarp; embryo basal; endosperm abundant. x = 5–ca. 100.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide.</description>
  <number>210.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Sedge Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera ca. 100, species ca. 5000 (27 genera, 843 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>No consensus exists regarding the number of genera and the overall relationships of genera within Cyperaceae. The most recent account of the family (P. Goetghebeur 1998) recognized 104 genera distributed among 4 subfamilies and 14 tribes. That arrangement differs somewhat from that of J. Bruhl (1995). With one minor exception the arrangement of the family here follows that of Goetghebeur.</discussion>
  <discussion>The family is characterized by the occurrence of a number of unusual cytological features including: (1) chromosomes with diffuse centromeres, (2) post-reductional meiosis, and (3) pollen grains formed from tetrads in which 3 of the 4 microspores fail to develop. The first two features are found in at least some Juncaceae and are unique to the two families. Juncaceae also have pollen in tetrads, but in that family all four microspores produce pollen grains. Some species in some genera of Cyperaceae (particularly Eleocharis) possess chromosomes with localized centromeres (S. S. Bir et al. 1993). The wide range of chromosome numbers found in Cyperaceae is largely because of agmatoploidy; polyploidy has been hypothesized for some genera, especially Eleocharis, although polyploidy has not been demonstrated unequivocally.</discussion>
  <discussion>Because of morphologic similarities in vegetative and inflorescence characters, the family has commonly been associated with Poaceae. Cytological features discussed above clearly indicate that to be a superficial similarity. Data from rbcL studies also support the view that Cyperaceae and Poaceae are not closely related (M. R. Duvall et al. 1993b; G. M. Plunkett et al. 1995); they do support the concept of close relationship between Cyperaceae and Juncaceae.</discussion>
  <discussion>For most families of flowering plants the phenological data given are flowering times. Because most Cyperaceae cannot be reliably identified when in flower, in this volume fruiting time is given for all species by season, sometimes qualified by early, mid, or late, or by months. The fruiting time has been interpreted broadly to include the period when the fruit is more or less fully formed but not yet ripe. The fruiting period provided covers the entire range of the taxon. Quite a difference between fruiting periods in different parts of the range of the species may well occur, especially for widespread species and species with extensive elevation range.</discussion>
  <discussion>For a recent, comprehensive review of the economic importance of Cyperaceae, see D. A. Simpson and C. A. Inglis (2001).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bruhl, J. 1995. Sedge genera of the world: Relationships and a new classification of the Cyperaceae. Austral. Syst. Bot. 8: 125–305.</reference>
    <reference>Goetghebeur, P. 1998. Cyperaceae. In: K. Kubitzki et al., eds. 1990+. The Families and Genera of Vascular Plants. 4+ vols. Berlin etc. Vol. 4, pp. 141–190.</reference>
    <reference>Mackenzie, K. K. 1931–1935. Cyperaceae [in part]. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora…. 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 18, parts 1–7, pp. 1–478.</reference>
    <reference>Simpson, D. A. and C. A. Inglis. 2001. Cyperaceae of economic, ethnobotanical and horticultural importance: A checklist. Kew Bull. 56: 257–360.</reference>
    <reference>Svenson, H. K. 1957. Cyperaceae. Tribe 2, Scirpeae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 18, pp. 505–556.</reference>
    <reference>Tucker, G. C. 1987. The genera of Cyperaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 68: 361–445.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers and achenes partially to completely enclosed in scalelike structure (perigynium); perigynium in axil of scale ; flowers unisexual (see Plate 1. A, B, C).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynia open to 1 side, at least some containing 1–3 staminate flowers as well as 1</description>
      <determination>25. Kobresia , p. 252</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynia closed except for pore at tip through which style protrudes, always containing only 1 pistillate flower (see Plate 1. B, C).</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms usually with several blade-bearing leaves, sometimes all basal; blades flat, V -shaped, M -shaped, rarely terete or involute in cross section, commonly less than</description>
      <determination>26. Carex , p. 254</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with 1(–2) basal leaves; blades flat, usually 2–5 cm wide, without evident</description>
      <determination>27. Cymophyllus , p. 573</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers and achenes not enclosed in scalelike perigynium; flowers in axil of scale; flowers usually bisexual, sometimes some, rarely all, flowers unisexual.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers with perianth of 1 or more hairs, bristles, scales, or bristles and scales, usually persistent on achene (see Plate 1. D, E, F; Plate 2. A).</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth of hairs or bristles, much exceeding subtending scales in fruit, more than 2 times as long as achene, including persistent style base, if present (see Plate 1. D).</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth hairs strongly curled, tangled in fruit (woolly in appearance)</description>
      <determination>1. Scirpus (in part), p. 8</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth hairs ± straight, not tangled (silky in appearance).</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth hairs (8–)10+ in each flower; spikelets (excluding hairs) 1+ cm</description>
      <determination>2. Eriophorum (in part), p. 21</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth hairs mostly 6 in each flower; spikelets (excluding hairs) not more than 1 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth hairs antrorsely barbed; leaf blades to 25 cm × 2.5–4 mm</description>
      <determination>2. Eriophorum (in part), p. 21</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth hairs smooth; leaf blades less than 1 cm × 1 mm</description>
      <determination>4. Trichophorum (in part), p. 28</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth not or scarcely exceeding subtending scales in fruit, not more than 2 times as long as achene, including persistent style base, if present (see Plate 1. E, F; Plate 2. A).</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets compressed laterally; scales 2-ranked at least in proximal 1 / 2 , keeled (see Plate 2. C).</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes biconvex; styles 2-fid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Persistent style base of achene enlarged (see Plate 2. B)</description>
      <determination>21. Rhynchospora (in part), p. 200</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Persistent style base of achene linear .</description>
      <determination>19. Dulichium , p. 198</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes trigonous; styles 3-fid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes with persistent enlarged style base; culms simple with 1 spikelet; scales</description>
      <determination>8. Eleocharis (in part), p. 60</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes without persistent enlarged style base; culms distally branched with</description>
      <determination>22. Schoenus (in part), p. 239</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets ± rounded in cross section; scales spirally arranged, not keeled (distichous in Websteria ) (see Plate 2. D).</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth consisting of scales or of 3 scales and 3 bristles (see Plate 1. E, F).</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth consisting of 3 bristles and 3 spatulate scales; leaves usually hairy,</description>
      <determination>5. Fuirena , p. 32</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth consisting of 1–2 scales; leaves glabrous (see Plate 2. F)</description>
      <determination>18. Lipocarpha (in part), p. 195</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth consisting of hairs or bristles, bristles rarely somewhat flattened and straplike (see Plate 2. A).</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms apparently without blade-bearing leaves; leaves absent or consisting only of sheaths.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets consisting of 2 scales, distal scale subtending flower; culms with branches in successive false whorls, which terminate in clusters of leaves essentially indistinguishable from stems; spikelets borne singly on branches</description>
      <determination>9. Websteria , p. 120</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with 4+ scales and 2+ flowers; culms unbranched except sometimes in inflorescence; either 1 terminal spikelet or several spikelets in branched inflorescence.</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base enlarged, persistent in fruit, usually clearly differentiated</description>
      <determination>8. Eleocharis (in part), p. 60</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base not or scarcely enlarged, deciduous in fruit; culms usually with several spikelets in branched though sometimes congested</description>
      <determination>7. Schoenoplectus (in part), p. 44</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with blade-bearing leaves; at least distal leaves with blades 5+ mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base enlarged, persistent as differentiated tubercle on achene (see Plate 2. A, B).</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms unbranched, with 1 spikelet; spikelets with 1 proximal scale</description>
      <determination>8. Eleocharis (in part), p. 60</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms usually distally branched, with more than 1 spikelet; spikelets</description>
      <determination>21. Rhynchospora (in part), p. 200</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base not or only slightly enlarged, deciduous or small portion persistent as undifferentiated beak.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 2+, arranged in distichous spike</description>
      <determination>20. Blysmopsis , p. 199</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 1–500, arranged in panicle or clustered into 1 or more heads or solitary.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades and bracts with prominent midrib forming keel on abaxial surface, or blades folded along midrib; inflorescences obviously terminal (see Plate 2. F).</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales glabrous, never both notched and awned at tip; spikelets less than 3.5(–5) mm diam.; achenes 0.6–1.8 mm, mi-</description>
      <determination>1. Scirpus (in part), p. 8</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales puberulent on abaxial surface, often glabrescent, notched and awned at tip; spikelets mostly 4–10 mm diam.; achenes</description>
      <determination>6. Bolboschoenus , p. 37</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades and bracts various, midrib not forming prominent keel on abaxial surface, sometimes with several ribs equally prominent; proximal bract sometimes erect, as if continuation of culm; inflorescences then appearing lateral.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts 2+, the proximal 10+ mm, exceeding spikelets by at least 3 mm; spikelets usually 2+.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal leaf sheaths often disintegrating into fibers; stems</description>
      <determination>3. Amphiscirpus (in part), p. 27</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal leaf sheaths never disintegrating into fibers; leaf</description>
      <determination>7. Schoenoplectus (in part), p. 44</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bracts mostly 1–2, less than 10 mm, shorter than or exceeding spikelet by no more than 3 mm; spikelets always solitary.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Anthers 3 mm; achenes 2.5–3.5 mm</description>
      <determination>7. Schoenoplectus (in part), p. 44</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Anthers 1–2.5 mm; achenes 1.5–2.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with all leaves basal; sheaths often disintegrating into fibers; perianth bristles retrorsely spinulose</description>
      <determination>3. Amphiscirpus (in part), p. 27</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with bladeless sheaths or distal sheaths with blade to 5 mm; sheaths not fibrous; perianth bristles</description>
      <determination>4. Trichophorum (in part), p. 28</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers without perianth of hairs, bristles, or scales.</description>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with scales arranged in 2 rows, at least proximally, commonly compressed; scales keeled (see Plate 2. C).</description>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with 1–2+ proximal scales empty.</description>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences of 1–5 straw-colored spikelets</description>
      <determination>12. Abildgaardia , p. 136</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences of (1–)10–25 black or dark purple spikelets.</description>
      <determination>22. Schoenus (in part), p. 239</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets usually with all scales subtending flowers.</description>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 3-fid; achenes trigonous</description>
      <determination>15. Cyperus (in part), p. 141</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 2-fid; achenes flat to biconvex.</description>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with 5–many scales; inflorescences variously arranged</description>
      <determination>15. Cyperus (in part), p. 141</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with 1–3 scales; inflorescences with 1–4 dense spikes.</description>
      <determination>17. Kyllinga , p. 193</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with scales spirally arranged or arranged in more than 2 rows, usually not compressed; scales not keeled (see Plate 2. D).</description>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base enlarged, persistent in fruit as differentiated or conic apical tubercle (see Plate 2. A, B).</description>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with 1 spikelet, without blade-bearing leaves or with blade not exceed-</description>
      <determination>8. Eleocharis (in part), p. 60</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with inflorescences of 2+ spikelets, with 1+ blade-bearing leaves usually much exceeding 4 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mouth of leaf sheaths fimbriate-ciliate; styles 3-fid; achenes trigonous</description>
      <determination>11. Bulbostylis (in part), p. 131</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Mouth of leaf sheaths glabrous; styles usually 2-fid; achenes usually</description>
      <determination>21. Rhynchospora (in part), p. 200</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base not or scarcely enlarged, deciduous or undifferentiated portion persisting as cylindric beak.</description>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers unisexual; spikelets with only one pistillate flower or entirely stami-</description>
      <determination>24. Scleria , p. 242</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Flowers usually bisexual; spikelets usually with 2+ bisexual flowers.</description>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves ligulate, ligules membranous or row of hairs or cilia (see Plate 2. F).</description>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 2-fid; achenes biconvex.</description>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with all scales subtending flower</description>
      <determination>1. Scirpus (in part), p. 8</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with proximal 1–2+ scales empty</description>
      <determination>10. Fimbristylis (in part), p. 121</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 3-fid; achenes trigonous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with single terminal spikelet</description>
      <determination>4. Trichophorum (in part), p. 28</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms with 2+ spikelets.</description>
      <next_statement_id>40.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades and bracts not prominently keeled on abaxial sur-</description>
      <determination>10. Fimbristylis (in part), p. 121</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades and bracts with midrib forming prominent keel on abaxial surface.</description>
      <next_statement_id>41.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence bracts not ciliate; scales not spinose</description>
      <determination>1. Scirpus (in part), p. 8</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence bracts ciliate proximally; scales with spinose</description>
      <determination>14. Oxycaryum , p. 140</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves not ligulate, rarely with lateral groups of hairs at junction of blade and sheath.</description>
      <next_statement_id>42.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves with 2 lateral groups of hairs (at least some hairs 0.3 mm) at junction of blade</description>
      <determination>11. Bulbostylis (in part), p. 131</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves glabrous or with only short hairs at junction of blade and sheath.</description>
      <next_statement_id>43.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences apparently lateral; proximal bract erect, appearing to be continuation of stem (see Plate 2. G).</description>
      <next_statement_id>44.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes faintly to prominently rugose or transversely ridged</description>
      <determination>7. Schoenoplectus (in part), p. 44</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes smooth, papillose, or longitudinally ridged.</description>
      <next_statement_id>45.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with 8–25 scales</description>
      <determination>13. Isolepis (in part), p. 137</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with (1–)3 scales</description>
      <determination>18. Lipocarpha (in part), p. 195</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences evidently terminal (sometimes some axillary); bracts ascending or spreading, none appearing to be continuation of stem.</description>
      <next_statement_id>46.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with all scales subtending flowers</description>
      <determination>13. Isolepis (in part), p. 137</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets with 1+ proximal scales empty.</description>
      <next_statement_id>47.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>47.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 2-fid; achenes biconvex</description>
      <determination>10. Fimbristylis (in part), p. 121</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>47.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 3-fid; achenes trigonous or round in cross section.</description>
      <next_statement_id>48.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>48.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants annual, not rhizomatous; widest leaves not more than 2 mm wide; achenes usually 1.5 mm or less, reticulate-honeycombed</description>
      <determination>10. Fimbristylis (in part), p. 121</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>48.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, rhizomatous; widest leaves usually more than 2 mm wide; achenes 1.5–3 mm, smooth or rugose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>49.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>49.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences terminal, capitate; culms not more than 20 cm</description>
      <determination>16. Remirea , p. 191</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>49.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences terminal or some lateral, corymbose or subcapitate;</description>
      <determination>23. Cladium , p. 240</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
