<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>422.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Carex</genus_name><species_name>globosa</species_name><species_authority>Boott</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Proc. Linn. Soc. London</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 259. 1845</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Carex</genus_name><species_name>umbellata</species_name><species_authority>Schkuhr ex Willdenow</species_authority><variety_name>globosa</variety_name><variety_authority>(Boott) Kükenthal</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants loosely cespitose; rhizomes arching to ascending, dark reddish brown to purplish brown, 0–12 mm, slender or stout. Culms 7–47 cm, scabrous distally; bases strongly fibrous. Leaf blades bright green, usually shorter than stems, 1.4–4.5 mm wide, herbaceous, glabrous abaxially, strongly scabrous to papillose adaxially. Inflorescences usually with both staminate and pistillate spikes; peduncles of basal spikes arching, elongate, slender; peduncles of terminal staminate spikes 2–5 mm; proximal cauline bracts leaflike, usually shorter than (occasionally slightly exceeding) inflorescences. Spikes: proximal pistillate spikes 2–4 (basal spikes 1–2); cauline spikes overlapping or somewhat separated, with 3–10 perigynia; terminal staminate spikes 10–25 × 1.5–3.2 mm. Scales: pistillate scales purplish brown or reddish brown, with similarly colored or narrow white margins, ovate, 4.2–6.5 × 1.8–2.1 mm, equaling or exceeding perigynia, apex obtuse to cuspidate (awned in some basal spikes); staminate scales ovate to lanceolate, 4.2–7.6 × 1.8–2.1 mm, apex obtuse to acute or short-awned. Anthers 2–3.3 mm. Perigynia green, 12–20-veined conspicuous to at least mid body, globose to obovoid, (3.5–)3.8–5 × (1.6–)1.8–2.3 mm; beak straight, pale green, often tinged with dark reddish brown near apex, (0.5–)0.7–1.4 mm, ciliate-serrulate, apical teeth 0.2–0.3 mm. Stigmas 3. Achenes brown, globose to obovoid, round to obtusely trigonous in cross section, 1.9–2.7 × 1.6–2.3 mm.</description><phenology_fruiting>apr</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>spring</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>may</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jun</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>summer</phenology_fruiting><habitat>moist, shaded, acidic and serpentine slopes and stream banks in redwood, cypress, pine, and oak forests</habitat><elevation>90–1500 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution></treatment>
