<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>William J. Crins</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="G. Don in J. C. Loudon" date="1830">Clandestinae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. C. Loudon, Hort. Brit.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>376. 1830</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus carex;section Clandestinae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Fries) H. Christ" date="unknown">Digitatae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Carex;section Digitatae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose, short to long rhizomatous. Culms red-purple at the base, shorter or
    longer than leaves. Leaves: basal sheaths not fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades V-shaped
    in cross section when young, glabrous, widest leaf blades 2–4 mm wide, distal leaves bladeless
    or with blades 1 mm or less, not longer than sheaths. Inflorescences racemose, with 2–6 spikes;
    proximal nonbasal bracts bladeless or blade usually less than 2 mm, purple tinged, sheathing;
    lateral spikes pistillate or androgynous, with not more than 25 perigynia, sometimes basal,
    pedunculate, prophyllate, ovoid; terminal spike staminate or androgynous. Proximal pistillate
    scales dark brown to black, apex obtuse to subacute, cuspidate or awned. Perigynia erect or
    ascending, veinless or veined with 2 prominent marginal veins, stipitate, obovoid,
    rounded-trigonous, 2–3.5 mm, base tapering or cuneate, apex abruptly contracted to beak,
    pubescent, sometimes glabrescent; beak straight or bent, 0.2–0.5 mm, orifice entire or
    emarginate. Stigmas 3–4. Achenes trigonous, rarely quadrangular, almost as large as bodies of
    perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumboreal (circumpolar and north temperate).</description>
  <number>26ccc.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 20 (4 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex sect. Clandestinae has close affinities with sect. Pictae Kükenthal and perhaps
    with sect. Acrocystis Dumortier. The Eurasian species, C. ericetorum Pollich, which has been
    placed in sect. Acrocystis by Eurasian authors, actually belongs in sect. Clandestinae, based on
    its bract morphology and perigynium pubescence. Although most species of sect. Clandestinae, as
    circumscribed here, form a cohesive morphologic group, C. pedunculata shows a number of
    similarities to C. baltzellii Chapman of sect. Pictae, including inflorescence morphology, scale
    morphology, and perigynium pubescence. Developmental and anatomic studies may help to determine
    whether the sections with pubescent perigynia exhibit homologous or analogous character
    states.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Most pistillate spikes emerging from basal nodes on long peduncles to 13 cm;
        pistillate scales retuse to obtuse, cuspidate; perigynia 3.7–6 mm; leaves dark green,
        equaling or mostly</description>
      <determination>442. Carex pedunculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">All pistillate spikes emerging from cauline nodes on shorter peduncles or sessile;
        pistillate scales acute to obtuse; perigynia less than 3.5 mm; leaves pale green, shorter
        than culms.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate spikes less than 7 mm; anthers less than 2 mm; plants densely
        cespitose,</description>
      <determination>445. Carex concinna</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate spikes usually more than 10 mm; anthers more than 2 mm; plants loosely
        cespitose, long-rhizomatous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigmas 3, flexuous, thin, strongly papillose; pistillate spikes widely separated,
        proximal spikes long-pedunculate, peduncles to 7 cm; proximal bracts
        long-sheathing;</description>
      <determination>443. Carex richardsonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Stigmas 4, erect or convolute, thick, weakly papillose; pistillate spikes
        aggregated, subsessile or short-pedunclulate; proximal bracts short-sheathing;
        northwestern</description>
      <determination>444. Carex concinnoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
