<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>444.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Carex</genus_name><species_name>concinnoides</species_name><species_authority>Mackenzie</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Bull. Torrey Bot. Club</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>33: 440. 1906</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Northwest sedge</common_name><description>Plants loosely cespitose, long-rhizomatous. Culms 14–37 cm. Leaves: basal sheaths dark reddish brown; blades mostly basal, pale green, shorter than culms, thick, 1.7–4.5 mm wide. Inflorescences: peduncles of proximal spikes short; peduncles of terminal staminate spikes 1.5–3(–10) mm; proximal bracts short-sheathing; pistillate spikes 1–3, emerging from cauline nodes, aggregated, ascending, ovoid to short-cylindric; staminate spikes 8–22 × 1.8–3.1 mm. Scales: pistillate scales dark reddish brown, ovate to obovate, apex obtuse to acute, minutely ciliate; staminate scales dark reddish to purplish brown, ovate to obovate, margins white, apex acute, scarious. Anthers 1.9–3.1 mm. Perigynia ellipsoid to obovoid, 2.5–3 × 1.4–1.7 mm, base tapering, pubescent with straight white hairs; beak 0.5 mm. Stigmas 4, erect or convolute, thick, weakly papillose. Achenes obovoid, 1.9–2.5 × 1.3–1.6 mm.</description><phenology_fruiting>spring</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>mar</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>summer</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>aug</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>apr</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>may</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jun</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jul</phenology_fruiting><habitat>moist to dry, open pine, spruce, douglas-fir, and aspen woods</habitat><habitat>often on slopes</habitat><elevation>60–2100 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>Alta.</ca_distribution><ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution><discussion>Carex cocinnoides is the only North American sedge with four stigmas per pistil. It is most similar to C. richardsonii; differs in its more closely aggregated, short-pedunculate pistillate spikes with very short-sheathing bracts. These close relatives are sympatric only at the northern and eastern edge of the range of C. concinnoides.</discussion></treatment>
