<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26ddd.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Pictae</section_name>
    <section_authority>Kükenthal</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler, Pflanzenr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20[IV,38]: 82. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>Peter W. Ball</author>
  <description>Plants loosely cespitose, short- and stout-rhizomatous. Culms red-purple or red-brown
    at base. Leaves: basal sheaths fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades V-shaped in cross
    section when young, widest blades 4 mm or wider, distal leaves sometimes bladeless, glabrous.
    Inflorescences solitary or racemose, with 3–8 spikes; proximal nonbasal bracts bladeless or
    blade not more than 2 mm, sheathing; solitary inflorescences unisexual, bractless spikes;
    racemose inflorescences with lateral spikes pistillate or androgynous, some basal, pedunculate,
    prophyllate; terminal spike staminate or androgynous. Proximal pistillate scales with apex
    obtuse to awned. Perigynia ascending, veined, stipitate, oblong-obovate, trigonous in cross
    section, 4–5 mm, base tapering, apex tapering, beakless or beaked, pubescent; beak orifice
    emarginate. Stigmas 3. Achenes trigonous, almost as large as bodies of perigynia; style
    deciduous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>e North America.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Carex sect. Pictae appears to be closely related to sections Digitatae, Scirpinae, and
    Acrocystis.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate and pistillate flowers on same plant; spikes 3–8, terminal spike mainly
        staminate, usually with pistillate flowers at base; lateral spikes mainly pistillate;
        proximal leaf blades</statement>
      <determination>446. Carex baltzellii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate and pistillate flowers on different plants; spike 1, unisexual; proximal
        leaf blades</statement>
      <determination>447. Carex picta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
