<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26qqq.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Inflatae</section_name>
    <section_authority>Kükenthal</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler, Pflanzenr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20[IV,38]: 96. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>Lisa A. Standley</author>
  <description>Plants cespitose, short-rhizomatous. Culms brown at base. Leaves: basal sheaths not
    fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades filiform, glabrous. Inflorescence 1 spike; bractless;
    spike androgynous, dense, with 15+ perigynia. Pistillate scales persistent, less than 10 mm,
    apex obtuse, acute to acuminate, rarely awned. Perigynia eventually spreading, usually veinless,
    inflated, stipitate or sessile, elliptic or broadly elliptic, rounded-trigonous in cross
    section, (4–)4.5–10 mm, usually not more than 2 times as long as wide, base rounded, margins
    rounded, apex abruptly beaked, glossy, glabrous; beak less than 2 mm, entire to erose. Stigmas
    3. Achenes trigonous, smaller than and loosely enveloped by the bodies of perigynia; style
    deciduous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>alpine regions of w North America.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Additional characters of the floral scale and the perigynia are important in
    recognizing members of Carex sect. Inflatae. The floral scales are brown with hyaline margins,
    ovate, and papery. The perigynia are pale brown at the base and dark brown distally, inflated
    although flattened when dry, glossy, membranous, and glabrous.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescences 1.4–2.5 cm; pistillate scales 3–5-veined with thick, white median
        portion, shorter and narrower than perigynia; perigynia broadly elliptic with short veins on
        angles</statement>
      <determination>477. Carex breweri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescences 0.7–2 cm; pistillate scales 1-veined with narrow, yellow-brown
        median portion, equaling perigynia in width; perigynia elliptic, veinless.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia 3–5 × 1.5–2.5 mm, base rounded, sessile; pistillate scales acute,
        involute,</statement>
      <determination>478. Carex engelmannii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia 2.5–3.5 × 1.5 mm, base narrowly cuneate, stipitate; pistillate scales
        obtuse or</statement>
      <determination>479. Carex subnigricans</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
