<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>9.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Scirpus</genus_name><species_name>ancistrochaetus</species_name><species_authority>Schuyler</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>64: 44, plate 1266, fig. 1. 1962</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Scirpe à crochets</common_name><description>Plants cespitose; rhizomes brownish, short, tough, fibrous. Culms: fertile ones upright or reclining; nodes sometimes with axillary bulblets. Leaves 5–9 per culm; sheaths of proximal leaves green to whitish or brown; proximal sheaths and blades with septa many, conspicuous; blades 32–68 cm × 7–13(–16) mm. Inflorescences terminal, rarely also with 1 lateral inflorescence from distal leaf axil; rays all arching or sometimes 1 or 2 ascending, distal branches scabrous, proximal branches smooth, rarely scabrellous, rays sometimes with axillary bulblets; bases of involucral bracts green, margins usually speckled with red-brown, not glutinous. Spikelets in clusters of 2–18 (largest cluster with 8 or more), spikelets sessile, ovoid to narrowly ovoid, 3–5 × 2–3 mm; scales brown or blackish brown with greenish midribs, elliptic, 1.5–2.5 mm, apex slightly mucronate, mucro 0.05–0.1(–0.2) mm. Flowers: perianth bristles persistent, 6, stout, straight or curved, slightly shorter to slightly longer than achene, with retrorse, thick-walled, sharp-pointed teeth densely arranged in distal 0.6–0.9, enclosed within scales; styles 3-fid. Achenes pale brown, elliptic to obovate in outline, plano-convex, 1.1–1.7 × 0.6–0.8 mm. 2n = 54.</description><phenology_fruiting>spring</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>mar</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>apr</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>may</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>summer</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jun</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>aug</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jul</phenology_fruiting><habitat>growing in wet depressions</habitat><habitat>bogs</habitat><habitat>sinkhole ponds</habitat><habitat>or adjacent to pools</habitat><elevation>100–1100 m;</elevation><ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mass.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.H.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.Y.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Pa.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Vt.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution><us_distribution>W.Va.</us_distribution><discussion>Scirpus ancistrochaetus occasionally hybridizes with S. hattorianus. Scirpus ancistrochaetus once grew in Washington County, New York; it is apparently no longer present in the state.</discussion><discussion>Scirpus ancistrochaetus is in the Center for Plant Conservation’s National Collection of Endangered Plants.</discussion></treatment>
