<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">scirpus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Vahl" date="1805">polyphyllus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 274. 1805</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus scirpus;species polyphyllus</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose; rhizomes short, tough, fibrous. Culms: fertile ones erect or reclining; nodes sometimes with axillary bulblets. Leaves 14–22(–26) per culm; sheaths of proximal leaves green or brownish; proximal sheaths and blades with septa usually few, inconspicuous; blades 16–31 cm × 5–8 mm. Inflorescences terminal, rarely also with 1 lateral inflorescence from distal leaf axil; rays divaricate, smooth throughout or scabrous distally, rays usually with axillary bulblets; bases of involucral bracts green, not glutinous. Spikelets in dense clusters of 3–9 (largest cluster with 6 or more), spikelets sessile, broadly ovoid, 2.5–4 × 1.6–3 mm; scales reddish brown with green midribs, circular or nearly so, 1–1.5 mm, apex mucronate or occasionally short-awned, mucro or awn 0.2–0.3 mm. Flowers: perianth bristles persistent, 6, stout, contorted, much longer than achene and projecting beyond it, retrorsely barbed in distal 1/2, exserted from scales at maturity; styles 3-fid. Achenes pale brown, obovate or nearly obtriangular in outline, plumply trigonous or plano-convex, 1.1–1.4(–1.8) × 0.8–1 mm. 2n = 58.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Fruiting summer (Jul–Aug).</description>
  <description type="habitat">Along wooded streams and other swampy places, usually shaded by trees;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–1000 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Ark., Conn., D.C., Ga., Ill., Ind., Ky., Md., Mass., Miss., Mo., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Pa., S.C., Tenn., Vt., Va., W.Va.</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <discussion>Scirpus polyphyllus occasionally hybridizes with S. atrovirens.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
