<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown" date="1810">eleocharis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="unknown" date="unknown">eleocharis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="Svenson" date="1929">tenuissimae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Michaux) Roemer &amp; Schultes in J. J. Roemer et al." date="1817">tuberculosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. J. Roemer et al., Syst. Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 152. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus eleocharis;section eleocharis;series tenuissimae;species tuberculosa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Scirpus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">tuberculosus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 30. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Scirpus;species tuberculosus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eleocharis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="unknown" date="unknown">tuberculosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Fernald" date="unknown">pubnicoensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eleocharis;species tuberculosa;variety pubnicoensis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, forming dense clumps, not stoloniferous. Rhizomes present or not,
        caudexlike, ascending, 1 mm thick; internodes and scales hidden by crowded culms, not
        evident. Culms elliptic or sometimes circular, with several rounded ridges and sulcate when
        dry, 15–75 cm × 0.3(–1.5) mm, firm, minutely granular at 10X. Leaves: distal leaf sheaths
        persistent; stramineous to green, often minutely red-spotted, papery to membranous, apex
        subacute to narrowly acute, often with tooth-like callus. Spikelets: basal spikelets absent;
        never proliferous, ovoid, terete, 5–15 × 2.5–4 mm, apex acute; proximal scale empty,
        deciduous, clasping 1/2 of culm, similar to floral scales; subproximal scale often empty;
        floral scales spiraled, 10–30, 5–6 per mm of rachilla, pale orange-brown, midribs green,
        broadly ovate, 2.5–4 × 1.5–2.5 mm, central area and often flanks papery to cartilaginous (or
        membranous), midrib evident, apex broadly rounded to obtuse. Flowers: perianth bristles 5–6,
        bright brown, stout, slightly shorter than to equaling tubercle; spinules rarely absent,
        dense, variably from divaricate to antrorse, very short, and blunt to acute, to often much
        longer and retrorse, sharply acute; stamens 2–3; anthers 0.5–1 mm; styles 3-fid. Achenes
        medium brown, obovoid to obpyriform, compressed (often obscurely) trigonous, angles evident,
        0.9–1.7 × 0.8–2 mm; apex often constricted proximal to tubercle, very coarsely cancellate at
        10X, each face with 8–10 longitudinal rows of large depressions. Tubercles bone-white to
        pale orange-brown, often red-spotted, subpyramidal, cross section plano-convex,
        0.9–1.7(–2.4) × 0.7–1.2–2(–2.2) mm, at least as high and wide as achene, spongy, apex
        rounded, often with an abaxial acute projection.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Fruiting spring (in south)–fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Wet soil, freshwater, ponds, lakeshores, streams, meadows, pine woods, grasslands, disturbed places, bogs;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–500 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.S.; Ala., Ark., Fla., Ga., La., Mass., Miss., N.J., N.C., S.C., Tenn., Tex.</description>
  <number>27.</number>
  <discussion>Eleocharis tuberculosa evidently is closely related to E. tortilis, from which it
        differs in its larger tubercles, culms that are always elliptic in cross section, and
        perianth bristle spinules that are often divaricate to antrorse and often blunt. The
        specimens of E. tuberculosa from throughout its range which are like E. tortilis in having
        retrorsely spinulose perianth bristles have been named E. tuberculosa forma retrorsa Svenson
        (type from Massachusetts). Plants from Nova Scotia with nearly smooth bristles have been
        named E. tuberculosa var. pubnicoensis Fernald and E. tuberculosa forma pubnicoensis
        (Fernald) Svenson.</discussion>
  <discussion>We have not seen voucher specimens for literature reports of Eleocharis tuberculosa
        from Connecticut, Delaware, Maine, Maryland, New Hampshire, New York, Pennsylvania, Rhode
        Island, or Virginia.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
