<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eleocharis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Torrey" date="unknown">microcarpa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Lyceum Nat. Hist. New York</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 312. 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Eleocharis;species microcarpa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants usually annual, tufted, sometimes mat-forming via proliferating and arching inflorescences (stoloniferous), sometimes entirely vegetative; rhizomes absent. Culms often ascending or arching, quadrangular or broadly elliptic, 2–40 cm × 0.1–0.4(–0.6) mm, soft. Leaves: distal leaf sheaths persistent or disintegrating, pale brown, green or red-brown, streaked or mottled red-brown or purple, translucent, membranous, apex narrowly acute. Spikelets: basal spikelets absent; often proliferous, ovoid to ellipsoid or lanceoloid, terete, 2–10.7 × 1–2 mm, apex acute; proximal scale empty, persistent, amplexicaulous, dissimilar to floral scales, often longer, often resembling an involucral bract, ovate to lanceolate, midrib markedly thickened and broad and often prolonged beyond lamina; subproximal scale with flower; floral scales spiraled, colorless, whitish, or pale brown, streaked or mottled red-brown or purple, midribs green and red-brown or green and purple, ovate to elliptic, 0.8–1.5 × 0.4–0.8 mm, membranous, midrib obscure to prominent. Flowers: perianth bristles present or sometimes apparently absent; stamens 3; anthers 0.15–0.35; styles 3-fid. Achenes whitish to olive or pale brown, sometimes spotted olive or red-brown, obovoid, trigonous (or subterete), angles prominent, 0.55–0.8 × 0.3–0.5 mm, apex constricted proximal to tubercle, smooth. Tubercles green or pale brown to red-brown, trigonous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies.</description>
  <number>30.</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Specimens of Eleocharis brittonii and E. microcarpa without achenes are often difficult to distinguish. More detailed study of the four apparent entities across the two species is warranted.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles 0.2–0.4 mm, shorter than achene; proximal scale of spikelets 0.4–0.5 mm wide</description>
      <determination>30a. Eleocharis microcarpa var. microcarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles 0.6–1 mm, shorter than to equaling achene; proximal scale of spikelets 0.8–1 mm</description>
      <determination>30b. Eleocharis microcarpa var. filiculmis</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
