<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert Kral</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Vahl" date="unknown">FIMBRISTYLISFimbristylis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 285. 1805</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus FIMBRISTYLISFimbristylis;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin fimbria, fringe, and stylus , style]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, usually cespitose, rhizomatous or not. Culms sometimes solitary, scapose, stiff or flaccid, terete, compressed, or 3–5-angled, coarse or fine. Leaves basal, distichous or polystichous; sheaths open apically, shorter than blade, with broad scarious margins; ligule absent at junction with blade or, if present, of erect short hairs, transverse, continuous or interrupted; blades flat or variously folded, terete, or sulcate, not prominently keeled on abaxial surface, the widest not more than 2 mm wide. Inflorescences simple or compound anthelae, rarely capitate; spikelets 1–80+, rarely single; involucral bracts 2–5, spreading or rarely erect, scalelike or leaflike. Spikelets mainly ovoid to lanceoloid or cylindric, sometimes compressed; scales 8–100+, spirally arranged, each subtending flower or proximal 1–2 empty. Flowers bisexual; perianth absent; stamens 1–3; styles flattened or subterete, 2–3-fid, base enlarged, deciduous. Achenes biconvex or trigonous, reticulate-honeycombed.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly subtropical and tropical</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly in sunny</description>
  <description type="distribution">moist to wet places.</description>
  <number>10.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Fimbristyle</other_name>
  <discussion>Species well over 100 (16 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Culms terminate in scapes; scapes are variously elongate, slender, shallowly to strongly ribbed, overtopping leaves. Leaf blades are mostly linear, compressed or thickened, rarely onefacial. Involucral bracteal blades (more common than scales in Fimbristylis) are linear to setaceous, abbreviated or exceeding inflorescence. Spikelet scales are erect or ascending, rarely nearly distichous; proximal scales sterile, usually bladed, larger than fertile scales; fertile scales mostly uniform, carinate or convex, thin, medially with thicker, longitudinally ribbed band, margins entire; ribs converging apically, often short or longexcurrent. Flowers are protandrous, on short rachilla joint; filaments flattened; anthers bilocular, two- to four-sporangiate; ovary two- to three-carpellate; styles disarticulating at very base, flat, fimbriate, or slender, angular, smooth or papillose. Achenes are tumid, obscurely threeribbed, with faces and angles variously sculpted.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kral, R. 1971. A treatment of Abildgaardia, Bulbostylis and Fimbristylis (Cyperaceae) for North America. Sida 4: 57–227.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 3-fid; plants annual.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ligule of short hairs present; leaf blades flat; spikelets mostly narrow, narrowly lanceoloid</description>
      <determination>15. Fimbristylis autumnalis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ligule not evident; leaf blades strongly folded, bifacial ; spikelets plump, broadly ovoid</description>
      <determination>16. Fimbristylis miliacea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles 2-fid; plants annual or perennial.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ligule of short hairs absent or incomplete.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants low, usually less than 20 cm ( F. squarrosa 30 cm or more), often densely tufted, slender, weedy annuals; leaf blades linear-filiform, to 1 mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets ovoid; achenes cylindric</description>
      <determination>11. Fimbristylis perpusilla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets lance cylindric; achenes obovoid, biconvex.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets sessile or subsessile in dense, terminal, headlike cluster; base of</description>
      <determination>9. Fimbristylis vahlii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets in open anthelae; base of style with slender, recurved fimbriae</description>
      <determination>10. Fimbristylis squarrosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants tall, usually (20–)30–150(–200) cm, more robust, densely to sparsely tufted perennials; leaf blades 1+ mm wide.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets less than 5 mm, in headlike or dense clusters; apex of fertile scales rounded, mostly notched, midrib not exserted; leaf blades shallowly concave</description>
      <determination>12. Fimbristylis cymosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets usually more than 5 mm, mostly in more diffuse clusters; apex of fertile scales rounded, sometimes ciliolate, midrib reaching tip or excurrent as mucro; leaf blades mostly strongly involute; achenes lenticular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants densely cespitose; bases of leaves hard, leathery, usually dark brown</description>
      <determination>13. Fimbristylis castanea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants loosely cespitose in small tufts or culms solitary; bases of leaves not</description>
      <determination>14. Fimbristylis puberula (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Ligule of short hairs evident and complete (most noticeable in plants having broadly linear leaf blade base, harder to detect in narrower, more involute or adaxially sulcate leaf blades).</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes slender, elongate; robust perennials with wandlike culms, at least 50 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets lance-ovoid to cylindric-ellipsoid; scales with abaxial surface dull, uniformly puberulent, scale apex broadly acute, midrib excurrent as mucro or</description>
      <determination>2. Fimbristylis thermali s</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets ovoid to lance-ovoid, rarely cylindric, scales with abaxial surface lustrous, glabrous or puberulent apically, scale apex abruptly rounded, midrib excurrent as mucro.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fertile scales puberulent apically; scapes broadly linear, distally flattened or oval, edges usually scabrid; achene finely but definitely cancellate</description>
      <determination>1. Fimbristylis caroliniana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fertile scales glabrous; scapes narrowly linear, distally angular, glabrous; achene nearly smooth or with longitudinal rows of shallow, isodiametric</description>
      <determination>14. Fimbristylis puberula (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Rhizomes absent or, if present, stout, strongly tapering or made up of thickened contiguous culm bases; annuals or perennials infrequently exceeding 50 cm, mostly under 40 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets pale (stramineous on herbarium specimens, pale red-brown on living plants), usually solitary on scape, infrequently in anthela of 2–3; achenes appearing smooth under 10–20X magnification, under higher power showing</description>
      <determination>3. Fimbristylis schoenoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets dark, usually in open or congested multispikeleted anthelae; achenes appearing smooth, finely striate, or coarsely reticulate on face.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Face (1 side) of achene smoothish or with many (20 or more) longitudinal</description>
      <determination>4. Fimbristylis tomentosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Face (1 side) of achene more coarsely reticulate, usually with 12 or fewer longitudinal rows of horizontally oriented, rectangular cells; annual or perennial.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants perennial; achenes without warts.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plant base bulbous, also scaly-rhizomatous; spikelet scales glabrous</description>
      <determination>5. Fimbristylis brevivaginata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plant base not bulbous, not producing rhizomes; spikelet scales</description>
      <determination>6. Fimbristylis dichotoma</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants annual; achenes variably warty.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades hirsute-ciliate at least proximally; warts present only</description>
      <determination>7. Fimbristylis decipiens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaf blades uniformly smooth to scabrid or ciliolate at margin; warts of achene usually distributed, or rarely achenes smooth</description>
      <determination>8. Fimbristylis annua</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
