<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Vahl" date="1805">fimbristylis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Michaux) Vahl" date="unknown">puberula</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 289. 1805</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus fimbristylis;species puberula</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Scirpus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">puberulus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 31. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Scirpus;species puberulus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, mostly loosely cespitose, to 100 cm, bases swollen; rhizomes short, knotty, or scaly, slender, contorted. Culms sometimes solitary, narrowly linear, distally angular, glabrous. Leaves ascending, from 1/3 as long to equally as long as culms, glabrous to pubescent; sheaths apically ciliate; ligule essentially absent or (in rhizomatous individuals) present, complete or incomplete; blades narrowly linear, 1–2 mm wide, mostly strongly involute, scabrid-ciliate. Inflorescences: anthelae simple or compound, compact or diffuse, mostly broad, ascending-branching; scapes slender, wandlike, 1 mm thick; lower leafy involucral bracts exceeded by or exceeding panicle. Spikelets variously red-brown, broadly ovoid to lance-cylindric, 5–10 mm; fertile scales broadly ovate, obtuse or obtuse-angled, 2.5–3.5 mm, abaxially glabrous or variously puberulent, midrib excurrent as mucro. Flowers: stamens 3; styles 2-fid, flat, fimbriate. Achenes yellowish to dark brown, lenticular-obovoid, 1 mm, with 11–20 vertical lines of horizontally rectangular or isodiametric, distinct or indistinct pits. 2n = 20.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America.</description>
  <number>14.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">puberulum</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culm bases swollen, knotty, closely joined forming short thick, knotty rhizomes; leaves and sheaths totally pubescent or glabrous; ligule absent or incomplete; backs of involucral sheaths and fertile scales puberulent at least distally</description>
      <determination>4a. Fimbristylis puberula var. puberula</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culm bases not swollen, producing several slender, scaly, orange rhizomes; leaves and sheaths mostly glabrous; ligule present, mostly complete; involucral sheaths and fertile scales usually smooth</description>
      <determination>14b. Fimbristylis puberula var. interior</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
