<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert Kral</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kunth" date="1837">Bulbostylis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 205. 1837, name conserved, not Steven 1817 or de Candolle 1836</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus Bulbostylis</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin bulbus , bulb, and stylus , style]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Martius" date="unknown">Oncostylis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Oncostylis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">Stenophyllus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Stenophyllus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, cespitose, scapose, not rhizomatous. Roots diffuse, very fine. Culms stiff or flaccid, usually terete, ribbed. Leaves basal, polystichous, spreading to ascending; sheaths open apically, apex fimbriate-ciliate, rarely entire; ligules absent, lateral tufts of hair at junction of blade and sheath; blades mostly linear or filiform, coarsely ribbed, usually longer than sheaths, 1 mm wide or less, mostly strongly involute, margins variably scabrid-ciliate. Inflorescences terminal on slender scapes, rarely axillary to culm leaves, simple or compound anthelae or spikelet solitary; spikelets 1–50+; involucral bracts (1–)2–8, spreading or erect, leaflike or scalelike. Spikelets mostly ovoid to lanceoloid or lance-cylindric; scales 6–50, spirally arranged, rarely nearly distichous, each subtending flower or 1–2 proximal scales empty. Flowers bisexual; perianth absent; stamens 1–3; styles slender, (2–)3-fid, glabrous, base enlarged, persistent in fruit. Achenes trigonous or 3-lobed, rarely biconvex, usually 3-ribbed.</description>
  <description type="distribution">mostly of dry or periodically dry, sunny, sandy uplands, particularly savanna in warm-temperate and tropical regions worldwide.</description>
  <number>11.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Bulbostyle</other_name>
  <other_name type="invalid_name">names rejected</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 100 (8 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Culms of bulbostylises are coarse or fine, leafy only at the base, and terminating in scape (or rarely not scapose). Scapes are linear to filiform, wiry, variously ribbed. Spikelets or florets are short-stalked, even sessile in leaf axils. Flowers are protandrous and subsessile on short pedicellar joints; anthers are mostly linear-oblong or oblong-elliptic, two- to four-sporangiate, bilocular; style base is articulated to ovary summit and persists on fruit as buttonlike tubercle.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kral, R. 1971. A treatment of Abildgaardia, Bulbostylis and Fimbristylis (Cyperaceae) for North America. Sida 4: 57–227.</reference>
    <reference>Lye, K. A. 1971b. The generic concept of Bulbostylis Kunth ex C. B. Clarke. Mitt. Bot. Staatssamml. München 10: 539–547.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets sessile or subsessile, forming globose to hemispheric head, head subtended by setaceous-tipped or cuspidate involucral bracts.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achene faces finely reticulate, not transversely rugose or rugulose; achenes 0.5–0.6 mm; spikelets red, red-brown, or dull brown; longer involucral bracts rarely exceeding inflo-</description>
      <determination>3. Bulbostylis barbata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achene faces transversely rugose or rugulose; achenes 1–1.2 mm; spikelets pale or greenish or tan; longer involucral bracts exceeding inflorescence.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucral bracts with broad, scarious, strongly pectinate-fimbriate sheath border</description>
      <determination>1. Bulbostylis warei</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Involucral bracts with scarious, entire border gradually narrowing to blade; plants</description>
      <determination>2. Bulbostylis stemophylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets either solitary at culm tip or in anthelae, sometimes short-stalked ( B. capillares ), at plant base in leaf axils.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 1 per culm; plants diminutive, delicate annuals.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets of 2 sorts, sterile and fertile, respectively producing non-viable achenes,</description>
      <determination>4. Bulbostylis funckii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets fertile, achenes all viable, 1 mm</description>
      <determination>5. Bulbostylis schaffneri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets prevalently more than 1 per culm, in anthelae; plants tall annuals or peren-nials.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Surface of ripe achenes waxy gray, evenly papillate; Coastal Plain of United States</description>
      <determination>6. Bulbostylis ciliatifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Surface of ripe achenes pale red-brown, greenish or yellow-brown, tan, or gray, minute alveolae or papillae raised into finely or coarsely transversely rugose or rugulose faces; wider distribution.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants hard-based, perennial; achene surfaces gray, yellow-brown or dark brown,</description>
      <determination>7. Bulbostylis juncoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants soft-based, annual; achene surfaces mostly yellow to pale brown, rug-</description>
      <determination>8. Bulbostylis capillaris</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
