<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>13.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>ISOLEPISIsolepis</genus_name><genus_authority>R. Brown</genus_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Prodr.,</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>221. 1810</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><etymology>[Greek, isos , equal, similar, and lepis , a scale]</etymology><author>S. Galen Smith</author><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Scirpus</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><section_name>Isolepis</section_name><section_authority>(R. Brown) Grisebach</section_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, annual or perennial, cespitose, rhizomatous or not, smooth, glabrous. Culms terete. Leaves all basal; sheaths green to stramineous, sometimes reddish proximally; ligules absent; blades rudimentary to exceeding culms. Inflorescences terminal, sometimes pseudolateral, capitate or solitary spikelet; spikelets 1–3(–15); involucral bracts 1(–2), spreading to erect, like foliage leaf blades. Spikelets: scales 8–25, spirally arranged, each subtending flower. Flowers bisexual; perianth absent; stamens 1–3; styles linear, 2–3-fid, base persistent, sometimes slightly enlarged. Achenes biconvex or trigonous, papillose or longitudinally ribbed.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 69 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>worldwide in cool-tropical and temperate regions</global_distribution><global_distribution>especially Africa and Australia.</global_distribution><discussion>Isolepis is difficult to delimit on a worldwide basis and has been included in Scirpus in the broad sense. Data derived from embryologic, genetic, and other studies led in recent years to the acceptance of Isolepis as a distinct genus (J. J. Bruhl 1995; P. Goetghebeur 1998; A. M. Muasya et al. 2001).</discussion><references>
    <reference> Muasya, A. M. 1998. Systematics of the Genus Isolepis R. Br. (Cyperaceae). Ph.D. thesis. University of Reading. Muasya, A. M. and D. A. Simpson. 2002. A monograph of the genus Isolepis R. Br. (Cyperaceae). Kew Bull. 57: 257–362.</reference>
    <reference> Muasya, A. M., D. A. Simpson, M. W. Chase, and A. Culham. 2001. A phylogeny of Isolepis (Cyperaceae) inferred using plastid rbcL and trnL-F sequence data. Syst. Bot. 26: 342–353.</reference>
  </references><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikelets with scales markedly gibbous, often clasping shed achenes, colorless to stramineous, or orangish, or greenish; achenes acutely equilaterally trigonous; leaf sheaths green to stramineous or brown.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Scales from middle of spikelet 1.8–2 mm, with awns 0.2–0.5 mm; achenes 1–1.5 mm</statement>
      <determination>1. Isolepis carinata</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Scales from middle of spikelet 1–1.2 mm, with mucros to 0.1 mm; achenes 0.7–0.9 mm</statement>
      <determination>2. Isolepis pseudosetacea</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikelets with scales neither gibbous nor clasping shed achenes, usually at least partly orange- to red-brown or blackish; achenes compressed-trigonous or thickly plano-convex; leaf sheaths usually reddish proximally.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Achenes papillose, not ribbed; culms, leaves, and involucral bracts not orange-punctate</statement>
      <determination>3. Isolepis cernua</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Achenes not papillose, prominently longitudinally ribbed at 10X and minutely transversely ridged at 20–30X; culms, leaves, and involucral bracts orange-punctate at 10–</statement>
      <determination>4. Isolepis setacea</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
