<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert Kral</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Vahl" date="unknown">RHYNCHOSPORA</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 229. 1805</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus RHYNCHOSPORA</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek rhynchos , snout, and spora , seed]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">Dichromena</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Dichromena;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="A. Gray" date="unknown">Psilocarya</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Psilocarya;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual or perennial, cespitose or not, often scaly-rhizomatous. Culms procumbent to erect, usually trigonous, wiry to stout. Leaves basal and cauline, polystichous, mostly 3-ranked; sheaths open apically, glabrous; ligules present or absent; blades flat, V-shaped in cross section or terete, typically keeled abaxially, margins involute or revolute, usually scabrid or scabridulous. Inflorescences terminal, rarely pseudolateral, paniculate, corymbose, anthelate, racemose, or capitate; spikelets 3–100 or more; involucral bracts 1–6, spreading or rarely the proximal erect, leaflike. Spikelets: scales spirally or distichously arranged, each subtending flower; 1 or more proximal scales empty. Flowers all bisexual or sometimes distalmost staminate; perianth absent or of 2–12(–20) bristles, usually persistent in fruit, rarely deciduous, variously barbed or plumed, shorter or longer than achene, seldom smooth; stamens 2–3; styles undivided or shallowly 2-fid, or deeply cleft into 2(–3) linear stigmatic branches; style base persistent as tubercle on fruit, usually articulate to achene apex, distinct, enlarged. Fruits achenes, borne on pedicellar joint, directly distal to compact, dilated receptacle; body various shades of brown, flattened, lenticular (biconvex), or nearly terete, smooth and lustrous or variously ridged, pitted, alveolate (honeycombed), cancellate (netted, latticed), papillate, or warty; tubercle mostly conic or variously triangular, terete or flattened and 2-edged, sometimes longitudinally sulcate, widest across base; base along narrow transverse suture, lunate, 2-lobed, or topping achenial “neck” or buttress, much narrower, as wide as, or wider than achene apex, decurrent down achene margins.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide, mostly in sunny places with wet, acidic soils.</description>
  <number>21.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">Rynchospora</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">Beak-rush</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">rhynchospore</other_name>
  <discussion>Species over 250 (68 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The working basis for the classification used here is from G. Kükenthal, the first modern monographer of Rhynchospora worldwide (1949–1951). He divided the genus into two subgenera, Haplostylae (Nees) Bentham and Diplostylae Bentham, based on degree of stylar branching. In subg. Haplostylae the stylar apex is virtually unlobed, surmounted by two tuberclelike stigmas, or shallowly bifid with the stigmatic branches rarely approaching 1 mm. Thus the stigmatic area is small compared to that of plants in subg. Diplostylae, in which the stylar apex is divided into two narrowly linear, elongate stigma branches.</discussion>
  <discussion>The North American flora has representatives of only two sections of subg. Haplostylae: sect. Longirostres Kunth and sect. Polycephalae C. B. Clarke. Sect. Longirostres, comprising both cespitose and clonal species, contains some of the largest, most robust species in the genus (e.g., Rhynchospora careyana, R. corniculata, R. inundata), with culms often reaching nearly two meters. Section Polycephalae is represented in the flora by only one species, R. tracyi Britton, which forms large clones by slender, stoloniferous rhizomes. Subg. Haplostylae makes up species 1–6 in this treatment; the remaining 62 species all have deeply bifid styles, in most cases with slender stigmas fully half as long as to nearly equaling the undivided slender portion of the style, and therefore belong to subg. Diplostylae. A clear majority of 54 species were very competently evaluated by S. Gale (1944) who referred them to sect. Eurhynchospora, now treated as subg. Rhynchospora. These species sort into several species groups called “series,” “subsections,” “pars,” or “sections,” depending on treatment authors. Two sections of Rhynchospora with the deeply divided styles, Dichromena (4 species in the flora) and Psilocarya (3 species in the flora), both without vestigial perianth, were omitted from Gale’s treatment. Members of the sect. Dichromena, with leafy, often whitened, involucral bracts subtending whitish heads of spikelets, and sect. Psilocarya, with spikelets peduncled in congested to diffuse panicles, were treated as genera until recently.</discussion>
  <discussion>Most members of Rhynchospora are cespitose. This does not preclude the possibility of some species (e.g., R. caduca, R. mixta) from having welldeveloped scaly rhizomes or others (e.g., R. oligantha, R. breviseta, R. rariflora, R. stenophylla) from forming dense, hard-based tufts from packed, intertwined short rhizomes. Only a few species are strongly clonal by elongate rhizomes; those are mostly in subg. Haplostylae (e.g., R. tracyi, R. careyana, R. inundata) or subg. Diplostylae sect. Dichromena (e.g., R. colorata).</discussion>
  <discussion>Also in this treatment the term “fruit” is used not just for the achene but for the achene and all structures attached and subsequently shed with it. A total length measure begins at the pedicellar joint (nearly always very contracted) and proceeds through the receptacle and fruit body (achene) to the tubercle tip. Tubercle length is measured from the middle of the achene summit to the tip of the tubercle. For accuracy one must measure completely ripened fruit, particularly to note the very narrow zone at the tubercle tip where the proximal portion of the style disarticulates.</discussion>
  <discussion>Unless specifically stated, fruit measurements include the tubercle.</discussion>
  <discussion>Rhynchosporas are often dominant or co-dominant herbaceous graminoids in marshlands and savannas. Many species occuring in marshlands provide food for migratory waterfowl.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Gale, S. 1944. Rhynchospora sect. Eurhynchospora in Canada, the United States and the West Indies. Rhodora 46: 80–134, 159–197, 255–278.</reference>
    <reference>Kral, R. 1996. Supplemental notes on Rhynchospora crinipes and related species in sect. Fuscae (Cyperaceae). Sida 17: 385–411. Kükenthal, G. 1949–1951. Vorarbeiten zu einer Monographie der Rhynchosporoideae 18. Rhynchospora Vahl. Bot. Jahrb. Syst. 74: 375–509; 75: 90–115, 273–314, 451–497.</reference>
    <reference>Moore, A. G. 1977. A Taxonomic Investigation of Rhynchospora Sect. Longirostres Kunth. Ph.D. dissertation. Vanderbilt University.</reference>
    <reference>Thomas, W. W. 1984. Systematics of Rhynchospora sect. Dichromena. Mem. New York Bot. Gard. 37: 1–116.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles simple or 2-fid only at tip; fruit tubercles either stout-conic and 2-sulcate, equaling fruit body or linear to narrowly triangular-subulate, distinctly longer than fruit body; plants usually tall, slender to robust, often 1–1.5+ m.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Larger spikelet clusters dense, globose or subglobose; tubercle tip barely exserted; mature spikelet less than 10 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants strongly rhizomatous; fruit body 2.5–3(–4) × 1.5–2 mm, edges not crimped;</description>
      <determination>1. Rhynchospora tracyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not rhizomatous; fruit body 3–4 × 2–2.5 mm, edges crimped; fruit tubercle</description>
      <determination>2. Rhynchospora indianolensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Larger spikelet clusters dense or open, hemispheric to turbinate; tubercle tip long exserted; mature spikelet well over 10 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants scaly rhizomatous; some perianth bristles nearly reaching apex of fruit body or beyond.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles ± 2 times as long as fruit body; fruit body broadest near middle, usually less than 3 mm wide; longer leafy bracts extending beyond inflores-</description>
      <determination>3. Rhynchospora inundata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles slightly longer to slightly shorter than fruit body; fruit body broadest distal to middle, 2.8–3.5 mm wide; longer leafy bracts usually overtopped by inflorescence; rhizomal internodes mostly more than 3 mm thick</description>
      <determination>4. Rhynchospora careyana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not rhizomatous, mostly in tufts; perianth bristles shorter or longer than fruit body.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles ± 2 times as long as fruit body; clusters of spikelets compact, distant</description>
      <determination>5. Rhynchospora macrostachya</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles usually 1 / 2 as long as fruit body; clusters of spikelets open, more diffuse</description>
      <determination>6. Rhynchospora corniculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Styles deeply divided into 2 slender stigmatic branches; fruit tubercle compressed, mostly triangular subulate, slightly shorter than, equaling, or slightly longer than fruit body; plants from less than 10 cm with filiform leaves and culms to 1+ m with linear, wandlike culms and linear leaves.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles retrorsely barbellate (except in scattered forms of R. capitellata , R. cephalantha , and R. capillacea , in which bristles are either smooth or antrorsely barbellate); base of fruit body narrowed to stipe.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets whitish to straw colored, pale dull brown to pale red brown (pallid in living material); perianth bristles 10–20.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles 10–12; fruit body 1.5–1.8(–2) × 0.9–1.2 mm</description>
      <determination>14. Rhynchospora alba</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles 18–20; fruit body (1.7–)2–2.2 × (0.8–)1–1.5 mm</description>
      <determination>15. Rhynchospora macra</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets rich red brown (rarely pale brown) to dark brown; perianth bristles 6.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Clusters of spikelets ovoid or ellipsoid; spikelets all ascending or erect; fruit</description>
      <determination>13. Rhynchospora capillacea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Clusters of spikelets turbinate to hemispheric or globose; spikelets spreading to erect; fruit body obovoid or round.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting florets (1–)2–3(–5) per spikelet, if 1, then terminal floret reduced.</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 2–3 mm; fruits 1.5–1.9 mm; tubercle triangular, distinctly</description>
      <determination>9. Rhynchospora knieskernii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 3.5–6.5 mm; fruits (2–)2.5–4 mm; tubercle triangular-subulate, slightly shorter to slightly longer than fruit body.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 3.5–4(–5); fruits (2–)2.5–3 mm</description>
      <determination>7. Rhynchospora capitellata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 4.5–6.5 mm; fruits 3–3.5(–4) mm</description>
      <determination>8. Rhynchospora glomerata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruiting florets 1 per spikelet, terminating rachilla.</description>
      <next_statement_id>14.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets mostly pale red brown, narrowly ellipsoid to lanceoloid, spreading to erect in turbinate to hemispheric clusters; fruit body (2.5–)2.7–3.3(–3.5) mm; tubercle less than 0.5 mm wide at base</description>
      <determination>10. Rhynchospora chalarocephala</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>14.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets dark red brown, more broadly lanceoloid, erect to reflexed in dense, mostly globose clusters; fruit body 2.5–4.5 mm; tubercle at least 0.5 mm wide at base.</description>
      <next_statement_id>15.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Clusters of spikelets mostly 1–2 cm thick; fruit 3.5–4(–4.2) mm,</description>
      <determination>11. Rhynchospora cephalantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>15.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Clusters of spikelets mostly 0.5–1 cm thick; fruit 2.5–3 mm, body</description>
      <determination>12. Rhynchospora microcephala</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles, when present, antrorsely barbellate (shortest ones may be smooth); base of fruit body not stipelike.</description>
      <next_statement_id>16.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles absent; tubercle of fruit broad based, often decurrent on fruit body (fruit body usually margined).</description>
      <next_statement_id>17.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets brown to nearly black, stalked, in diffuse cymose or paniculate inflorescences; plants annual.</description>
      <next_statement_id>18.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base triangular to subulate, at least 0.5 mm</description>
      <determination>22. Rhynchospora scirpoides</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>18.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Style base depressed, crescent-shaped, less than 0.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>19.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets acuminate, (5–)6–10 mm, dull brown or tan; achene margin with narrow, distinct sulcus; style base ends turned up, hornlike</description>
      <determination>20. Rhynchospora eximia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>19.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets acute, mostly 4–6(–8) mm, dark brown to nearly black; achene margin without sulcus; style base ends not turned up or hornlike</description>
      <determination>21. Rhynchospora nitens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>17.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets whitened, crowded in capitate, leafy involucrate cluster; plants perennial.</description>
      <next_statement_id>20.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants solitary or sparsely cespitose, with scaly rhizomes; fruit 1.5–2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>21.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Longer involucral bracts at least 5 mm wide at base, mostly abruptly narrowed and green at or distal to midbract; fruit widest at midbody; tubercle base lunate, decurrent; rhizomes mostly 2–4 mm thick; in acid,</description>
      <determination>16. Rhynchospora latifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>21.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Longer involucral bracts mostly less than 5 mm wide at base, mostly gradually narrowing, green well proximal to midbract; fruit widest at or near apex; tubercle base transverse or slightly lunate, scarcely decurrent; rhizomes mostly 2 mm or less thick; in calcareous or basic sub-</description>
      <determination>17. Rhynchospora colorata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>20.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants densely cespitose, without scaly rhizomes; fruit 0.8–1.2 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>22.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body rugose; keels of spikelet scales not ciliolate; sw United States</description>
      <determination>18. Rhynchospora nivea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>22.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body rugulose; keels of at least proximal spikelet scales ciliolate;</description>
      <determination>19. Rhynchospora floridensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>16.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles present or absent, if absent then tubercle base thickened, not decurrent, or tubercle strongly flattened and sharply 2 edged.</description>
      <next_statement_id>23.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bases or entire length of perianth bristles densely plumose; fruit tubercle conic.</description>
      <next_statement_id>24.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets on divaricate capillary stalks, 1–5 at common level along filiform culm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>25.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles more than 1 / 2 length of fruit body; fruits 1–3 per spikelet; tubercle base</description>
      <determination>23. Rhynchospora oligantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>25.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bristles equal to or less than 1 / 2 length of fruit body; fruits 3–8 per spikelet;</description>
      <determination>24. Rhynchospora breviseta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>24.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets on shorter, thicker stalks, more densely crowded, in spreading to ascending branched spikelet clusters.</description>
      <next_statement_id>26.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets light brown, narrowly lanceoloid, 8–10 mm; fertile scales 5–8 mm; perianth bristles more than 2 times as long as fruit, excurved, strongly exserted</description>
      <determination>25. Rhynchospora megaplumosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>26.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets light red-brown to dark brown or dark red-brown, broadly fusiform to ovoid or lance-ovoid, 3.5–6 mm; fertile scales no longer than 4 mm; perianth bristles rarely extending past fruit tubercle apex, closely surrounding fruit body, erect, not exposed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>27.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body (1.5–)2–2.2 mm, tubercle conic, 0.5–0.8(–1) mm, prominently 2-lobed at base; leaves linear, (1–)2–3 mm wide, shallowly involute; plant</description>
      <determination>26. Rhynchospora pineticola</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>27.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body 1.3–1.8(–2) mm, tubercle depressed-conic to conic, 0.3–0.5 mm; leaves linear-filiform, 1–1.5 mm wide, deeply involute; plant base dull brown</description>
      <determination>27. Rhynchospora plumosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>23.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Bases of perianth bristles not densely plumose (may be setose), or perianth absent; tubercle variously shaped.</description>
      <next_statement_id>28.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle of fruit a “button” (as in Bulbostylis ), its base not broader than fruit apex; perianth none; densely cespitose; fruit 1 mm or less.</description>
      <next_statement_id>29.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body transversely rugulose, not striate-reticulate, glassy</description>
      <determination>28. Rhynchospora pusilla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>29.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body not transversely rugulose, finely striate-reticulate, glassy</description>
      <determination>29. Rhynchospora divergens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>28.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle of fruit not a “button” (except in R. divergens ), its base broader than fruit apex; perianth bristles 0–6(–12 in R. megolocarpa , R. alba , R. baldwinii ); habit various; fruit mostly more than 1 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>30.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body irregularly transversely finely or more often coarsely ridged, ridges separated by rows of isodiametric or vertically oriented alveolae or lattices, these slightly to deeply concave and sharply bordered (shape of alveolae measured at midbody of fruit).</description>
      <next_statement_id>31.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants forming mats or dense tussocks of filiform leaves and scapes; spikelets few to many per cluster, solitary or paired on capillary secondary or ultimate stalks; perianth present.</description>
      <next_statement_id>32.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit 1 mm, body distinctly margined, cancellate; transverse ridges only slightly</description>
      <determination>30. Rhynchospora thornei</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>32.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit 2–3 mm, body not distinctly margined, narrowly alveolate; transverse ridges much stronger than vertical ridges.</description>
      <next_statement_id>33.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 5 mm; fruit tubercle narrowly triangular acuminate, (0.8–)1–1.5 mm;</description>
      <determination>31. Rhynchospora stenophylla</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>33.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 3–4(–4.5) mm; fruit tubercle short triangular, 0.3–0.6 mm; bristles rarely</description>
      <determination>32. Rhynchospora rariflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>31.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants, if forming mats or tussocks, with broader leaves and culms; spikelets in dense or open clusters; perianth present or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>34.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit (1.8–)2+ mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>35.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles reaching tubercle base or beyond.</description>
      <next_statement_id>36.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body strongly compressed, faces nearly level.</description>
      <next_statement_id>37.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets lanceoloid, 5–7 mm; mature culms arching outward, drooping tipped; fruit body narrowly oblong ellipsoid, tubercle narrowly</description>
      <determination>33. Rhynchospora inexpansa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>37.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets ovoid, 4–5 mm; mature culms ± erect; fruit broadly oblong-</description>
      <determination>34. Rhynchospora punctata (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>36.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body distinctly biconvex (lenticular) or tumid.</description>
      <next_statement_id>38.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose or solitary, with well-developed rhizomes; clusters of spikelets mostly diffuse; fruit body ellipsoid to obovoid oblong, tubercle trian-</description>
      <determination>38. Rhynchospora mixta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>38.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose, sometimes with short rhizomes or rhizomes absent; spikelets usually few in ultimate clusters, these close on ascending secondary branches, clusters dense; fruit body pyriform, broadly obovoid or suborbicular, tubercle short triangular with edges setulose or narrowly triangular subulate with edges not setulose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>39.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 5–7 mm; pedicellar joint 0.3–0.6 mm; tubercle edges setulose</description>
      <determination>37. Rhynchospora odorata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>39.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 3–5 mm; pedicellar joint 1.5–3 mm; tubercle edges entire or setulose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>40.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body pyriform, surfaces vertically striate-alveolate between ridges; tubercle subulate-triangular, edges not setulose; California</description>
      <determination>35. Rhynchospora californica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>40.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body broadly obovoid to suborbicular, surfaces vertically finely striate and rectangular-alveolate; tubercle triangular-</description>
      <determination>36. Rhynchospora caduca</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>35.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles, if present, not reaching beyond tubercle base (except in R. punctata ), usually extending only 2 / 3 or less length of fruit body.</description>
      <next_statement_id>41.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Larger leaf blades 2–3 mm or less wide; fruit body compressed, obovoid, 2 mm; tubercle flat, low triangular, 0.2–0.3(–0.5) mm, lunately curved to fit fruit</description>
      <determination>39. Rhynchospora torreyana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>41.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Larger leaf blades mostly 3–4 mm wide; fruit body compressed or tumid, mostly 2–2.5(–3) mm, tubercle more narrowly triangular to subulate, compressed or shallowly biconvex, 0.5–1 mm, tubercle base and fruit summit either level or curved.</description>
      <next_statement_id>42.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body distinctly flattened, mostly 2–2.5(–3) mm; plants cespitose, not rhizomatous.</description>
      <next_statement_id>43.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles extending past tubercle base; alveolae broadly rectangular to nearly isodiametric; tubercle somewhat compressed, directly</description>
      <determination>34. Rhynchospora punctata (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>43.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth bristles extending to midbody of fruit; alveolae narrowly rec- tangular to oblong-linear; tubercle conic subulate, strongly rimmed at</description>
      <determination>40. Rhynchospora compressa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>42.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body lenticular or tumidly biconvex, 1.3–1.6(–1.8) mm; plants solitary or cespitose, rhizomatous or not.</description>
      <next_statement_id>44.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose, rhizomes absent; spikelets rich red brown; tubercle</description>
      <determination>41. Rhynchospora recognita</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>44.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants solitary or cespitose, rhizomes stoloniferous; spikelets deep dark</description>
      <determination>42. Rhynchospora kunthii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>34.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit mostly 1.3–1.7 mm (to 1.8 or 2 mm in R. globularis var. saxicola ).</description>
      <next_statement_id>45.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Longer perianth bristles mostly not reaching past midbody of fruit, or vestigial, or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>46.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit strongly compressed; perianth absent or vestigial</description>
      <determination>48. Rhynchospora perplexa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>46.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit distinctly biconvex or tumid; perianth vestigial to ± as long as fruit body.</description>
      <next_statement_id>47.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>47.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle of fruit conic</description>
      <determination>45. Rhynchospora globularis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>47.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle of fruit triangular, sharp edged</description>
      <determination>46. Rhynchospora microcarpa (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>45.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Longer perianth bristles reaching at least to, more often beyond, tubercle base.</description>
      <next_statement_id>48.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>48.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body strongly flattened; longer perianth bristles spreading widely</description>
      <determination>47. Rhynchospora elliottii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>48.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body biconvex or tumid; perianth bristles closely ascending around fruit.</description>
      <next_statement_id>49.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>49.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose, rhizomatous; culms wandlike, to 1.5 m; inflorescence branches</description>
      <determination>43. Rhynchospora miliacea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>49.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose, not rhizomatous (except rarely in R. decurrens ); culms stiff, or if wandlike scarcely exceeding 1 m; inflorescence branches ascending, not divaricately spreading.</description>
      <next_statement_id>50.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>50.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body narrowly obovoid or ellipsoid; branches of inflorescence capillary, clusters elongate, diffuse; tubercle triangular, confluent with narrow,</description>
      <determination>44. Rhynchospora decurrens</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>50.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body broadly obovoid to suborbicular; branches of inflorescence stouter, clusters shorter, compact; tubercle depressed-conic or triangular, confluent or not with fruit edge, edge without pale, wirelike rim.</description>
      <next_statement_id>51.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>51.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit tubercle depressed-conic or even patelliform, apiculate; rimmed</description>
      <determination>45. Rhynchospora globularis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>51.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit tubercle broadly triangular, compressed; rimless base more confluent with edges of more shallowly convex fruit body</description>
      <determination>46. Rhynchospora microcarpa (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>30.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body, if cross ridged, with ridges fine, low, and many, forming narrow border for transverse rows of broadly rectangular to isodiametric lattices, shallow alveolae, or lattices or body smooth to glassy or minutely pitted.</description>
      <next_statement_id>52.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>52.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body tumid at least apically, not edged; surfaces smooth or with transverse rows of lattices; fruit tubercle subconic.</description>
      <next_statement_id>53.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>53.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Midbody of fruit with irregular transverse rows of broadly rectangular to subisodiametric lattices; thickened tubercle base and fruit summit not connected by</description>
      <determination>45. Rhynchospora globularis (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>53.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Midbody of fruit smooth or with many undulate transverse rows of pits; thickened tubercle base and fruit summit connected by distinct buttress.</description>
      <next_statement_id>54.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>54.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 4–8 mm; fruit body smooth or longitudinally striate; body (3.5–)4–5</description>
      <determination>49. Rhynchospora megalocarpa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>54.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 2.5–5.5 mm; fruit body pitted between many fine, undulate, transverse ridges; body usually 3 mm or less; no leaf blades as wide as 5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>55.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>55.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit 2.5–3 mm; spikelets 4–5.5 mm; perianth reaching past fruit midbody</description>
      <determination>50. Rhynchospora grayi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>55.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit 2–2.5 mm; spikelets 2.5–4 mm; perianth not reaching past fruit mid-</description>
      <determination>51. Rhynchospora harveyi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>52.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body distinctly lenticular, narrow edged, surface mostly either smooth, even glassy, or transversely striate with fine pits; fruit tubercle compressed, thin edged.</description>
      <next_statement_id>56.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>56.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle edges setulose ciliate; perianth bristle bases and/or pedicellar joint often setose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>57.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>57.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 3–4 mm</description>
      <determination>57. Rhynchospora filifolia</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>57.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets (4.5–)5–7 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>58.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>58.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body narrowly oblong ellipsoid; leaf blades filiform</description>
      <determination>56. Rhynchospora curtissii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>58.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit body obovoid; leaf blades filiform or linear.</description>
      <next_statement_id>59.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>59.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants sparsely or densely cespitose, strongly clonal, rhizomes stoloniferous, 1–2 mm thick; pedicellar stipe joint stout, no longer than 0.3 mm; leaf blades filiform.</description>
      <next_statement_id>60.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>60.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms few per clump; longer involucral bracts surpassing subtended fascicle; fruit from base of pedicellar joint to tubercle tip 2.5 mm,</description>
      <determination>52. Rhynchospora fusca</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>60.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms densely clumped; longer involucral bracts barely if at all surpassing subtended fascicle; fruit from base of pedicellar joint to tubercle tip 2 mm, joint setose, tubercle edges setulose</description>
      <determination>53. Rhynchospora pleiantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>59.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose, not clonal, without rhizomes (except in R. crinipes ); pedicellar stipe joint 0.3–0.6 mm, setose; leaf blades linear to filiform.</description>
      <next_statement_id>61.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>61.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Principal leaf blades no wider than 2 mm; fruit from stipe base to tubercle tip to 2.5 mm; pedicellar stipe joint sparsely setose, to 0.4 mm; fruit body obovoid, 1–1.1 mm wide; spikelet clusters</description>
      <determination>54. Rhynchospora harperi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>61.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Principal leaf blades 2–3 mm wide; fruit from stipe base to tubercle tip 2.5–3 mm; pedicellar stipe joint densely curled-setose, 0.6–1 mm; fruit body narrowly obovoid, 0.8–1 mm wide; spikelet</description>
      <determination>55. Rhynchospora crinipes</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>56.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle edges not setulose ciliate; perianth bristle bases and/or pedicellar joint not setose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>62.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>62.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets 2–3.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>63.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>63.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit not over 1.8 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>64.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>64.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth evident, some bristles reaching or slightly exceeding tip of</description>
      <determination>60. Rhynchospora fernaldii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>64.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth not evident, vestigial, no bristles exceeding midbody of fruit.</description>
      <next_statement_id>65.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>65.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence compounds solitary, dense, hemispheric, rarely with 2d compound approximate beneath; spikelets light brown; fertile scales attenuate-aristate; fruit body pale green, ends dark brown</description>
      <determination>58. Rhynchospora chapmanii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>65.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence compounds rarely solitary, sparse, turbinate or ellipsoid, (1–)2–3, distant; spikelets pale red-brown; fertile scales acute aristulate; fruit body red-brown with pale center</description>
      <determination>59. Rhynchospora brachychaeta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>63.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit 1.8+ mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>66.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>66.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit tubercle flat, sometimes apiculate; perianth none or more often</description>
      <determination>63. Rhynchospora debilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>66.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit tubercle tip subulate or blunt; perianth bristles no shorter than apex of fruit body.</description>
      <next_statement_id>67.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>67.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle tip subulate, perianth extending to or slightly beyond it</description>
      <determination>61. Rhynchospora gracilenta (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>67.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tubercle tip blunt, perianth not exceeding it</description>
      <determination>62. Rhynchospora wrightiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>62.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets (3.5–)4–7 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>68.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>68.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves 3+ mm wide, spreading, coarse; fruit 3–3.5(–3.7) mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>69.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>69.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms triquetrous, harsh edged; perianth bristles 12</description>
      <determination>64. Rhynchospora baldwinii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>69.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms terete or obscurely trigonous, not triquetrous or harsh-edged; perianth</description>
      <determination>65. Rhynchospora ciliaris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>68.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Basal leaves mostly 1–3 mm wide, ascending, not coarse; fruit (1.9–)2–2.5 mm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>70.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>70.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets ovoid or lance ovoid, 3.5–5 mm, brown or red brown; fruit tubercle acutely or subulately triangular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>71.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>71.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit tubercle abruptly long-subulate; perianth reaching at least to tubercle tip,</description>
      <determination>61. Rhynchospora gracilenta (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>71.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Fruit tubercle no more than triangular or concavely triangular; perianth reach-</description>
      <determination>68. Rhynchospora fascicularis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>70.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikelets narrowly lance fusiform, 5–7 mm, near white to straw colored or orangish brown; fruit tubercle low-triagular or depressed-triangular.</description>
      <next_statement_id>72.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>72.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth reaching to at least base of tubercle, fruit 2 mm; culm bases not bul-</description>
      <determination>66. Rhynchospora solitaria</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>72.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perianth vestigial or absent; fruit 1.5–2 mm; culm bases bulbous; spikelets whitish</description>
      <determination>67. Rhynchospora pallida</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
