<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Vahl" date="unknown">rhynchospora</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="A. Gray" date="1835">oligantha</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Ann. Lyceum Nat. Hist. New York</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 212. 1835</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus rhynchospora;species oligantha</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, densely cespitose, knottybased, 20–40 cm; rhizomes absent. Culms filiform, leafy at base, wiry. Leaves ascending to erect; blades filiform, nearly terete, or channeled, sometimes compressed, nearly reaching distal inflorescence or much shorter, 0.2–0.3 mm thick, apex subulate. Inflorescences: spikelet clusters 2–6, simple or reduced to 1 spikelet, branches ascending to divaricate or reflexed; leafy bracts single per cluster, filiform, setaceous, with clusters appearing lateral to bracts. Spikelets pale redbrown, ellipsoidlanceoloid, 5–6(–8) mm, apex acute to acuminate; fertile scales oblongelliptic, convex, acuminate, 3.5–5 mm, apex broadly acute, midrib forming apiculus. Flowers: perianth bristles 6, reaching to or slightly past tubercle base, increasingly plumose from middle to base. Fruits 1–3 per spikelet, (2.5–)2.7–3(–3.4) mm; body light brown to brown, ellipsoidobovoid, distally conspicuously necked, tumidly lenticular, 1.7–2.5 × 1.5–1.8 mm; surfaces smooth or minutely transversely rugulose; tubercle conicsubulate, 0.5–0.7 mm, base flaring.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Fruiting spring–summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sands and peats of bogs, depressions in savannas, open pinelands, seeps;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–200 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Del., D.C., Fla., Ga., La., Miss., N.J., N.C., S.C., Tex., Va.; West Indies; Central America.</description>
  <number>23.</number>
  <discussion>Rhynchospora oligantha is distinguished from other taxa of its complex mostly by the distinctive neck at the achene apex, a feature essentially absent in R. breviseta, its closest relative. Those two species have been heavily impacted by conversion of pine savannas to cropland or pine plantations; even with abandonment or clearing of such land, they are very slow to reoccupy the disturbed sites.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
