<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Scirpus</genus_name><species_name>lineatus</species_name><species_authority>Michaux</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>1: 32. 1803</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Scirpus</genus_name><species_name>fontinalis</species_name><species_authority>R. M. Harper</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants cespitose; rhizomes short, stout. Culms: fertile ones lax, reclining, inflorescences lopping over to (or nearly to) ground; nodes sometimes with axillary bulblets. Leaves 4–9 per culm; sheaths of proximal leaves whitish; proximal sheaths and blades with septa few, inconspicuous; blades 18–32 cm × 6–13 mm. Inflorescences terminal and axillary in 2–3 distal leaves; rays ascending or divergent, rays and pedicels scabrous or scabrellous throughout or sometimes only in distal 1/2, rays often bearing axillary bulblets; bases of involucral bracts green, not glutinous. Spikelets in open cymes, central spikelet of each cyme sessile, others long-pedicellate, spikelets ovoid, narrowly ovoid, or narrowly ellipsoid, 4–7(–10) × 2–3 mm; scales brown to red-brown with green midribs, ovate to narrowly elliptic, 1.8–2.5 mm, apex mucronate, mucro 0.1–0.3 mm. Flowers: perianth bristles persistent, 6, slender, much longer than achene, strongly contorted and not or scarcely projecting beyond it, smooth, enclosed within scales or scarcely projecting beyond them; styles 3-fid. Achenes pale brown, elliptic in outline, plano-convex or plumply trigonous, 1.1–1.5 × 0.6–0.7 mm. 2n = 36.</description><phenology_fruiting>spring</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>mar</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>apr</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>summer</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jul</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>aug</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>may</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jun</phenology_fruiting><habitat>usually along wooded streams</habitat><habitat>often associated with calcareous substrates</habitat><elevation>0–100 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution>La.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Miss.</us_distribution><us_distribution>N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution>S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Va.</us_distribution><discussion>Authors prior to 1966 incorrectly applied the name Scirpus lineatus to plants of S. pendulus and treated plants of S. lineatus as S. fontinalis (A. E. Schuyler 1966).</discussion></treatment>
