<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>A. A. Reznicek,John E. Fairey III,Alan T. Whittemore</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="P. J. Bergius" date="1765">Scleria</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Kongl. Vetensk. Acad. Handl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>26: 142, plates 4, 5. 1765</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus Scleria</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek scleros , hard; perhaps in refernce to the hypogynium]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs usually perennial, sometimes annual, cespitose or not, rhizomatous or not. Culms solitary or not, unbranched proximal to inflorescence, trigonous, (6–)10–100(–125) cm (high-climbing into trees), weak or wiry. Leaves few to many per culm, cauline, 3-ranked; sheaths present; ligules usually well developed, sometimes obsolete; blades well developed (or rudimentary, sometimes absent on proximal leaves), shorter than, equaling, or overtopping culms, plane, keeled, or revolute, 0.5–9 mm wide, stiff, with prominent midvein, glabrous, scabrous, or pubescent. Inflorescences terminal, often axillary, sometimes pseudolateral, panicles, spikes, or 1 or more capitate or fasciculate clusters; spikelets 1–100+; bracts 1–3, ascending or erect, bristle-shaped, awl-shaped, or leaflike, sometimes appearing to be continuation of culm, 10–150 mm, shorter than or exceeding spikelets, glabrous or ciliate. Spikelets: scales 3–10+, each subtending flower, distichous, proximal 2–4 scales empty, proximal fertile scale pistillate, distal fertile scales staminate or sometimes empty; occasionally some spikelets entirely pistillate or staminate. Flowers unisexual; perianth absent; stamens 1–3; anthers 2–4 mm, apex usually mucronate or awned; styles linear, 2–3-fid, base deciduous or persistent, hypogynium rudimentary or prominent, slender or enlarged. Achenes trigonous or rounded, 1–4 mm, smooth, tuberculate, verrucose, or reticulate, occasionally pubescent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and warm-temperate regions of both hemispheres.</description>
  <number>24.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 200 (14 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Unusual structures provide important taxonomic markers in Scleria, necessitating some specialized terminology. The hypogynium is a peculiar, hardened disc at the base of the achene. In some species the hypogynium forms a prominent collar, while in others it is an inconspicuous ridge around the point of attachment of the achene. Before the achene abscises, the hypogynium is attached to a concave disc, the cupula, which remains with the inflorescence when the achene is shed. The contra-ligule (sometimes called the ligula) is a membranous flap on the rim of the leaf sheath on the opposite side from the blade. Contra-ligules are present in some other genera of Cyperaceae; their structure is seldom used taxonomically outside Scleria.</discussion>
  <discussion>Scleria vaginata Steudel, native to Central and South America, was collected once as an adventive in southern Florida, where it is an aggressive vine over two meters. The hypogynium is well developed but lacks tubercles, and the achene is smooth, shining, and gray or purplish.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>SELECTED RERENCES Fairey, J. E. 1967. The genus Scleria in the southeastern United States. Castanea 32: 37–71.</reference>
    <reference>Kessler, J. W. 1987. A treatment of Scleria (Cyperaceae) for North America north of Mexico. Sida 12: 391–407.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium absent or vestigial, achene base tapered, indented or with small pits, appearing continuous with achene body in texture and color.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes reticulate; plants annuals with weak bases, lacking rhizomes, with fibrous roots</description>
      <determination>1. Scleria verticillata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes essentially smooth; plants perennials with firm bases, with rhizomes.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences ± branched, spicate-paniculate; contra-ligules well developed, ciliate</description>
      <determination>5. Scleria lithosperma</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescences not obviously branched, headlike or spikelike; contra-ligules minute or absent.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence interruptedly spicate</description>
      <determination>2. Scleria distans</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence a single cluster at summit of culm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes 3–4 mm, base indented, without granulose pits</description>
      <determination>3. Scleria baldwinii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes 2–3 mm, base with 6 granulose pits</description>
      <determination>4. Scleria georgiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium present, appearing as basal zone differentiated from rest of achene by change in tissue appearance or physical border or gap or both.</description>
      <next_statement_id>6.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 10–25 mm wide; hypogynium bluntly 3-angled, smooth; main stem strongly re-</description>
      <determination>6. Scleria lacustris</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>6.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 1–9 mm wide; hypogynium of lobes, papillose tubercles, or continuous papillose band; main stem ciliate or smooth.</description>
      <next_statement_id>7.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium with narrow, smooth base proximal to 8–9 small, rounded, papillose</description>
      <determination>9. Scleria oligantha</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>7.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium with 3 or 6 lobes or papillose tubercles or continuous and papillate with neither lobes nor distinct tubercles.</description>
      <next_statement_id>8.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium continuous and without distinct lobes or tubercles, densely covered with whitish to brownish papillae; body of achene smooth.</description>
      <next_statement_id>9.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 3–9 mm wide; achenes 2–3 mm</description>
      <determination>7. Scleria triglomerata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>9.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves 1–2.5 mm wide; achenes 1.5–2 mm</description>
      <determination>8. Scleria minor</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>8.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium with 3 or 6 lobes or tubercles; body of achene usually reticulate or papillose.</description>
      <next_statement_id>10.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium with 3 oblong lobes; inflorescence paniculate, with visible branches.</description>
      <next_statement_id>11.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximalmost lateral panicle spreading or drooping on filiform, flexuous peduncle (15–)20–100 mm; achene usually with tufts or lines of spreading, whitish or tawny hairs on ridges, rarely glabrous; distalmost lateral panicle with bract (including sheath) usually 1 / 4 – 3 / 4 length of</description>
      <determination>13. Scleria muehlenbergii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>11.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximalmost lateral panicle erect, sessile or on stiff, ± erect peduncle to 20(–90) mm; achene glabrous; distalmost lateral panicle with bract (including sheath) usually 3 / 4 or more length of terminal internode</description>
      <determination>14. Scleria reticularis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>10.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium not distinctly 3-lobed, with 3 or 6 tubercles; inflorescence</description>
      <next_statement_id>12.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes reticulate-ridged</description>
      <determination>12. Scleria curtissii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>12.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Achenes tuberculate, verrucose, or papillate, rarely nearly smooth.</description>
      <next_statement_id>13.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium with 6 distinctly separate tubercles arranged in pairs;</description>
      <determination>11. Scleria pauciflora</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>13.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Hypogynium with 3 tubercles (these often irregular or 2-lobed);</description>
      <determination>10. Scleria ciliata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
