<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26b.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Heleoglochin</section_name>
    <section_authority>Dumortier</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Belg.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>146. 1827</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>Theodore S. Cochrane</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <section_name>Paniculatae</section_name>
    <section_authority>G. Don</section_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants densely cespitose, short-rhizomatous. Culms brown to dark brown at base, not
    more than 1 mm wide distally. Leaves: basal sheaths not fibrous; sheath fronts dotted red or
    copper, sometimes weakly transversely rugose, membranous; blades V-shaped in cross section when
    young, glabrous. Inflorescences compound, from evidently paniculate to often condensed, with
    numerous spikes; proximal bracts awl-shaped or bristlelike, others scalelike or absent,
    sheathless; lateral spikes androgynous or pistillate, sessile, without prophylls; terminal
    spikes androgynous. Proximal pistillate scales with apex acute to cuspidate. Perigynia usually
    spreading, strongly veined abaxially, obscurely veined or veinless adaxially, shortly stipitate,
    lance- to deltate-ovate or obovate, unequally biconvex or plano-convex in cross section,
    thick-walled or leathery, base tapered to rounded, with spongy tissue, margins acutely angled,
    apex ± abruptly beaked, glabrous; beak shortly bidentate, with abaxial suture. Stigmas 2.
    Achenes biconvex, smaller than bodies of perigynia; style deciduous, slightly thickened at
    base.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 11 or 12 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>temperate regions of North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Eurasia</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>n Africa</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Canary Islands</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>and Australasia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Species of Carex sect. Heleoglochin are closely related to those of sections
    Multiflorae and Vulpinae; the three sections form a natural group characterized especially by
    the inflorescence tending to be compound. A distinctive morphologic characteristic of these
    groups (as well as of sect. Phaestoglochin) is the production of very short (slightly elongate
    in sect. Vulpinae), rather slender, tough, dark brown to blackish rhizomes; although seldom
    collected, these are sometimes visible as nubbins protruding from the base of the specimen.
    Plants that otherwise might key to sect. Heleoglochin should be sought in sections Divisae,
    Intermediae, or Ammoglochin if they lack red dots on the leaf sheaths and have relatively long
    anthers (ca. 2–4 instead of 1–2.5 mm).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence mostly 7–15 cm, proximal 3–9 branches well separated, basal 1 with
        9–33(–48) spikes; perigynia deep olive green to brown at maturity, obpyramidal or broadly
        obovoid, body very abruptly contracted into beak 0.4–0.7 mm; leaf sheaths concave at
        mouth,</statement>
      <determination>10. Carex decomposita</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inflorescence mostly 2–8 cm, proximal 1–5 branches obscure to ±  separated, basal
        1 with 2–21 spikes (or, occasionally, ca. 40 spikes in C. cusickii ); perigynia golden brown
        to brownish black, lance-ovoid to ovoid (broader in the western C. cusickii ), body tapered
        or abruptly contracted into beak 0.8–1.4 mm; leaf sheaths truncate to convex (concave in C.
        cusickii ) and prolonged at mouth beyond base of blade.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inner band of leaf sheath whitish except for reddish dots; inflorescence straight,
        little interrupted, proximal branches usually at least slightly overlapping 1 above;
        perigynia</statement>
      <determination>13. Carex diandra</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Inner band of leaf sheath strongly copper colored toward summit (as well as red
        dotted); inflorescence commonly ± flexuous and interrupted, proximal branches often
        separated; perigynia plane on adaxial face distal to thick body, appressed to spreading at
        maturity, nearly or completely concealed by scales.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Broadest leaf blades not over 3 mm wide; sheath prolonged 2–8 mm beyond base of
        blade, continuous with short ligule to form collar of uniform length or longest
        on</statement>
      <determination>11. Carex prairea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Broadest leaf blades 4–6 mm wide; sheath prolonged 1–4(–6) mm beyond base of blade,
        tapering distally on adaxial side of blade and forming ligule 1.5–7(–12) times as long as
        adnate prolonged portion of leaf sheath; perigynia shiny; scales straw</statement>
      <determination>12. Carex cusickii</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
