<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Theodore S. Cochrane</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">Physoglochin</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Belg.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>145. 1827</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Carex;section Physoglochin;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Tuckerman) Pax" date="unknown">Dioicae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Carex;section Dioicae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants loosely cespitose or not, rhizomatous; rhizomes yellow-brown, long [short or
    lacking], slender, not more than 1.4 mm wide, mostly without persistent scales. Culms brown at
    base. Leaves: basal sheaths not fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades filiform or V-shaped
    in cross section when young, widest less than 1 mm wide, glabrous. Inflorescence a solitary
    spike; proximal bract absent; spikes unisexual or androgynous, ovoid to cylindric. Proximal
    pistillate scales with apex acute to acuminate or cuspidate. Perigynia appressed to usually
    spreading or reflexed at maturity, veined on abaxial face, veined or veinless on adaxial face,
    stipitate, mostly oblong-ovate [ovate to lanceolate], plano-convex or unequally biconvex in
    cross section, almost leathery, base rounded to broadly cuneate, with spongy tissue, margins
    rounded [sharp], apex abruptly contracted to beak, glabrous; beak 0.5–1 mm, with abaxial suture,
    weakly and sparsely serrulate, obscurely bidentulate. Stigmas 2. Achenes biconvex, almost as
    large as bodies of perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">arctic</description>
  <description type="distribution">boreal</description>
  <description type="distribution">and alpine regions of North America and Eurasia.</description>
  <number>26g.</number>
  <discussion>Species 4–6 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex sect. Physoglochin consists of six closely related taxa that are traditionally
    accepted as distinct species. The American-east Asian plant, C. gynocrates in the strict sense,
    is very closely related to C. dioica and has been treated as a major race of that species. Other
    species may be more morphologically distinct (e.g., C. davalliana Smith) or less so (e.g., C.
    redowskiana C. A. Meyer). Detailed studies of variation within and between species are
    needed.</discussion>
  <discussion>Section Physoglochin was included in subg. Primocarex by G. Kükenthal (1909). Because
    of the close morphogical similarity and the readiness with which hybrids are formed with species
    of sections Foetidae and Glareosae, sect. Physoglochin is now placed in subg. Vignea by most
    authors (A. O. Chater 1980; T. V. Egorova 1999).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms trigonous, distinctly furrowed, arising from cordlike rhizomes 0.5–1.4 mm in
        diam.; perigynia appressed to weakly spreading, plano-convex, gradually tapering to ±
        prominent,</description>
      <determination>48. Carex parallela</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culms ± terete, scarcely furrowed, arising from threadlike rhizomes 0.3–0.8 mm in
        diam.; perigynia soon becoming widely spreading to reflexed, biconvex, abruptly contracted
        to short, glabrous or obscurely scabrid beak, beak 0.5 mm; transcontinental and including
        w</description>
      <determination>49. Carex gynocrates</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
