<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>A. A. Reznicek,Paul M. Catling</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="H. Christ ex Kükenthal in H. G. A. Engler" date="1909">Divisae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler, Pflanzenr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20[IV,38]: 119. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus carex;section Divisae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants not cespitose, sometimes colonial, long-rhizomatous; rhizomes with tight
    cortex, not detaching on drying, mostly more than 1 mm wide, covered with persistant scales.
    Culms brown at base, rough, scabrous-angled distally or not. Leaves: basal sheaths fibrous or
    not; sheath fronts membranous, with hyaline band; blades V-shaped in cross section when young or
    involute, widest leaves 1+ mm wide, glabrous. Inflorescences racemose, with 3–25+ spikes, ovoid
    to cylindric, often very condensed; proximal bracts scalelike or cuspidate, or absent,
    sheathless; spikes staminate, pistillate, or, sometimes, androgynous, sessile, without
    prophylls. Proximal pistillate scales with apex acuminate, cuspidate, or short-awned. Perigynia
    ascending to erect, both faces veined or veinless adaxially, often stipitate, ovate to narrowly
    ovate, plano-convex or biconvex, base rounded, ± spongy, margins acutely angled, apex tapering
    or contracted to beak, glabrous; beak 0.25–1.9 mm, at least 1/4 length of body, with abaxial
    suture, margins often serrulate, apex slightly bidentate. Stigmas 2. Achenes biconvex, smaller
    than bodies of perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">South Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>26i.</number>
  <discussion>Species 14 (6 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>The key to species in sect. Divisae integrates both pistillate and staminate features,
    but staminate specimens of the section can be more difficult to determine than pistillate ones,
    especially if the anthers have shed. Staminate culms are usually taller at flowering time than
    pistillate culms and often conspicuous because of their yellow anthers.</discussion>
  <discussion>Two types of rhizomes exist in the section. Rhizomes of Carex douglasii, C.
    duriuscula, and the Eurasian C. stenophylla are slender and terminate in a shoot or more often a
    cluster of shoots and do not produce shoots regularly along their length. Rhizomes of all other
    species are coarse, thick, and long creeping and form lines of shoots regularly along their
    entire length. Eurasian species with slender rhizomes also differ from most other species in the
    section in all having androgynous spikes and conspicuously spongy-based perigynia and occurring
    in dryland habitats. T. V. Egorova (1999) placed these species with slender rhizomes onto their
    own section, Boernera. Carex douglasii, however, is intermediate in some features, having
    unisexual inflorescences and perigynia not or little spongy-based, and frequently occurring in
    wetland habitats. One species, C. chordorrhiza, placed by Egorova in the section is excluded
    here because it has a dramatically different growth form with noncreeping rhizomes and elongate,
    leafy vegetative culms that become prostrate and root at the nodes.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culm angles smooth distally; inflorescences usually dense and headlike, usually 1 /
        2 + as wide as long (if pistillate); rhizomes slender, 0.6–1.9 mm thick, shoots often
        arising 2–several in a cluster and many nodes without shoots.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate scales (4.3–)4.7–7.5 mm, pale brown to ± whitish hyaline; spikes
        6–20(–25), usually entirely unisexual; perigynia (3–)3.5–4.2(–4.8) mm; beak (0.9–)1.2–1.9
        mm;</description>
      <determination>52. Carex douglasii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate scales 2.4–4.1 mm, reddish brown; spikes 3–8, androgynous; perigynia
        2.4–3.9 mm; beak 0.3–0.9 mm; anthers 1.4–3 mm, apiculus smooth to warty, very
        short</description>
      <determination>53. Carex duriuscula</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Culm angles at least slightly scabrous distally; inflorescences various; rhizomes
        coarse,</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynium beak 0.25–0.5 mm; apex of inner band of leaf sheath prolonged
        beyond</description>
      <determination>54. Carex simulata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynium beak 0.5–1.5 mm; apex of inner band of leaf sheath not prolonged beyond
        base of blade; anther apiculus bristly hairy (30X).</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales and spike bracts, at least at base, dark brown or purple-brown, very shiny,
        darker than the perigynia; inflorescences, if pistillate, compact and broadly
        ovoid;</description>
      <determination>55. Carex pansa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scales and spike bracts brown to pale yellowish to reddish brown, ± dull, same
        color as or lighter than perigynia; inflorescences usually elongate, ellipsoid to narrowly
        ovoid; not restricted to Pacific Northwest.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynium beak 1 / 4 – 1 / 2 length of body; spikes mostly 5–18, mostly
        entirely</description>
      <determination>56. Carex praegracilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynium beak 1 / 5 – 1 / 4 length of body; spikes mostly 3–10, androgynous;
        rare</description>
      <determination>57. Carex divisa</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
