<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>A. A. Reznicek</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">Ammoglochin</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Belg.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>146. 1827</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Carex;section Ammoglochin;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants not cespitose, sometimes extensively colonial, long-rhizomatous; rhizomes 1–3 mm thick, with persistent, brown scales, thin, loose cortex, easily detatched when dry. Culms brown or black at base. Leaves: basal sheaths eventually fibrous; sheath fronts membranous, distal leaves with narrow hyaline or whitish-hyaline band extending at least 1/2 sheath length; blades V-shaped in cross section when young, widest leaves 1+ mm, glabrous. Inflorescences racemose, with 3–25 spikes, ovoid to cylindric; proximal bracts scalelike, usually cuspidate, sheathless; lateral spikes pistillate, staminate, or androgynous, sessile, without prophylls; terminal spike pistillate or androgynous. Proximal pistillate scales with apex obtuse to acuminate or short-awned. Perigynia ascending, veined on both faces, sessile, lanceolate to broadly ovate, plano-convex, base rounded, not spongy, margins acutely angled, at least distally, winglike margins 0.1+ mm wide, apex abruptly contracted to beak, glabrous; beak more than 0.25 mm, with abaxial suture, margins often serrulate, apex bidentate. Stigmas 2. Achenes biconvex, smaller than bodies of perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate regions of the Northern Hemisphere.</description>
  <number>26j.</number>
  <discussion>Species 14 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynia thin-margined but without prominent, expanded wing; pistillate scales shorter</description>
      <determination>58. Carex siccata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynia thin-margined and prominently winged at base of beak; pistillate scales usually</description>
      <determination>59. Carex arenaria</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
