<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26k.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Macrocephalae</section_name>
    <section_authority>Kükenthal</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler, Pflanzenr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>20[IV,38]: 186. 1909</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>Joy Mastrogiuseppe</author>
  <description>Plants usually not cespitose, rhizomatous. Culms brown at base. Leaves: basal sheaths
    fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades V-shaped in cross section when young, widest leaves
    4–8 mm wide, glabrous. Inflorescences paniculate, with 20+ spikes, ovoid or oblong capitate,
    occasionally with proximal 1–2 spikes separated, sessile; proximal bracts leaflike or
    threadlike, sheathless; spikes staminate, pistillate, or androgynous, sessile, without
    prophylls. Proximal pistillate scales with apex awned. Perigynia ascending or at length
    spreading, veined on both faces, short-stipitate, narrowly ovate, thickly plano-convex in cross
    section, base tapering or rounded, with spongy tissue, margins serrulate-winged, apex tapering
    to beak, glabrous; beak with abaxial suture, margins entire, apex bidentate. Stigmas 3. Achenes
    rounded-trigonous, smaller than bodies of perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>e Asia.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms bluntly angled, smooth or, sometimes, weakly serrulate on 1 angle immediately
        proximal to inflorescences; proximal spikes appressed to ascending; proximal pistillate
        scales</statement>
      <determination>60. Carex kobomugi</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Culms sharply angled, at least 1 angle serrulate immediately proximal to
        inflorescences; proximal spikes ascending-spreading to spreading; proximal pistillate scales
        with awn to</statement>
      <determination>61. Carex macrocephala</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
