<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Drejer" date="unknown">vacillans</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in C. J. Hartman, Sv. Norsk Exc.-Fl.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>131. 1846</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Carex;species vacillans;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="E. Lepage" date="unknown">×subnigra</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Carex;species ×subnigra;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Kükenthal) E. Lepage" date="unknown">×super-goodenoughii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Carex;species ×super-goodenoughii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>174.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Carex vacillant</other_name>
  <discussion>Carex vacillans represents the apparently stabilized hybrid between C. nigra and C. paleacea. It occurs frequently within the common range of the two parents and is therefore considered to be a taxon of recent origin. Fertility is variable; most of the plants produce a few achenes. Carex vacillans represents almost all of what was previously known as C. recta, C. salina var. cuspidata, and C. salina var. fuliginea from the New England states, and about half of the reports of C. recta from the maritime provinces of Canada.</discussion>
  <discussion>The circumscription of Carex vacillans follows the concept of N. Hylander (1982) and A. O. Chater (1980). Carex vacillans as recognized by E. Hultén and M. Fries (1986), at least for North America, is synonymous with C. recta. Carex vacillans differs from C. recta in having dark scales with a narrow central stripe, papillose and veined perigynia with a frequently scabrous beak orifice, and dark, dull, invaginated achenes. Intergrading individuals seem to exist, mostly with C. paleacea; they require additional study. Some of the specimens determined as C. lyngbyei for eastern North America were re-identified as C. vacillans (J. Cayouette 1987).</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
