<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>197.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Carex</genus_name><species_name>aquatilis</species_name><species_authority>Wahlenberg</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Kongl. Vetensk. Acad. Nya Handl.</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>24: 165. 1803</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants not cespitose. Culms 20–150 cm. Leaves: basal sheaths red-brown or brown; sheaths of proximal leaves glabrous, fronts with indistinct spots, veinless, apex U-shaped; blades usually amphi-stomic, papillose on both surfaces. Inflorescences: proximal bract longer than inflorescence. Spikes: erect; proximal 2–6 spikes pistillate; terminal (1–)2–4 spikes staminate. Pistillate scales red-brown to purple-brown, apex obtuse or acute, awnless. Perigynia ascending, veinless, somewhat flattened, loosely enclosing achenes, ellipsoid or obovoid, dull, apex obtuse or acute, papillose. Achenes not constricted, glossy. 2n = 72–80.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Varieties 4 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution>North America</global_distribution><global_distribution>Europe.</global_distribution><discussion>Carex aquatilis is circumboreal and variable; four extensively intergrading varieties are recognized in North America. The species is distinguished by amphistomic (epistomic in var. dives) papillose leaves, glabrous sheaths with a concave apex, perigynia that lack veins and are usually brown-spotted on the proximal half, and have glossy achenes.</discussion><key><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikes pendent or the terminal erect; proximal peduncle to 11 cm; perigynia ellipsoid; beak purple-brown, 0.3–0.4 mm; culms scabrous on angles</statement>
      <determination>193b. Carex aquatilis var. dives</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Spikes erect; proximal peduncle not more than 4 cm; perigynia usually obovoid; beak pale or purple-brown, not more than 0.2 mm; culms glabrous or scabrous on angles.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pistillate scales pale brown with narrow red-brown margins and broad pale midvein</statement>
      <determination>197c. Carex aquatilis var. substricta</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pistillate scales red- or purple-brown and narrow pale midvein.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia pale brown; staminate spikes usu-</statement>
      <determination>197a. Carex aquatilis var. aquatilis</determination>
    </key_statement><key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia purple-brown on apical 1 / 2 ; staminate spikes usually 1–2</statement>
      <determination>197d. Carex aquatilis var. minor</determination>
    </key_statement></key></treatment>
