<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26x.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Glaucescentes</section_name>
    <section_authority>Reznicek</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 457. 2001</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>Lisa A. Standley</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <section_name>Pendulinae</section_name>
    <section_authority>Fries</section_authority>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants densely cespitose, in large clumps, short-rhizomatous; rhizomes brown or
    black, without yellow-brown felty covering. Culms reddish purple at base. Leaves: basal sheaths
    sometimes fibrous; sheath fronts reddish or green, veined, herbaceous; blades with 2 lateral
    adaxial veins more prominent than midvein, M-shaped in cross section when young, glabrous or
    scabrous, strongly glaucous. Inflorescences racemose, with 5–8 spikes; proximal bracts leaflike,
    long-sheathing, sheath shorter than diameter of stem; lateral spikes pistillate or some
    androgynous, pendent, pedunculate, prophyllate; terminal spikes usually staminate. Proximal
    pistillate scales with apex acute to acuminate or awned, awn to 3.5 mm; staminate scales awned.
    Perigynia divergent or ascending, weakly to strongly veined on faces, with 2 strong marginal
    veins, usually sessile, elliptic or ovate, trigonous in cross section, base tapering, apex
    abruptly beaked, glabrous, papillose; beak less than 5 mm, erose-ciliate to very shortly
    bidentate. Stigmas 3. Achenes trigonous, smaller than bodies of perigynia; style
    deciduous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 3 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>southeastern coastal plain</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>interior low plateau</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>and Piedmont plateau provinces of North America.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia prominently 6–8-veined; pistillate scale apex acute</statement>
      <determination>241. Carex joorii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia indistinctly veined or veinless; pistillate scales retuse.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Faces of perigynia weakly veined; achenes rhomboid, length and width equal;
        leaves</statement>
      <determination>242. Carex verrucosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Faces of the perigynia veinless or indistinctly 3 – 4-veined on each face; achenes
        ellipsoid,</statement>
      <determination>243. Carex glaucescens</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
