<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="L. H. Bailey" date="unknown">hassei</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Gaz.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>21: 5. 1896</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Carex;species hassei;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Mackenzie" date="unknown">saliniformis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Carex;species saliniformis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>246.</number>
  <discussion>Carex hassei probably occurs in Colorado.</discussion>
  <discussion>K. K. Mackenzie (1931–1935, parts 2–3, pp. 233–234) combined Carex hassei with C. garberi; a number of characteristics distinguish the two, though none gives an absolute separation. Eastern floras recognise C. garberi as a distinct species; recent western floras do not distinguish the two and some treat both as synonyms of C. aurea. Much western material of C. garberi has been determined as C. hassei; much material of C. hassei has in turn been determined as C. aurea. The two species are for the most part allopatric with an area of overlap in the northwestern United States and especially Oregon and Washington, where many of the populations show various combinations of the characters of C. aurea, C. hassei, and C. garberi</discussion>
  <discussion>The eastern limits of the distribution of Carex hassei are unclear. It appears to be very uncommon in the eastern part of its range, where it has been confused with C. aurea. Most specimens from that area were collected too early in the season for the distinctive fruit characteristics to have developed, so they are difficult to determine with certainty.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
