<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Scirpus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Makino" date="unknown">hattorianus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>J. Jap. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8: 44. 1933</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Scirpus;species hattorianus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Scirpus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Willdenow" date="unknown">atrovirens</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="Farwell" date="unknown">viviparus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Scirpus;species atrovirens;variety viviparus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>6.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Scirpe de Hattori</other_name>
  <discussion>Scirpus hattorianus has been confused in the past with both S. atrovirens and S. georgianus. Scirpus hattorianus tends to be a more slender plant, and the scales of its spikelets are usually black, not brown. The perianth bristles are superficially intermediate between the other two. They are typically shorter and more delicate than those of S. atrovirens. In S. hattorianus the longest bristles are usually only 0.6–0.8 times as long as the achene, and barbed in the distal (0.1–)0.2–0.4; in S. atrovirens the longest bristles are usually 0.9–1.2 times as long as the achene and barbed in the distal 0.3–0.6. Some individuals fall outside these ranges and identification must be based on comparison of all the characters mentioned in the key. Separation from S. georgianus is discussed under S. georgianus.</discussion>
  <discussion>Scirpus hattorianus occasionally hybridizes with S. ancistrochaetus, S. atrocinctus, S. atrovirens, S. georgianus, and S. pedicellatus. The name Scirpus peckii Britton has been applied to hybrids between S. hattorianus and S. atrocinctus or S. pedicellatus.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
