<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26cc.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Granulares</section_name>
    <section_authority>(O. Lang) Mackenzie</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in N. L. Britton et al., N. Amer. Fl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18: 260. 1935</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>Theodore S. Cochrane</author>
  <author>Robert F. C. Naczi</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <unranked_epithet_name>Granulares</unranked_epithet_name>
    <unranked_epithet_authority>O. Lang</unranked_epithet_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea </publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>24: 582. 1851</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants cespitose or not, short to long rhizomatous, sometimes inconspicuously
    rhizomatous. Culms sometimes solitary, brown at base. Leaves: basal sheaths not fibrous; sheath
    fronts membranous; blades M-shaped in cross section when young, adaxial side of blade with 2
    lateral veins more prominent than midvein, widest leaves not more than 10 mm wide, glabrous.
    Inflorescences racemose, with (2–)3–6 spikes; proximal nonbasal bracts leaflike, long-sheathing,
    sheath more than 4 mm, longer than diameter of stem; lateral spikes pistillate or androgynous,
    rarely distal 1–3 spikes staminate, sometimes some basal, pedunculate, prophyllate; terminal
    spike staminate. Proximal pistillate scales with apex acute, acuminate, or short-awned.
    Perigynia ascending to spreading, minute red-brown or yellowish streaks and dots, distinctly
    veined, sessile, ellipsoid or rhomboid to broadly ovoid, obovoid, or subglobose, obscurely
    trigonous to round in cross section, base rounded, apex rounded, abruptly beaked, glabrous; beak
    0.1–0.9 mm, orifice entire to minutely bidentulate, teeth 0–0.3 mm. Stigmas 3. Achenes
    trigonous, smaller than bodies of perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 6 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>temperate and subtropical regions of North America</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>s Mexico</global_distribution>
  <global_distribution>Central America (Guatemala).</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Carex sect. Granulares is a monophyletic section diagnosed by at least three
    apormorphies: red-brown or yellowish cells scattered in the epidermis of the perigynia, often 25
    or more perigynia per well-developed lateral spike, and perigynia loosely enveloping the achenes
    (R. F. C. Naczi 1992, 1997). Recent phylogenetic analyses indicate section Granulares is the
    sister group of a clade composed of sections Careyanae and Griseae (R. F. C. Naczi
    1992).</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants with short or inconspicuous rhizomes; culms in tufts; terminal spike and
        distal lateral spike usually overlapping; proximal spikes usually arising from distal 1 / 2
        of culms.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves green, not glaucous; longest bract blade (per plant) of distal lateral spike
        1.6–4.6(–7.1) cm; ligule of proximal bract 0.5–6.5 mm; perigynia (1.6–)1.9–3 times as
        long</statement>
      <determination>274. Carex gholsonii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves not green, usually glaucous; longest bract blade (per plant) of distal
        lateral spike 4.1–15.8 cm; ligule of proximal bract (2–)3–17.5(–26) mm; perigynia
        1.4–2.2(–2.4)</statement>
      <determination>275. Carex granularis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Plants with long-creeping rhizomes; culms mostly solitary; terminal spike and
        distal lateral spike (unless staminate) usually separated; proximal spikes usually arising
        from proximal 1 / 2 of culms.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate scales with apex acute to awned; widest leaves 2.8–8.3 mm wide;
        perigynium</statement>
      <determination>276. Carex microdonta</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Staminate scales with apex rounded to obtuse; widest leaves 1.8–3(–4.4) mm
        wide;</statement>
      <determination>277. Carex crawei</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
