<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Willdenow" date="unknown">conoidea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4(1): 280. 1805</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Carex;species conoidea;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Fernald" date="unknown">katahdinensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Carex;species katahdinensis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>301.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Carex conoïde</other_name>
  <discussion>Carex conoidea is an uncommon plant throughout most of its wide range and is most frequent in New England. The species has been collected once in Arizona, where it is likely an introduction and does not appear to be persisting. Carex conoidea is unusual in Carex sect. Griseae in inhabiting open sites; it is the only species of the section regularly found in sunny habitats. Carex conoidea often grows with C. buxbaumii, C. tetanica, and C. pallescens.</discussion>
  <discussion>Several previous authors have regarded Carex katahdinensis as distinct from C. conoidea. The name C. katahdinensis applies to dwarf plants of C. conoidea in the northern portions of its range. Carex conoidea exhibits clinal variation in several morphologic characters, including those used to recognize C. katahdinensis. Plants from higher latitudes are smaller in most features than plants from father south, but environmental factors also account for the morphology of plants matching the description of C. katahdinensis. Invariably, these plants have been collected from habitats with drastically fluctuating water levels, such as lake, pond, and river shores. The dwarfed morphology appears to be adaptive for rapid completion of the life cycle in such habitats.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
