<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="F. J. Hermann" date="unknown">roanensis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Castanea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12: 113. 1948</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Carex;species roanensis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>311.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Roan Mountain sedge</other_name>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern;</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex roanensis, a problematic taxon, has not been recollected from its type locality, although a second collection from Spivey Falls, about 37 km west-southwest of Roan Mountain (J. A. Churchill and K. Wurdack 1986) and several recent collections in Virginia have now been referred to this species (T. F. Wieboldt et al. 1998). Similarities to Carex virescens have been noted by all those who have investigated this species. Carex roanensis may be simply a form of C. virescens with longer-sheathing proximal inflorescence bracts, or possibly a form of C. aestivalis with pubescent perigynia and broader leaves. These characters are variable both among and within populations. However, perigynia are also somewhat larger in C. roanensis, and several puzzling specimens from Virginia and North Carolina that appear to be C. aestivalis with large perigynia further confuse the situation. Further study is required before the status of C. roanensis can be decided.</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex roanensis is in the Center for Plant Conservation’s National Collection of Endangered Plants.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
