<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="(Drejer) L. H. Bailey in J. M. Coulter" date="1885">hymenochlaenae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="1803">debilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 172. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus carex;section hymenochlaenae;species debilis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants densely cespitose. Culms dark maroon at base; flowering stems 25–100 cm, as long as leaves at maturity or often longer, 0.5–1 mm thick, glabrous but scabrous within inflorescence. Leaves: basal sheaths maroon, bladeless, glabrous or rarely minutely pubescent; others grading from maroon to green on back, pale brown-hyaline or reddish brown on front, often red dotted, sometimes finely pubescent; blades flat, 2–7 mm wide, glabrous on both surfaces, margins and abaxial midribs often finely scabrous. Inflorescences: peduncles of lateral spikes slender, to 50 mm, usually shorter than spikes or only slightly longer, scabrous; of terminal spike 15–50 mm, finely scabrous; proximal bracts longer, or more often, shorter than inflorescences; sheaths 1–7 cm; blades 1–3.5 mm wide. Lateral spikes 2–5, 1 per node, well separated, erect at anthesis, soon nodding, pistillate with 10–25 perigynia attached 2–9 mm apart, linear, 25–80 × 2–3 mm. Terminal spike staminate or sometimes gynecandrous with a few pistillate flowers distally; 15–50 × 0.6–1.2 mm. Pistillate scales white-hyaline, sometimes tinged with pale brown or suffused with chestnut, with broad green midrib, finely red dotted, oblong, 2.8–6 mm, much shorter than mature perigynia, apex obtuse, acute or cuspidate, awn to 0.2 mm, glabrous, distal margin ciliate. Perigynia green to olive-green, usually red dotted, prominently 2-ribbed, finely 12–20-veined, loosely enveloping achene, fusiform to lance-ovoid, 5–9.5 × 1.1–2.2 mm, membranous, base acute, apex tapering gradually to abruptly contracted beak, glabrous or short-pubescent; beak bidentate 0.7–2 mm, including teeth to 1 mm. Achenes stipitate, 1.9–2.5 × 1–1.5 mm, stipe 0.5–1.5 mm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e North America.</description>
  <number>315.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">White-edge sedge</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">weak sedge</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex debilis is extremely variable and has been variously subdivided into as many as six varieties or three subspecies. Only two weakly differentiated varieties can be maintained: the typical variety with broadly southern distribution and C. debilis var. rudgei, which replaces it in the Northeast, the Midwest, and the eastern mountains. Both varieties appear to hybridize with C. virescens but these hybrids have not been studied to confirm parentage.</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynia fusiform, 5.5–9.5 mm, tapering very gradually to elongate beak; pistillate scales usually with apex blunt to acute, rarely cuspidate, white or very pale hyaline margins</description>
      <determination>315a. Carex debilis var. debilis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynia lance-ellipsoid, 5–6.2 mm, more abruptly narrowed to beak; pistillate scales with apex acute to cuspidate to short-awned, hyaline margins usually suffused or streaked with reddish</description>
      <determination>315b. Carex debilis var. rudgei</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
