<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">CYPERACEAE</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Buckley" date="unknown">misera</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Amer. J. Sci. Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>45: 173. 1843</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family CYPERACEAE;genus Carex;species misera;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants densely cespitose. Culms dark maroon at base; flowering stems 25–50 cm, as long or slightly longer than leaves at maturity, 0.4–0.6 mm thick, glabrous, sometimes scabrous on angles within inflorescence. Leaves: basal sheaths maroon, bladeless, pubescent, often only sparsely so; others grading from maroon to green on back, brown-hyaline on front, red dotted and pubescent toward apex; blades flat, 1–2 mm wide, sparsely pilose on adaxial surface, margins ciliate. Inflorescences: peduncles of lateral spike 0–35 mm; peduncle of terminal spike 5–35 mm, minutely scabrous; proximal bracts equaling or often exceeding inflorescences; sheathless and auriculate or with sheaths less than 3 mm; blades to 1 mm wide. Lateral spikes 1–3, 1 per node, each overlapping 1 above but not crowded, proximal 1 often well separated, erect to ascending, sessile or pedunculate, pistillate with 10–25 perigynia attached less than 1 mm apart, narrowly elongate, 10–35 × 2–3 mm. Terminal spike staminate, 10–24 × 1.5–2.5 mm. Pistillate scales reddish brown with narrow hyaline margins and green midrib, ovate, shorter than mature perigynia, apex rounded to acute or cuspidate, glabrous. Perigynia green, usually red dotted, 2-ribbed and conspicuously 6–10-veined, narrowly lance-ellipsoid, loosely enveloping achene, 4–4.8 × 1.2–1.5 mm, membranous, base with stipe 1 mm, apex gradually tapering to beak, pubescent toward apex; beak truncate or minutely toothed, 1 mm. Achenes substipitate, 2–2.5 × 0.8–1 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology" scope="fruiting">summer</description>
  <description type="phenology" scope="fruiting">jun</description>
  <description type="phenology" scope="fruiting">jul</description>
  <description type="phenology" scope="fruiting">aug</description>
  <description type="habitat">rock ledges</description>
  <description type="habitat">cliffs</description>
  <description type="habitat">balds in s appalachians</description>
  <description type="elevation">900–1900;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tenn.</description>
  <number>318.</number>
  <other_name type="past_name">miser</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">Wretched sedge</other_name>
  <references>
    <reference>Schell, C. M. and M. J. Waterway. 1992. Allozyme variation and the genetic structure of populations of the rare sedge Carex misera (Cyperaceae). Pl. Spec. Biol. 7: 141–150.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
