<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>332.</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Carex</genus_name><species_name>fissuricola</species_name><species_authority>Mackenzie</species_authority><place_of_publication>
    <publication_title>Muhlenbergia</publication_title>
    <place_in_publication>5: 53. 1909</place_in_publication>
  </place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Carex</genus_name><species_name>ablata</species_name><species_authority>L. H. Bailey</species_authority><variety_name>luzuliformis</variety_name><variety_authority>L. H. Bailey</variety_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants densely or loosely cespitose; rhizomes thick, short. Culms to 80 cm. Leaves: blades 3–8 mm wide. Inflorescences with 3–5 spikes; peduncles of proximal spikes exserted more than 1 cm; proximal bracts with blade (10–) 15–50 mm, sheaths cylindric to ± expanded to mouth, 20–37 mm, mouth with narrow, ± purple band at top, usually Y- or V-shaped, mouth 0.7–1.8 mm wide. Lateral spikes pistillate or often androgynous, purple to brown, proximal spikes pendent to erect, 14–25 × 4–7 mm. Terminal spike staminate or androgynous, ± erect, 10–21 × 4.5–6 mm. Pistillate scales purple or brown with pale, usually indistinctly veined, ovate to elliptic, 2.3–3.8 × 0.8–1.7 mm, midvein and margins ciliate, apex obtuse to short-awned. Staminate scales purple or reddish brown with pale midvein, ovate to obovate, 3–4.4 × 1–1.4 mm, margins slightly ciliate, apex obtuse. Anthers 1.5–3 mm. Perigynia ascending, usually purple or red-brown, veins usually indistinct, ovate to elliptic, 3.2–5.5 × 0.9–1.7(–2) mm, margins flat, less than 1/2 mature achene width, margins setose-ciliate distally, usually at least sparsely hispidulous to shortly setose; beak ± distinct, apex brown to purple, setose-ciliate, distance from beak tip to achene apex usually more than 2 mm. Achenes obovoid, body 1.5–2 × 0.8–1 mm.</description><phenology_fruiting>summer</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jun</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>jul</phenology_fruiting><phenology_fruiting>aug</phenology_fruiting><habitat>meadows</habitat><habitat>rocky stream banks</habitat><elevation>1500–3500 m;</elevation><us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution><us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution><us_distribution>Utah.</us_distribution><discussion>Carex fissuricola is intermediate between C. luzulifolia and C. luzulina. A population in Lemhi County, Idaho, has the terminal spike gynecandrous and the perigynium glabrous or subglabrous. It is tentatively included in C. fissuricola.</discussion></treatment>
