<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Peter W. Ball</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Reznicek" date="2001">Hirtifoliae</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Novon</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>11: 458. 2001</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus carex;section Hirtifoliae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants loosely cespitose, short-rhizomatous. Culms red-brown at base. Leaves: basal
        sheaths not fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades M-shaped in cross section when young,
        adaxial surface with 2 lateral veins more prominent than midvein, pilose. Inflorescences
        racemose, with 2–5 spikes; proximal bracts sheathless or sheath less than 4 mm; lateral
        spikes pistillate, subsessile or short-pedunculate not more than 1 cm, prophyllate; terminal
        spikes staminate. Proximal pistillate scales with apex awned, glabrous. Perigynia ascending,
        veinless except for 2 strong marginal veins, stipitate, ellipsoid-obovoid, trigonous in
        cross section, less than 10 mm, base rounded, apex abruptly contracted to beak, pilose; beak
        0.7–1.5 mm, bidentate, teeth less than 0.8 mm. Stigmas 3. Achenes trigonous, nearly as large
        as bodies of perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">temperate e North America.</description>
  <number>26nn.</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex sect. Hirtifoliae was included by K. K. Mackenzie (1931–1935, parts 2–3, pp.
        215–219) in C. sect. Triquetrae; it is easily distinguished from that section
        morphologically, and it is also ecologically and geographically anomalous in that section.
        Its relationships are unclear, but it is similar to C. sect. Hymenochlaenae in many
        respects.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
