<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="G. Don in J. C. Loudon" date="1830">paludosae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Steudel" date="1855">hyalinolepis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Pl. Glumac.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 235. 1855</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus carex;section paludosae;species hyalinolepis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants colonial; rhizomes long-creeping. Culms central, coarse, trigonous, 40–110 cm, smooth. Leaves: basal sheaths pale green to brownish or pale red tinged, base with marescent remains of previous year’s leaves; longest ligules 2–10(–12) mm, less than 2 times longer than wide; blades glaucous, flat to V-shaped, (4–)5.5–13 mm wide, glabrous. Inflorescences 15–50 cm; proximal 2–4 spikes pistillate, ascending to arching; distal spikes erect; terminal 3–6 spikes staminate. Pistillate scales lanceolate to ovate, apex obtuse to acute, glabrous, awn 0.9–8.5 mm, scabrous. Perigynia ascending, obscurely 10–15-veined, veins somewhat impressed, narrowly ovoid, (4.5–)5.5–7.7 × 1.6–3 mm, glabrous; beak obscure, 0.9–1.7 mm, bidentulate, teeth straight, 0.4–0.8 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Fruiting Apr–Jul.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Swamp forests, river bottoms, shores of streams, ponds and lakes, wet meadows, often in clay soils, seasonally moist sites;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0–400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont.; Ark., Fla., Ga., Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Ky., La., Md., Mich., Miss., Mo., Nebr., N.C., Ohio, Okla., Pa., S.C., Tex., Va.</description>
  <number>355.</number>
  <discussion>Carex hyalinolepis is abundant in the Mississippi lowlands and often dominant in the understory of open, wet floodplain forests and bottomland meadows. It is a rapid invader of ditches and other disturbed areas. Sometimes extensive stands are seen without fertile culms.</discussion>
  <discussion>Occasionally, Carex hyalinolepis hybridizes with C. pellita (= C. ×subimpressa Clokey, according to A. A. Reznicek and P. M. Catling 1986), and rarely with C. lacustris. Carex ×subimpressa is sufficiently frequent that it has been treated as a species in some floras. It can form large colonies in suitable sites.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
