<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="unknown" date="unknown">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Sprengel" date="1826">atherodes</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syst. Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 828. 1826</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus carex;section carex;species atherodes</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Culms hollow, ± spongy near base, trigonous in cross section, 35–125 cm; vegetative
        culms hollow, flattened when pressed, taller than fertile culms. Leaves: basal sheaths
        reddish purple, inner bands fibrillose with age; sheaths with apex of inner band pale brown
        to dull reddish purple, pubescent or scabrous, at least apically, rarely glabrous; ligules
        (6–)11–45 mm; blades 3–10 mm wide, usually sparsely to moderately long-pubescent, finely
        papillose abaxially, glabrous adaxially. Inflorescences 12–60 cm; spikes erect or ascending;
        proximal 2–5 spikes pistillate; terminal (1–)2–6 spikes staminate. Pistillate scales
        lanceolate to narrowly ovate, apex acute, conspicuously scabrous-awned, glabrous or scabrous
        near midrib. Staminate scales lanceolate to narrowly ovate, apex obtuse to acuminate,
        scabrous-awned, glabrous or, rarely, sparsely pubescent. Perigynia 12–21-veined, (6.5–)7–12
        × 1.8–3.8 mm, glabrous; beak 2.1–4 mm, glabrous (rarely few spreading hairs on main veins),
        teeth spreading to outcurved, (1.2–)1.5–3 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Fruiting Jun–Aug.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Marshes, wet prairies and meadows, open swamps, wet, open thickets, open stream, pond, and lakeshores, ditches, often in water (to 60–80 cm deep);</description>
  <description type="elevation">50–2800 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Man., N.W.T., Ont., Que., Sask., Yukon; Alaska, Ariz., Calif., Colo., Idaho, Ill., Ind., Iowa, Maine, Mich., Minn., Mo., Mont., Nebr., Nev., N.Mex., N.Y., N.Dak., Ohio, Oreg., Pa., S.Dak., Utah, Vt., Va., Wash., W.Va., Wis., Wyo.; Eurasia.</description>
  <number>368.</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Carex épi-de-blé</other_name>
  <discussion>Carex atherodes is a major wetland species in portions of the Midwest and West and
        becomes increasingly uncommon and local in the eastern portions of its range. It forms large
        clones and can tolerate deeper water than most Carex. Glabrous forms occur and seem to be
        more common in the western portion of the range.</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex atherodes rarely hybridizes with C. trichocarpa.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
