<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="R. Brown" date="1810">eleocharis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="unknown" date="unknown">eleocharis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="series" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eleocharis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus eleocharis;section eleocharis;series Eleocharis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, often mat-forming, never stoloniferous or proliferating from
        spikelets. Rhizomes horizontal and long, or ascending and caudexlike. Culms 0.3–5 mm wide;
        distal leaf sheaths usually persistent, rarely disintegrating, papery to membranous, apex
        subtruncate to sometimes acute, tooth sometimes present. Spikelets: floral scales membranous
        to thinly papery; proximal scales empty. Flowers: styles 2-fid to 3-fid. Achenes yellow,
        orange, brown or greenish, biconvex, trigonous, or sometimes nearly terete, smooth at 30X,
        or rugulose or cancellate or reticulate at 10–30X. Tubercles distinct from achene summit in
        texture and/or color and form.</description>
  <description type="distribution">worldwide.</description>
  <number>8a1a.</number>
  <discussion>Species ca. 70 (22 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Eleocharis subg. Eleocharis ser. Eleocharis has been called by the invalid names
        Eleocharis ser. Palustriformes Svenson and E. sect. Palustriformes Zinserling. Species 1–7
        belong to subser. Eleocharis (= E. ser. Palustriformes subser. Palustres Svenson, name
        invalid), which comprise the extremely difficult “E. palustris complex” (M. L. Fernald and
        A. E. Brackett 1929; L. J. Harms 1968; S.-O. Strandhede 1966; H. K. Svenson 1947); see 1. E.
        palustris for a discussion of this complex. Species 8–22 belong to subser. Truncatae
        Svenson, within which species 16–21 comprise the extremely difficult “E. tenuis complex” (L.
        J. Harms 1972); see 17. E. compressa for a discussion of this complex.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. and A. E. Brackett. 1929. The representatives
            of Eleocharis palustris in North America. Rhodora 31: 57–77.</reference>
    <reference>Harms, L. J. 1968. Cytotaxonomic studies in Eleocharis subser. Palustres: Central
            United States taxa. Amer. J. Bot. 55: 966–974.</reference>
    <reference>Harms, L. J. 1972. Cytotaxonomy of the Eleocharis tenuis complex. Amer. J. Bot.
            59: 483–487.</reference>
    <reference>Strandhede, S.-O. 1965. Chromosome studies in Eleocharis subser. Palustres. III.
            Observations on western European taxa. Opera Bot. 9(2): 1–86.</reference>
    <reference>Strandhede, S.-O. 1966. Morphologic variation and taxonomy in European Eleocharis
            subser. Palustres. Opera Bot. 10(2): 1–187.</reference>
    <reference>Strandhede, S.-O. 1967. Eleocharis subser. Eleocharis in North America:
            Taxonomical comments and chromosome numbers. Bot. Not. 120: 355–368.</reference>
    <reference>Svenson, H. K. 1947. The group of Eleocharis palustris in North America.
            Rhodora 49: 61–67.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
