<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26uu.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Squarrosae</section_name>
    <section_authority>J. Carey</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Carices North. U.S.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>564. 1847</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>Bruce A. Ford</author>
  <author>A. A. Reznicek</author>
  <description>Plants cespitose or colonial, short to long rhizomatous. Culms brown or red-brown at
    base. Leaves: basal sheaths not fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades septate-nodulose,
    usually V-shaped in cross section when young, usually glabrous. Inflorescences single spike or
    racemose, with 2–9 spikes; proximal bracts leaflike or threadlike, sheathless or sheath longer
    than diameter of stem, at least 3 times as long as inflorescence; lateral spikes pistillate or
    infrequently gynecandrous, larger spikes usually with more than 50 perigynia, pedunculate,
    prophyllate; terminal spike staminate or gyncecandrous. Proximal pistillate scales sometimes
    with narrow, indistinct body, apex obtuse to awned. Perigynia ascending to spreading,
    many-veined, sessile or shortly stipitate, inflated, obconic, round in cross section, not more
    than 10 mm, base tapering or rounded-tapering, apex truncate, abruptly beaked, glabrous; beak
    1.2–3.8, bidentate, teeth 0.3 mm or longer. Stigmas 3. Achenes trigonous, 1.2–3 mm, smaller than
    bodies of perigynia; style persistent or deciduous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species 4 (4 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <global_distribution>temperate regions of e and mid w North America and temperate South
    America.</global_distribution>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Terminal spike largely staminate; pistillate scales with long awns, exceeding
        perigynia bodies; achenes 1.2–2.1 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pistillate scales with narrow, indistinct body, 0.1–0.4 mm wide; staminate scales
        linear, 0.3–0.8 mm wide, loosely, irregularly imbricated with tips spreading; plants
        cespitose,</statement>
      <determination>403. Carex frankii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Pistillate scales with wider, translucent body, 0.4–0.9(–1.1) mm wide; staminate
        scales lanceolate, narrowly ovate, or oblong-obovate, 0.9–1.6 mm wide, ± tightly imbricate
        in</statement>
      <determination>404. Carex aureolensis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Terminal spike gynecandrous; pistillate scales with short awns or awnless,
        completely hidden by perigynia; achenes 2–3 mm.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Style persistent, sinuous; achenes 1.9–2.5 times as long as wide; spikes 1–2(–3)
        per stem; pistillate portion of spike ovate to oblong; perigynia widely radiating, the
        proxi-</statement>
      <determination>405. Carex squarrosa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <statement>Style deciduous, straight; achenes 1.2–1.9 times as long as wide; spikes
        (1–)2–4(–6) per stem; pistillate portion of spike oblong to elliptic; perigynia, including
        the proximal,</statement>
      <determination>406. Carex typhina</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
