<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
  <number>26ww.</number>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority>
    <section_name>Spirostachyae</section_name>
    <section_authority>(Drejer) L. H. Bailey</section_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. M. Coulter, Man. Bot. Rocky Mt.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>381. 1885</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <author>William J. Crins</author>
  <author>A. A. Reznicek</author>
  <TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM">
    <genus_name>Carex</genus_name>
    <unranked_epithet_name>Spirostachyae</unranked_epithet_name>
    <unranked_epithet_authority>Drejer</unranked_epithet_authority>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Symb. Caricol., </publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>10. 1844</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
  </TaxonIdentification>
  <description>Plants cespitose, short-rhizomatous. Culms red-brown at base. Leaves: basal sheaths
    not fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades not or sparingly septate-nodulose, V-shaped in
    cross section when young, glabrous. Inflorescences racemose, with 3–6 spikes; proximal nonbasal
    bracts leaflike, long-sheathing, sheath 4+ mm, longer than diameter of stem; lateral spikes
    pistillate, pedunculate, peduncle usually not longer than spike, prophyllate; terminal spike
    staminate. Proximal pistillate scales with apex acute or cuspidate. Perigynia ascending or
    spreading, yellow-or gray-green or brown, usually speckled reddish brown, strongly 10–16-veined,
    elliptic or ovate, rounded-trigonous in cross section, base cuneate, apex tapering to beak,
    glabrous; beak 0.4–1.4 mm, bidentate, teeth 0.2–0.4 mm. Stigmas 3. Achenes trigonous, smaller
    than bodies of perigynia; style deciduous.</description>
  <number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 15 (3 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa>
  <introduced>introduced;</introduced>
  <global_distribution>Eurasia.</global_distribution>
  <discussion>Carex sect. Spirostachyae is closely related to sect. Ceratocystis Dumortier and has
    often been included with it under the name “Extensae.” W. J. Crins and P. W. Ball (1988)
    clarified the distinctions between the two sections.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference> Crins, W. J. and P. W. Ball. 1988. Sectional limits and
      phylogenetic considerations in Carex section Ceratocystis (Cyperaceae). Brittonia 40:
      38–47.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves of flowering stems channelled or involute, widest blades 1–3.5(–4.3) mm
        wide; distal 2–3 pistillate spikes usually clustered near stem apex beside staminate spike;
        staminate spikes</statement>
      <determination>408. Carex extensa</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <statement>Leaves of flowering stems flat, widest blades 3.3–5 mm wide; pistillate spikes
        widely spaced, with at most 1 or 2 near, but not clustered about, staminate spike; staminate
        spikes on peduncles 1–5(–8.5) cm; proximal bract shorter than to no more than 1.5 times as
        long as inflorescence.</statement>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia 3.5–4.6 mm, apex contracted; beak (0.8–)1–1.4 mm, scabrous; proximal
        bract usually shorter than the inflorescence; longer peduncles of staminate spikes
        2–5(–8.5)</statement>
      <determination>409. Carex distans</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <statement>Perigynia 2.6–3.5 mm, apex gradually tapered; beak 0.4–0.7 mm, smooth; proximal
        bract mostly equaling or exceeding inflorescence; longer peduncles of staminate spikes
        1–2(–4) cm; distal 1–2 pistillate spikes usually aggregated near staminate spike;
        leaves</statement>
      <determination>410. Carex diluta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</treatment>
