<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>William J. Crins</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Jussieu" date="unknown">cyperaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="1754">carex</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="section" authority="Dumortier" date="1827">Ceratocystis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Belg.,</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>147. 1827</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family cyperaceae;genus carex;section Ceratocystis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose or not, short-rhizomatous. Culms brown at base. Leaves: basal
    sheaths not fibrous; sheath fronts membranous; blades sparsely septate-nodulose, usually
    V-shaped in cross section when young, glabrous. Inflorescences racemose, with 2–6 spikes;
    proximal nonbasal bracts leaflike, long-sheathing, shorter or longer than diameter of stem;
    lateral spikes pistillate, rarely distal androgynous, larger spikes with not more than 40
    perigynia, dense, pedunculate, prophyllate; terminal spike staminate or, occasionally,
    androgynous. Proximal pistillate scales with apex obtuse, acute, or cuspidate. Perigynia
    ascending, spreading, or reflexed, proximal and middle perigyinia separated by internodes less
    than 1/10 their length, yellow-brown to brown, strongly veined on faces, slightly stipitate,
    obovoid or, rarely, narrowly ovoid, rounded-trigonous, less than 10 mm, base tapering to
    rounded, apex abruptly contracted or, rarely, tapering to beak, glabrous; beak bidentate, teeth
    less than 0.5 mm. Stigmas 3. Achenes trigonous, 1–2 mm, smaller than bodies of perigynia; style
    deciduous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumboreal, north and south temperate regions in North America, Europe, Asia, Australia.</description>
  <number>26xx.</number>
  <discussion>Species 7 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <discussion>Sterile hybrids regularly form among species of Carex sect. Ceratocystis. These
    include Carex hostiana × C. flava (= C. ×xanthocarpa Dégland), C. hostiana × C. viridula (= C.
    ×fulva Goodenough), C. flava × C. viridula (= C. ×ruedtii Kneucker), and C. cryptolepis × C.
    viridula.</discussion>
  <discussion>Some taxa included within C. viridula have been treated as species. Hybrids that form
    among these taxa (subspecies and varieties) are partially fertile, indicating that they have not
    diverged widely enough to be reproductively isolated. Their morphologic variation patterns also
    overlap (W. J. Crins and P. W. Ball 1989).</discussion>
  <discussion>Carex sect. Ceratocystis is most closely related to sect. Spirostachyae (Drejer) L. H.
    Bailey, an Old World group with three introduced species in North America. These sections often
    have been combined as sect. Extensae Fries (a later name), but several characteristics
    distinguish the sections (W. J. Crins and P. W. Ball 1988).</discussion>
  <discussion>In the keys that follow, curvature of the perigynium beak is measured as the angle
    formed by the junction of a straight line through the beak with a straight line through the
    abaxial portion of the perigynium body. Perigynium length includes the body and beak, unless
    noted otherwise.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Crins, W. J. and P. W. Ball. 1988. Sectional limits and
      phylogenetic considerations in Carex section Ceratocystis (Cyperaceae). Brittonia 40:
      38–47.</reference>
    <reference>Crins, W. J. and P. W. Ball. 1989. Taxonomy of the Carex flava complex
      (Cyperaceae) in North America and northern Eurasia. II. Taxonomic treatment. Canad. J. Bot.
      67: 1048–1065.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants not cespitose, with short, stout, horizontal rhizomes; inner band of bract
        sheaths with convex projections to 3.2 mm; scales dark brown with conspicuous white
        borders;</description>
      <determination>411. Carex hostiana</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Plants cespitose; inner band of bract sheaths truncate or concave; scales yellowish
        green to reddish brown with inconspicuous hyaline borders; perigynia (in fruit) spreading or
        reflexed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Perigynia spreading; beak straight or forming angle less than 25 ° with body;
        ligules on</description>
      <determination>415. Carex viridula (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Proximal perigynia reflexed; perigynium beak forming angle usually greater than 20
        ° with body; ligules on distal cauline leaves truncate or rounded, well
        developed.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate scales yellowish green, similar in color to perigynia.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tallest culms 25 – 50 cm; proximal pistillate spike bracts 1.5 – 4 times as long as
        inflorescences; peduncles of staminate spikes 0.2 – 0.5 length of staminate
        spikes;</description>
      <determination>413. Carex cryptolepis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Tallest culms 65–125 cm; proximal pistillate spike bracts 0.5 – 1.3( – 1.9) times
        as long as inflorescences; peduncles of staminate spikes mostly 0.7 – 2.5 length of
        staminate spikes; perigynium beak usually sparsely scabrous; achenes 1.2 –</description>
      <determination>414. Carex lutea</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Pistillate scales brownish, contrasting with yellowish green perigynia.</description>
      <next_statement_id>5.</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate spikes sessile or short-pedunculate, peduncles usually less than 5 mm;
        cauline leaves usually nearly as long as culms; perigynium beak conspicu-</description>
      <determination>412. Carex flava</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>5.</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate spikes on peduncles usually more than 4.5 mm; cauline leaves 0.5 times as
        long as culms or less; perigynium beak weakly scabrous, usually less</description>
      <determination>415. Carex viridula (in part)</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
