<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment>
    <number>3.</number>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED">
        <genus_name>Eleocharis</genus_name>
        <species_name>macrostachya</species_name>
        <species_authority>Britton</species_authority>
        <place_of_publication>
            <publication_title>in J. K. Small, Fl. S.E. U.S.,</publication_title>
            <place_in_publication>184, 1327. 1903</place_in_publication>
        </place_of_publication>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <common_name>Éléocharide à gros épi</common_name>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Eleocharis</genus_name>
        <species_name>perlonga</species_name>
        <species_authority>Fernald &amp; Brackett</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM">
        <genus_name>Eleocharis</genus_name>
        <species_name>xyridiformis</species_name>
        <species_authority>Fernald &amp; Brackett</species_authority>
    </TaxonIdentification>
    <description>Plants perennial, mat-forming; rhizomes evident, long, 1–2 mm thick, firm, cortex
        persistent, longer internodes 10–55 mm, scales often fugaceous, 5–10 mm, membranous, not
        fibrous. Culms terete to markedly compressed, to 3 times wider than thick, often with to 25
        blunt ridges when dry, 10–100 cm × 0.5–2.5(–3.5) mm, firm (to soft), internally spongy.
        Leaves: distal leaf sheaths persistent, rarely splitting abaxially, proximally mostly red,
        distally green (or red), papery (to membranous), apex truncate to obtuse, tooth sometimes
        present on some or all culms, 0.1–0.6(–1) mm. Spikelets narrowly lanceoloid to ovoid, 5–40 ×
        2–5 mm, acute, rarely obtuse; proximal scale clasping (2/3–)3/4 or more of culm to
        amplexicaulous, usually variably in same plant; subproximal scale empty or with flower,
        usually empty in some spikelets and with flower in other spikelets in same plant; floral
        scales deciduous, often spreading in fruit, 30–80, 3–5 per mm of rachilla, medium brown,
        sometimes red-brown or dark chestnut-brown, midrib regions often stramineous to green, ovate
        to narrowly lanceolate, 2.5–5.5 × 1.5–2.5 mm, entire, mostly carinate in distal part of
        spikelet. Flowers: perianth bristles 4(–5), sometimes rudimentary or absent, brown, slender
        to stout, much shorter than achene to equaling tubercle; stamens 3; anthers dark yellow to
        orange-brown, 1.3–2.7 mm; styles 2-fid. Achenes not persistent, yellow maturing to
        yellow-brown or dark brown, ellipsoid, obovoid, or obpyriform, biconvex to plano-convex,
        angles obscure, 1.1–1.9 × 0.8–1.5 mm, apex rounded, neck absent or short, smooth at 30X, or
        finely rugulose at 10–20X with 20 or more horizontal ridges in a vertical series. Tubercles
        brown to whitish, pyramidal, as high as or sometimes much higher than wide, 0.35–0.7 ×
        0.25–0.7 mm. 2n = 18, 19, 38.</description>
    <phenology_fruiting>spring</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>mar</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>apr</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>may</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>summer</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>jun</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>jul</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>aug</phenology_fruiting>
    <phenology_fruiting>all year in s texas and louisiana</phenology_fruiting>
    <habitat>fresh to slightly brackish or alkaline
        shores</habitat>
    <habitat>stream beds</habitat>
    <habitat>swales</habitat>
    <habitat>vernal pools</habitat>
    <habitat>pastures</habitat>
    <habitat>ditches</habitat>
    <habitat>artificial ponds</habitat>
    <elevation>10–2300 m;</elevation>
    <ca_distribution>Alta.</ca_distribution>
    <ca_distribution>B.C.</ca_distribution>
    <ca_distribution>Man.</ca_distribution>
    <ca_distribution>Ont.</ca_distribution>
    <ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution>
    <ca_distribution>Yukon</ca_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Alaska</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Ariz.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Ark.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Calif.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Colo.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Idaho</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Ill.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Iowa</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Kans.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>La.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Minn.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Miss.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Mo.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Mont.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Nebr.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Nev.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>N.Mex.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>N.Dak.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Okla.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Oreg.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>S. Dak.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Utah</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Wash.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Wis.</us_distribution>
    <us_distribution>Wyo.</us_distribution>
    <global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution>South America (Argentina).</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution>South America (Colombia).</global_distribution>
    <global_distribution>South America (Uruguay).</global_distribution>
    <discussion>The chromosome numbers 2n = 10 and 2n = 16 have also been reported from North
        America but have not been verified.</discussion>
    <discussion>Eleocharis macrostachya probably occurs in Saskatchewan; I have not seen specimens.
        It is extremely variable. Cytotaxonomic studies (S.-O. Strandhede 1967; L. J. Harms 1968)
        and morphology suggest that it is a diploid-polyploid complex at least partly of hybrid
        origin from E. palustris and both E. erythropoda and E. uniglumis. The 2n = 38 plants of E.
        macrostachya may comprise the American counterpart of the European E. palustris subsp.
        vulgaris, which presumably originated from E. palustris subsp. palustris and E. uniglumis
        (S.-O. Strandhede 1966). Although recognition of infraspecific taxa is premature, the
        following three intergrading variants are notable:</discussion>
    <discussion>Variant a (= Eleocharis xyridiformis) almost certainly deserves taxonomic
        recognition, perhaps as a species. It has markedly compressed culms to 3 times wider than
        thick; distal leaf-sheath apices subtruncate, usually with a tooth to 0.6(–1) mm on some or
        all culms; spikelets narrowly lanceoloid; floral scales medium brown to stramineous, mostly
        lanceolate and carinate, 2.5–4 × 1.5 mm; achenes 1.1–1.5 × 0.8–1.2 mm; chromosome numbers
        (for which I have seen vouchers, all from Kansas and South Dakota), 2n = 18. It is known
        from 20–450 m in Arizona, California, Illinois, Kansas, Missouri, New Mexico, Oklahoma,
        South Dakota, Texas, and Mexico (Coahuila, Durango, Nuevo León). Both the holotype of E.
        xyridiformis from Mexico and the vouchers of the 2n = 18 chromosome counts reported for E.
        xyridiformis, all from Kansas and South Dakota, have stomates 55–60 µm, which is typical of
        2n = 18 plants (S.-O. Strandhede 1967). The holotype of E. macrostachya from Oklahoma, which
        is otherwise much like the type of E. xyridiformis except for less markedly compressed
        culms, has stomates averaging 59–68 µm, which is typical of plants of E. macrostachya with
        2n = 38 as in variant b.</discussion>
    <discussion>Variant b is very variable in comparison with variant a. It differs from variant a
        in having culms terete or slightly compressed; distal leaf-sheath apices often obtuse, tooth
        rarely present, to 0.1 mm; spikelets broadly lanceoloid to ovoid; floral scales 3.5–4(–4.5)
        × 1.7–2+ mm; achenes 1.3–1.5 mm, rarely to 1.8 mm; culm stomates 60–72 µm; chromosome
        numbers (for which I have seen vouchers, all from Kansas and South Dakota), 2n = ca. 38. It
        is wide-ranging, known from inland localities at 20–2300 m from Manitoba west to Yukon and
        British Columbia, south to Alabama, Mississippi, Louisiana, Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, and
        California, and in Mexico from Baja California. Intermediates between variant b and both
        Eleocharis erythropoda and E. uniglumis are widespread, and intermediates with E. ambigens
        occur in Louisiana. Most plants of variant b have floral scales to 4 mm and achenes to 1.5
        mm; plants with scales to 4–5 mm and achenes sometimes more than 1.6 mm occur in California,
        Nevada, Oregon, and Washington.</discussion>
    <discussion>Variant c differs from variant b in having spikelet scales mostly uniformly dark
        chestnut-brown, not carinate, (3.5–)4–5.5 × 2–2.5 mm. Its achenes are often unusually large,
        1.3–1.8(–2) × 1.1–1.5 mm. It is known from near sea level on the coasts of British Columbia,
        Ontario, and Quebec (James Bay and Magdalen Islands); Alaska, California, Oregon, and
        Washington. Some plants are intermediate between variant c and variant b. Several specimens
        I have seen from far eastern Russia are very similar to American plants of Eleocharis
        macrostachya, variant c. Except for having incompletely amplexicaulous proximal scales, and
        subproximal scales often without a flower, variant c closely resembles many Eurasian
        specimens of E. uniglumis.</discussion>
</treatment>
