<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>5</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Acoelorraphe</genus_name><genus_authority>H. Wendland</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Bot. Zeitung (Berlin)</publication_title><place_in_publication>37: 148. 1879</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Paurotis palm</common_name><common_name> palmier des Everglades</common_name><etymology>[Greek a-, without, coelo, hollow, and raphe, in reference to shape of the seed]</etymology><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Paurotis</genus_name><genus_authority>O. F. Cook</genus_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants moderate, clusteringed palms. Stems caespitose, erect, slender, less than 15 cm diam. Leaves: sheath fibers soft, eventually sloughing off to reveal smooth to fissured stem; petiole not split at base, armed with stout teeth, occasionally obscurely armed with minute teeth; abaxial hastula absent; adaxial hastula conspicuous, acute to acuminate; costa minute to absent; blade palmate; plication induplicate; segments lanceolate, stiff, basally connate. Inflorescences axillary within crown of leaves, paniculate, arching, longer than leaves, with 3(--4) orders of branching; prophyll short; peduncular bracts 2, tubular, 2-keeled, long; rachillae pendulous, pubescent. Flowers bisexual, borne singly or in clusters of 2--3 along rachillae, sessile; perianth 2-seriate; sepals 3, imbricate, briefly connate, margins ciliate; petals 3, basally connate, valvate, triangular with adaxial crest; stamens 6, filaments basally connate, acuminate; anthers dorsifixed, versatile; dehiscence latrorse-introrse; pistils 3(--4), distinct basally, glabrous; styles connate, filiform; stigmas minute. Fruits globose, stigmatic scar apical; exocarp blackish, smooth, slightly rugose when dry; mesocarp thin, fleshy; endocarp membranaceous. Seeds 1 per fruit, globose, with circular raphe; endosperm bony, homogeneous; embryo nearly basal; eophyll undivided, lanceolate. xn = 18.</description><discussion>Acoelorraphe is a widespread monotypic genus. The taxa A. wrightii forma inermis Hadac&amp;#269; and A. wrightii var. novo-geronensis Beccari probably have no biological significance.</discussion><discussion>Recent molecular studies indicated that Serenoa is the sister genus to Acoelorraphe (N. W. Uhl et al. 1995).</discussion><number_of_infrataxa>Species 1:</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> widespread</global_distribution><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> se Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> and n South America (Colombia--Isla de Providencia).</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCE"><reference> Galeano-Garc&amp;eacute;s, G. 1986. Primer registro de dos g&amp;eacute;neros de palmas para la flora Colombiana. Mutisia 66: 1--4.</reference></references></treatment>
