<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Acrocomia</genus_name><species_name>totai</species_name><species_authority>Martius</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>in A. D. d’Orbigny,Voyage dans l'Amérique Méridionale</publication_title><place_in_publication>7(3): 78. 1844; 8(1): plate 9, fig. 1. 1842</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Stems armed with spines 12--13 cm. Leaves ca. 4 m; segments glabrous abaxially. Fruits brownish green, globose, 2--3 cm diam., brownish green.; endocarp globose, brown, bearing 3 germination pores. Seeds: eophyll undivided.</description><discussion>Acrocomia totai is sparingly naturalized in central Florida in Brevard County (B. Peterson 1991b), as well as in Dade County in the vicinity of Miami.</discussion><phenology>Flowering in the summer</phenology><habitat> Woodlands and hammocks</habitat><elevation>0--30 m</elevation><introduced>introduced</introduced><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution>native</global_distribution><global_distribution> to South America.</global_distribution><references heading="Other References"><reference>Barford, A. 1991. A monographic study of the subfamily Phytelephantoideae (Arecaceae). Opera Bot. 105: 1--73.</reference><reference> Barthlott, W. and D. Fr&amp;ouml;lich. 1983. Mikromorphologie und Orientierungsmuster epicuticularer Wachs-Kristalloide: Ein neues systematisches Merkmal bei Monokotylen. Pl. Syst. Evol. 142: 171--185.</reference><reference> Bartram, W. 1791. Travels through North and South Carolina, Georgia, East and West Florida, the Cherokee Country, the Extensive Territories of the Muscogulges, or Creek Confederacy, and the Country of the Chactawas. . . . Philadelphia. Beal, J. M. 1937. Cytological studies in the genus Phoenix. Bot. Gaz. 99: 400--407.</reference><reference> Bernal, R. G., G. Galeano, and A. Henderson. 1991. Notes on Oenocarpus (Palmae) in the Colombian Amazon. Brittonia 43: 154--164.</reference><reference> Borchsenius, F. 1997. Flowering biology of Geonoma irena and G. cuneata var. sodiroi (Arecaceae). Pl. Syst. Evol. 208: 187--196.</reference><reference> Brummitt, R. K. 1996. Report of the Committee for Spermatophyta: 44. Taxon 45: 671--681.</reference><reference> Bullock, S. H. 1980. Dispersal of a desert palm by opportunistic frugivores. Principes 24: 29--32.</reference><reference> Chase, M. W. et al. 1993. Phylogenetics of seed plants: An analysis of nucleotide sequences from the plastid gene rbcL. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 80: 528--580.</reference><reference> Cooper, J. G. 1861. On the forests and trees of Florida and the Mexican boundary. Rep. (Annual) Board Regents Smithsonian Inst. 1860: 439--442.</reference><reference> Cunningham, S. A. 1995. Ecological constraints on fruit initiation by Calyptrogyne ghiesbreghtiana (Arecaceae): Floral herbivory, pollen availability, and visitation by pollinating bats. Amer. J. Bot. 82: 1527--1536.</reference><reference> Dahlgren, R. M. T., H. T. Clifford, and P. F. Yeo. 1985. The Families of the Monocotyledons. Structure, Evolution, and Taxonomy. Berlin etc. Davis, J. I. 1995. A phylogenetic structure for the monocotyledons, as inferred from chloroplast DNA restriction site variation, and a comparison of measures of clade support. Syst. Bot. 20: 503--527.</reference><reference> Dowe, J. L. and N. W. Uhl. 1989. Carpoxylon macrospermum. Principes 33: 68--73.</reference><reference> Dransfield, J. 1989. Voanioala (Arecoideae: Cocoeae: Butiinae), a new palm genus from Madagascar. Kew Bull. 44: 191--198.</reference><reference> Dransfield, J. 1991. Lemurophoenix (Palmae: Arecoideae), a new genus from Madagascar. Kew Bull. 46: 61--68.</reference><reference> Dransfield, J. and H. J. Beentje. 1995. Satranala (Coryphoideae: Borasseae: Hyphaeninae), a new palm genus from Madagascar. Kew Bull. 50: 85--92.</reference><reference> Dransfield, J. and H. Beentje. 1995b. Palms of Madagascar. Kew. Duvall, M. R. et al. 1993b. Phylogenetic hypotheses for the monocotyledons constructed from rbcL data. Ann. Missouri Bot. Gard. 80: 607--619.</reference><reference> Ervik, F. and J. P. Feil. 1997. Reproductive biology of the monoecious understory palm Prestoea schultzeana in Amazonian Ecuador. Biotropica 29: 309--317.</reference><reference> Fisher, J. B., J. G. Chong, and A. N. Rao. 1989. Non-axillary branching in the palms Eugeissona and Oncosperma (Arecaceae). Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 99: 347--363.</reference><reference> Harlow, R. F. 1961. Fall and winter foods of Florida white-tailed deer. Quart. J. Florida Acad. Sci. 24: 19--38.</reference><reference> Harris, P. J. and R. D. Hartley. 1980. Phenolic constituents of the cell walls of monocotyledons. Biochem. Syst. &amp; Ecol. 8: 153--160.</reference><reference> Henderson, A. and M. J. Balick. 1991. Attalea crassispatha, a rare and endemic Haitian palm. Brittonia 43: 189--194.</reference><reference> Iverson, J. B. 1979. Behaviour and ecology of the rock iguana Cyclura carinata. Bull. Florida State Mus., Biol. Sci. 24: 175--358.</reference><reference> Johnson, C. D., S. Zona, and J. A. Nilsson. 1995. Bruchid beetles and palm seeds: Recorded relationships. Principes 39: 25--35.</reference><reference> Klimstra, W. D. and A. L. Dooley. 1990. Foods of the Key deer. Florida Sci. 53: 264--273.</reference><reference> Listabarth, C. 1992. A survey of pollination strategies in the Bractridinae (Palmae). Bull. Inst. Fran&amp;ccedil;. &amp;Eacute;tudes Andines 21: 699--714.</reference><reference> Listabarth, C. 1993. Insect-induced wind pollination of the palm Chamaedorea pinnatifrons and pollintion in the related Wendlandiella sp. Biodivers. &amp; Conservation 2: 39--50.</reference><reference> Listabarth, C. 1993b. Pollination in Geonoma macrostachys and three congeners, G. acaulis, G. gracilis, and G. interrupta. Bot. Acta 106: 496--506.</reference><reference> Listabarth, C. 1994. Pollination and pollinator breeding in Desmoncus. Principes 38: 13--23.</reference><reference> Maehr, D. S. 1984. The black bear as a seed disperser in Florida. Florida Field Natuarlist 12: 40--42.</reference><reference> Maehr, D. S. and J. R. Brady. 1984. Food habits of Florida black bears. J. Wildlife Managem. 48: 230--235.</reference><reference> Moldenke, H. N. 1967. Notes on new and noteworthy plants. XLVI. Phytologia 14: 325--326.</reference><reference> Read, R. W. 1964. Palm chromosome studies facilitated by pollen culture on chochicine-lactose medium. Stain Technol. 39: 99--106.</reference><reference> Read, R. W. 1965. Palm chromosomes by air mail. Principes 9: 4--10.</reference><reference> Read, R. W. 1965b. Chromosome numbers in the Coryphoideae. Cytologia 30: 385--391.</reference><reference> Read, R. W. 1966. New chomosome counts in the Palmae. Principes 10: 55--61.</reference><reference> Scariot, A. O., E. Lleras, and J. D. Hay. 1991. Reproductive biology of the palm Acrocomia aculeata in central Brazil. Biotropica 23: 12--22.</reference><reference> Sharma, A. K. and S. K. Sarkar. 1956. Cytology of different species of palms and its bearing on the solution of the problems of phylogeny and speciation. Genetica 28: 361--488.</reference><reference> Simpson, B. J. 1988. A Field Guide to Texas Trees. Austin. Thorne, R. F. 1992b. Classification and geography of the flowering plants. Bot. Rev. (Lancaster) 58:. 225--348.</reference><reference> Uhl, N. W. et al. 1990. Phylogenetic analyses within Coryphoideae (Palmae). [Abstract.] Amer. J. Bot. 77(suppl.): 160--161.</reference><reference> Uhl, N. W. et al. 1995. Phylogenetic relationships among palms: Cladistic analysis of morphological and chloroplast DNA restriction site variation. In: P. J. Rudall et al., eds. 1995. Monocotyledons: Systematics and Evolution. 2 vols. Kew. Vol. 2, pp. 623--662.Pp. xxx. Uhl, N. W. et al. 1990. Phylogenetic analyses within Coryphoideae (Palmae). [Abstract.] Amer. J. Bot. 77(suppl.): 160--161.</reference><reference> Zona, S. 1994. Proposal to conserve Oreodoxa regia Kunth, the basionym of Roystonea regia (Kunth) O. F. Cook, against Palma elata W. Bartram (Arecaceae). Taxon 43: 662--663.</reference><reference> Zona, S. 1997. The genera of Palmae (Arecaceae) in the southeastern United States. Harvard Pap. Bot. 2: 71--107.</reference><reference> Zona, S. and A. Henderson. 1989. A review of animal-mediated seed dispersal of palms. Selbyana 11: 6--21.</reference></references></treatment>
