<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Calla</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 968. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5; 414, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Calla;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[a plant name used by Pliny, perhaps from Greek kallos, beauty]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, wetland. Rhizomes horizontal. Leaves appearing before flowers, several, emergent, arising along rhizome, also clustered terminally; petiole 1.5--2 or more times as long as blade; blade bright green, simple, not peltate, ovate to nearly round, base cordate, apex short-acuminate to apiculate; lateral veins parallel. Inflorescences: peduncle erect, as long as or longer than petiole, apex not swollen; spathe white, often green or partially green abaxially, not enclosing spadix; spadix cylindric. Flowers all bisexual or distal ones staminate; perianth absent. Fruits not embedded in spadix, red. Seeds 4--9(--11), embedded in mucilage. x = 18.</description>
  <description type="distribution">circumboreal.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Water arum arum</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">wild calla</other_name>
  <discussion>Numerous cytogenetic studies have been conducted on Calla with both diploid (2n = 36) and apparently tetraploid (2n = 72) populations reported (see G. Petersen 1989). All counts from North American populations counted have a somatic number of 36 chromosomes.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Dudley, M. G. 1937. Morphological and cytological studies of Calla palustris. Bot. Gaz. 98: 556--571.</reference>
    <reference>Lehmann, N. L. and R. Sattler. 1992. Irregular floral development in Calla palustris (Araceae) and the concept of homeosis. Amer. J. Bot. 79: 1145--1157.</reference>
    <reference>Scribailo, R. W. and P. B. Tomlinson. 1992. Shoot and floral development in Calla palustris. Int. J. Pl. Sci. 153: 1--13.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
