<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Canna</genus_name><species_name>glauca</species_name><species_authority>Linnaeus</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>1: 1. 1753</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Louisiana canna</common_name><description>Rhizomes far-creeping, 0.5--1.5 cm diam. Leaves: sheath and blade glaucous; blade narrowly ovate, 28--70 &amp;#180; 1.5--14 cm, base cuneate, apex very gradually narrowing to acute. Inflorescences racemes, simple or occasionally branched, bearing 2-flowered cincinni, more than 10 flowers per inflorescence; primary bracts 10--30 cm; secondary bracts 5--20 cm; floral bracts persistent, (broadly) ovate-triangular, 0.7--2.5 &amp;#180; 0.4--1 cm, apex entire or irregularly lobed, glaucous; bracteoles (broadly) ovate-triangular, 0.3--2 cm &amp;#61620; 4--8 mm, apex entire or irregularly lobed. Flowers pure yellow, 7.5--10 cm; pedicels short, to 0.5 cm; sepals narrowly elliptic-triangular, 1.2--2 &amp;#180; 0.3--0.5 cm; petals erect, 5--9 cm, tube 1--2 cm, lobes narrowly ovate, 4--7 &amp;#180; 0.7--1.1 cm; staminodes 4, narrowly elliptic to narrowly ovate, 7.5--10 cm, free part 0.5--2.3 cm wide, apex sometimes slightly notched; labellum strongly reflexed, linear, approximately equal to other staminodes. Capsules globose to ellipsoid, 2--5 &amp;#180; 2--4 cm. Seeds brown, ovoid, 7--10 &amp;#180; 6--8 mm. 2n = 18.</description><discussion>Canna glauca is introduced in Florida and probably in South Carolina.</discussion><phenology>Flowering summer</phenology><phenology_fruiting>fruiting summer--fall (Jun--Sep)</phenology_fruiting><habitat> Margins of marshes, swamps, ponds, and wet ditches</habitat><elevation>0--100 m</elevation><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> La.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Tex.</us_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution>South America.</global_distribution><references heading="Other References"><reference>Belling, J. 1931. Chromomeres of liliaceous plants. Univ. Calif. Publ. Bot. 16: 153---170. Honing, J. A. 1928. Canna crosses II. Meded. Landbouwhoogeschool 32: 1--14.</reference><reference> Lerman, J. C. and E. M. Cigliano. 1971. New carbon-14 evidence for six hundred years old Canna compacta seed. Nature 232: 568--570.</reference><reference> Yeo, P. F. 1993. Secondary pollen presentation: Form, function and evolution. Pl. Syst. Evol., Suppl. 6: 204--208.</reference></references></treatment>
