<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schultz Schultzenstein" date="unknown">arecaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Willdenow" date="unknown">Chamaedorea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4(2): 638, 800. 1806</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family arecaceae;genus Chamaedorea</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek chamai, on the ground, and dorea, gift, in reference to small, low-growing palms of great beauty]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants small, usually low-growing, unarmed. Stems clustered [solitary], erect [creeping, lianoid], slender, unarmed. Leaves: sheaths tubular, unarmed, forming crownshaft; blade pinnate [undivided], with leaf segments regularly spaced along unarmed rachis, in 1 plane [many planes]; plication reduplicate; segments linear-lanceolate, apical pair of segments sometimes wider than others. Inflorescences axillary below crown of leaves, ascending, with 1 order of branching [spicate or 2 orders]; prophyll small; peduncular bracts 5--6, tubular, papery; rachillae green at anthesis, turning orange in fruit. Flowers unisexual, sessile, staminate and pistillate flowers on different plants. Staminate flowers borne singly, partially sunken into fleshy rachillae; sepals 3, briefly connate at base [distinct]; petals 3, ovate, basally briefly connate [connate by tips]; stamens 6, distinct; anthers dorsifixed; pistillode minute. Pistillate flowers borne singly, slightly sunken into fleshy rachillae; sepals 3, free; petals 3, free, ovate; staminodes 6, minute; pistil 1, 3-loculate; ovules 1 per locule; style indistinct; stigmas minute. Fruits drupes, globose; stigmatic scar basal, exocarp black, smooth; mesocarp thin; endocarp bony. Seeds globose; endosperm homogeneous; embryo subapical; eophyll 2-cleft [pinnate], segments linear. nx = 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; Fla., Mexico, Central America, and n South America.</description>
  <number>11</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Bamboo palm</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">parlor palm</other_name>
  <discussion>Chamaedorea species are understory palms in Mexico, Central America, and northern South America. Many species are cultivated in North America both as houseplants and, in warm areas, as garden plants.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 77--100 or more (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
