<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. de Jussieu" date="unknown">hydrocharitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Planchon" date="1849">Egeria</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Annales des Sciences Naturelles, Botanique</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>sér. 3, 11: 79. 1849</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hydrocharitaceae;genus Egeria</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Latin egeri, a nymph, in reference to aquatic habitat]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, of fresh waters. Rhizomes and stolons absent. Erect stems rooted in substrate, branched or unbranched, elongate. Leaves cauline, in whorls of 5 or more [opposite], submersed, sessile; blade linear, base sloping to stem, apex obtuse; midvein without rows of lacunae along side(s), blade uniform in color throughout;; abaxially surface without prickles or aerenchyma; intravaginal squamules entire. Inflorescences 1-flowered, sessile; spathes not winged. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants, projected to surface by slender, elongate floral tube base, pedicellate; petals white. Staminate flowers: filaments distinct; anthers linear; pollen in monads. Pistillate flowers: ovary 1-locular; styles 3, not 2-fid. Fruits ovoid, smooth, dehiscing irregularly. Seeds fusiform, mucilaginous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced, North America; Central America; South America; Eurasia; Africa; Australia.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">South American elodea</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cook, C. D. K., and K. Urmi-K&amp;ouml;nig. 1984b. A revision of the genus Egeria (Hydrocharitaceae). Aquatic Bot. 19: 73--96. St.</reference>
    <reference>John, H. 1961. Monograph of the genus Egeria Planchon. Darwiniana 12: 293--307.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
