<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eriocaulon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Van Heurck &amp; Muller-Argoviensis" date="unknown">koernickianum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. F. Van Heurck,Observ. Bot.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 101. 1870</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eriocaulon;species koernickianum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, 5--8 cm. Leaves linear-attenuate, 2--5 cm, apex subulate to blunt. Inflorescences: scape sheaths as long as leaves, inflated; scapes filiform, 0.5 mm wide, 3--4-ribbed; heads dark gray or gray-green with rims of bracts and perianth pale, nearly globose or short-oblong, 3--4 mm wide, soft; receptacle glabrous; outer involucral bracts usually not reflexed, not obscured by bracteoles and perianth, straw-colored, very lustrous, broadly oblong to suborbiculate, 1--1.25 mm, margins nearly entire, apex rounded, glabrous; inner bracts, receptacular bracteoles dark gray, gray-green, or gray-brown, very lustrous, oblong to cuneate, obliquely keeled, 1.5 mm, margins slightly erose, apex acute to obtuse, apiculate, with a few white, club-shaped hairs. Staminate flowers: sepals 2, grayish, linear-curvate, 1--1.5 mm, apex with a few white, club-shaped hairs abaxially, marginally; androphore broadly club-shaped; petals 2, low, toothlike, nearly equal, apex with club-shaped hairs; stamens 4; anthers black. Pistillate flowers: sepals 2, gray, linear-curvate, 1 mm, apex with scattered hairs abaxially, hairs pale, club-shaped, otherwise glabrous; petals 2, yellow-white, stipitate, broadly suborbiculate-rhombic, 1 mm, apex with white, club-shaped hairs abaxially; pistil 2-carpellate. Seeds deep reddish brown, broadly ovoid or ellipsoid, 0.5 mm, often indistinctly reticulate or rugulose, papillate.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring--early fall</description>
  <description type="habitat">Moist to wet sands and sandy silts of seeps, particularly over and around arenaceous outcrops</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1000 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ark.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Okla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <discussion>Eriocaulon koernickianum is the most diminutive of our eriocaulons, widely disjunct in Georgia but seemingly most abundant on Piedmont granites.</discussion>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
