<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Palisot de Beauvois ex Desvaux" date="unknown">eriocaulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">eriocaulon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Orzell &amp; E. L. Bridges" date="1993">nigrobracteatum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Phytologia</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>74: 105, figs. 1--4. 1993</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family eriocaulaceae;genus eriocaulon;species nigrobracteatum</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, 5--15(--19) cm. Leaves linear-attenuate, 0.5--1.5(--4) cm, apex subulate. Inflorescences: scape sheaths longer than principal leaves; scapes filiform, 0.3--0.4 mm, 4-ribbed; mature heads blackish at level of involucre, white above it, hemispheric to globose, 3--4(--5) mm wide, soft; receptacle glabrous; involucral bracts spreading, not obscured by bracteoles and flowers, blackish, very lustrous, broadly ovate to orbiculate, 1--3 mm, margins entire to erose, apex broadly rounded, glabrous; inner bracts, receptacular bracteoles blackish or with pale base, broadly to narrowly ovate, 2--3 mm, margins somewhat erose with age, apex rounded or apiculate, margins and abaxial surfaces with white, club-shaped hairs, apically ciliate. Staminate flowers: sepals 2, gray-brown, broadly spatulate to oblong-obovate, curved, keeled, 1--1.2 mm, keel and margin with white, club-shaped hairs; androphore club-shaped to campanulate, flaring; petals 2, oblong-obovate, nearly equal, 1 mm, apex ciliate and abaxially with white, club-shaped hairs; stamens 4; anthers black. Pistillate flowers: sepals 2, gray, oblong, curved, keeled, 1 mm, adaxial surfaces pilose, hairs translucent, sharp, apically with white, club-shaped hairs; petals 2, pale, short-stipitate or nearly sessile, oblong, 1 mm (narrower and longer than those of E. koernickianum), apex obtuse, adaxial surface and margins with white, club-shaped hairs; pistil 2-carpellate. Seeds brown, nearly round, 0.3 mm, obscurely reticulate, alveolae irregularly and horizontally rectangular.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Muck of deep sphagnous seep bogs in longleaf pinelands;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--100 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <number>9</number>
  <discussion>Eriocaulon nigrobracteatum is a very limited, local endemic whose relationships with E. aquaticum should be clarified.</discussion>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Orzell, S. L. and E. L. Bridges. 1993. Eriocaulon nigrobracteatum (Eriocaulaceae), a new species from the Florida panhandle with a characterization of its poor fen habitat. Phytologia 74: 104--124.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
