<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">eriocaulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eriocaulon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Kornicke" date="unknown">texense</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>27: 494. 1856</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family eriocaulaceae; genus Eriocaulon;species texense;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, 5--30 cm. Leaves linear-attenuate, (1--)2--5(--7) cm, apex subulate. Inflorescences: scape sheaths mostly longer than principal leaves, inflated; scapes filiform to linear, 0.5--1 mm wide, 4--7-ribbed; mature heads white or gray, hemispheric to nearly globose, 5--10 mm wide, soft, much flattened when pressed; receptacle pilose; involucral bracts becoming reflexed, obscured by bracteoles and proximal flowers, straw-colored to gray, suborbiculate to broadly obovate, 1.5 mm, margins entire, apex rounded to apiculate, glabrous; inner bracts, receptacular bracteoles gray to dark gray, obovate to cuneate, 1.5 mm, apex obtuse to acute, blade densely ciliate, hairs white, club-shaped. Staminate flowers: sepals 2, proximally pale, distally dark gray, opaque, linear-spatulate, 1.5 mm, apex acute, distal adaxial surfaces, margins with white, club-shaped hairs; androphore club-shaped; petals 2, unequal, narrowly triangular, short, apically ciliate with white, club-shaped hairs; stamens 4; anthers black. Pistillate flowers: sepals 2, dark gray, narrowly oblong-obovate, curved, keeled, 1.5 mm, keels with white, club-shaped hairs; petals 2, yellow-white, linear to oblong or obovate, 1--1.5 mm, apex acute, blade ciliate with white, club-shaped hairs, adaxial surfaces pilose with mixture of translucent, tapering and white, club-shaped hairs; pistil 2-carpellate. Seeds brownish, ovoid or broadly ellipsoid, 0.6 mm, indistinctly alveolate, proximal ribs often with fine pale papillae.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering in spring</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sphagnous bogs and low pine savanna, seeps</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--150 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <description type="distribution">La.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Miss.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <discussion>In habit Eriocaulon texense is much like a diminutive version of E. compressum, likewise preferring deep bogs and also just as variable in the color of its bracts, bracteoles, and perianth.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
