<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>2</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Eriocaulon</genus_name><species_name>parkeri</species_name><species_authority>B. L. Robinson</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Rhodora</publication_title><place_in_publication>5: 175. 1903</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>&amp;Eacute;riocaulon de Parker</common_name><description>Herbs, perennial, 10--20(--30) cm. Leaves linear-attenuate, 2--6(--9) cm, apex filiform-terete. Inflorescences: scape sheaths slightly longer or slightly shorter than leaves, loose; scapes linear, 0.5--1 mm wide, 4--5-ribbed; mature heads dull gray or lead-colored, rarely straw-colored, hemispheric to subglobose, 3--4 mm wide, mostly nearly glabrous; receptacle glabrous; outer involucral bracts usually not reflexed, not obscured by braceteoles and perianth, straw-colored, greenish, or light gray to gray, dull, ovate to suborbiculate or obovate, 2 mm, margins often erose or lacerate, apex blunt, glabrous; inner bracts, receptacular bracteoles grayish, cuneate to narrowly obovate, 2 mm, margins often erose or lacerate, apex obtuse, glabrous or with a few white hairs abaxially at apex. Staminate flowers: sepals 2, gray, linear to oblong or oblanceolate, 2 mm, apex obtuse, glabrous or with a few white hairs abaxially at apex; androphore club-shaped; petals 2, triangular, minute, white-hairy; stamens 4; anthers black. Pistillate flowers: sepals 2, gray, oblong or oblanceolate, 2 mm, scarious, apex obtuse, abaxially hairy apically; petals 2, yellow-white, spatulate, 2 mm, apex obtuse, glabrous or with a few white, club-shaped hairs apically, adaxially; pistil 2-carpellate. Seeds red-brown, ovoid to broadly ellipsoid, 0.5(--7) mm, with delicate reticulum of horizontally oriented alveolae.</description><discussion>A considerable amount of transitional material occurs between Eriocaulon parkeri and E. aquaticum at places along coastal streams where brackish habitat meets more acid habitat upstream.</discussion><phenology>Flowering summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Muddy tidewater banks, brackish marsh, mud flats</habitat><elevation>0--100 m</elevation><ca_distribution>Que.</ca_distribution><us_distribution>Conn.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Del.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Maine</us_distribution><us_distribution> Md.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Mass.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.J.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.Y.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Va.</us_distribution></treatment>
