<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. de Jussieu" date="unknown">hydrocharitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Thouars" date="1806">halophila</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ascherson in G. B. von Neumayer" date="1875">engelmannii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in G. B. von Neumayer,Anleitung zu Wissenschaftlichen Beobachtungen auf Reisen</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>368. 1875</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hydrocharitaceae;genus halophila;species engelmannii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes with 2 scales at each node. Erect stem apparent, scales 2, near middle. Leaves in pseudowhorl at apex of erect stem, 10--30 &amp;#180; 3--6 mm; blade linear-oblong to oblong, base cuneate, margins serrulate, apex obtuse to apiculate. Inflorescences: spathes 1-flowered. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants; staminate flowers unknown; pistillate flowers sessile to nearly sessile, ca. 4 mm. Fruits beaked. Seeds 0.3 mm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy to coral substrates of marine waters;</description>
  <description type="elevation">-40--0 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla., La., Tex.; West Indies (Cuba, Bahama Islands).</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <references>
    <reference>Allen, G. E. 1976. Investigations and current status of insect enemies as biological control agents of aquatic weeds. In: C. K. Varshney and J. Rz&amp;oacute;ska, eds. 1976. Aquatic Weeds in South East Asia. The Hague. Pp. 299--306.</reference>
    <reference>Austin, D. F. 1978. Exotic plants and their effects in southeastern Florida. Environm. Conservation 5: 25--34.</reference>
    <reference>Davenport, L. J. 1980. In: IOPB chromosome number reports LXVII. Taxon 29: 347--367.</reference>
    <reference>Gadella, T. W. J. and E. Kliphuis. 1973. Chromosome numbers of flowering plants in The Netherlands. VI. Proc. K. Ned. Acad. Wet., Ser. C, 76: 303--311.</reference>
    <reference>Tarver, D. P. et al. 1978. Aquatic and Wetland Plants of Florida. Tallahassee.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
