<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Hechtia</genus_name><genus_authority>Klotzsch</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Allgemeine Gartenzeitung</publication_title><place_in_publication>3: 401. 1835</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, terrestrial or among or on rocks, caulescent or without evident stems, occasionally stoloniferous. Leaves rosulate, straight to falcate; blade narrowly triangular, margins spinose. Inflorescences lateral [terminal or lateral], many-flowered, simple or compound and paniculate; branches capitate to lax and elongate; floral bracts broad [broad to narrow], conspicuous. Flowers dimorphic, functionally unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants; sepals distinct, symmetric; staminate petals distinct or appearing briefly connate basally from adnation of filaments to adjacent petals; stamens included or exserted; filaments adnate [free or adnate] to petals; pistillate petals distinct, triangular or ovate; ovary largely superior to largely inferior. Capsules ovoid, dehiscent. Seeds narrowly winged to almost wingless, plumose appendages absent.</description><discussion>The Texas species are unusual in their scaly capsules and flowers with scaly sepals, petals, and ovaries.</discussion><number_of_infrataxa>Species ca. 50 (2 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America.</global_distribution><author>Kathleen Burt-Utley </author><author>John F. Utley</author><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCE"><reference> Burt-Utley, K. and J. F. Utley. 1987. Contributions toward a revision of Hechtia (Bromeliaceae). Brittonia 39: 37--43.</reference></references><key><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Staminate flowers with sepals 2.5--4 mm, petals 3.5--4.5 mm; pistillate flowers with sepals 3--4 mm, petals 4.5--5 mm; capsules 6--8.5</statement><determination>1 Hechtia glomerata</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Staminate flowers with sepals 4.5--5 mm, petals 7.5--9 mm; pistillate flowers with sepals 4.5--7 mm, petals 7.5--9 mm; capsules 8.5--12.5 mm</statement><determination>2 Hechtia texensis</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
