<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Takhtajan ex Cronquist" date="unknown">limnocharitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Richard" date="1815">Hydrocleys</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Memoires du Museum d'Histoire Naturelle</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 368. 1815</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family limnocharitaceae;genus Hydrocleys</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hydro, water, and clavis, club-shaped, presumably from shape of pistils]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stolons often present, terete. Leaves: submersed leaves phyllodia, (expanded petioles resembling and functioning like leaves), sessile; floating leaves long-petiolate, petioles terete, septate; blade orbiculate to oblong-lanceolate, base cordate [rounded], apex mucronate to obtuse. Inflorescences occasionally proliferating with stolons, leaves; scape septate; bracts subtending pedicel, distinct, elliptic to lanceolate, shorter than pedicel, delicate. Flowers: sepals persistent, erect, green, lanceolate, leathery, midvein absent [present], apex hoodlike; petals erect to spreading, yellow to white, orbiculate [oblong-obovate], longer than [shorter than] sepals; stamens in [1--]4--5 series, outer often sterile; pistils terete, linear-lanceoloid, attenuate into style, style curved inward, apex papillose. Fruits ± terete, linear-lanceoloid, membranous, dehiscing along adaxial margins. Seeds 50 or more, sparsely to densely glandular-pubescent.</description>
  <description type="distribution">introduced; North America; South America.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Water-poppy</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 5 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kenton, A. 1982. A Robertsonian relationship in the chromosomes of two species of Hydrocleys (Butomaceae sens. lat.). Kew Bull. 36: 487--492.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
