<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. de Jussieu" date="unknown">hydrocharitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Richard" date="1814">Hydrilla</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Memoires de la Classe des Sciences Mathematiques et Physiques de L'Institut National de France</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12(2): 9, 61, 73, plate 2a--k. 1814</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hydrocharitaceae;genus Hydrilla</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hydr-, water, and -illa, diminutive]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, of fresh or brackish waters. Rhizomes present, stolons absent. Erect stems rooted in substrate, branched or unbranched, elongate. Leaves cauline, whorled, 3--8 per node, submersed, sessile; blade linear, rarely slightly elliptic, base tapering to stem, apex acute; midvein without lacunae along side(s), blade uniform in color throughout; abaxial surface ly with prickles along midvein, without aerenchyma; intravaginal squamules fringed with orange-brown hairs. Inflorescences 1-flowered, sessile to subsessile; spathe not winged. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants or on same plants, submersed, sessile; petals whitish to reddish. Staminate flowers: filaments distinct, released under water, rising to surface; anthers oval; pollen in monads; . pPistillate flowers: ovary 1-locular; floral tube long, styles 1, not 2-fid. Fruits linear, cylindric, smooth or with simple spiny processes, indehiscent. Seeds cylindric, glabrous.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 1: introduced, North America; Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>introduced, North America; Central America, South America, Eurasia, Africa, Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>8</number>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Allen, G. E. 1976. Investigations and current status of insect enemies as biological control agents of aquatic weeds. In: C. K. Varshney and J. Rz&amp;oacute;ska, eds. 1976. Aquatic Weeds in South East Asia. The Hague.</reference>
    <reference>Blackburn, R. D. and L. W. Weldon. 1970. Control of Hydrilla verticillata. Hyacinth Control J. 8: 4--9.</reference>
    <reference>Cook, C. D. K. and R. L&amp;uuml;&amp;ouml;nd. 1982b. A revision of the genus Hydrilla (Hydrocharitaceae). Aquatic Bot. 13: 485--504.</reference>
    <reference>Lakshmanan, C. 1951. A note on the occurrence of turions in Hydrilla verticillata Presl. J. Bombay Nat. Hist. Soc. 49: 802--804.</reference>
    <reference>Shireman, J. V. , and M. J. Maceina. 1981. The utilization of grass carp, Ctenopharyngodon idella Val., for Hydrilla control in Lake Baldwin, Florida. J. Fish Biol. 19: 629--636.</reference>
    <reference>Tarver, D. P., J. A. Rodgers, M. J. Mahler, and R. L. Lazor. 1978. Aquatic and Wetland Plants of Florida. Tallahassee.</reference>
    <reference>Austin, D. 1978. Exotic plants and their effects in southeastern Florida. Environm. Conserv. 5: 25--34.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
