<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">hydrocharitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Hydrocharis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1036. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5; 458, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hydrocharitaceae; genus Hydrocharis;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek hydr-, water, and chari, grace]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, of fresh waters. Rhizomes absent; stolons present. Stems floating on or suspended in water, rooted or not, unbranched, short. Leaves basal, emergent or floating, petiolate; blade cordate to reniform or orbiculate, base reniform or cordate, apex obtuse to almost truncate; midvein without rows of lacunae along sides, uniform in color throughout, abaxial surface without prickles, smooth on emergent leaves or with aerenchymous tissue on floating leaves; intravaginal squamules entire. Inflorescences 1-flowered or cymose, sessile or short-pedunculate; spathe not winged. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants [on same plants], emersed, pedicellate; petals white to pinkish. Staminate flowers: filaments distinct or basally connate, distinct portion longer than connate; anthers oval; pollen in monads. Pistillate flowers: ovary 1-locular; styles 6, 2-fid less than ½ length. Fruits spheric, smooth to ridged, dehiscing irregularly. Seeds ellipsoid, minutely tuberculate or muricate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Eurasia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Frog-bit</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 3 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cook, C. D. K. and R. L&amp;uuml;&amp;ouml;nd. 1982. A revision of the genus Hydrocharis (Hydrocharitaceae). Aquatic Bot. 14: 177--204.</reference>
    <reference>Roberts, M. L., R. L. Stuckey, and R. S. Mitchell. 1981. Hydrocharis morsus-ranae (Hydrocharitaceae) new to the United States. Rhodora 83: 147--148.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
