<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Palisot de Beauvois ex Desvaux" date="unknown">eriocaulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kunth" date="1841">lachnocaulon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Ruhland in H. G. A. Engler" date="1903">engleri</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler,Das Pflanzenreich</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13[IV,30]: 241. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family eriocaulaceae;genus lachnocaulon;species engleri</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, short-lived perennial, solitary or cespitose, forming low domes of rosettes, 6--15 cm. Leaves mostly linear-triangular, 2--4 cm, apex acute. Inflorescences: scape sheaths shorter than or as long as principal leaves; scapes filiform, distally 0.4 mm thick, 4--5-ribbed, glabrous; mature heads dark brown or reddish brown, nearly globose, usually short cylindric by seeding time, 3--4 mm; receptacle densely pilose; involucral bracts soon reflexed, brown, mostly ovate, 1(--1.5) mm, apex broadly acute to obtuse, surfaces glabrous or apex sparsely pilose, hairs translucent, club-shaped; receptacular bracts, dark brown, broadly spatulate or obovate-cuneate, concave, with broad, low, pale keel, 1--1.5 mm, apex short-acuminate, glabrous or abaxial surface with translucent, club-shaped hairs distally. Staminate flowers: sepals 3, dark brown, narrowly spatulate to oblanceolate-cuneate, concave, 1 mm, glabrous or abaxially with scattered translucent, club-shaped hairs distally; androphore pale, narrowly obconic, as long as sepals, glabrous, rarely apex with few club-shaped hairs; stamens 2--3, appendages (2--)3. Pistillate flowers: sepals 3, dark brown, spatulate-oblong, concave, 1 mm, abaxially sparsely pubescent distally, hairs translucent; gynoecium 3-carpellate; styles: apex 3-cleft, appendages 3. Seeds rich translucent brown, broadly ovoid to ellipsoid, 0.4--0.5 mm, longitudinal ribs conspicuous and pale, transverse striae fine forming linear cancellae.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer--fall</description>
  <description type="habitat">Moist sandy-peaty lake and pond shores, drawdowns, ditchbanks, low sandy clearings in savanna and flatwoods</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--100 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
