<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Palisot de Beauvois ex Desvaux" date="unknown">eriocaulaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Kunth" date="1841">Lachnocaulon</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>3: 497. 1841</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family eriocaulaceae;genus Lachnocaulon</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek lachnos, wool, and chaulos, stem, in reference to the long, soft, upwardly pointed hairs on scapes of the type]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, cespitose, rosulate. Roots branched, dark, not septate, slender, fibrous. Stems sparingly branched, short or elongate. Leaves crowded, in spirals; blade mostly linear, lacunar tissue not evident, base pale, dilated. Inflorescences: scape sheaths tubular, orifice oblique, acute, or 2-cleft; scapes usually several per stem, filiform, glabrous or hairy, hairs neither swollen nor glandular apically; heads white, gray, gray-brown, or brown, ovoid to globose or short-cylindric; receptacle densely pale-pilose; involucral bracts pale to dark, gradate, broad, chaffy, basal ones often reflexed, obscured by inflorescence; receptacular bracts as long as involucral bracts. Flowers: staminate and pistillate on same plants, 3-merous (2-merous in Lachnocaulon digynum); sepals 3, connivent forming club-shaped flower, nearly distinct, spatulate, scarious, apex with club-shaped hairs, surface glabrous or sparsely hairy; petals absent or reduced to small scales or hairs. Staminate flowers: androphore cylindric; stamens (2--)3; apex of staminal column with 2--3 lance-ovoid or peglike, often appendaged glands; filaments adnate to rim of androphore, alternating with glands; anthers 1-locular, 2-sporangiate, dorsifixed, versatile, exserted at anthesis, yellowish or pale. Pistillate flowers: gynophore short; pistil 3-carpellate (2-carpellate in L. digynum); style 1, appendaged at apex, style branches 2--3, 2-cleft, alternating with appendages similar to those of staminate flower.</description>
  <description type="distribution">se United States and Cuba.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species ca. 10 (5 in the flora): se United States and Cuba.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species ca. 10 (5 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>se United States and Cuba.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hat-pins</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">bog bachelor's buttons</other_name>
  <discussion>Species ca. 10 (5 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Apical hairs of receptacular bracts and perianth white, mealy, opaque; heads pale gray to white; scapes hairy (except for glabrous-scaped, s Florida extreme of Lachnocaulon anceps).</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Apical hairs of bracts and perianth translucent, not white, the brown color of bract and perianth showing through; heads brown or gray-brown; scapes glabrous or with ascending hairs.</description>
      <next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves narrowly linear, abruptly attenuate; mature heads seldom wider than 4 mm, dull gray-brown or pale gray; scapes glabrous or nearly so distally; seeds dark red-brown, very lustrous, longitudinal ribs faint, transverse ribs forming finely cross-striolate pattern</description>
      <determination>1 Lachnocaulon beyrichianum</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves linear, gradually attentuate; mature heads seldom as narrow as 4 mm, whitish to pale gray; scapes pilose from base to apex; seeds pale to dark brown, not lustrous, longitudinal ribs conspicuous, transverse ribs less conspicuous than longitudinal ribs, but coarser than in Lachnocaulon beyrichianum</description>
      <determination>2 Lachnocaulon anceps</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scapes with ascending hairs; heads dull gray-brown; hairs of receptacle copious, partly obscuring flowers (old heads may lose some hairs); gynoecium 3-carpellate</description>
      <determination>3 Lachnocaulon minus</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>3</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Scapes glabrous; heads either chocolate brown or dull brown, if dull brown, with sepals of pistillate flowers yellow-white, hardly obscured by receptacular hairs; gynoecium 2--3-carpellate.</description>
      <next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads dark brown or reddish brown, usually short cylindric by seeding time; gynoecium 3-carpellate; leaves 2--4 cm; scape sheaths shorter than or as long as leaves</description>
      <determination>4 Lachnocaulon engleri</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>4</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Heads gray or gray-brown, usually globose by seeding time; gynoecium 2-carpellate; leaves 0.5--2 cm, scape sheaths longer than or at least rising above leaves</description>
      <determination>5 Lachnocaulon digynum</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
