<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>3</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Lachnocaulon</genus_name><species_name>minus</species_name><species_authority>(Chapman) Small</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Flora of the Southeastern United States</publication_title><place_in_publication>235, 1328. 1903</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="BASIONYM"><genus_name>Lachnocaulon</genus_name><species_name>michauxii</species_name><species_authority>Kunth</species_authority><variety_name>minor</variety_name><variety_authority>Chapman</variety_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Fl. South. U.S. ed. </publication_title><place_in_publication>3, 531. 1897</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Lachnocaulon</genus_name><species_name>eciliatum</species_name><species_authority>Small</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, short-lived perennial, solitary or cespitose, forming low domes of rosettes, 6--15(--20) cm. Leaves linear-triangular, 2--4 cm, apex narrowly acute to subulate. Inflorescences: scape sheaths shorter than principal leaves; scapes filiform, 0.3--0.4 mm thick, 4--5-ribbed, pilose from base to apex, with ascending hairs; mature heads dull gray-brown, globose to short-cylindric, 3--4 mm wide; receptacle copiously hairy, partly obscuring flowers (old heads may lose some hairs); involucral bracts soon reflexed, pale to dark brown, mostly ovate or broadly oblong, 1 mm, apex broadly acute, distal margins pilose, hairs translucent, capitate, abaxial surface distally pilose, hairs translucent; receptacular bracts pale brown to chestnut brown, broadly spatulate or pandurate, concave, 1(--1.5) mm, apex rounded or obtuse, abaxial surface pilose toward apex, hairs translucent; Staminate flowers: sepals 3, chestnut brown, base greenish, spatulate, blade concave, 1--1.5 mm, apex rounded or obtuse, abaxial surface pilose toward apex, hairs translucent; androphore yellow-white, narrowly obconic, as long as sepals, glabrous, rarely with apex hairy, hairs club-shaped, short; anthers 3, appendages 3. Pistillate flowers: sepals 3, pale, spatulate, concave, 1--1.5 mm, apex obtuse or short-acuminate, abaxial surface apically with translucent hairs; gynoecium 3-carpellate; stylar column pale, apex 3-cleft, appendages 3. Seeds deep clear brown, ellipsoid, 0.5 mm, apex apiculate, body longitudinally low-ribbed, ribs pale, transverse striae fine.</description><discussion>The favorite habitat of Lachnocaulon minus is the fluctuating shores of karst ponds where it may be aspect dominant along the edge of the maximum pool.</discussion><phenology>Flowering summer--fall</phenology><habitat> Sands and peats of pond edges, ditchbanks, lake shores, drawdowns or moist exposed seeps</habitat><elevation>0--200 m</elevation><us_distribution>Ala.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Fla.</us_distribution><us_distribution> Ga.</us_distribution><us_distribution> N.C.</us_distribution><us_distribution> S.C.</us_distribution></treatment>
