<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Gray" date="unknown">lemnaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">lemna</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Landolt" date="1975">turionifera</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Aquatic Botany</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 355, fig. 4g--h. 1975</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family lemnaceae;genus lemna;species turionifera</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots shorter than 15 cm, tip mostly rounded; sheath not winged. Stipes white, small, often decaying. Fronds floating, 1 or 2--few, coherent in groups, obovate, scarcely gibbous, flat, 1--4 mm, 1--1.5 times as long as wide, margins entire; veins 3, greatest distance between lateral veins near or distal to above middle; papillae distinct on midline of upper surface (apical papilla scarcely larger than others); lower surface often red (more intensely so than on upper), coloring beginning at attachment point of root, upper surface (especially near apex) sometimes with red spots; air spaces to 0.3 mm; turions sometimes present, rootless, olive to brown, 0.8--1.6 mm diam., sinking to bottom. Flowers: ovaries 1-ovulate, utricular scale with narrow opening at apex. Fruits 0.5--0.6 mm, not winged. Seeds with 30--60 indistinct ribs, staying within fruit wall after ripening. 2n = 40, 42 (G), 50, 80.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering (occasional) summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Mesotrophic to --eutrophic, quiet waters, in continental, temperate regions;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--3700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">St. Pierre and Miquelon; Alta., B.C., Man., N.B., Nfld. and Labr., N.W.T., N.S., Ont., P.E.I., Que., Sask., Yukon; Ala., Alaska, Ariz., Calif., Colo., Conn., Idaho, Ill., Ind., Iowa, Kans., Mass., Mich., Minn., Mo., Mont., Nebr., Nev., N.J., N.Mex., N.Y., N.Dak., Ohio, Okla., Oreg., Pa., R.I., S.Dak., Tex., Utah, Vt., Wash., W. Va., Wis., Wyo.; Mexico (Baja California); Eurasia.</description>
  <number>4</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Lenticulare turionifère</other_name>
  <discussion>I know of no specimens of Lemna turionifera from Maine, New HampshireSt. Pierre and Miquelon, or from New Jersey, but the species is to be expected there..</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
