<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Richard" date="unknown">juncaginaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Bonpland in A. von Humboldt and A. J. Bonpland" date="1808">lilaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Poiret) Hauman" date="1925">scilloides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Publ. Inst. Invest. Geogr. Fac. Filos. Letras Univ. Buenos Aires</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>A 10:26. 1925</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family juncaginaceae;genus lilaea;species scilloides</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Phalangium</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Poiret" date="unknown">scilloides</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. Lamarck et al., Encycl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 251. 1804</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Phalangium;species scilloides;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Lilaea</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Humboldt &amp; Bonpland" date="unknown">subulata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Lilaea;species subulata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, to 30 cm. Leaves to 35 cm; sheath 2--5 cm; blade 15--30 cm &amp;#180; 0.9--3.1 mm. Inflorescences axillary or sessile, the axillary scapose, 0.3--4 cm &amp;#180; 1.5--8 mm; scape 8--10 cm &amp;#180; 0.5--1.5 mm.; sessile inflorescences solitary flowers. Flowers sessile; perianth 1--1.5 &amp;#180; 0.5 mm; anther 0.5 &amp;#180; 0.4 mm; ovary 1--2 mm; style 0.5 mm (bisexual), 30 cm (pistillate). Fruits 2--5 mm. 2n = 12.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Shallow water and adjacent mud flats;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--1700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C., Sask.; Calif., Mont., Nev., Oreg., Wash.; Mexico; South America (Argentina, Chile, Ecuador, Peru); introduced, se Australia.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <discussion>The taxonomic position of Lilaea is uncertain. The genus often is treated as a monotypic family (Lilaeaceae) that is closely allied to the Juncaginaceae. Lilaea, for example, possesses lactifers, unknown in other Juncaginaceae. The lactifers, plus uncertainty regarding the interpretation of floral morphology in Lilaea, prompted a decision to retain it in the Liliaeaceae pending further study (P. B. Tomlinson 1982). Embryologic, cytologic, and palynologic evidence, however, indicate a close relationship between Lilaea and other genera of the Juncaginaceae. Despite the presence of lactifers, Lilaea has been considered similar enough to warrant the inclusion of the genus in the Juncaginaceae (A. Cronquist 1981). Molecular evidence also corroborates the close relationship between Lilaea and Triglochin (D. L. Les and R. R. Haynes 1995).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cronquist, A. 1981. An Integrated System of Classification of Flowering Plants. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Tomlinson, P. B. 1982. Helobiae (Alismatidae). In: C. R. Metcalfe, ed. 1982. Anatomy of the monocotyledons. Oxford. Vol. 7.</reference>
    <reference>Les, D. H. and R. R. Haynes. 1995. Systematics of Alismatiflorae: A synthesis of molecular and non-molecular approaches. In: P.</reference>
    <reference>Rudell, P. et al., eds. 1995. Monocotyledons: Systematics and Evolution. Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Great Britain. Pp. 353--377.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
