<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. de Jussieu" date="unknown">hydrocharitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Richard" date="1814">Limnobium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Memoires de la Classe des Sciences Mathematiques et Physiques de L'Institut National de France</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>12(2): 66. 1814</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hydrocharitaceae;genus Limnobium</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek limnobios, living in pools]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants perennial, of fresh waters. Rhizomes absent; stolons floating on or suspended in water, rooted or not, unbranched, short. Leaves basal, emergent or floating, petiolate; blade elliptic to orbiculate, base reniform or cordate, apex obtuse to acuminate; midvein without rows of lacunae along sides, blade uniform in color throughout, abaxially surface without prickles, smooth on emergent leaves or with aerenchymous tissue on floating leaves; intravaginal squamules entire. Inflorescences cymose, sessile or short-pedunculate; spathe not winged. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on same plants, emersed, pedicellate; petals greenish white to yellowish. Staminate flowers: filaments connate at least ½ their length; anthers elongate; pollen in monads. Pistillate flowers: ovary 1-locular, falsely 6--9-locular; styles 3--9, 2-fid nearly to base. Fruits ellipsoid to spheric, smooth to ridged, dehiscing irregularly. Seeds ellipsoid, echinate, covered with blunt cylindric hairs.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 2 (1 in the flora): North America, Central America, South America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, Central America, South America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">American frog-bit</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 2 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cook, C. D. K. , and K. Urmi-K&amp;ouml;nig. 1983. A revision of the genus Limnobium including Hydromystria (Hydrocharitaceae). Aquatic Bot. 17: 1--27.</reference>
    <reference>D&amp;iacute;az-Miranda, D., D. Philcox, and P. Denny. 1981. Taxonomic clarification of Limnobium Rich. and Hydromystria G. W. F. Meyer (Hydrocharitaceae). Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 83: 311--323.</reference>
    <reference>Hunziker, A. T. 1981. Hydromystria laevigata (Hydrocharitaceae) en el centro de Argentina. Lorentzia 4: 5--8.</reference>
    <reference>Hunziker, A. T. 1982. Observaciones biol&amp;oacute;gicas y taxon&amp;oacute;micas sobre Hydromystria laevigata (Hydrocharitaceae). Taxon 31: 472--477.</reference>
    <reference>Wilder, G. J. 1974. Symmetry and development of Limnobium spongia (Hydrocharitaceae). Amer. J. Bot. 61: 624--642.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
