<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. Jussieu" date="unknown">juncaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="de Candolle in J. Lamarck and A. P. de Candolle" date="unknown">luzula</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hamet-Ahti" date="1971">hitchcockii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Annales Botanici Fennici</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8: 368. 1971</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family juncaceae;genus luzula;species hitchcockii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes short to long-running, thick. Culms cespitose, 15--50 cm. Leaves: basal blade flat, apex involute?? revolute??, mostly glabrous; cauline leaves 3--5, 2--6 cm &amp;#61620;x 3--10 mm. Inflorescences anthelate; branches spreading less than 90°, lax; proximal bracts much shorter than inflorescence; bracts brownish, clear toward apex, margins lacerate; bracteoles light brown, 1/2 length of tepals, margins dentate. Flowers solitary or in pairs; tepals reddish to dark brown, nearly equal, 2.5--3.5 mm, apex acute, not reflexed; anthers 3 times filament length; stigmas 2 times style length. Capsules blackish, ovoid, 2.5--3.5 mm; beak to 1 mm. Seeds dark brown, 1.2--1.8 mm; caruncle barely visible.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering and fruiting summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Montane forest to subalpine and alpine slopes, ridges, and meadows;</description>
  <description type="elevation">1700--2400 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Alta., B.C.; Idaho, Mont., Oreg., Wash.</description>
  <number>5</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Hitchcock's wood rush</other_name>
  <discussion>Although Luzula hitchcockii has been reported from California, no convincing specimens have been seen by this author. The species resembles the European L. glabrata (Hoppe) Desvaux very closely; however, it is readily distinguished from all other North American species. Plants may be heavily infested with Ustilago vuijckii Oudemans. and Beijerinck. complete last names??, which considerably alters their usual appearance.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
