<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">marantaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Maranta</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 2. 1753; Gen. Pl., ed. 5; 2, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family marantaceae; genus Maranta;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[for Bartolomea Maranti, Venetian physician and botanist who lived during the mid 1500s]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants terrestrial, prostrate, scandent, or upright, usually dying back to rhizome during dry season, 0.1--1.5(--1.8) m. Rhizomes occasionally swollen, storing starch. Stems branched or unbranched with basal and cauline leaves to highly branched above elongate, cane-like stem (internode) with few or no basal leaves. Leaves homotropic [rarely antitropic]; sheath usually auriculate, not spongy; blade [patterned] plain green, ovate to elliptic. Inflorescences usually 2--several per shoot, spikel-like, unbranched; bracts persistent, subtending 2--6 pedicellate flower pairs, herbaceous; prophylls keeled, membranous; secondary bracts absent; bracteoles usually absent. Flowers self-fertilizing [or outcrossing], corolla white, staminodes white [purple]; sepals persistent in fruit, more than 5 mm, herbaceous; corolla tube [4--]12--14 mm, corolla lobes unequal; outer staminodes 2, petal-like; callose staminode apex usually petal-like; cucullate staminode with 1 appendage, medial [subterminal], flaplike [fingerlike]; stylar movement in single plane; style unappendaged. Fruits capsules, 1-seeded, obliquely ellipsoid, pericarp relatively thin, dehiscent. Seeds brown, ellipsoid, rugose; perisperm canal 1, distally branched; aril conspicuous, white.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical and subtropical regions</description>
  <description type="distribution">s Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America (to n Argentina).</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Arrowroot</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">prayer-plant</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 32 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Andersson, L. 1986. Revision of Maranta subgen. Maranta. Nordic J. Bot. 6: 729--756. Anonymous. 1893. St. Vincent arrowroot. Bull. Misc. Inform. Kew 1893: 191--204.</reference>
    <reference>Hodge, W. H. and D. Taylor. 1957. The ethnobotany of the Island Caribs of Dominica. Webbia 12: 513--644.</reference>
    <reference>Morton, J. F. 1977. Wild Plants for Survival in South Florida, ed. 4. Miami.</reference>
    <reference>Sturtevant, W. C. 1969. History and ethnography of some West Indian starches. In: P. J. Ucko and G. W. Dimbleby, eds. 1969. The Domestication and Exploitation of Plants and Animals. Chicago. Pp. 177--199.</reference>
    <reference>Purseglove, J. W. 1972. Tropical Crops. Monocotyledons. 2 vols. London. Pp. 336--342.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
