<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Alan T. Whittemore</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. Jussieu" date="unknown">Musaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Musaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
    
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Treelike herbs, perennial, from corm [rhizome] [corm]. True aerial stems absent. Leaves basal, in several ranks, differentiated into basal sheath, petiole, and blade; sheaths overlapping, forming unbranched pseudostem, open, ligule absent; summit of petiole not differentiated; blade with lateral veins parallel, diverging from prominent midrib. Inflorescences 1 per aerial shoot, projecting from tip of pseudostem, pedunculate racemes of 12--20-flowered monochasial cymes (cincinni); bracts of main axis enclosing cincinni. Flowers unisexual (proximal flowers pistillate, distal flowers staminate), bilaterally symmetric; sepals and petals differentiated, sepals 3, petals 3, 3 sepals and 2 petals fused, remaining petal distinct; fertile stamens 5(--6), not petal-like; anthers 2-locular; occasionally 1 rudimentary staminode; ovary inferior, 3-carpellate, 3-locular, all locules fertile; placentation axile; ovules many per locule; style terminal, filiform; stigma 3-lobed. Fruits berries; sepals not persistent in fruit. Seeds: aril absent; endosperm copious; perisperm copious; embryo straight. x = 9, 10, 11.</description>
  <description type="distribution">tropical parts of Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia</description>
  <description type="distribution">and Oceania</description>
  <description type="distribution">often persisting around gardens and plantations throughout the wet tropics.</description>
  <number>216</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Banana Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 3, species ca. 40 (1 genus, 1 species, and 1 stable hybrid in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
