<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>1</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Najas</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 1015. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5; 445, 1754</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Bushy-pondweed</common_name><common_name> naid</common_name><common_name> water-nymph</common_name><common_name> naiade</common_name><etymology>[Greek Nnaias, a water-nymph]</etymology><description>Herbs, aquatic, glabrous, submersed in fresh or brackish waters. Stems slender, much branched, rooting at proximal nodes, sometimes armed with prickles on internodes. Leaves: sheaths variously shaped, margins usually toothed with 1--15 teeth per side, teeth similar in size and structure to those of blades; blade linear, 1-veined, sometimes armed with prickles on midvein abaxially, margins usually serrate to minutely serrulate with 5--100 teeth per side, apex acute to acuminate, with 1--3 teeth, teeth multicellular, formed by layers of cells decreasing in cell number distally, terminated by large, sharp-tipped cell, or teeth unicellular. Inflorescences: involucres mostly present in staminate flowers, rare in pistillate, clear, bronze, brown, light green, purple, or red-purple. Staminate flowers subtended by membranous involucre, involucre rarely absent; peduncle short, elongating at anthesis, pushing flower through involucre; anther sessile, 1- or 4-loculed. Pistillate flowers sessile; ovary 1-loculed; ovules basal, 1; style terminal (arising off-center at apex of ovary and fruit in Najas gracillima), 2--4-branched. Fruits dehiscing by decay of ovary wall; ovary wall extremely delicate, closely enveloping seed. Seeds fusiform to obovoid, apex occasionally asymmetric or recurved, aerolateareolate; raphe basal; testa 3 or 10--15 cell layers thick, hard, brittle; aeroleareoles formed by outer two cell layers of testa, irregularly arranged or in 15--60 longitudinal rows, end walls often raised, giving testa papillose appearance; endosperm absent. x = 6.</description><discussion>Seeds are necessary for certain determination of species of Najas.</discussion><number_of_infrataxa>Species 40 (8 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> nearly worldwide.</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference> Chase, S. S. 1947. Preliminary Studies in the Genus Najas in the United States. Ph.D. thesis. , Cornell University. Chase, S. S. 1947b. Polyploidy in an immersed aquatic angiosperm. [Abstract.] Amer. J. Bot. 34: 581--582.</reference><reference> Haynes, R. R. 1979. Revision of North and Central American Najas (Najadaceae). Sida 8: 34--56.</reference><reference> Haynes, R. R. and C. B. Hellquist. 1996. New combinations in North American Alismatidae. Novon 6: 370--371.</reference><reference> Lowden, R. M. 1986. Taxonomy of the genus Najas L. (Najadaceae) in the Neotropics. Aquatic Bot. 24: 147--184.</reference><reference> Triest, L. 1988. A revision of the genus Najas L. (Najadaceae) in the Old World. M&amp;eacute;m. Acad. Roy. Sci. Belgique, Cl. Sci. (8&amp;#176; ), n. s. 22: 1--172, 29 plates. Wentz, W. A. and R. L. Stuckey. 1971. The changing distribution of the genus Najas (Najadaceae) in Ohio. Ohio J. Sci. 71: 292--302.</reference></references><key><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Staminate and pistillate flowers on different plants; testa pitted, 10--15 cell layers thick; midrib of leaf blade abaxially with prickles; internodes of stem usually with prickles; seeds 1.2 mm wide or wider</statement><determination>1 Najas marina</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>1</statement_id><statement>Staminate and pistillate flowers on same plants; testa smooth or pitted, 3 cell layers thick; midrib of leaf blade abaxially without prickles; internodes of stem without prickles; seeds 1.2 mm or less wide, if 1.2 mm wide, then with smooth testa.</statement><next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Style offset to one side of center at seed apex</statement><determination>5 Najas gracillima</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>2</statement_id><statement>Style situated at center of seed apex.</statement><next_statement_id>3</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3</statement_id><statement>Seeds recurved; leaves usually recurved with age.</statement><next_statement_id>4</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>3</statement_id><statement>Seeds not recurved; leaves spreading to ascending with age.</statement><next_statement_id>5</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>4</statement_id><statement>Areoles of testa broader than long, ladderlike; widespread in a variety of habitats</statement><determination>7 Najas minor</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>4</statement_id><statement>Areoles of testa longer than broad, never ladderlike; plants of Florida and Georgia in sandy-bottomed lakes</statement><determination>6 Najas filifolia</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>5</statement_id><statement>Teeth of leaf blade multicellular, 8--22 per side</statement><determination>8 Najas wrightiana</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>5</statement_id><statement>Teeth of leaf blade unicellular, 18--100 per side.</statement><next_statement_id>6</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>6</statement_id><statement>Testa smooth, glossy; seeds narrowly to broadly obovoid, deep brown to yellow; anthers 1-loculed</statement><determination>2 Najas flexilis</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>6</statement_id><statement>Testa pitted, dull; seeds fusiform, yellowish white to greenish or reddish brown or with purple tinge; anthers 1- or 4-loculed.</statement><next_statement_id>7</next_statement_id></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>7</statement_id><statement>Leaf sheath deeply auriculate at apex; restricted in North America to California</statement><determination>4 Najas graminea</determination></key_statement><key_statement><statement_id>7</statement_id><statement>Leaf sheath rounded to truncate slightly auriculate at apex; widespread in the flora.</statement><determination>3 Najas guadalupensis</determination></key_statement></key></treatment>
