<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">araceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Orontium</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 324. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5; 151, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family araceae; genus Orontium;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[ancient Greek name for plant that grew on River Orontes]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, wetland. Rhizomes vertical. Leaves appearing before flowers, several, emergent or sometimes floating, clustered; petiole longer than blade; blade abaxially paler green, adaxially dark bluish green with distinctive velvety sheen, simple, not peltate, oblong-elliptic, base acute to obtuse or sometimes oblique, apex rounded-apiculate or short-acuminate; venation parallel to midvein except near base. Inflorescences: peduncle reclining in fruit, usually equal to or longer than leaves, apex swollen; spathe absent; spadix long-conic. Flowers mostly bisexual, the distal staminate; perianth present. Fruits partially embedded in spadix, green to blue-green. Seed 1, embedded in mucilage. x = 13.</description>
  <description type="distribution">e United States</description>
  <description type="distribution">primarily on coastal plain.</description>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Golden-club</other_name>
  <discussion>The leaf sheathing the peduncle, which has been interpreted as the spathe in Orontium, is a sympodial leaf and is not equivalent to the spathe of other Araceae (T. S. Ray 1988). Orontium also differs in several other characteristics from the presumably related genera Lysichiton and Symplocarpus and has been segregated as a monogeneric tribe (M. H. Grayum 1990).</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Grear, J. W. Jr. 1966. Cytogeography of Orontium aquaticum (Araceae). Rhodora 68: 25--34.</reference>
    <reference>Klotz, L. H. 1992. On the biology of Orontium aquaticum L. (Araceae), golden club or floating arum. Aroideana 15: 25--33.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
