<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">hydrocharitaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Persoon" date="unknown">Ottelia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Syn. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 400. 1805</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family hydrocharitaceae; genus Ottelia;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Malay am ottelambel, apparently from otta, to stick to, in reference to thin leaves that stick to body, and am bel, nymphaea]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants annual or perennial, of fresh waters. Rhizomes and stolons absent [present]. Erect stems rooted in substrate, unbranched, short. Leaves basal, submersed [floating], petiolate; blade lanceolate to reniform [linear], base cuneate to cordate, apex rounded to acute; midvein without rows of lacunae along sides, blade uniform in color throughout; abaxial surface without prickles or aerenchyma, smooth; intravaginal squamules entire. Inflorescences scapose, long-pedunculate; spathes winged or ribbed. Flowers bisexual [unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants], sessile [staminate pedicellate], floating or occasionally opening under water; petals white to pink or light violet, often yellow at base; filaments distinct; pollen in monads; ovary 1-locular; styles 3--9, not 2-fid. Fruits oblong, ridged, dehiscing irregularly. Seeds fusiform, covered with hairs.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <number>3</number>
  <discussion>Species 21 (1 in flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Cook, C. D. K., J.-J. Symoens, and K. Urmi-K&amp;ouml;nig. 1984. A revision of the genus Ottelia (Hydrocharitaceae). I1. Generic considerations. Aquatic Bot. 18: 263--274.</reference>
    <reference>Cook, C. D. K. and K. Urmi-K&amp;ouml;nig. 1984. A revision of the genus Ottelia (Hydrocharitaceae). 2. The species of Eurasia, Australasia, and America. Aquatic Bot. 20: 131--177.</reference>
    <reference>Holmes, W. C. 1978. Range extension for Ottelia alismoides (L.) Pers. (Hydrocharitaceae). Castanea 43: 193--194.</reference>
    <reference>Turner, C. E. 1980. Ottelia alismoides (L.) Pers. (Hydrocharitaceae) — U.S.A., California. Madro&amp;ntilde;o 27: 177.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
