<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Peltandra</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Linnaeus) Schott" date="unknown">virginica</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. W. Schott and S. L. Endlicher,Meletemata Botanica</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>19. 1832</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Peltandra;species virginica;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Arum</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">virginicum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 966. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Arum;species virginicum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Peltandra</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Fernald" date="unknown">luteospadix</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Peltandra;species luteospadix;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Peltandra</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="F. A. Barkley" date="unknown">tharpii</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Peltandra;species tharpii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Arrow arum</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">t Arrow arum</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">u tTuckahoe</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">peltandre</other_name>
  <discussion>Leaf shape is highly variable in Peltandra virginica, and different forms have been recognized taxonomically, both at the specific and infraspecific levels. Since Because leaf shape varies within populations and even within an individual clump of plants, P. virginica is treated here as a single taxon.</discussion>
  <discussion>Populations of Peltandra virginica are most common along the Atlantic Coastal Plain, but its range appears to be actively expanding. Since 1978, the species was reported as new to the floras of Iowa, Kansas, Minnesota, West Virginia, and Wisconsin, and introduced populations may persist in Oregon and California. Fruits and seeds of P. virginica are a food for wildlife, especially waterfowl, and their use by migratory birds is an important factor in the spread of this species.</discussion>
  <discussion>The flowers of Peltandra virginica are pollinated by a chloropid fly, Elachiptera formosa (Diptera: Chloropidae), which uses the inflorescence as a mating site and a larval food source. Eggs are deposited within the inflorescence, and the emerging larvae feed on the rotting male portion of the spadix. The fruits are primarily dispersed by water, although animals also play a role.</discussion>
  <discussion>Peltandra virginica may have been an important food plant for eastern Native Americans, especially in the mid-Atlantic coastal region from Pennsylvania to Virginia, where the plants are now common and grow in large, dense populations. Historical accounts mention use of the rhizomes as well as the leaves, fruits, and seeds as food.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
