<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Juss." date="unknown">araceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">pistia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="1753">stratiotes</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 963. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family araceae;genus pistia;species stratiotes</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Pistia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">spathulata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pistia;species spathulata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Roots to 50 cm, with short branches. Leaves light green to grayish green, 2--15(--20) cm, spongy, pubescence dense, white; major veins 5--13(--15), nearly parallel, abaxially prominent. Inflorescences: spathe white to pale green, convolute basally, slightly constricted above middle, spreading apically, pwhite to pale green, pubescent outside, glabrous inside; spadix adnate to spathe more than 1/2 its length, shorter than spathe; axis naked at base of staminate part and sometimes extending beyond staminate flowers. Flowers: staminate flowers (2--)6--8, in single whorl around central stalk, stamens 2, connate; pistillate flower solitary; ovariesy 1-locular, 4--5 mm; ovules 4--15(--20), orthotropous; styles ca. 3 mm; stigmas obtuse, with small hairs. ; staminate flowers (2--)6--8, in single whorl around central stalk; stamens 2, connate. Fruits with thin pericarp. Seeds light brown, cylindric, 2 &amp;#180; 1 mm. 2n = 28 (India, Borneo).</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering mainly late summer--early winter (although</description>
  <description type="habitat">plants have been collected in flower in almost all months). Slow-moving streams, canals, drainage ditches, ponds, lakes, and springs</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--10 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">La.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Asia</description>
  <description type="distribution">Africa</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pacific Islands</description>
  <description type="distribution">Australia.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering mainly late summer--early winter (although; plants have been collected in flower in almost all months). Slow-moving streams, canals, drainage ditches, ponds, lakes, and springs; 0--10 m; Fla., La., Tex.; Mexico; West Indies; Central America; South America; Asia; Africa; Pacific Islands; Australia.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering mainly late summer--early winter (although; plants have been collected in flower in almost all months).</phenology>
      <habitat>Slow-moving streams, canals, drainage ditches, ponds, lakes, and springs;</habitat>
      <elevation>0--10 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Fla., La., Tex.; Mexico; West Indies; Central America; South America; Asia; Africa; Pacific Islands; Australia.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Water-lettuce</other_name>
  <discussion>Pistia stratiotes has been collected north and west of its U.S. range in Arizona, California, Georgia, Missouri, New Jersey, Ohio, and South Carolina. These are probably populations that do not persist. Although P. stratiotes is often reported as occurring from Florida to Texas, I saw no verifying herbarium specimens from Alabama or Mississippi, nor were any populations located during my fieldwork in those states.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Arditti, J. and E. Rodriguez. 1982. Dieffenbachia: Uses, abuses and toxic constituents: A review. J. Ethnopharmacol. 5: 293--302.</reference>
    <reference>Barrett, O. W. and O. F. Cook. 1910. Promising root crops for the South. U.S.D.A. Bur. Pl. Industr. Bull. 164: 1--43.</reference>
    <reference>Bartram, W. 1791. Travels through North and South Carolina, Georgia, East and West Florida, the Cherokee Country, the Extensive Territories of the Muscogulges, or Creek Confederacy, and the Country of the Chactaws.... Philadelphia.</reference>
    <reference>Blackwell, W. H. and K. P. Blackwell. 1974. The taxonomy of Peltandra (Araceae). J. Elisha Mitchell Sci. Soc. 90: 137--140.</reference>
    <reference>Blair, A. 1975. Karyotypes of five plant species with disjunct distributions in Virginia and the Carolinas. Amer. J. Bot. 62: 833--837.</reference>
    <reference>Boivin, B. 1967--1979. Flora of the prairie provinces. Part I (--IV). Phytologia 15--18, 22--23, 42--43; passim. [Reprinted as Provancheria 2--5 with auxiliary pagination.]</reference>
    <reference>Bruner, M. C. 1982. Water-lettuce, Pistia stratiotes L. Aquatics 4(3): 4--5.</reference>
    <reference>Camazine, S. and K. J. Niklas. 1984. Aerobiology of Symplocarpus foetidus: Interactions between spathe and spadix. Amer. J. Bot. 71: 843--850.</reference>
    <reference>Case, F. W. , Jr. 1992. Plants for the bog garden. Bull. of the Amer. Rock Garden Soc. 50: 129--144.</reference>
    <reference>Clay, K. 1993. Size-dependent gender change in green dragon (Arisaema dracontium; Araceae). Amer. J. Bot. 80: 769--777.</reference>
    <reference>Coates, D. J., D. E. Yen, and P. M. Gaffey. 1988. Chromosome variation in taro, Colocasia esculenta: Implications for origin in the Pacific. Cytologia 53: 551--560.</reference>
    <reference>Croat, T. B. 1994. The use of the New World Araceae as drug plants. J. Jap. Bot. 69: 185--203.</reference>
    <reference>Dorn, R. D. 1977. Manual of the Vascular Plants of Wyoming. 2 vols. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Duncan, W. H. and J. T. Kartesz. 1981. Vascular Flora of Georgia: An Annotated Checklist. Athens, Ga.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L., and A. C. Kinsey, and (revised by R. C. Rollins). 1958. Edible Wild Plants of Eastern North America, revised ed. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Grayum, M. H. 1987. A summary of the evidence and arguments supporting the removal of Acorus from the Araceae. Taxon 36: 723--729.</reference>
    <reference>Harley, K. L., R. C. Kassulke, D. P. Sands, and M. D. Day. 1990. Biological control of water lettuce, Pistia stratiotes (Araceae) by Neohydronomus affinis (Coleoptera: Curculionidae). Entomophaga 35: 363--374.</reference>
    <reference>Henkel, A. 1907. American root drugs. U.S.D.A. Bur. Pl. Industr. Bull. 107: 1--80.</reference>
    <reference>Huttleston, D. G. 1949. The three subspecies of Arisaema triphyllum. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 76: 407--413.</reference>
    <reference>Huttleston, D. G. 1981. The four subspecies of Arisaema triphyllum. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 108: 479--481.</reference>
    <reference>Judd, W. W. 1961. Insects and other invertebrates associated with flowering skunk cabbage, Symplocarpus foetidus (L.) Nutt., at Fanshawe Lake, Ontario. Canad. Entomol. 93: 241--249.</reference>
    <reference>Kalm, P. 1770--1771. Travels into North America.... 3 vols. Warrington and London.</reference>
    <reference>Kinoshita, E. 1986. Size-sex relationship and sexual dimorphism in Japanese Arisaema (Araceae). Ecol. Res. (Tokyo) 1: 157--171.</reference>
    <reference>Knutson, R. M. 1972. Temperature measurements of the spadix of Symplocarpus foetidus (L.) Nutt. Amer. Midl. Naturalist 88: 251--254.</reference>
    <reference>Lammers, T. G. and A. G. van der Valk. 1979. A checklist of the aquatic and wetland vascular plants of Iowa: II. Monocotyledons, plus a summary of the geographic and habitat distribution of all aquatic and wetland species in Iowa. Proc. Iowa Acad. Sci. 85: 121--163.</reference>
    <reference>Lampe, K. F. and M. A. McCann. 1985. AMA Handbook of Poisonous and Injurious Plants. Chicago, Illinois.</reference>
    <reference>L&amp;ouml;ve, &amp;Aacute;. and S. Kawano. 1961. A note on amphi-pacific Lysichitum. J. Jap. Bot. 36: 359--361.</reference>
    <reference>L&amp;ouml;ve, &amp;Aacute;. and J. C. Ritchie. 1966. Chromosome numbers from central northern Canada. Canad. J. Bot. 44: 429--439.</reference>
    <reference>Marchant, C. J. 1971. Chromosome variation in Araceae: 2. Richardieae to Colocasieae. Kew Bull. 25: 47--56.</reference>
    <reference>Marchant, C. J. 1973. Chromosome variation in Araceae: 5. Acoreae to Lasieae. Kew Bull. 28: 199--210.</reference>
    <reference>Mason, H. L. 1957. A Flora of the Marshes of California. Berkeley, California.</reference>
    <reference>Moerman, D. E. 1986. Medicinal Plants of Native America. 2 vols. Ann Arbor. [Univ. of Michigan, Mus. of Anthropol. Techn. Reports. 19:.] 1--910 (Research Reports in Ethnobotany, Contrib. 2).</reference>
    <reference>Perkins, K. D. and W. W. Payne. 1978. Guide to the Poisonous and Irritant Plants of Florida. Gainesville, Florida.</reference>
    <reference>Ray, T. S. 1988. Survey of shoot organization in the Araceae. Amer. J. Bot. 75: 56--84.</reference>
    <reference>Sanders, L. L. and C. J. Burk. 1992. A naturally-occurring population of putative Arisaema triphyllum subsp. stewardsonii × A. dracontium hybrids in Massachusetts. Rhodora 94: 340--347.</reference>
    <reference>Scoggan, H. J. 1957. Flora of Manitoba. Bull. Natl. Mus. Canada 140: 1--619.</reference>
    <reference>Small, J. A. 1959. Skunk cabbage, Symplocarpus foetidus. Bull. Torrey Bot. Club 86: 413--416.</reference>
    <reference>Taylor, R. L. and G. A. Mulligan. 1968. Flora of the Queen Charlotte Islands. Part 2. Cytological Aspects of the Vascular Plants. Ottawa. Uemura, S., K.</reference>
    <reference>Young, R. A. 1936. The dasheen: A southern root crop for home use and market. U.S.D.A. Farmers Bull. 1396: 1--38.     TABLE 203.1. Cultivated Araceae which that occasionally naturalize or persist from cultivation. Taxon Will Key To Distinguishing CharacterISTICs Comments Aglaonema commutatum Schott Peltandra Leaves oblanceolate to oblong with thick midveins and parallel venation; creeping or erect above-ground stem; spathe not differentiated into tube and blade Dade Co., Florida; persisting after cultivation, rarerarely found Alocasia macrorrhizos (Linnaeus) Schott Peltandra Leaves net-veined between primary lateral veins; aboveground stem; spadix with sterile appendage Dade Co., Florida; persisting for short periods, rarerarely found Arum italicum Linnaeus Peltandra Leaves net-veined between primary lateral veins; long sterile appendage California, Louisiana, North Carolina, Oregon; escaping locally and forming colonies Caladium bicolor (Aiton) Ventenat Colocasia Leaves usually variegated with pink, red, or white; spadix without sterile appendage Florida, Louisiana; rarerarely found Dracunculus vulgaris Schott Arisaema dracontium Spadix about as long as spathe; spathe with large distinct blade California, Oregon; rarerarely found Epipremnum pinnatum (Linnaeus) Engler cv. 'Aureum' Will not key well to any genus Stem scandent; juvenile leaves entire, adult leaves irregularly pinnatifid, leaves variegated with yellow; rarely flowering Florida; escaping and persisting in shady hammocks and on roadside trees Pinellia ternata (Thunberg) Makino Arisaema triphyllum Petiole with bulbils basally and at apex; base of spadix adnate to spathe on one side California, District of Columbia, Maryland, New Jersey, New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania, West Virginia; very local, forming colonies usually in gardens and nurseries Syngonium podophyllum Schott Arisaema Stems scandent; milky sap; juvenile leaves entire, adult leaves pedatisect Florida; established on roadside trees and hammocks, local; other species of Syngonium may persist, but are rarerarely found Xanthosoma spp. Peltandra Leaves not peltate, net-veined between primary lateral veins; may have aboveground stem; spadix without sterile appendage Southern Florida, Louisiana, and Texas; persisting from cultivation, rarely spreading Zantedeschia aethiopica (Linnaeus) Sprengel Peltandra Spathe funnel-shaped, not constricted, white California; uncommon</reference>
    <reference>Bierzychudek, P. 1982. The demography of Jack-in-the-pulpit, a forest perennial that changes sex. Ecol. Monogr. 52: 335--351.</reference>
    <reference>Bowden, W. M. 1940. Diploidy, polyploidy, and winter hardiness relationships in the flowering plants. Amer. J. Bot. 27: 357--370.</reference>
    <reference>Dray, F. A. Jr. and T. D. Center. 1989. Seed production by Pistia stratiotes L. (water lettuce) in the United States. Aquatic Bot. 33: 155--160.</reference>
    <reference>Eastwood, A. 1900. Some plants of Mendocino County new to the flora of California. Zo&amp;euml;e 5: 58--60.</reference>
    <reference>Greenwell, A. B. 1947. Taro---with special reference to its culture and uses in Hawaii. Econ. Bot. 1: 276--289.</reference>
    <reference>Kartesz, J. T. and K. N. Gandhi. 1992. Nomenclatural notes for the North American flora, X. Phytologia 72: 80--92.</reference>
    <reference>Matuda, E. 1954. Las Araceas mexicanas. Anales Inst. Biol. Univ. Nac. M&amp;eacute;xico 32: 147--155.</reference>
    <reference>Mulligan, G. A. and D. B. Munro. 1990. Poisonous Plants of Canada. Ottawa, Canada. O’</reference>
    <reference>Hair, S. K. and M. P. Asokan. 1986. Edible aroids: Botany and horticulture. Hort. Rev. 8: 43--99.</reference>
    <reference>Petersen, G. 1989. Cytology and systematics of Araceae. Nordic J. Bot. 9: 119--166.</reference>
    <reference>Ohkawara, G. Kudo, N. Wada, and S. Higashi. 1993. Heat-production and cross-pollination of the Asian skunk cabbage Symplocarpus renifolius (Araceae). Amer. J. Bot. 80: 635--640.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
