<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Pistia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 963. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5; 411, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Pistia;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[Greek pistra, watertrough, in reference to the aquatic habitat]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>8</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Water-lettuce</other_name>
  <discussion>Although many names have been published in Pistia, it is currently considered to contain a single, highly variable species. Morphological variation is strongly influenced by environmental conditions and population density. Some botanists consider the genus to have been introduced into the United States and many regional floras state that fruits and seeds are not produced in the flora area. However, s Seeds with high rates of germination have been reported from many sites in Florida, however (F. A. Dray Jr. and T. D. Center 1989). The status of Pistia as native to the United States has not been resolved; available evidence suggests that it is indigenous.</discussion>
  <discussion>Pistia is economically and biologically important as a breeding site for insects, especially species of mosquitoes in the genus Mansonia, and it is often an aquatic weed. Although a serious pest in some areas of the world, Pistia has not caused major problems in the United States (M. C. Bruner 1982). At least 23 species of insects worldwide have been reported to feed on P. stratiotes; those shown to be effective in biological control include Neohydronomus affinis (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Erirhininae) and Samea multiplicalis (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae: Pyraustinae) (M. C. Bruner 1982; K. L. Harley et al. 1990). Plants are cultivated as aquatic ornamentals in greenhouses and gardens.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Mitra, E. 1966. Contributions to our knowledge of Indian freshwater plants 5. On the morphology, reproduction and autecology of Pistia stratiotes Linn. J. Asiat. Soc. 8: 115--135.</reference>
    <reference>Stoddard, A. A. 1989. The phytogeography and paleoflo[r]istics of Pistia stratiotes L. Aquatics 11(3): 21--24.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
