<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">potamogetonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">potamogeton</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Tuckerman" date="1843">pulcher</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>American Journal of Science, and Arts</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>45:38. 1843</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family potamogetonaceae;genus potamogeton;species pulcher</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes present. Cauline stems terete, conspicuously spotted, 8--95 cm; nodal glands absent. Turions absent. Leaves both submersed and floating, &amp;#177; spirally arranged. Submersed leaves petiolate, lax; stipules deliquescent, inconspicuous, convolute, free from blade, light to dark brown, not ligulate, 0.7--1.2 cm, not fibrous, not shredding at tip, apex obtuse; petioles 0.5--4.5 cm; blade dark green, linear-lanceolate to lanceolate, often arcuate, 3.5--13.8 cm &amp;#180; 60--165 mm acute, base acute to rounded, without basal lobes, margins entire, crispate, apex not hoodlike, acute to obtuse, lacunae in 2--5 rows each side of midrib; veins 7--19. Floating leaves: petioles continuous in color to apex, 1--16.5 cm; blade adaxially light to dark green, lanceolate to round-ovate, 2.5--8.5 cm &amp;#180; 11--44 mm, base rounded to cordate, apex acute to rounded; veins 15--21. Inflorescences unbranched, emersed; peduncles not dimorphic, terminal or axillary, erect to ascending, cylindric, 3.3--9.4 cm; spikes not dimorphic, cylindric, 17--36 mm. Fruits sessile, dark green to dark brown, ovoid to obovoid, turgid, abaxially keeled, laterally ridged, 5--6.5 &amp;#180; 4.1--5 mm, lateral ridges without points; beak erect, 0.5 mm; embryo with 1 full spiral. Chromosome number apparently unknown not available.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowers summer--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Stagnant to slow-flowing waters of streams, lakes, ponds, and small rivers;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--700 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.B., N.S., Ont. , P.E.I.; Ala., Ark., Conn., Del., Fla., Ga., Ill., Ind., Ky., La., Maine, Md., Mass., Mich., Minn., Miss., Mo., N.H., N.J., N.Y., N.C., Ohio, Okla., Pa., R.I., S.C., Tenn., Tex., Va., W.Va., Wis.</description>
  <number>25</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Spotted pondweed</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">potamot gracieux</other_name>
  <discussion>Potamogeton pulcher is similar in morphology to P. amplifolius and occurs in similar habitats. Potamogeton pulcher differs from P. amplifolius by the former having lanceolate to linear-lanceolate submersed leaves with fewer than 19 veins, whereas the latter has ovate submersed leaves with more than 19 veins.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
