<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">potamogetonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potamogeton</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Hellquist &amp; R. L. Hilton" date="unknown">ogdenii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Systematic Botany</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>8: 88, figs. 1--3, plates 1--2, figs. 1--3. 1983</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family potamogetonaceae; genus Potamogeton;species ogdenii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes absent. Cauline stems compressed-filiform, without spots, to 50 cm; glands green, golden brown to dark brown, 0.2--0.6 mm diam. Turions terminal or lateral, uncommon, 3.7--9.9 &amp;#180; 2.6--6 cm, soft to hard; leaves flattened with outer and inner leaves in same plane; outer leaves 1--2 per side, base not corrugate, apex apiculate; inner leaves undifferentiated or rolled into hardened, fusiform structure. Leaves submersed, &amp;#177; spirally arranged, sessile, rigid; stipules persistent, inconspicuous, convolute, free from blade, brown or rarely white, not ligulate, 0.9--2.1 cm, slightly fibrous, partially shredding at tip, apex obtuse; blade somewhat reddish to olive-green, linear, not arcuate, 1.5--10 cm &amp;#180; 1.2--2.9 mm, base slightly tapering, without basal lobes, not clasping, margins entire, not crispate, apex not hoodlike, cuspidate to bristle-tipped, lacunae present or absent, in 0--3 rows each side of midvein; veins 3--9(--13). Inflorescences unbranched, emersed; peduncles not dimorphic, terminal or occasionally axillary, erect or rarely recurved, slightly clavate, 1--3 cm; spikes not dimorphic, cylindric, 5--11 mm. Fruits sessile, dark green, orbicular, turgid, abaxial keel obscure, lateral keels obscure or absent, 2.5--3 &amp;#180; 2.2--3 mm, lateral keels if present without points; beak erect, 0.5 mm; sides without basal tubercles; embryo with 1 full spiral. Chromosome number unknownnot available.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering mid summer--fall</description>
  <description type="habitat">Alkaline waters of ponds and lakes</description>
  <description type="elevation">100--300 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Conn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mass.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Vt.</description>
  <number>10</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Ogden's pondweed</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">potamot d’Ogden</other_name>
  <discussion>Potamogeton ogdenii is an extremely local species, probably known from fewer than a dozen localities. The species is herein reported for the first time from Canada, being known from that country by a single collection made in 1987.</discussion>
  <discussion type="conservation">of conservation concern</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
