<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">potamogetonaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potamogeton</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Morong" date="unknown">hillii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Botanical Gazette</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>6: 290, fig. 3. 1881</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family potamogetonaceae; genus Potamogeton;species hillii;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Potamogeton</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Fernald" date="unknown">porteri</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Potamogeton;species porteri;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Rhizomes absent. Cauline stems slightly compressed, without spots, 30--60 cm; glands rare, when present, brown to green, 0.1--0.3 mm diam. Turions terminal, rare, 2.8--3 cm &amp;#180; 1.5--3 mm, soft; leaves &amp;#177; 2-ranked; outer leaves 3--4 per side, base not corrugate, apex acute to apiculate; inner leaves undifferentiated. Leaves submersed, &amp;#177; spirally arranged, sessile, delicate; stipules persistent, inconspicuous, convolute, free from blade, white to light brown, not ligulate, 0.7--1.6 cm, slightly fibrous, rarely shredding at tip, apex obtuse; blade pale green to olive-green, linear, not arcuate, 2--6 cm &amp;#180; 0.6--2.5(--4) mm, base slightly tapering, without basal lobes, not clasping, margins entire, not crispate, apex not hoodlike, apiculate to bristle-tipped or rarely blunt, lacunae in 1--2 rows each side of midrib; veins 3. Inflorescences unbranched, emersed; peduncles not dimorphic, axillary and/or terminal, erect to ascending, rarely recurved, slightly clavate, 6--13.5 mm; spikes not dimorphic, globose, (2--) 4--7 mm. Fruits brown to light greenish brown, ovoid to orbicular, turgid, sessile, abaxially and laterally keeled (3-keeled), 2.3--4 &amp;#180; 2--3.2 mm, lateral keels without points; beak erect, 0.3--0.7 mm; sides without basal tubercles; embryo with 1 full spiral. Chromosome number unknownnot available.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering and fruiting summer</description>
  <description type="habitat">Alkaline waters of marshes, ponds, lakes, and slow-moving streams</description>
  <description type="elevation">50--400 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ont.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Conn.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mass.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mich.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.Y.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ohio</description>
  <description type="distribution">Pa.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Vt.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Va.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Wis.</description>
  <number>13</number>
  <discussion>Potamogeton hillii is an easily recognized species either in fruit or when sterile. The leaf blade has a bristle tip and five or fewer veins. Those characters combined with the usual absence of nodal glands will separate this species from all other North American linear-leaved species. Ecologically, it is consistently found in more alkaline waters than any other North American pondweed. A study of 35 localities established the mean to be 124.1 mg/l CaCO3 (C. B. Hellquist 1984).</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hellquist, C. B. 1984. Observations of Potamogeton hillii Morong in North America. Rhodora 86: 101--111.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
