<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>14</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Roystonea</genus_name><genus_authority>O. F. Cook</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Science</publication_title><place_in_publication>ser. 2, 12:479. 1900</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Royal palm palm</common_name><common_name> palmier royal</common_name><etymology>[for Roy Stone, 1836--1905]</etymology><description>Stems solitary, erect, greater than 20 cm in diam., smooth, unarmed. Leaves: leaf bases unarmed, forming crownshaft, crownshaft prominent, green, smooth; petiole unarmed; blade pinnate; plication reduplicate; segments linear-lanceolate, in more than 1 plane. Inflorescences axillary below crown of leaves, paniculate, with 2 or 3 orders of branching; prophyll tubular; peduncular bract greatly exceeding prophyll, leathery, splitting longitudinally on abaxial side and circumscissilly at base; rachillae covered with copious caducous dendritic trichomes, becoming glabrous. Flowers unisexual, sessile, in triads of 1 pistillate flower flanked by 2 staminate flowers. Staminate flowers: sepals 3, imbricate, membranaceous; petals 3, valvate; stamens  6(--10, rarely); anthers dorsifixed, often twisting upon drying; pistillode minute, obscurely 3-cleft. Pistillate flowers globose to conic; sepals 3, imbricate; petals 3, basally connate, distally valvate; staminodes 6, basally connate, adnate to corolla basally; pistil 1; ovules 1; style indistinct; stigmas 3. Fruits drupes, fibrous; stigmatic scar basal; exocarp ripening from green to red to purplish black at maturity, thin, leathery; mesocarp fleshy, oily; endocarp hard. Seeds 1, nearly globose [obovoid], dorsiventrally compressed, abaxially attached to endocarp; endosperm homogeneous; embryo basal; eophyll undivided, linear-lanceolate. x n = 18.</description><discussion>Most species of Roystonea are widely known as royal palms. They are cultivated worldwide and are especially favored as avenue trees. Long rows of gray-white columnar trunks are unmatched for their magnificence and stateliness. In some parts of the Caribbean, especially Cuba, Roystonea is a significant resource for thatch (leafbases only), timber, livestock feed, palmito (palm cabbage or heart-of-palm), and edible oil (F. A. Reynoso 1976; C. Ruebens 1968; T. A. Zanoni 1991; S. Zona 1991, 1996).</discussion><number_of_infrataxa>Species 11 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> Florida</global_distribution><global_distribution> Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution> West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America.</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference> Cook, O. F. 1936. Royal palms in upper Florida. Science, ser. 2, 84: 60--61.</reference><reference> Reynoso, F. A. 1976. Importancia econ&amp;oacute;mica de la palma real dominicana (Roystonea hispaniolana). Agroconocimiento 1: 8--9.</reference><reference> Ruebens, C. 1968. Industrializaci&amp;oacute;n del palmiche en Cuba. Industr. Alimenticia 1: 8--25.</reference><reference> Small, J. K. 1937. Facts and fancies about our royal palm. J. New York Bot. Gard. 38: 49--58.</reference><reference> Zanoni, T. A. 1991. The royal palm on the island of Hispaniola. Principes 35: 49--54.</reference><reference> Zona, S. 1991. Notes on Roystonea in Cuba. Principes 35: 225--233.</reference><reference> Zona, S. 1996. Roystonea (Arecaceae: Arecoideae). In: Organization for Flora Neotropica. 1968+. Flora Neotropica. 75+ nos. New York. No. 71, pp.1--36.</reference></references></treatment>
