<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Mark A. Nienaber</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="F. Rudolphi" date="unknown">Scheuchzeriaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family Scheuchzeriaceae</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, rhizomatous, caulescent; turions absent. Leaves alternate, emergent, sessile; sheath with remains often persisting, auriculate; blade linear, nearly cylindric, with conspicuous round pore adaxially on leaf tip; intravaginal squamules hairs, numerous. Inflorescences terminal, bracteate racemes, not subtended by spathe; pedicels following fertilization elongating, not spiraling. Flowers bisexual; subtending bracts present; perianth present; tepals 6; stamens 6, epitepalous; anthers basifixed, distinct, dehiscing longitudinally, extrorse; pollen globose; pistils 3(--6), distinct to slightly connate at base; ovules basal-marginal, anatropous. Fruits follicles. Seeds 1--2(--3).</description>
  <description type="distribution">colder parts of the Northern Hemisphere.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Genus Genera 1, species 1: colder parts of the Northern Hemisphere.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Genus Genera 1, species 1</discussion>
      <distribution>colder parts of the Northern Hemisphere.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>193</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Scheuchzeria Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Scheuchzeriaceae have sometimes been included in Juncaginaceae. That Scheuchzeria represents a family by itself is accepted by the majority of post-1940 workers (J. W. Thieret 1988).</discussion>
  <discussion>Genus Genera 1, species 1:</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Britton, N. L. 1909. Scheuchzeriaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 17(1), , pp. 41--42.</reference>
    <reference>Cody, W. J. 1975. Scheuchzeria palustris L. (Scheuchzeriaceae) in northwestern North America. Canad. Field-Naturalist 89: 69--71.</reference>
    <reference>Fernald, M. L. 1923. The American variety of Scheuchzeria palustris. Rhodora 25: 177--179.</reference>
    <reference>Thieret, J. W. 1988. The Juncaginaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 69: 1--23.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
