<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Schultz Schultzenstein" date="unknown">arecaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Martius" date="1826">Syagrus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Palm. Fam.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>18. 1824</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family arecaceae;genus Syagrus</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[classical name, derivation unknown, but a name used by Pliny for a kind of palm]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Stems solitary, erect, robust, unarmed, bearing conspicuous nodal rings. Leaves: petiole unarmed; sheath not forming crownshaft; blade pinnate, unarmed; plication reduplicate; segments regularly arranged in multiple planes, apices acute to 2-cleft. Inflorescences axillary within crown of leaves, paniculate, 1 order of branching, ascending, becoming pendulous in fruit; prophyll short; peduncular bract woody, beaked, splitting abaxially, becoming boat-shaped. Flowers unisexual, sessile, borne in triads of 1 pistillate flower flanked by 2 staminate, staminate flowers borne singly along distal portions of rachillae. Staminate flowers: sepals 3, connate; petals 3, free, valvate, leathery; stamens 6, free; anthers linear; pistillode with 3 minute lobes. Pistillate flowers borne basally on rachillae, massive; sepals 3, imbricate, free; petals 3, imbricate, free; staminode a low annular ring at base of pistil; pistil 1, large; ovules 1; style indistinct; stigmas 3. Fruits drupes, ovoid, less than 4 cm diam.; exocarp orange, thin, smooth; mesocarp fleshy, oily; endocarp thick, bony, irregularly folded into seed, with 3 basal germination pores. Seeds irregular with hollow cavity; endosperm homogeneous; embryo basal; eophyll undivided, lanceolate.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies (Lesser Antilles)</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Species 32 (1 in the flora): North America, West Indies (Lesser Antilles), South America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <discussion>Species 32 (1 in the flora)</discussion>
      <distribution>North America, West Indies (Lesser Antilles), South America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>17</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Queen palm</other_name>
  <discussion>Species 32 (1 in the flora):</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
