<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Syngonanthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Michaux) Ruhland" date="unknown">flavidulus</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in H. G. A. Engler,Das Pflanzenreich</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>13[IV,30]: 256. 1903</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Syngonanthus;species flavidulus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="BASIONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Eriocaulon</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Michaux" date="unknown">flavidulum</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. Bor.-Amer.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 166. 1803</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Eriocaulon;species flavidulum;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Paepalanthus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="(Michaux) Kunth" date="unknown">flavidulus</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Paepalanthus;species flavidulus;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, cespitose, rosulate, 5--30 cm. Stems contracted or elongate to 5 cm, chaffy. Leaves: principal leaves mostly spreading-recurved, narrowly linear, 2--6 cm, base pale, apex narrowly acute to subulate, abruptly dilated, surfaces nearly glabrous or grading to copiously hairy. Inflorescences: scape sheaths erect or narrowly ascending, as long as leaves, proximal surfaces glabrous or scattered glandular-pilosulous; scapes filiform, to 1 mm wide, pilose, hairs variably ascending to spreading, translucent, pubescence increasingly glandular distally; mature heads white or yellow-white (aging dull white or pale gray), hemispheric to globose, 5--10 mm wide; receptacle densely pilose, hairs translucent, sharp; involucral bracts ascending, later spreading to recurved, lance-oblong or narrowly ovate, larger ones 3 mm, margins entire, apex acute, glabrous; receptacular bracts absent. Staminate flowers: sepals pale translucent, spatulate to oblanceolate, 2--3 mm, apex acute, adaxially pilose distally; androphore 2.5 mm, hairy at base; petals pale yellow, short-triangular. Pistillate flowers: sepals pale, translucent, linear or narrowly oblong, 3 mm, apex acuminate, surfaces glabrescent; petals connivent or connate above ovary forming beaklike apex, pale, narrowly linear, 3 mm; gynophore hairy; style with apex unappendaged; stigma branches exsert, linear. Seeds translucent brown, ovoid, 0.5 mm, finely longitudinally lined, very finely cross-lined, apex apiculate.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring--early summer</description>
  <description type="habitat">Moist sands of bog and pond edges, ditchbanks, pine savanna, sandhills ecotones</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--200 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ga.</description>
  <description type="distribution">N.C.</description>
  <description type="distribution">S.C.</description>
  <number>1</number>
</bio:treatment>
