<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Thalia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Fraser" date="unknown">dealbata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Thalia dealbata</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>[plate]. 1794</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Thalia;species dealbata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Thalia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Small" date="unknown">barbata</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Thalia;species barbata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Powdery thalia</other_name>
  <discussion>Thalia dealbata is the only species of Marantaceae endemic to North America and the only one not found in the tropics. Its sister species, T. multiflora Horkel ex K&amp;ouml;rnicke, is similarly restricted, but to the southernmost part of the range, southern Brazsil to Uruguay. It is possible that our species is the result of an early, chance long-distance dispersal event from a South American population. This might partially explain why the plants are autogamous in spite of the elaborate floral mechanism.</discussion>
  <discussion>Thalia dealbata is grown as an ornamental in tropical and temperate gardens and is hardy as far north as Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Vancouver, British Columbia when the rhizome is submersed during winter.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bentley, R. and H. Trimen. [1875--]1880. Medicinal Plants.... 4 vols. in 42 parts. London. Vol. 4, p. 265. Hartgerink, T. et al. 1978. Pollination of clumped and dispersed inflorescences of Thalia geniculata. Field Problem report, Tropical Biology -- ---An Ecological Approach, 78-1. Organization for Tropical Studies, Inc., Costa Rica. Pp. 159--162. Kennedy, H. 1992. Calatheas---their distribution, diversity, and potential for horticulture. Bull. Heliconia Soc. Int. 6(2): 3--4. Koch, K. 1857. Maranta, Thalia, Phrynium und Calathea. Bermerkungen im Allgemeinen, ihre Kultur und Beschreibung einiger neuen Arten. Allg. Gartenzeitung 21: 145--149. Mahanty, H. K. 1970. A cytological study of the Zingiberales with special reference to their taxonomy. Cytologia 35: 13--49. McAtee, W. L. 1915. Eleven important wild-duck foods. Bull. U.S.D.A. 205: 1--25. Miege, J. 1960. Troisi&amp;egrave;me liste de nombres chromosomiques d'esp&amp;egrave;ces d'Afrique occidentale. Ann. Fac. Sci. Univ. Dakar 5: 75--85. Sat&amp;ocirc, D. 1960. The karyotype analysis in Zingiberales with special reference to the proto-karyotype and stable karyotype. Sci. Pap. Coll. Gen. Educ. Univ. Tokyo 10: 225--243. Shuey, A. G. 1975. A red-petioled form of Thalia geniculata L. from central Florida. Rhodora 77: 210--212. Simmonds, N. W. 1954. Chromosome behaviour in some tropical plants. Heredity 8: 139--146. Suessenguth, K. 1921. Bemerkungen zur meiotischen und somatischen Kernteilung bei einigen Monokotylen. Flora 114: 313--328. Titford, W. J. 1812. Sketches toward a Hortus Botanicus Americanus. London.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
