<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Thalia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 1193. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5; 3, 1754</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Thalia;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[FfFor Johann Thal, German physician and botanist who lived during the mid 1500s]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>2</number>
  <discussion>Thalia is not closely related to any of the other Neotropical genera (L. Andersson 1981), and it is the only genus of Marantaceae that is strictly aquatic. The cucullate staminode bearing two appendages, the helical stylar movement, and the appendaged style are unique within the family. Also unique is the prevalence of various air chambers in the leaf sheath and petiole, a specialization for the aquatic habitat, which gives the sheath its distinctive spongy texture. Dispersal by water is probably the most common means of dispersal: a gas-filled space between the seed and the fruit wall in Thalia makes the fruit buoyant (C. J. Grootjen 1983). Fruits of T. geniculata have also been reported to be eaten by ducks (W. L. McAtee 1915). Carpenter bees (Xylocopa spp.) are reported to pollinate T. geniculata in Costa Rica ( T. Hartgerink et. al. 1978) and in cultivation in Asia (R. Classen-Backhoff 1991).</discussion>
  <discussion>The widely varying chromosome numbers reported for species of Thalia probably represent errors or misinterpretations. Chromosome counts in Marantaceae are difficult, and few taxa have been adequately studied.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 6 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Andersson, L. 1981b. Revision of the Thalia geniculata complex (Marantaceae). Nordic J. Bot. 1: 48--56. Classen-</reference>
    <reference>Dressler, R. L. et al. 1987. Identification Manual for Wetland Plant Species of Florida.... Gainesville. P. 119. Classen-</reference>
    <reference>Godfrey, R. K. and J. W. Wooten. 1979. Aquatic and Wetland Plants of Southeastern United States: Monocotyledons. Athens, Ga. Pp. 621--622.</reference>
    <reference>Gris, A. 1859. Observations sur la fleur des Marant&amp;eacute;es. Ann. Sci. Nat., Bot. s&amp;eacute;r. 4, 12: 193--219, plates 11--14.</reference>
    <reference>Koechlin, J. 1964. Marantac&amp;eacute;es. In: A. Aubr&amp;eacute;ville and J.-F. Leroy. 1961+. Flore du Gabon. 354+ vols. Paris. Vol. 9, pp. 91--158.</reference>
    <reference>Bockhoff, R. 1991. Untersuchungen zur Konstruktion des Best&amp;auml;ubungsapparates Von Thalia geniculata (Marantaceen). Bot. Acta 104: 183--193.</reference>
    <reference>Bockhoff, R. 1991. Untersuchungen zur Konstruktion des Best&amp;auml;ubungsapparates Von Thalia geniculata (Marantaceen). Bot. Acta 104: 183--193.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves glabrous adaxially; inflorescences lax, broadly spreading to pendant, paniclelike array; rachis internodes 5--20 mm; bracts not pruinose, green or streaked or tinged with purple</description>
      <determination>1 Thalia geniculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves pilose at base adaxially; inflorescences erect, tightly clustered, compact array; rachis internodes 2--3 mm; bracts markedly pruinose, appearing whitish, red-brown to red-purple beneath waxy coating</description>
      <determination>2 Thalia dealbata</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
