<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>9</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Thalassia</genus_name><genus_authority>Banks &amp; Solander ex K. D. König</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Annals of Botany</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 96. 1805</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Turtle-grass</common_name><etymology>[Greek thalass, sea]</etymology><description>Plants perennial, of marine waters. Rhizomes present; leaf-bearing branches arising from rhizomes at distances of several internodes; stolons absent. Erect stems rooted in substrate, unbranched, short. Leaves 2--6, basal, submersed, sessile; blade linear, base tapering to stem; apex obtuse; midvein without lacunae along side(s), blade uniform in color throughout; abaxial surfacely without prickles; intravaginal scales entire. Inflorescences 1-flowered to cymose, pedunculate; spathes not winged. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants, submersed, short-pedicellate to nearly sessile; petals absent. Staminate flowers: filaments distinct; anthers linear; pollen embedded in gelatinous matrix, in moniliform chains. Pistillate flowers: ovary 1-locular; styles 6--8, not 2-fid. Fruits spheric, echinate, dehiscing into 6--8 irregular valves. Seeds pyriform; seed coat ephemeral.</description><number_of_infrataxa>Species 2 (1 in flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution> Asia</global_distribution><global_distribution> Australia.</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference> Grey, W. F. and M. D. Moffler. 1978. Flowering of the seagrass Thalassia testudinum (Hydrocharitaceae) in the Tampa Bay, Florida area. Aquatic Bot. 5: 251--259.</reference><reference> Moffler, M. D., M. J. Durako, and W. F. Grey. 1981. Observations on the reproductive ecology of Thalassia testudinum (Hydrocharitaceae) in Tampa Bay, Florida. Aquatic Bot. 10: 183--187.</reference><reference> Moore, D. R. 1963. Distribution of the sea grass, Thalassia, in the United States. Bull. Mar. Sci. Gulf Caribbean 13: 329--342.</reference><reference> Orpurt, P. R. and L. L. Boral. 1964. The flowers and seeds of Thalassia testudinum K&amp;ouml;nig. Bull. Mar. Sci. Gulf Caribbean 14: 296--302.</reference></references></treatment>
