<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. Jussieu" date="unknown">bromeliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">tillandsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Swartz" date="1797">setacea</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Flora Indiae Occidentalis</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>1: 593. 1797</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bromeliaceae;genus tillandsia;species setacea</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tillandsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus (in part)" date="unknown">tenuifolia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tillandsia;species tenuifolia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants densely clustering, flowering to 30 cm. Stems short. Leaves 15--30, many-ranked, finely appressed, erect, green to reddish green, 20--30 &amp;#180; 0.1--0.4 cm, uniformly scaly throughout; sheath rust-colored, broadly triangular, flat, not forming pseudobulb, 0.8--1.8 cm wide; blade very narrowly linear-triangular, ribbed, leathery, margins involute, apex filiform-attenuate. Inflorescences: scape conspicuous, erect, 8--15 cm, 2--4 mm diam.; bracts densely imbricate, erect; sheath of bracts, especially upper ones, narrowing abruptly into blade; spikes erect, palmate (rarely simple), linear, compressed, 1--4 &amp;#180; 0.5--0.6 cm, apex acute; branches 1--5. Floral bracts imbricate, erect, green or tinged red, broad (covering all or most of rachis, rachis not visible at anthesis), ovate, keeled only toward apex, 0.8--1.2 cm, thin-leathery, base not visible at anthesis, apex attenuate to acute, surfaces appressed-pale scaly, venation slight. Flowers 3--15, conspicuous; sepals with adaxial pair connate, elliptic, keeled, 0.8--1 cm, thin-leathery, veined, apex acute, surfaces slightly scaly; corolla tubular, petals erect, lavender, ligulate, 1.8--2.2 cm; stamens exserted; stigma exserted, conduplicate-spiral. Fruits 2--3 cm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring--fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Epiphytic on a variety of hosts in swamps and humid forests;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--60 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla., Ga.; Mexico; West Indies; Central America.</description>
  <number>9</number>
  <discussion>It is probable that Mexican and Central American materials represent one or more additional species.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
