<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. Jussieu" date="unknown">bromeliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">tillandsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Schultes f. in J. J. Roemer and J. A. Schultes" date="1830">balbisiana</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>in J. J. Roemer and J. A. Schultes,Syst. Veg.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>7(2):1212. 1830</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bromeliaceae;genus tillandsia;species balbisiana</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants single or clustering, flowering to 75 cm. Stems short. Leaves 15--30, many-ranked, reflexed, twisted or contorted, gray, often flushed red, to 65 &amp;#180; 0.6--1.4 cm, appressed-grayish-scaly; sheath conspicuously rust-colored toward base, ovate to elliptic, conspicuously inflated, forming small pseudobulb, 2--4 cm wide; blade linear-triangular, leathery, channeled to involute, apex attenuate. Inflorescences: scape conspicuous, erect, 8--30 cm, 2--4 mm diam.; bracts densely imbricate, spreading, recurved and twisted like leaves; sheath of bracts narrowing gradually into blade; spikes erect, 2-pinnate, linear, compressed, 2--10 &amp;#180; 1 cm, apex acute; lateral branches 2--10 (rarely simple). Floral bracts imbricate, erect, green to red, broad (covering all or most of rachis, rachis not visible at anthesis), elliptic, keeled, 1.5--2 cm, leathery, base not visible at anthesis, apex acute, surfaces glabrous to inconspicuously scaly near apex only, venation even to slight. Flowers 5--30, conspicuous; sepals with adaxial pair connate, lanceolate, keeled, 1.5--2 cm, leathery, apex acute, surfaces glabrous; corolla tubular; petals erect, violet, ligulate, to 3.5 cm; stamens exserted; stigma exserted, conduplicate-spiral. Fruits to 4 cm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring--summer</description>
  <description type="habitat">Epiphytic on a variety of hosts in open woods, cypress swamps, coastal forest</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--30 m</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla.</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <verbatim>
    <text>Flowering spring--summer. Epiphytic on a variety of hosts in open woods, cypress swamps, coastal forest; 0--30 m; Fla.; Mexico; West Indies; Central America; South America.</text>
    <parsed>
      <phenology>Flowering spring--summer.</phenology>
      <habitat>Epiphytic on a variety of hosts in open woods, cypress swamps, coastal forest;</habitat>
      <elevation>0--30 m;</elevation>
      <distribution>Fla.; Mexico; West Indies; Central America; South America.</distribution>
    </parsed>
  </verbatim>
  <number>6</number>
</bio:treatment>
