<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="A. L. Jussieu" date="unknown">bromeliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">tillandsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Elliott" date="1817">bartramii</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <place_in_publication>1: 379. 1817</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family bromeliaceae;genus tillandsia;species bartramii</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants densely clustering, flowering to 20--40 cm. Stems short. Leaves 15--30, many-ranked, erect to spreading, gray, 15--40 &amp;#180; 0.2--0.5 cm, coarsely appressed-scaly; sheath rust-colored toward base, broadly triangular, flat, not forming pseudobulb, 1--2 cm wide; blade linear-subulate, leathery, margins involute, apex attenuate. Inflorescences: scape conspicuous, erect, 8--15 cm, 2--4 mm diam.; bracts densely imbricate, erect; sheath of bracts narrowing gradually into blade; spikes erect, simple or palmate, linear, compressed, 2--4 &amp;#180; 1 cm, apex acute; simple or lateral branches 1--5. Floral bracts imbricate, erect, uniformly red to rose, broad (covering all or most of rachis, rachis not visible at anthesis), elliptic, keeled apically, 1.4--1.7 cm, thin-leathery, base not visible at anthesis, apex acute, surfaces scaly distally, becoming sparsely scaly toward base, venation slight. Flowers 5--20, conspicuous; sepals with adaxial pair connate, elliptic, keeled, to 1.5 cm, thin-leathery, veined, apex obtuse, surfaces scaly; corolla tubular, petals erect, violet, ligulate, 3--4.5 cm; stamens exserted; stigma exserted, conduplicate-spiral. Fruits 2.5--3 cm.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring--summer.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Epiphytic on a variety of hosts in swamps and hammocks;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--60 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Fla., Ga.; Mexico (Tamaulipas).</description>
  <number>10</number>
</bio:treatment>
