<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>12</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Tillandsia</genus_name><species_name>variabilis</species_name><species_authority>Schlechtendal</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Linnaea</publication_title><place_in_publication>18:418. 1844</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Tillandsia</genus_name><species_name>houzeavii</species_name><species_authority>Chapman</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><TaxonIdentification Status="SYNONYM"><genus_name>Tillandsia</genus_name><species_name>valenzuelana</species_name><species_authority>A. Richard</species_authority></TaxonIdentification><description>Plants usually single, rarely clustering, flowering to 40 cm. Stems short. Leaves 15--20, many-ranked, spreading, gray-green or flushed rose, 12--30 &amp;#180; 1--2 cm, finely appressed-scaly; sheath pale to nearly chestnut brown, ovate, flat, not forming pseudobulb, 2--4 cm wide; blade narrowly triangular, tapering evenly from base to apex, nearly plane to channeled, soft, brittle, margins involute, apex attentuate. Inflorescences: scape conspicuous, erect or ascending, 3--10 cm, 2--5 mm diam.; bracts densely imbricate, erect, blade often hanging, like leaves but gradually smaller; sheath of bracts narrowing abruptly into blade; spikes erect or ascending, never palmate, linear, compressed, 5--20 &amp;#180; 0.8--1.2 cm, apex acute; simple or laxly 2--3 lateral branches. Floral bracts laxly imbricate, erect, green, red, or purple, broad (covering all or most of rachis, rachis not visible at anthesis), elliptic, keeled toward apex, 1.8--2 &amp;#180; 0.6--0.9 cm, leathery, base visible in fruit, apex acute, surfaces glabrous. Flowers 5--30, conspicuous; sepals with adaxial pair connate, oblong, keeled, 1.5--1.8 cm, thin-leathery, slightly veined, apex obtuse, surfaces glabrous; corolla tubular, petals erect, lavender-blue, ligulate, to 3 cm; stamens exserted; stigma exserted, conduplicate-spiral. Fruits to 3 cm.</description><phenology>Flowering spring--fall</phenology><habitat> Epiphytic in moist, shaded habitats</habitat><elevation>0--30 m</elevation><us_distribution>Fla.</us_distribution><global_distribution>Mexico</global_distribution><global_distribution>West Indies</global_distribution><global_distribution>Central America</global_distribution><global_distribution>South America.</global_distribution></treatment>
