<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tillandsia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Swartz" date="unknown">fasciculata</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Prodr.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>56. 1788</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tillandsia;species fasciculata;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants clustering, flowering to 65 cm. Stems short. Leaves 20--50, many-ranked, erect to spreading, gray to gray-green, 25--50 &amp;#180; 1--2.5 cm, grayish-scaly; sheath dark rust colored toward base, broadly elliptic, flat, not forming pseudobulb, 3--4 cm wide; blade narrowly triangular, tapering evenly from base to apex, stiff, leathery, channeled to involute, apex attenuate. Inflorescences: scape conspicuous, erect or ascending, 10--35 cm, 4--8 mm diam.; bracts densely imbricate, erect to spreading, like leaves but gradually smaller; sheath of bracts narrowing gradually into blade; spikes erect to spreading, densely palmate to laxly 2(--3)-pinnate, narrowly elliptic, compressed, 5--20 &amp;#180; 1.5--2.5 cm, apex acute; lateral branches 3--15. Floral bracts imbricate, erect, red, red-yellow-green, or green, broad (covering all or most of rachis, rachis not visible at anthesis), elliptic, keeled, 2--4.8 &amp;#180; 1.2--2 cm, thin-leathery, base not visible at anthesis, apex acute, surfaces glabrous or slightly scaly toward apex, venation even to slight. Flowers 10--50, conspicuous; sepals with adaxial pair connate, lanceolate, to 1/2 keeled, to 4.2 cm, leathery, slightly veined, apex acute, surfaces glabrous to slightly scaly; corolla tubular, petals erect, violet (white), ligulate, 5--6 cm; stamens exserted; stigma exserted, conduplicate-spiral. Fruits to 4 cm.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Mexico</description>
  <description type="distribution">West Indies</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America</description>
  <description type="distribution">South America.</description>
  <number>13</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Cardinal airplant</other_name>
  <discussion>Varieties 7 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Luther, H. E. 1993. A new record for Tillandsia (Bromeliaceae) in Florida. Rhodora 95: 342--347.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikes of inflorescence rarely less than 10 cm; floral bracts to 3--4.8 cm</description>
      <determination>13a var. fasciculata</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Spikes of inflorescence, or at least their fertile portions, rarely over 10 cm; floral bracts 2--3 cm.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence laxly palmate, spikes stipitate with elongate, slender, sterile bracteate bases</description>
      <determination>13b var. clavispica</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Inflorescence densely palmate, spikes short-stipitate to subsessile, without elongate, slender, sterile bracteate bases</description>
      <determination>13c var. densispica</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
