<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">commelinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">tradescantia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="E. S. Anderson &amp; Woodson" date="1935">paludosa</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contr. Arnold Arbor.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>9: 83; plate 2, fig. 4; plate 4, fig. 6; plate 11;. 1935</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family commelinaceae;genus tradescantia;species paludosa</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Tradescantia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rafinesque" date="unknown">ohiensis</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="variety" authority="(E. S. Anderson &amp; Woodson) MacRoberts" date="unknown">paludosa</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Tradescantia;species ohiensis;variety paludosa;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, erect, ascending, or occasionally decumbent, rarely rooting at nodes. Stems often much branched distally, 15--60 cm; internodes not at all to slightly glaucous, glabrous. Leaves spirally arranged, sessile, forming nearly right angle with stem, straight; blade narrowly oblong-elliptic to linear-lanceolate, 4--11(--20) &amp;#180; 0.4--1.2 cm (distal leaf blades equal to or narrower than sheaths when sheaths opened, flattened), base often constricted, apex acuminate, not at all to slightly glaucous, glabrous. Inflorescences terminal, often axillary; bracts foliaceous. Flowers distinctly pedicillate; pedicels 0.8--1.5 cm, glabrous; sepals 0.6--0.8 mm, glabrous or with apical tuft of eglandular hairs; petals distinct, pale blue, ovate, not clawed, 1.3--1.5 cm; stamens free; filaments bearded. Capsules 2--5 mm. Seeds 2--3 mm. 2n = 12.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring (Mar--May), sporadically to early fall.</description>
  <description type="habitat">Alluvial bottoms and swamps, forests, roadsides, railroad rights-of-way, fields, ditches, and lawns;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Ark., Fla., La., Miss., Tex.</description>
  <number>6</number>
  <discussion>Tradescantia paludosa is clearly Anderson and Woodson's weakest species, and D. T. MacRoberts (1979) may be correct in treating it as a variety of Trandescantia ohiensis. In view of its importance as a research tool, however, I prefer to maintain T. paludosa as a species until a more rigorous analysis of its variation is published. Plants of this species do not seem to require a winter dormancy, hence they can be cultivated in greenhouses year-round.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
