<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="R. Brown" date="unknown">commelinaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">tradescantia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Rose" date="1899">humilis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Contributions from the U. S. National Herbarium</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>5: 204. 1899</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family commelinaceae;genus tradescantia;species humilis</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, erect or ascending, rarely rooting at nodes. Roots tuberous in part, not brownish-tomentose. Stems spreading, diffusely branched, particularly at base, 0.5--20(--45) cm, densely pubescent to glabrescent. Leaves somewhat recurved or falcate; blade deep green, or paler and somewhat glaucous, linear-lanceolate, 11--20 &amp;#180; 1--2 cm (distal leaf blades equal to or narrower than sheaths when sheaths opened, flattened), margins usually tinged with purple, crisped, puberulent to glabrescent. Inflorescences terminal, solitary, or more frequently also axillary and pedunculate from distal nodes; bracts foliaceous, similar to leaves in form, puberulent to glabrescent. Flowers distinctly pedicillate; pedicels 1.5--2.5 cm, puberulent or pilose with mixed glandular, eglandular hairs; sepals dull green or occasionally edged or suffused with purple, 9--11 mm, pubescent with mixed glandular, eglandular hairs; petals distinct, bright blue or occasionally pink, broadly ovate, not clawed, 11--19 mm; stamens free; filaments bearded. Capsules 6--7 mm. Seeds 2--3 mm; hilum as long as seed. 2n = 12.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering spring (Mar--Jun)</description>
  <description type="habitat">Sandy and rocky soil, formerly also in rich black soil at the edge of the coastal plain, now more commonly in disturbed sites, such as roadsides, fencerows, and railroad rights-of-way</description>
  <description type="distribution">Tex.</description>
  <number>16</number>
</bio:treatment>
