<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>13</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Tradescantia</genus_name><species_name>pedicellata</species_name><species_authority>Celarier</species_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Field &amp; Laboratory</publication_title><place_in_publication>24:6. 1956</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><description>Herbs, erect or ascending, rarely rooting at nodes. Roots: some tuberous, thick. Stems spreading and diffuse, much branched, mainly from base, pubescent with glandular hairs, eglandular hairs, or mixture. Leaves recurved and somewhat lax; blade dark green to yellowish green, linear-lanceolate, mostly 20--30 &amp;#180; 0.5--1.0 cm (distal leaf blades equal to or narrower than sheaths when sheaths opened, flattened), sparsely to densely pubescent. Inflorescences terminal, solitary, or more commonly also with lateral, pedunculate inflorescences; bracts foliaceous, similar to leaves in form, sparsely to densely pubescent. Flowers distinctly pedicillate; pedicels 2.5--4.5 cm, densely pubescent with medium to long, glandular hairs; sepals 6--11 mm, densely pubescent with glandular hairs like those of pedicels, occasionally with a few eglandular hairs; petals distinct, pink to dark blue, broadly ovate, not clawed; stamens free; filaments bearded. Seeds 2--4 mm; hilum as long as seed. 2n = 12.</description><discussion>Tradescantia pedicellata is a most unsatisfactory species. The species may have arisen as a hybrid between Tradescantia humilis and T. occidentalis and been recognized as a species because of its constant morphology and high pollen fertility (R. P. Celarier 1956). C. Sinclair (1967) concluded, however, that there was no evidence for the species' existence, and I have found it very difficult to recognize specimens that agree with the original description (no type has been located).</discussion><discussion>Tradescantia diffusa Bush, a name overlooked by E. Anderson and R. E. Woodson Jr. (1935), has been considered the correct name for this plant (D. T. MacRoberts 1978). After examining the type of T. diffusa, I concluded that it was conspecific with the type of T. humilis.</discussion><phenology>Flowering spring</phenology><habitat> Rocky soil</habitat><us_distribution>Tex.</us_distribution></treatment>
