<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Typha</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">latifolia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>2: 971. 1753</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Typha;species latifolia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>1</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Broad-leaved cat-tail</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">tule espedilla</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">quenouille à feuilles larges</other_name>
  <discussion>The erect shoots of Typha latifolia are more fanlike when young than in other North American species because the proximal leaves (dying by mid season) spread more widely. Undoubtedly native throughout its North American range, where it is often a codominant or minor component of marshes, wet meadows, fens, and other communities. In many places it is apparently being replaced by T. angustifolia and T. angustifolia &amp;#61620; T. latifolia (T. &amp;#61620;glauca) at least partly due to human disturbance of habitats. There is a specimen of T. xglauca from Anticosti Island, Quebec. Locally in California and perhaps elsewhere where hybrids are common, the pollen grains of some T. latifolia plants separate slightly and may be shed partly as mixtures of triads, dyads, and monads, perhaps due to introgression ([S. G. Smith, unpublisheddeletion.). Ph.D. thesis]. See also hybrids in key and genus.</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Kaul, R. B. 1974. Ontogeny of foliar diaphragms in Typha latifolia. Amer. J. Bot. 61: 318--323.</reference>
    <reference>Rowlatt, U. and H. Morshead. 1992. Architecture of the leaf of the greater reed mace, Typha latifolia L. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 110: 161--170.</reference>
    <reference>Yeo, R. R. 1964. Life history of common cattail. Weeds 12: 284--288.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
