<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<treatment><number>4</number><TaxonIdentification Status="ACCEPTED"><genus_name>Vallisneria</genus_name><genus_authority>Linnaeus</genus_authority><place_of_publication><publication_title>Sp. Pl.</publication_title><place_in_publication>2: 1015. 1753; Gen. Pl. ed. 5; 446, 1754</place_in_publication></place_of_publication></TaxonIdentification><common_name>Wild-celery</common_name><etymology>[for Antonio Vallisneri, Italian botanist, 1661--1730]</etymology><description>Plants perennial, of fresh or brackish waters. Rhizomes and stolons present. Erect stems rooted in substrate, unbranched, short. Leaves basal, submersed, sessile; blade linear, base grading into sheath, apex obtuse to apiculate; midvein with 4--5 rows of lacunae on each side, balde appearing 3-zoned with light-colored middle zone bordered on each side by darker zone; abaxial surfacely without prickles or aerenchyma; intravaginal squamules entire. Inflorescences cymose, long-pedunculate; spathe not winged. Flowers unisexual, staminate and pistillate on different plants, submersed or floating, sessile (staminate) or pedicellate (pistillate); petals transparent. Staminate flowers: filaments distinct, released from spathe and floating to surface; anthers spheric; pollen in monads. Pistillate flowers floating; ovary 1-locular; styles 1, not 2-fid. Fruits cylindric to ellipsoid, ridged, dehiscing irregularly. Seeds ellipsoid, glabrous.</description><discussion>Vallisneria is generally considered to have 1-flowered pistillate inflorescences. A few populations in southern United States and Central America, however, have cymes with up to 30 flowers. The United States populations include those in Florida, Alabama, and Mississippi.</discussion><number_of_infrataxa>Species 26 (1 in the flora):</number_of_infrataxa><global_distribution> North America</global_distribution><global_distribution> South America</global_distribution><global_distribution> Eurasia</global_distribution><global_distribution> Africa</global_distribution><global_distribution> Australia.</global_distribution><references heading="SELECTED REFERENCES"><reference> Fernald, M. L. 1918. The diagnostic character of Vallisneria americana. Rhodora 20: 108--110.</reference><reference> Lowden, R. M. 1982. An approach to the taxonomy of Vallisneria L. (Hydrocharitaceae). Aquatic Bot. 13: 269--298. Marie-Victorin, Fr&amp;egrave;re. 1943. Les Vallisn&amp;eacute;ries Am&amp;eacute;ricaines. Contr. Inst. Bot. Univ. Montr&amp;eacute;al 46: 1--38.</reference></references></treatment>
