<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">arecaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="H. Wendland" date="unknown">Washingtonia</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Bot. Zeitung (Berlin)</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>37: 68, 148. 1879</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family arecaceae; genus Washingtonia;</taxon_hierarchy>
    <other_info_on_name type="etymology">[fFor George Washington, 1732--1799, American patriot and first president of the United States]</other_info_on_name>
  </taxon_identification>
  <taxon_identification status="SYNONYM">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Sudworth" date="unknown">Neowashingtonia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Neowashingtonia;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Plants tree palms. Stems solitary, erect, tall, massive in one species (more than 10020 cm diam.)(100--150 cm diam.), partly or completely covered with old leaf bases and marcescent dry leaves forming conspicuous skirt around trunk. Leaves: sheath fibers soft; petiole split at base, conspicuously armed with teeth along margins, sometimes unarmed in tall plants; abaxial hastula absent; adaxial hastula irregularly shaped, margin becoming tattered, fibrous; costa prominent; blade costapalmate; plication induplicate; segments lanceolate, basally connate, bearing fibers between segments; apices 2-cleft or irregularly tattered into fibers. Inflorescences axillary within crown of leaves, paniculate, arching well beyond leaves, with 2 orders of branching; prophyll leathery; rachis bracts very conspicuous, tubular at base, distally flattened and leathery, long; rachillae glabrous. Flowers bisexual, borne singly along rachillae, short- pedicellate; perianth 2-seriate; calyx cupulate, 3-lobed, apices and margins irregular; petals 3, long, chaffy, basally connate into tube; stamens 6, adnate briefly to petals; pistils 3, distinct basally, glabrous; styles connate, slender, long; stigma inconspicuous. Fruits drupes, blackish, ellipsoid; exocarp smooth; mesocarp thin, fleshy; endocarp thin. Seeds ellipsoid; endosperm homogeneous; embryo basal; eophyll undivided, lanceolate. n = 18.</description>
  <description type="distribution">w North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">nw Mexico.</description>
  <number>7</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Fan palm</other_name>
  <other_name type="common_name">palmier evantail de Californie</other_name>
  <discussion>The two species are easy to distinguish when cultivated side by side, but they are sometimes difficult to identify from herbarium specimens. Analysis of flavonoids (S. Zona and R. Scogin 1988) can reliably distinguish the two species.</discussion>
  <discussion>Species 2 (2 in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Bailey, L. H. 1936. Washingtonia. Gentes Herb. 4: 51--82.</reference>
    <reference>Zona, S. and R. Scogin. 1988. Flavonoid aglycones and C-glycosides of the palm genus Washingtonia (Arecaceae: Coryphoideae). SouthW. Naturalist. 33: 498.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trunk greater than 100 cm diam.</description>
      <determination>1 Washingtonia filifera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Trunk less than 80 cm diam.</description>
      <determination>2 Washingtonia robusta</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
