<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="unknown" date="unknown">xyridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="unknown" date="unknown">Xyris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Chapman" date="unknown">difformis</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Fl. South. U.S.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>500. 1860</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family xyridaceae; genus Xyris;species difformis;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, cespitose, (10--)15--70(--90) cm, base not bulbous. Stems compact. Leaves in narrow to broad fans, 5--50 cm; sheaths soft, base reddish; blade deep green, linear to linear---sword-shaped, flat, not twisted, under 7 mm wide, papillate or smooth, margins smooth or papillate, somewhat scabrous. Inflorescences: scape sheaths exceeded by leaves; scapes linear to filiform, terete proximally, terete or ancipital-2-edged--winged distally, 0.5--3 mm wide, variably ribbed, distally with 3 or more somewhat scabrous ribs, ribs papillate to scabrous; spikes prevalently ovoid, 5--20 mm, apex usually acute; fertile bracts (4--)5--7(--9) mm, margins entire, apex rounded. Flowers: lateral sepals included, slightly curved, 5--7 mm, keel brown, scarious, lacerate; petals unfolding in morning, blade obtriangular, 4 mm; staminodes bearded. Seeds translucent to mealy, ovoid to ellipsoid, 0.5 mm, finely lined longitudinally with small papillae.</description>
  <description type="distribution">North America</description>
  <description type="distribution">Central America.</description>
  <number>17</number>
  <discussion>Varieties 3 (3 in the flora):</discussion>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and scapes (except for edges and ribs) smooth; scapes somewhat to much widened distally; 2 ribs comparably wider, making wings, smooth or papillate; seeds translucent</description>
      <determination>17a var. difformis</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Leaves and scapes variously papillate or minutely scabrous; scapes not much widened distally; ribs all equally prominent, somewhat scabrous; seeds translucent or mealy.</description>
      <next_statement_id>2</next_statement_id>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seeds translucent; leaves spreading-ascending in broad fans, rarely as long as 10 cm, linear--sword-shaped; spikes rarely longer than 5 mm.</description>
      <determination>17b var. curtissii</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>2</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Seeds mealy; leaves ascending in broad to narrow fans, rarely shorter than (10--)15 cm, linear; spikes 6--10(--15) mm</description>
      <determination>17c var. floridana</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
