<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>unknown</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="C. Agardh" date="unknown">xyridaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Gronovius in C. Linnaeus" date="1754">xyris</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="species" authority="Beyrich ex Kunth" date="1843">ambigua</taxon_name>
    <place_of_publication>
      <publication_title>Enum. Pl.</publication_title>
      <place_in_publication>4: 13. 1843</place_in_publication>
    </place_of_publication>
    <taxon_hierarchy>family xyridaceae;genus xyris;species ambigua</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, perennial, cespitose or solitary, 30--100 cm. Leaves in broad or narrow fans, (5--)10--40(--50) cm; sheath base tan, straw-colored, or pale pink; blade pale or olive green, linear-triangular, (2--)3--7(--10) mm wide, smooth or slightly papillate, margins smooth to minutely scabrous or papillate. Inflorescences: scape sheaths much exceeded by leaves; scapes linear, rarely flexuous, terete or nearly terete, 1--1.5 mm wide, distally usually 2-ribbed, sometimes with additional ribs; spikes ovoid to ellipsoid, lanceoloid, or cylindric, 10--20(--30) mm; fertile bracts 5--8 mm, margins entire, apex rounded. Flowers: lateral sepals included, dark brown, strongly curved, 4--7 mm, keel firm, ciliate, petals unfolding in morning, blade obovate, 10 mm; staminodes bearded. Seeds translucent, ovoid to ellipsoid, 0.5--0.6 mm, finely multiribbed and cross ribbed. 2n = 18.</description>
  <description type="phenology">Flowering late spring--fall (all year south).</description>
  <description type="habitat">Acid, sandy, moist pine or oak savanna, pine flatwoods, pond shores, ditches, bogs;</description>
  <description type="elevation">0--300 m;</description>
  <description type="distribution">Ala., Ark., Fla., Ga., La., Miss., N.C., S.C., Tenn., Tex., Va.; Mexico; West Indies (Cuba); Mexico; Central America (Belize, Honduras, Nicaragua).</description>
  <number>8</number>
  <discussion>Xyris ambigua is one of the more widespread and weedy of xyrids, frequently invading disturbed moist, sandy areas. It is also one of the most variable in habit and apparently forms intermediates with X. stricta and X. torta.</discussion>
</bio:treatment>
