<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert R. Haynes,                                                       C. Barre Hellquist</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Zannichellia</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">Zannichelliaceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Zannichellia;family Zannichelliaceae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <description type="morphology">Herbs, annual [perennial], not rhizomatous, caulescent; turions absent. Leaves alternate, opposite, or pseudowhorled, often all on same plant, submersed, sessile; sheath not persisting longer than blade, not leaving circular scar when shed, ligulate, not auriculate; blade linear; intravaginal squamules scales, 2. Inflorescences axillary, cymes, without subtending spathe, sessile. Flowers uniasexual, staminate and pistillate flowers on same plant; subtending bracts absent; perianth absent. Staminate flowers: stamens 1; anther dehiscing longitudinally; pollen globose. Pistillate flowers: pistils (1--)4--5(--8), distinct, short-stipitate; ovules pendulous, anatropous. Fruits drupaceous. Seeds 1; embryo curved.</description>
  <description type="distribution">nearly worldwide.</description>
  <number>198</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Horned- pondweed Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Genera 4, species 10--12 (1 genus, 1 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Campbell, D. H. 1897. A morphological study of Naias and Zannichellia. Proc. Calif. Acad. Sci., ser. 3, 1: 1--70.</reference>
    <reference>Haynes, R. R. and L. B. Holm-Nielsen. 1987. The Zannichelliaceae in the southeastern United States. J. Arnold Arbor. 68: 259--268.</reference>
    <reference>Posluszny, U. and P. B. Tomlinson. 1977. Morphology and development of floral shoots and organs in certain Zannichelliaceae. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 75: 21--46.</reference>
    <reference>Taylor, N. 1909. Zannichelliaceae. In: N. L. Britton et al., eds. 1905+. North American Flora.... 47+ vols. New York. Vol. 17, pp. 13--27.</reference>
    <reference>Tomlinson, P. B. and U. Posluszny. 1976. Generic limits in the Zannichelliaceae (sensu Dumortier). Taxon 25: 273--279.</reference>
  </references>
</bio:treatment>
