<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<bio:treatment xmlns:bio="http://www.github.com/biosemantics" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.github.com/biosemantics http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <meta>
    <source>
      <author>Robert R. Haynes</author>
      <date>unknown</date>
    </source>
  </meta>
  <taxon_identification status="ACCEPTED">
    <taxon_name rank="genus" authority="Linnaeus" date="unknown">Zostera</taxon_name>
    <taxon_name rank="family" authority="Dumortier" date="unknown">Zosteraceae</taxon_name>
    <taxon_hierarchy>genus Zostera;family Zosteraceae;</taxon_hierarchy>
  </taxon_identification>
  <number>200</number>
  <other_name type="common_name">Eel-grass Family</other_name>
  <discussion>Substantial differences occur in the literature concerning the morphology of the Zosteraceae, especially the reproductive structures. For a discussion of those differences, see C. den Hartog (1970). In summary, the flowers are unisexual, embedded in a spadix, and may or may not each be subtended by a bract or retinaculum. The spadix is subtended by a spathe, and it may or may not be retained within that spathe following fruit production. Spathes are produced on specialized branches (generative shoots), rather than occurring over the entire plant. The generative shoots may or may not contain normal vegetative leaves, but they do contain one or more spathes. The term inflorescence is ambiguous for Zosteraceae, and den Hartog used ‘rhipidium’ instead. In this treatment ‘inflorescence’ is used to include the spathe, spadix, and flowers.</discussion>
  <discussion>Genera 3, species 18 (2 genera, 5 species in the flora):</discussion>
  <references>
    <reference>Hartog, C. den. 1970. The Sea-grasses of the World. Amsterdam.</reference>
    <reference>Phillips, R. C. and C. P. McRoy, eds. 1980. Handbook of Seagrass Biology: An Ecosystem Perspective. New York.</reference>
    <reference>Haynes, R. R. and L. B. Holm-Nielsen. 1985. A generic treatment of Alismatidae in the Neotropics. Acta Amazon. 15(suppl.): 153--193.</reference>
  </references>
  <key>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate and pistillate flowers on same plant; spadix always enclosed within spathe sheath</description>
      <determination>1 Zostera</determination>
    </key_statement>
    <key_statement>
      <statement_id>1</statement_id>
      <description type="morphology">Staminate and pistillate flowers on different plants; mature spadix projecting from spathe sheath</description>
      <determination>2 Phyllospadix</determination>
    </key_statement>
  </key>
</bio:treatment>
